<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Chapter 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>There was a man in the land of Hus, whose name was Job, and that man was simple and upright, and fearing God, and avoiding evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And there were born to him seven sons and three daughters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And his possession was seven thousand sheep, and three thousand camels, and five hundred yoke of oxen, and five hundred she asses, and a family exceeding great: and this man was great among all the people of the east.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And his sons went, and made a feast by houses every one in his day. And sending they called their three sisters to eat and drink with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when the days of their feasting were gone about, Job sent to them, and sanctified them: and rising up early offered holocausts for every one of them. For he said: Lest perhaps my sons have sinned, and have blessed God in their hearts. So did Job all days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now on a certain day when the sons of God came to stand before the Lord, Satan also was present among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the Lord said to him: Whence comest thou? And he answered and said: I have gone round about the earth, and walked through it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the Lord said to him: Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a simple and upright man, and fearing God, and avoiding evil?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And Satan answering, said: Doth Job fear God in vain?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hast not thou made a fence for him, and his house, and all his substance round about, blessed the works of his hands, and his possession hath increased on the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But stretch forth thy hand a little, and touch all that he hath, and see if he blesseth thee not to thy face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Satan: Behold, all that he hath is in thy hand: only put not forth thy hand upon his person. And Satan went forth from the presence of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now upon a certain day when his sons and daughters were eating and drinking wine in the house of their eldest brother,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>There came a messenger to Job, and said: The oxen were ploughing, and the asses feeding beside them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Sabeans rushed in, and took all away, and slew the servants with the sword, and I alone have escaped to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And while he was yet speaking, another came, and said: The fire of God fell from heaven, and striking the sheep and the servants, hath consumed them, and I alone have escaped to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And while he also was yet speaking, there came another, and said: The Chaldeans made three troops, and have fallen upon the camels, and taken them, moreover they have slain the servants with the sword, and I alone have escaped to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He was yet speaking, and behold another came in, and said: Thy sons and daughters were eating and drinking wine in the house of their elder brother:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>A violent wind came on a sudden from the side of the desert, and shook the four corners of the house, and it fell upon thy children and they are dead, and I alone have escaped to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then Job rose up, and rent his garments, and having shaven his head fell down upon the ground and worshipped,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And said: Naked came I out of my mother&#8217;s womb, and naked shall I return thither: the Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away: as it hath pleased the Lord so is it done: blessed be the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In all these things Job sinned not by his lips, nor spoke he any foolish thing against God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="Chapter 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And it came to pass, when on a certain day the sons of God came, and stood before the Lord, and Satan came among them, and stood in his sight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>That the Lord said to Satan: Whence comest thou? And he answered and said: I have gone round about the earth, and walked through it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the Lord said to Satan: Hast thou considered my servant Job, that there is none like him in the earth, a man simple, and upright, and fearing God, and avoiding evil, and still keeping his innocence? But thou hast moved me against him, that I should afflict him without cause.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Satan answered, and said: Skin for skin, and all that a man hath he will give for his life:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But put forth thy hand, and touch his bone and his flesh, and then thou shalt see that he will bless thee to thy face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the Lord said to Satan: Behold he is in thy hand, but yet save his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So Satan went forth from the presence of the Lord, and struck Job with a very grievous ulcer, from the sole of the foot even to the top of his head:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And he took a potsherd and scraped the corrupt matter, sitting on a dunghill.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And his wife said to him: Dost thou still continue in thy simplicity? bless God, and die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And he said to her: Thou hast spoken like one of the foolish women: if we have received good things at the hand of God, why should we not receive evil? In all these things Job did not sin with his lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now when Job&#8217;s three friends heard all the evil that had befallen him, they came every one from his own place, Eliphaz the Themanite, and Baldad the Suhite, and Sophar the Naamathite. For they had made an appointment to come together and visit him, and comfort him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when they had lifted up their eyes afar off, they knew him not, and crying out they wept, and rending their garments they sprinkled dust upon their heads toward heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they sat with him on the ground seven days and seven nights, and no man spoke to him a word: for they saw that his grief was very great.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="Chapter 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this Job opened his mouth, and cursed his day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And he said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Let the day perish wherein I was born, and the night in which it was said: A man child is conceived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let that day be turned into darkness, let not God regard it from above, and let not the light shine upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Let darkness, and the shadow of death cover it, let a mist overspread it, and let it be wrapped up in bitterness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let a darksome whirlwind seize upon that night, let it not be counted in the days of the year, nor numbered in the months.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Let that night be solitary, and not worthy of praise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Let them curse it who curse the day, who are ready to raise up a leviathan:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let the stars be darkened with the mist thereof: let it expect light and not see it, nor the rising of the dawning of the day:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Because it shut not up the doors of the womb that bore me, nor took away evils from my eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Why did I not die in the womb, why did I not perish when I came out of the belly?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Why received upon the knees? why suckled at the breasts?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For now I should have been asleep and still, and should have rest in my sleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>With kings and consuls of the earth, who build themselves solitudes:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Or with princes, that possess gold, and fill their houses with silver:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Or as a hidden untimely birth I should not be, or as they that being conceived have not seen the light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>There the wicked cease from tumult, and there the wearied in strength are at rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And they sometime bound together without disquiet, have not heard the voice of the oppressor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The small and great are there, and the servant is free from his master.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Why is light given to him that is in misery, and life to them that are in bitterness of soul?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>That look for death, and it cometh not, as they that dig for a treasure:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And they rejoice exceedingly when they have found the grave.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>To a man whose way is hidden, and God hath surrounded him with darkness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Before I eat I sigh: and as overflowing waters, so is my roaring:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For the fear which I feared, hath come upon me: and that which I was afraid of, hath befallen me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Have I not dissembled? have I not kept silence? have I not been quiet? and indignation is come upon me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="Chapter 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Eliphaz the Themanite answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>If we begin to speak to thee, perhaps thou wilt take it ill, but who can withhold the words he hath conceived?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Behold thou hast taught many, and thou hast strengthened the weary hands:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thy words have confirmed them that were staggering, and thou hast strengthened the trembling knees:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But now the scourge is come upon thee, and thou faintest: it hath touched thee, and thou art troubled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Where is thy fear, thy fortitude, thy patience, and the perfection of thy ways?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Remember, I pray thee, who ever perished being innocent? or when were the just destroyed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>On the contrary I have seen those who work iniquity, and sow sorrows, and reap them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Perishing by the blast of God, and consumed by the spirit of his wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The roaring of the lion, and the voice of the lioness, and the teeth of the whelps of lions are broken:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The tiger hath perished for want of prey, and the young lions are scattered abroad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now there was a word spoken to me in private, and my ears by stealth as it were received the veins of its whisper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In the horror of a vision by night, when deep sleep is wont to hold men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Fear seized upon me, and trembling, and all my bones were affrighted:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when a spirit passed before me, the hair of my flesh stood up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>There stood one whose countenance I knew not, an image before my eyes, and I heard the voice as it were of a gentle wind:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Shall man be justified in comparison of God, or shall a man be more pure than his maker?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold they that serve him are not steadfast, and in his angels he found wickedness:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>How much more shall they that dwell in houses of clay, who have an earthly foundation, be consumed as with the moth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>From morning till evening they shall be cut down: and because no one understandeth, they shall perish for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they that shall be left, shall be taken away from them: they shall die, and not in wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5" preferred_title="Chapter 5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Call now if there be any that will answer thee, and turn to some of the saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Anger indeed killeth the foolish, and envy slayeth the little one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I have seen a fool with a strong root, and I cursed his beauty immediately.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>His children shall be far from safety, and shall be destroyed in the gate, and there shall be none to deliver them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Whose harvest the hungry shall eat, and the armed man shall take him by violence, and the thirsty shall drink up his riches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Nothing upon earth is done without a cause, and sorrow doth not spring out of the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Man is born to labour and the bird to fly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Wherefore I will pray to the Lord, and address my speech to God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Who doth great things and unsearchable and wonderful things without number:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Who giveth rain upon the face of the earth, and watereth all things with waters:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Who setteth up the humble on high, and comforteth with health those that mourn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Who bringeth to nought the designs of the malignant, so that their hands cannot accomplish what they had begun:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Who catcheth the wise in their craftiness, and disappointeth the counsel of the wicked:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>They shall meet with darkness in the day, and grope at noonday as in the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But he shall save the needy from the sword of their mouth, and the poor from the hand of the violent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And to the needy there shall be hope, but iniquity shall draw in her mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Blessed is the man whom God correcteth: refuse not therefore the chastising of the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For he woundeth, and cureth: he striketh, and his hands shall heal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>In six troubles he shall deliver thee, and in the seventh, evil shall not touch thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In famine he shall deliver thee from death: and in battle, from the hand of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thou shalt be hidden from the scourge of the tongue: and thou shalt not fear calamity when it cometh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In destruction and famine thou shalt laugh: and thou shalt not be afraid of the beasts of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But thou shalt have a covenant with the stones of the lands, and the beasts of the earth shall be at peace with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And thou shalt know that thy tabernacle is in peace, and visiting thy beauty thou shalt not sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thou shalt know also that thy seed shall be multiplied, and thy offspring like the grass of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Thou shalt enter into the grave in abundance, as a heap of wheat is brought in its season.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Behold, this is even so, as we have searched out: which thou having heard, consider it thoroughly in thy mind.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6" preferred_title="Chapter 6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>O that my sins, whereby I have de-served wrath, and the calamity that I suffer, were weighed in a balance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>As the sand of the sea this would appear heavier: therefore my words are full of sorrow:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For the arrows of the Lord are in me, the rage whereof drinketh up my spirit, and the terrors of the Lord war against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Will the wild ass bray when he hath grass? or will the ox low when he standeth before a full manger?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Or can an unsavoury thing be eaten, that is not seasoned with salt? or can a man taste that which when tasted bringeth death?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The things which before my soul would not touch, now, through anguish are my meats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who will grant that my request may come: and that God may give me what I look for?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And that he that hath begun may destroy me, that he may let loose his hand, and cut me off?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And that this may be my comfort, that afflicting me with sorrow, he spare not, nor I contradict the words of the Holy One.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For what is my strength, that I can hold out? or what is my end that I should keep patience?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>My strength is not the strength of stones, nor is my flesh of brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Behold there is no help for me in myself, and my familiar friends also are departed from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He that taketh away mercy from his friend, forsaketh the fear of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>My brethren have passed by me, as the torrent that passeth swiftly in the valleys.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They that fear the hoary frost, the snow shall fall upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>At the time when they shall be scattered they shall perish: and after it groweth hot they shall be melted out of their place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The paths of their steps are entangled: they shall walk in vain, and shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Consider the paths of Thema, the ways of Saba, and wait a little while.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>They are confounded, because I have hoped: they are come also even unto me, and are covered with shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now you are come: and now seeing my affliction you are afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Did I say: Bring to me, and give me of your substance?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Or deliver me from the hand of the enemy, and rescue me out of the hand of the mighty?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Teach me, and I will hold my peace: and if I have been ignorant in any thing, instruct me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Why have you detracted the words of truth, whereas there is none of you that can reprove me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>You dress up speeches only to rebuke, and you utter words to the wind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>You rush in upon the fatherless, and you endeavour to overthrow your friend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>However finish what you have begun, give ear, and see whether I lie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Answer, I beseech you, without contention: and speaking that which is just, judge ye.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And you shall not find iniquity in my tongue, neither shall folly sound in my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7" preferred_title="Chapter 7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The life of man upon earth is a warfare, and his days are like the days of a hireling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As a servant longeth for the shade, as the hireling looketh for the end of his work;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So I also have had empty months, and have numbered to myself wearisome nights.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>If I lie down to sleep, I shall say: When shall I arise? and again I shall look for the evening, and shall be filled with sorrows even till darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>My flesh is clothed with rottenness and the filth of dust, my skin is withered and drawn together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>My days have passed more swiftly than the web is cut by the weaver, and are consumed without any hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Remember that my life is but wind, and my eye shall not return to see good things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Nor shall the sight of man behold me: thy eyes are upon me, and I shall be no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As a cloud is consumed, and passeth away: so he that shall go down to hell shall not come up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Nor shall he return any more into his house, neither shall his place know him any more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Wherefore I will not spare my mouth, I will speak in the affliction of my spirit: I will talk with the bitterness of my soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Am I a sea, or a whale, that thou hast enclosed me in a prison?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If I say: My bed shall comfort me, and I shall be relieved speaking with myself on my couch:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou wilt frighten me with dreams and terrify me with visions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So that my soul rather chooseth hanging, and my bones death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I have done with hope, I shall now live no longer: spare me, for my days are nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>What is a man that thou shouldst magnify him? or why dost thou set thy heart upon him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thou visitest him early in the morning, and thou provest him suddenly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>How long wilt thou not spare me, nor suffer me to swallow down my spittle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>I have sinned: what shall I do to thee, O keeper of men? why hast thou set me opposite to thee, and I am become burdensome to myself?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Why dost thou not remove my sin, and why dost thou not take away my iniquity? Behold now I shall sleep in the dust: and if thou seek me in the morning, I shall not be.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8" preferred_title="Chapter 8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Baldad the Suhite answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>How long wilt thou speak these things, and how long shall the words of thy mouth be like a strong wind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Doth God pervert judgment, or doth the Almighty overthrow that which is just?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Although thy children have sinned against him, and he hath left them in the hand of their iniquity:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Yet if thou wilt arise early to God, and wilt beseech the Almighty:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If thou wilt walk clean and upright, he will presently awake unto thee, and will make the dwelling of thy justice peaceable:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Insomuch, that if thy former things were small, thy latter things would be multiplied exceedingly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For inquire of the former generation, and search diligently into the memory of the fathers:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>(For we are but of yesterday, and are ignorant that our days upon earth are but a shadow:)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And they shall teach thee: they shall speak to thee, and utter words out of their hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Can the rush be green without moisture? or a sedge-bush grow without water?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When it is yet in flower, and is not plucked up with the hand, it withereth before all herbs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Even so are the ways of all that forget God, and the hope of the hypocrite shall perish:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>His folly shall not please him, and his trust shall be like the spider&#8217;s web.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He shall lean upon his house, and it shall not stand: he shall prop it up, and it shall not rise:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He seemeth to have moisture before the sun cometh, and at his rising, his blossom shall shoot forth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>His roots shall be thick upon a heap of stones, and among the stones he shall abide.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If one swallow him up out of his place, he shall deny him, and shall say: I know thee not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For this is the joy of his way, that others may spring again out of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>God will not cast away the simple, nor reach out his hand to the evildoer:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Until thy mouth be filled with laughter, and thy lips with rejoicing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>They that hate thee, shall be clothed with confusion: and the dwelling of the wicked shall not stand.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9" preferred_title="Chapter 9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Indeed I know it is so, and thatman cannot be justified compared with God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>If he will contend with him, he cannot answer him one for a thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He is wise in heart, and mighty in strength: who hath resisted him, and hath had peace?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who hath removed mountains, and they whom he overthrew in his wrath, knew it not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Who shaketh the earth out of her place, and the pillars thereof tremble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Who commandeth the sun and it riseth not: and shutteth up the stars as it were under a seal:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who alone spreadeth out the heavens, and walketh upon the waves of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Who maketh Arcturus, and Orion, and Hyades, and the inner parts of the south.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Who doth things great and incomprehensible, and wonderful, of which there is no number.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If he come to me, I shall not see him: if he depart I shall not understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If he examine on a sudden, who shall answer him? or who can say: Why dost thou so?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>God, whose wrath no man can resist, and under whom they stoop that bear up the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>What am I then, that I should answer him, and have words with him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I, who although I should have any just thing, would not answer, but would make supplication to my judge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And if he should hear me when I call, I should not believe that he had heard my voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For he shall crush me in a whirlwind, and multiply my wounds even without cause.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He alloweth not my spirit to rest, and he filleth me with bitterness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>If strength be demanded, he is most strong: if equity of judgment, no man dare bear witness for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>If I would justify myself, my own mouth shall condemn me: if I would shew myself innocent, he shall prove me wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Although I should be simple, even this my soul shall be ignorant of, and I shall be weary of my life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>One thing there is that I have spoken, both the innocent and the wicked he consumeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If he scourge, let him kill at once, and not laugh at the pains of the innocent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The earth is given into the hand of the wicked, he covereth the face of the judges thereof: and if it be not he, who is it then?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>My days have been swifter than a post: they have fled away and have not seen good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>They have passed by as ships carrying fruits, as an eagle flying to the prey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>If I say: I will not speak so: I change my face, and am tormented with sorrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>I feared all my works, knowing that thou didst not spare the offender.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>But if so also I am wicked, why have I laboured in vain?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>If I be washed as it were with snow waters, and my hands shall shine ever so clean:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Yet thou shalt plunge me in filth, and my garments shall abhor me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For I shall not answer a man that is like myself: nor one that may be heard with me equally in judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>There is none that may be able to reprove both, and to put his hand between both.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Let him take his rod away from me, and let not his fear terrify me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>I will speak, and will not fear him: for I cannot answer while I am in fear.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10" preferred_title="Chapter 10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My soul is weary of my life, I will let go my speech against myself, I will speak in the bitterness of my soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I will say to God: Do not condemn me: tell me why thou judgest me so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Doth it seem good to thee that thou shouldst calumniate me, and oppress me, the work of thy own hands, and help the counsel of the wicked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hast thou eyes of flesh: or, shalt thou see as man seeth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Are thy days as the days of man, and are thy years as the times of men:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>That thou shouldst inquire after my iniquity, and search after my sin?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And shouldst know that I have done no wicked thing, whereas there is no man that can deliver out of thy hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thy hands have made me, and fashioned me wholly round about, and dost thou thus cast me down headlong on a sudden?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Remember, I beseech thee, that thou hast made me as the clay, and thou wilt bring me into dust again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hast thou not milked me as milk, and curdled me like cheese?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thou hast clothed me with skin and flesh: thou hast put me together with bones and sinews:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thou hast granted me life and mercy, and thy visitation hath preserved my spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Although thou conceal these things in thy heart, yet I know that thou rememberest all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If I have sinned and thou hast spared me for an hour: why dost thou not suffer me to be clean from my iniquity?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And if I be wicked, woe unto me: and if just, I shall not lift up my head, being filled with affliction and misery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And for pride thou wilt take me as a lioness, and returning thou tormentest me wonderfully.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou renewest thy witnesses against me, and multipliest thy wrath upon me, and pains war against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Why didst thou bring me forth out of the womb: O that I had been consumed that eye might not see me!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I should have been as if I had not been, carried from the womb to the grave.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Shall not the fewness of my days be ended shortly? suffer me, therefore, that I may lament my sorrow a little:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Before I go, and return no more, to a land that is dark and covered with the mist of death:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A land of misery and darkness, where the shadow of death, and no order, but everlasting horror dwelleth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11" preferred_title="Chapter 11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Sophar the Naamathite answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Shall not he that speaketh much, hear also? or shall a man full of talk be justified?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Shall men hold their peace to thee only? and when thou hast mocked others, shall no man confute thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For thou hast said: My word is pure, and I am clean in thy sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I wish that God would speak with thee, and would open his lips to thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>That he might shew thee the secrets of wisdom, and that his law is manifold, and thou mightest understand that he exacteth much less of thee, than thy iniquity deserveth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Peradventure thou wilt comprehend the steps of God, and wilt find out the Almighty perfectly?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He is higher than heaven, and what wilt thou do? he is deeper than hell, and how wilt thou know?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The measure of him is longer than the earth, and broader than the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If he shall overturn all things, or shall press them together, who shall contradict him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For he knoweth the vanity of men, and when he seeth iniquity, doth he not consider it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A vain man is lifted up into pride, and thinketh himself born free like a wild ass&#8217;s colt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But thou hast hardened thy heart, and hast spread thy hands to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If thou wilt put away from thee the iniquity that is in thy hand, and let not injustice remain in thy tabernacle:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then mayst thou lift up thy face without spot, and thou shalt be steadfast, and shalt not fear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thou shalt also forget misery, and remember it only as waters that are passed away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And brightness like that of the noonday, shall arise to thee at evening: and when thou shalt think thyself consumed, thou shalt rise as the day star.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And thou shalt have confidence, hope being set before thee, and being buried thou shalt sleep secure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou shalt rest, and there shall be none to make thee afraid: and many shall entreat thy face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But the eyes of the wicked shall decay, and the way to escape shall fail them, and their hope the abomination of the soul.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12" preferred_title="Chapter 12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>THEN Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Are you then men alone, and shall wisdom die with you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I also have a heart as well as you: for who is ignorant of these things, which you know?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He that is mocked by his friends as I, shall call upon God and he will hear him: for the simplicity of the just man is laughed to scorn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The lamp despised in the thoughts of the rich, is ready for the time appointed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The tabernacles of robbers abound, and they provoke God boldly; whereas it is he that hath given all into their hands:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But ask now the beasts, and they shall teach thee: and the birds of the air, and they shall tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Speak to the earth, and it shall answer thee: and the fishes of the sea shall tell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Who is ignorant that the hand of the Lord hath made all these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In whose hand is the soul of every living thing, and the spirit of all flesh of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Doth not the ear discern words, and the palate of him that eateth, the taste?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>In the ancient is wisdom, and in length of days prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>With him is wisdom and strength, he hath counsel and understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If he pull down, there is no man that can build up: if he shut up a man, there is none that can open.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If he withhold the waters, all things shall be dried up: and if he send them out, they shall overturn the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>With him is strength and wisdom: he knoweth both the deceiver, and him that is deceived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He bringeth counsellors to a foolish end, and judges to insensibility.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He looseth the belt of kings, and girdeth their loins with a cord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He leadeth away priests without glory, and overthroweth nobles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He changeth the speech of the true speakers, and taketh away the doctrine of the aged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He poureth contempt upon princes, and relieveth them that were oppressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He discovereth deep things out of darkness, and bringeth up to light the shadow of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He multiplieth nations, and destroyeth them, and restoreth them again after they were overthrown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He changeth the heart of the princes of the people of the earth, and deceiveth them that they walk in vain where there is no way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>They shall grope as in the dark, and not in the light, and he shall make them stagger like men that are drunk.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13" preferred_title="Chapter 13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Behold my eye hath seen all these things, and my ear hath heard them, and I have understood them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>According to your knowledge I also know: neither am I inferior to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But yet I will speak to the Almighty, and I desire to reason with God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Having first shewn that you are forgers of lies, and maintainers of perverse opinions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I wish you would hold your peace, that you might be thought to be wise men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Hear ye therefore my reproof, and attend to the judgment of my lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Hath God any need of your lie, that you should speak deceitfully for him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Do you accept his person, and do you endeavour to judge for God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Or shall it please him, from whom nothing can be concealed? or shall he be deceived as a man, with your deceitful dealings?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He shall reprove you, because in secret you accept his person.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>As soon as he shall move himself, he shall trouble you: and his dread shall fall upon you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Your remembrance shall be compared to ashes, and your necks shall be brought to clay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Hold your peace a little while, that I may speak whatsoever my mind shall suggest to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Why do I tear my flesh with my teeth, and carry my soul in my hands?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Although he should kill me, I will trust in him: but yet I will reprove my ways in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And he shall be my saviour: for no hypocrite shall come before his presence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Hear ye my speech, and receive with your ears hidden truths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If I shall be judged, I know that I shall be found just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Who is he that will plead against me? let him come: why am I consumed holding my peace?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Two things only do not to me, and then from thy face I shall not be hid:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Withdraw thy hand far from me, and let not thy dread terrify me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Call me, and I will answer thee: or else I will speak, and do thou answer me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>How many are my iniquities and sins? make me know my crimes and offences.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Why hidest thou thy face, and thinkest me thy enemy?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Against a leaf, that is carried away with the wind, thou shewest thy power, and thou pursuest a dry straw.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For thou writest bitter things against me, and wilt consume me for the sins of my youth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thou hast put my feet in the stocks, and hast observed all my paths, and hast considered the steps of my feet:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Who am to be consumed as rottenness, and as a garment that is moth-eaten.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14" preferred_title="Chapter 14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Man born of a woman, living for a short time, is filled with many miseries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Who cometh forth like a flower, and is destroyed, and fleeth as a shadow, and never continueth in the same state.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And dost thou think it meet to open thy eyes upon such an one, and to bring him into judgment with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Who can make him clean that is conceived of unclean seed? is it not thou who only art?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The days of man are short, and the number of his months is with thee: thou hast appointed his bounds which cannot be passed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Depart a little from him, that he may rest, until his wished for day come, as that of the hireling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>A tree hath hope: if it be cut, it groweth green again, and the boughs thereof sprout.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>If its root be old in the earth, and its stock be dead in the dust:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>At the scent of water, it shall spring, and bring forth leaves, as when it was first planted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But man when he shall be dead, and stripped and consumed, I pray you where is he?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>As if the waters should depart out of the sea, and an emptied river should be dried up:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So man when he is fallen asleep shall not rise again; till the heavens be broken. he shall not awake, nor rise up out of his sleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Who will grant me this, that thou mayst protect me in hell, and hide me till thy wrath pass, and appoint me a time when thou wilt remember me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Shall man that is dead, thinkest thou, live again? all the days in which I am now in warfare, I expect until my change come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thou shalt call me, and I will answer thee: to the work of thy hands thou shalt reach out thy right hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thou indeed hast numbered my steps, but spare my sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou hast sealed up my offences as it were in a bag, but hast cured my iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A mountain falling cometh to nought, and a rock is removed out of its place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Waters wear away the stones, and with inundation the ground by little and little is washed away: so in like manner thou shalt destroy man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou hast strengthened him for a little while, that he may pass away for ever: thou shalt change his face, and shalt send him away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whether his children come to honour or dishonour, he shall not understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But yet his flesh, while he shall live, shall have pain, and his soul shall mourn over him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15" preferred_title="Chapter 15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And Eliphaz the Themanite, answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Will a wise man answer as if he were speaking in the wind, and fill his stomach with burning heat?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thou reprovest him by words, who is not equal to thee, and thou speakest that which is not good for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>As much as is in thee, thou hast made void fear, and hast taken away prayers from before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For thy iniquity hath taught thy mouth, and thou imitatest the tongue of blasphemers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thy own mouth shall condemn thee, and not I: and thy own lips shall answer thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Art thou the first man that was born, or wast thou made before the hills?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Hast thou heard God&#8217;s counsel, and shall his wisdom be inferior to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>What knowest thou that we are ignorant of? what dost thou understand that we know not?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>There are with us also aged and ancient men, much elder than thy fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Is it a great matter that God should comfort thee? but thy wicked words hinder this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Why doth thy heart elevate thee, and why dost thou stare with thy eyes, as if they were thinking great things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Why doth thy spirit swell against God, to utter such words out of thy mouth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>What is man that he should be without spot, and he that is born of a woman that he should appear just?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Behold among his saints none is unchangeable, and the heavens are not pure in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>How much more is man abominable, and unprofitable, who drinketh iniquity like water?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I will shew thee, hear me: and I will tell thee what I have seen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Wise men confess and hide not their fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>To whom alone the earth was given, and no stranger hath passed among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The wicked man is proud all his days, and the number of the years of his tyranny is uncertain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The sound of dread is always in his ears: and when there is peace, he always suspecteth treason.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He believeth not that he may return from darkness to light, looking round about for the sword on every side.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>When he moveth himself to seek bread, he knoweth that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Tribulation shall terrify him, and distress shall surround him, as a king that is prepared for the battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For he hath stretched out his hand against God, and hath strengthened himself against the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He hath run against him with his neck raised up, and is armed with a fat neck.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Fatness hath covered his face, and the fat hangeth down on his sides.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>He hath dwelt in desolate cities, and in desert houses that are reduced into heaps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He shall not be enriched, neither shall his substance continue, neither shall he push his root in the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He shall not depart out of darkness: the flame shall dry up his branches, and he shall be taken away by the breath of his own mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>He shall not believe, being vainly deceived by error, that he may be redeemed with any price.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Before his days be full he shall perish: and his hands shall wither away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He shall be blasted as a vine when its grapes are in the first flower, and as an olive tree that casteth its flower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For the congregation of the hypocrite is barren, and fire shall devour their tabernacles, who love to take bribes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>He hath conceived sorrow, and hath brought forth iniquity, and his womb prepareth deceits.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16" preferred_title="Chapter 16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I have often heard such things as these: you are all troublesome comforters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Shall windy words have no end? or is it any trouble to thee to speak?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I also could speak like you: and would God your soul were for my soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I would comfort you also with words, and would wag my head over you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I would strengthen you with my mouth, and would move my lips, as sparing you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But what shall I do? If I speak, my pain will not rest: and if I hold my peace, it will not depart from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But now my sorrow hath oppressed me, and all my limbs are brought to nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>My wrinkles bear witness against me, and a false speaker riseth up against my face, contradicting me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He hath gathered together his fury against me, and threatening me he hath gnashed with his teeth upon me: my enemy hath beheld me with terrible eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>They have opened their mouths upon me, and reproaching me they have struck me on the cheek, they are filled with my pains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>God hath shut me up with the unjust man, and hath delivered me into the hands of the wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I that was formerly so wealthy, am all on a sudden broken to pieces: he hath taken me by my neck, he hath broken me, and hath set me up to be his mark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He hath compassed me round about with his lances, he hath wounded my loins, he hath not spared, and hath poured out my bowels on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He hath torn me with wound upon wound, he hath rushed in upon me like a giant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I have sowed sackcloth upon my skin, and have covered my flesh with ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>My face is swollen with weeping, and my eyelids are dim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>These things have I suffered without the iniquity of my hand, when I offered pure prayers to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>O earth, cover not thou my blood, neither let my cry find a hiding place in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For behold my witness is in heaven, and he that knoweth my conscience is on high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>My friends are full of words: my eye poureth out tears to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And O that a man might so be judged with God, as the son of man is judged with his companion!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For behold short years pass away, and I am walking in a path by which I shall not return.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17" preferred_title="Chapter 17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My spirit shall be wasted, my days shall be shortened, and only the grave remaineth for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I have not sinned, and my eye abideth in bitterness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Deliver me, O Lord, and set me beside thee, and let any man&#8217;s hand fight against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thou hast set their heart far from understanding, therefore they shall not be exalted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>He promiseth a prey to his companions, and the eyes of his children shall fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He hath made me as it were a byword of the people, and I am an example before them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>My eye is dim through indignation, and my limbs are brought as it were to nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The just shall be astonished at this, and the innocent shall be raised up against the hypocrite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the just man shall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands shall be stronger and stronger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Wherefore be you all converted, and come, and I shall not find among you any wise man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>My days have passed away, my thoughts are dissipated, tormenting my heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>They have turned night into day, and after darkness I hope for light again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If I wait hell is my house, and I have made my bed in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have said to rottenness: Thou art my father; to worms, my mother and my sister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Where is now then my expectation, and who considereth my patience?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>All that I have shall go down into the deepest pit: thinkest thou that there at least I shall have rest?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18" preferred_title="Chapter 18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Baldad the Suhite answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>How long will you throw out words? understand first, and so let us speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Why are we reputed as beasts, and counted vile before you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thou that destroyest thy soul in thy fury, shall the earth be forsaken for thee, and shall rocks be removed out of their place?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Shall not the light of the wicked be extinguished, and the flame of his fire not shine?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The light shall be dark in his tabernacle, and the lamp that is over him, shall be put out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The step of his strength shall be straitened, and his own counsel shall cast him down headlong.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For he hath thrust his feet into a net, and walketh in its meshes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The sole of his foot shall be held in a snare, and thirst shall burn against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>A gin is hidden for him in the earth, and his trap upon the path.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Fears shall terrify him on every side, and shall entangle his feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let his strength be wasted with famine, and let hunger invade his ribs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Let it devour the beauty of his skin, let the firstborn death consume his arms.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Let his confidence be rooted out of his tabernacle, and let destruction tread upon him like a king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Let the companions of him that is not, dwell in his tabernacle, let brimstone be sprinkled in his tent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let his roots be dried up beneath, and his harvest destroyed above.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Let the memory of him perish from the earth, and let not his name be renowned in the streets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He shall drive him out of light into darkness, and shall remove him out of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>His seed shall not subsist, nor his offspring among his people, nor any remnants in his country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>They that come after him shall be astonished at his day, and horror shall fall upon them that went before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>These then are the tabernacles of the wicked, and this the place of him that knoweth not God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19" preferred_title="Chapter 19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>How long do you afflict my soul,and break me in pieces with words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Behold, these ten times you confound me, and are not ashamed to oppress me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For if I have been ignorant, my ignorance shall be with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But you set yourselves up against me, and reprove me with my reproaches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>At least now understand, that God hath not afflicted me with an equal judgment, and compassed me with his scourges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold I shall cry suffering violence, and no one will hear: I shall cry aloud, and there is none to judge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He hath hedged in my path round about, and I cannot pass, and in my way he hath set darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He hath stripped me of my glory, and hath taken the crown from my head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He hath destroyed me on every side, and I am lost, and he hath taken away my hope, as from a tree that is plucked up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>His wrath is kindled against me, and he hath counted me as his enemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>His troops have come together, and have made themselves a way by me, and have besieged my tabernacle round about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He hath put my brethren far from me, and my acquaintance like strangers have departed from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>My kinsmen have forsaken me, and they that knew me, have forgotten me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>They that dwell in my house, and my maidservants have counted me as a stranger, and I have been like an alien in their eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I called my servant, and he gave me no answer, I entreated him with my own mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>My wife hath abhorred my breath, and I entreated the children of my womb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Even fools despised me, and when I was gone from them, they spoke against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>They that were sometime my counsellors, have abhorred me: and he whom I loved most is turned against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The flesh being consumed, my bone hath cleaved to my skin, and nothing but lips are left about my teeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Have pity on me, have pity on me, at least you my friends, because the hand of the Lord hath touched me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Why do you persecute me as God, and glut yourselves with my flesh?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Who will grant me that my words may be written? who will grant me that they may be marked down in a book?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>With an iron pen and in a plate of lead, or else be graven with an instrument in flint stone?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For I know that my Redeemer liveth, and in the last day I shall rise out of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And I shall be clothed again with my skin, and in my flesh I shall see my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Whom I myself shall see, and my eyes shall behold, and not another: this my hope is laid up in my bosom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Why then do you say now: Let us persecute him, and let us find occasion of word against him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Flee then from the face of the sword, for the sword is the revenger of iniquities: and know ye that there is a judgment.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20" preferred_title="Chapter 20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Sophar the Naamathite answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Therefore various thoughts succeed one another in me, and my mind is hurried away to different things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The doctrine with which thou reprovest me, I will hear, and the spirit of my understanding shall answer for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>This I know from the beginning, since man was placed upon the earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>That the praise of the wicked is short, and the joy of the hypocrite but for a moment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If his pride mount up even to heaven, and his head touch the clouds:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>In the end he shall be destroyed like a dunghill, and they that had seen him, shall say: Where is he?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>As a dream that fleeth away he shall not be found, he shall pass as a vision of the night:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The eyes that had seen him, shall see him no more, neither shall his place any more behold him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>His children shall be oppressed with want, and his hands shall render to him his sorrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>His bones shall be filled with the vices of his youth, and they shall sleep with him in the dust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For when evil shall be sweet in his mouth, he will hide it under his tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He will spare it, and not leave it, and will hide it in his throat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>His bread in his belly shall be turned into the gall of asps within him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The riches which he hath swallowed, he shall vomit up, and God shall draw them out of his belly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He shall suck the head of asps, and the viper&#8217;s tongue shall kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>(Let him not see the streams of the river, the brooks of honey and of butter.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He shall be punished for all that he did, and yet shall not be consumed: according to the multitude of his devices so also shall he suffer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because he broke in and stripped the poor: he hath violently taken away a house which he did not build.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And yet his belly was not filled: and when he hath the things he coveted, he shall not be able to possess them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>There was nothing left of his meat, and therefore nothing shall continue of his goods:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When he shall be filled, he shall be straitened, he shall burn, and every sorrow shall fall upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>May his belly be filled, that God may send forth the wrath of his indignation upon him, and rain down his war upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He shall flee from weapons of iron, and shall fall upon a bow of brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The sword is drawn out, and cometh forth from its scabbard, and glittereth in his bitterness: the terrible ones shall go and come upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>All darkness is hid in his secret places: a fire that is not kindled shall devour him, he shall be afflicted when left in his tabernacle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The heavens shall reveal his iniquity, and the earth shall rise up against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The offspring of his house shall be exposed, he shall be pulled down in the day of God&#8217;s wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>This is the portion of a wicked man from God, and the inheritance of his doings from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21" preferred_title="Chapter 21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear, I beseech you, my words, and do penance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Suffer me, and I will speak, and after, if you please, laugh at my words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Is my debate against man, that I should not have just reason to be troubled?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Hearken to me and be astonished, and lay your finger on your mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>As for me, when I remember, I am afraid, and trembling taketh hold on my flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Why then do the wicked live, are they advanced, and strengthened with riches?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Their seed continueth before them, a multitude of kinsmen, and of children&#8217;s children in their sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Their houses are secure and peaceable, and the rod of God is not upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Their cattle have conceived, and failed not: their cow has calved, and is not deprived of her fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Their little ones go out like a flock, and their children dance and play.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>They take the timbrel, and the harp, and rejoice at the sound of the organ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They spend their days in wealth, and in a moment they go down to hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Who have said to God: Depart from us, we desire not the knowledge of thy ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Who is the Almighty, that we should serve him? and what doth it profit us if we pray to him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Yet because their good things are not in their hand, may the counsel of the wicked be far from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>How often shall the lamp of the wicked be put out, and a deluge come upon them, and he shall distribute the sorrows of his wrath?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>They shall be as chaff before the face of the wind, and as ashes which the whirlwind scattereth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>God shall lay up the sorrow of the father for his children: and when he shall repay, then shall he know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>His eyes shall see his own destruction, and he shall drink of the wrath of the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For what is it to him what befalleth his house after him: and if the number of his months be diminished by one half?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Shall any one teach God knowledge, who judgeth those that are high?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>One man dieth strong, and hale, rich and happy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>His bowels are full of fat, and his bones are moistened with marrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But another dieth in bitterness of soul without any riches:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And yet they shall sleep together in the dust, and worms shall cover them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Surely I know your thoughts, and your unjust judgments against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For you say: Where is the house of the prince? and where are the dwelling places of the wicked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Ask any one of them that go by the way, and you shall perceive that he knoweth these same things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Because the wicked man is reserved to the day of destruction, and he shall be brought to the day of wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Who shall reprove his way to his face? and who shall repay him what he hath done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>He shall be brought to the graves, and shall watch in the heap of the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He hath been acceptable to the gravel of Cocytus, and he shall draw every man after him, and there are innumerable before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>How then do ye comfort me in vain, whereas your answer is shewn to be repugnant to truth?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22" preferred_title="Chapter 22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Eliphaz the Themanite answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Can man be compared with God, even though he were of perfect knowledge?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>What doth it profit God if thou be just? or what dost thou give him if thy way be unspotted?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Shall he reprove thee for fear, and come with thee into judgment:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And not for thy manifold wickedness, and thy infinite iniquities?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For thou hast taken away the pledge of thy brethren without cause, and stripped the naked of their clothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thou hast not given water to the weary, thou hast withdrawn bread from the hungry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>In the strength of thy arm thou didst possess the land, and being the most mighty thou holdest it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou hast sent widows away empty, and the arms of the fatherless thou hast broken in pieces.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore art thou surrounded with snares, and sudden fear troubleth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And didst thou think that thou shouldst not see darkness, and that thou shouldst not be covered with the violence of overflowing waters?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Dost not thou think that God is higher than heaven, and is elevated above the height of the stars?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And thou sayst: What doth God know? and he judgeth as it were through a mist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The clouds are his covert, and he doth not consider our things, and he walketh about the poles of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Dost thou desire to keep the path of ages, which wicked men have trodden?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Who were taken away before their time, and a flood hath overthrown their foundation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Who said to God: Depart from us: and looked upon the Almighty as if he could do nothing:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whereas he had filled their houses with good things: whose way of thinking be far from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The just shall see, and shall rejoice, and the innocent shall laugh them to scorn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Is not their exaltation cut down, and hath not fire devoured the remnants of them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Submit thyself then to him, and be at peace: and thereby thou shalt have the best fruits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Receive the law of his mouth, and lay up his words in thy heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If thou wilt return to the Almighty, thou shalt be built up, and shalt put away iniquity far from thy tabernacle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He shall give for earth flint, and for flint torrents of gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the Almighty shall be against thy enemies, and silver shall be heaped together for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then shalt thou abound in delights in the Almighty, and shalt lift up thy face to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thou shalt pray to him, and he will hear thee, and thou shalt pay vows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thou shalt decree a thing, and it shall come to thee, and light shall shine in thy ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For he that hath been humbled, shall be in glory: and he that shall bow down his eyes, he shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The innocent shall be saved, and he shall be saved by the cleanness of his hands.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23" preferred_title="Chapter 23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now also my words are in bitterness, and the hand of my scourge is more grievous than my mourning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Who will grant me that I might know and find him, and come even to his throne?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I would set judgment before him, and would fill my mouth with complaints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>That I might know the words that he would answer me, and understand what he would say to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I would not that he should contend with me with much strength, nor overwhelm me with the weight of his greatness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Let him propose equity against me, and let my judgment come to victory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But if I go to the east, he appeareth not; if to the west, I shall not understand him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If to the left hand, what shall I do? I shall not take hold on him: if I turn myself to the right hand, I shall not see him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But he knoweth my way, and has tried me as gold that passeth through the fire:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>My foot hath followed his steps, I have kept his way, and have not declined from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I have not departed from the commandments of his lips, and the words of his mouth I have hid in my bosom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For he is alone, and no man can turn away his thought: and whatsoever his soul hath desired, that hath he done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when he shall have fulfilled his will in me, many other like things are also at hand with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And therefore I am troubled at his presence, and when I consider him I am made pensive with fear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>God hath softened my heart, and the Almighty hath troubled me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For I have not perished because of the darkness that hangs over me, neither hath the mist covered my face.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24" preferred_title="Chapter 24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Times are not hid from the Almighty: but they that know him, know not his days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Some have removed landmarks, have taken away flocks by force, and fed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They have driven away the ass of the fatherless, and have taken away the widow&#8217;s ox for a pledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They have overturned the way of the poor, and have oppressed together the meek of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Others like wild asses in the desert go forth to their work: by watching for a prey they get bread for their children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They reap the field that is not their own, and gather the vintage of his vineyard whom by violence they have oppressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They send men away naked, taking away their clothes who have no covering in the cold:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who are wet, with the showers of the mountains, and having no covering embrace the stones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They have violently robbed the fatherless, and stripped the poor common people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>From the naked and them that go without clothing, and from the hungry they have taken away the ears of corn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>They have taken their rest at noon among the stores of them, who after having trodden the winepresses suffer thirst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Out of the cities they have made men to groan, and the soul of the wounded hath cried out, and God doth not suffer it to pass unrevenged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They have been rebellious to the light, they have not known his ways, neither have they returned by his paths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The murderer riseth at the very break of day, he killeth the needy, and the poor man: but in the night he will be as a thief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The eye of the adulterer observeth darkness, saying: No eye shall see me: and he will cover his face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He diggeth through houses in the dark, as in the day they had appointed for themselves, and they have not known the light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If the morning suddenly appear, it is to them the shadow of death: and they walk in darkness as if it were in light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He is light upon the face of the water: cursed be his portion on the earth, let him not walk by the way of the vineyards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Let him pass from the snow waters to excessive heat, and his sin even to hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Let mercy forget him: may worms be his sweetness: let him be remembered no more, but be broken in pieces as an unfruitful tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For he hath fed the barren that beareth not, and to the widow he hath done no good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He hath pulled down the strong by his might: and when he standeth up, he shall not trust to his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>God hath given him place for penance, and he abuseth it unto pride: but his eyes are upon his ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>They are lifted up for a little while and shall not stand, and shall be brought down as all things, and shall be taken away, and as the tops of the ears of corn they shall be broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And if it be not so, who can convince me that I have lied, and set my words before God?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25" preferred_title="Chapter 25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Baldad the Suhite answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Power and terror are with him, who maketh peace in his high places.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Is there any numbering of his soldiers? and upon whom shall not his light arise?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Can men be justified compared with God, or he that is born of a women appear clean?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Behold even the moon doth not shine, and the stars are not pure in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>How much less man that is rottenness and the son of man who is a worm?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26" preferred_title="Chapter 26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Job answered, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whose helper art thou? is it of him that is weak? and dost thou hold up the arm of him that has no strength?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>To whom hast thou given counsel? perhaps to him that hath no wisdom, and thou hast shewn thy very great prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whom hast thou desired to teach? was it not him that made life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Behold the giants groan under the waters, and they that dwell with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Hell is naked before him, and there is no covering for destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He stretched out the north over the empty space, and hangeth the earth upon nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He bindeth up the waters in his clouds, so that they break not out and fall down together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He withholdeth the face of his throne, and spreadeth his cloud over it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He hath set bounds about the waters, till light and darkness come to an end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The pillars of heaven tremble, and dread at his beck.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>By his power the seas are suddenly gathered together, and his wisdom has struck the proud one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>His spirit hath adorned the heavens, and his obstetric hand brought forth the winding serpent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Lo, these things are said in part of his ways: and seeing we have heard scarce a little drop of his word, who shall be able to behold the thunder of his greatness?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27" preferred_title="Chapter 27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Job also added, taking up his parable, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As God liveth, who hath taken away my judgment, and the Almighty, who hath brought my soul to bitterness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>As long as breath remaineth in me, and the spirit of God in my nostrils,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>My lips shall not speak iniquity, neither shall my tongue contrive lying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>God forbid that I should judge you to be just: till I die I will not depart from my innocence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>My justification, which I have begun to hold, I will not forsake: for my heart doth not reprehend me in all my life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Let my enemy be as the ungodly, and my adversary as the wicked one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For what is the hope of the hypocrite if through covetousness he take by violence, and God deliver not his soul?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Will God hear his cry, when distress shall come upon him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Or can he delight himself in the Almighty, and call upon God at all times?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I will teach you by the hand of God, what the Almighty hath, and I will not conceal it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Behold you all know it, and why do you speak vain things without cause?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>This is the portion of a wicked man with God, and the inheritance of the violent, which they shall receive of the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If his sons be multiplied, they shall be for the sword, and his grandsons shall not be filled with bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>They that shall remain of him, shall be buried in death, and his widows shall not weep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If he shall heap together silver as earth, and prepare raiment as clay,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He shall prepare indeed, but the just man shall be clothed with it: and the innocent shall divide the silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He hath built his house as a moth, and as a keeper he hath made a booth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The rich man when he shall sleep shall take away nothing with him: he shall open his eyes and find nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Poverty like water shall take hold on him, a tempest shall oppress him in the night:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>A burning wind shall take him up, and carry him away, and as a whirlwind shall snatch him from his place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And he shall cast upon him, and shall not spare: out of his hand he would willingly flee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He shall clasp his hands upon him, and shall hiss at him, beholding his place.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28" preferred_title="Chapter 28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Silver hath beginnings of its veins, and gold hath a place wherein it is melted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Iron is taken out of the earth, and stone melted with heat is turned into brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He hath set a time for darkness, and the end of all things he considereth, the stone also that is in the dark and the shadow of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The flood divideth from the people that are on their journey, those whom the food of the needy man hath forgotten, and who cannot be come at.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The land, out of which bread grew in its place, hath been overturned with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The stones of it are the place of sapphires, and the clods of it are gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The bird hath not known the path, neither hath the eye of the vulture beheld it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The children of the merchants have not trodden it, neither hath the lioness passed by it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He hath stretched forth his hand to the flint, he hath overturned mountains from the roots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In the rocks he hath cut out rivers, and his eye hath seen every precious thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The depths also of rivers he hath searched, and hidden things he hath brought forth to light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But where is wisdom to be found, and where is the place of understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Man knoweth not the price thereof, neither is it found in the land of them that live in delights.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The depth saith: It is not in me: and the sea saith: It is not with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The finest gold shall not purchase it, neither shall silver be weighed in exchange for it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>It shall not be compared with the dyed colours of India, or with the most precious stone sardonyx, or the sapphire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Gold or crystal cannot equal it, neither shall any vessels of gold be changed for it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>High and eminent things shall not be mentioned in comparison of it: but wisdom is drawn out of secret places.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The topaz of Ethiopia shall not be equal to it, neither shall it be compared to the cleanest dyeing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Whence then cometh wisdom? and where is the place of understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>It is hid from the eyes of all living, and the fowls of the air know it not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Destruction and death have said: With our ears we have heard the fame thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>God understandeth the way of it, and he knoweth the place thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For he beholdeth the ends of the world: and looketh on all things that are under heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Who made a weight for the winds, and weighed the waters by measure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>When he gave a law for the rain, and a way for the sounding storms.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then he saw it, and declared, and prepared, and searched it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And he said to man: Behold the fear of the Lord, that is wisdom: and to depart from evil, is understanding.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29" preferred_title="Chapter 29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Job also added, taking up his parable, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Who will grant me, that I might be according to the months past, according to the days in which God kept me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When his lamp shined over my head, and I walked by his light in darkness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>As I was in the days of my youth, when God was secretly in my tabernacle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When the Almighty was with me: and my servants round about me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>When I washed my feet with butter, and the rock poured me out rivers of oil?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When I went out to the gate of the city, and in the street they prepared me a chair?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The young men saw me, and hid themselves: and the old men rose up and stood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The princes ceased to speak, and laid the finger on their mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The rulers held their peace, and their tongue cleaved to their throat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The ear that heard me blessed me, and the eye that saw me gave witness to me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Because I had delivered the poor man that cried out; and the fatherless, that had no helper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The blessing of him that was ready to perish came upon me, and I comforted the heart of the widow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I was clad with justice: and I clothed myself with my judgment, as with a robe and a diadem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I was an eye to the blind, and a foot to the lame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I was the father of the poor: and the cause which I knew not, I searched out most diligently.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I broke the jaws of the wicked man, and out of his teeth I took away the prey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And I said: I shall die in my nest, and as a palm tree shall multiply my days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>My root is opened beside the waters, and dew shall continue in my harvest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>My glory shall always be renewed, and my bow in my hand shall be repaired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They that heard me, waited for my sentence, and being attentive held their peace at my counsel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>To my words they durst add nothing, and my speech dropped upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>They waited for me as for rain, and they opened their mouth as for a latter shower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If at any time I laughed on them, they believed not, and the light of my countenance fell not on earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>If I had a mind to go to them, I sat first, and when I sat as a king, with his army standing about him, yet I was a comforter of them that mourned.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30" preferred_title="Chapter 30">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But now the younger in time scorn me, whose fathers I would not have set with the dogs of my flock:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The strength of whose hands was to me as nothing, and they were thought unworthy of life itself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Barren with want and hunger, who gnawed in the wilderness, disfigured with calamity and misery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And they ate grass, and barks of trees, and the root of junipers was their food.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who snatched up these things out of the valleys, and when they had found any of them, they ran to them with a cry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They dwelt in the desert places of torrents, and in caves of earth, or upon the gravel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They pleased themselves among these kind of things, and counted it delightful to be under the briers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The children of foolish and base men, and not appearing at all upon the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now I am turned into their song, and am become their byword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They abhor me, and flee far from me, and are not afraid to spit in my face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For he hath opened his quiver, and hath afflicted me, and hath put a bridle into my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>At the right hand of my rising, my calamities forthwith arose: they have overthrown my feet, and have overwhelmed me with their paths as with waves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They have destroyed my ways, they have lain in wait against me, and they have prevailed, and there was none to help.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>They have rushed in upon me, as when a wall is broken, and a gate opened, and have rolled themselves down to my miseries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I am brought to nothing: as a wind thou hast taken away my desire: and my prosperity hath passed away like a cloud.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And now my soul fadeth within myself, and the days of affliction possess me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>In the night my bone is pierced with sorrows: and they that feed upon me, do not sleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>With the multitude of them my garment is consumed, and they have girded me about, as with the collar of my coat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I am compared to dirt, and am likened to embers and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>I cry to thee, and thou hearest me not: I stand up, and thou dost not regard me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thou art changed to be cruel toward me, and in the hardness of thy hand thou art against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thou hast lifted me up, and set me as it were upon the wind, and thou hast mightily dashed me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I know that thou wilt deliver me to death, where a house is appointed for every one that liveth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But yet thou stretchest not forth thy hand to their consumption: and if they shall fall down thou wilt save.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I wept heretofore for him that was afflicted, and my soul had compassion on the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I expected good things, and evils are come upon me: I waited for light, and darkness broke out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>My inner parts have boiled without any rest, the days of affliction have prevented me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>I went mourning without indignation; I rose up, and cried in the crowd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>I was the brother of dragons, and companion of ostriches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>My skin is become black upon me, and my bones are dried up with heat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>My harp is turned to mourning, and my organ into the voice of those that weep.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31" preferred_title="Chapter 31">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I MADE a covenant with my eyes, that I would not so much as think upon a virgin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For what part should God from above have in me, and what inheritance the Almighty from on high?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Is not destruction to the wicked, and aversion to them that work iniquity?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Doth not he consider my ways, and number all my steps?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>If I have walked in vanity, and my foot hath made haste to deceit:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let him weigh me in a just balance, and let God know my simplicity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If my step hath turned out of the way, and if my heart hath followed my eyes, and if a spot hath cleaved to my hands:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then let me sow and let another eat: and let my offspring be rooted out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If my heart hath been deceived upon a woman, and if I have laid wait at my friend&#8217;s door:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Let my wife be the harlot of another, and let other men lie with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For this is a heinous crime, and a most grievous iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>It is a fire that devoureth even to destruction, and rooteth up all things that spring.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If I have despised to abide judgment with my manservant, or my maidservant, when they had any controversy against me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For what shall I do when God shall rise to judge? and when he shall examine, what shall I answer him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Did not he that made me in the womb make him also: and did not one and the same form me in the womb?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If I have denied to the poor what they desired, and have made the eyes of the widow wait:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If I have eaten my morsel alone, and the fatherless hath not eaten thereof:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>(For from my infancy mercy grew up with me: and it came out with me from my mother&#8217;s womb:)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>If I have despised him that was perishing for want of clothing, and the poor man that had no covering:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>If his sides have not blessed me, and if he were not warmed with the fleece of my sheep:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>If I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless, even when I saw myself superior in the gate:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Let my shoulder fall from its joint, and let my arm with its bones be broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For I have always feared God as waves swelling over me, and his weight I was not able to bear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If I have thought gold my strength, and have said to fine gold: My confidence:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>If I have rejoiced over my great riches, and because my hand had gotten much.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>If I beheld the sun when it shined, and the moon going in brightness:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And my heart in secret hath rejoiced, and I have kissed my hand with my mouth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Which is a very great iniquity, and a denial against the most high God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>If I have been glad at the downfall of him that hated me, and have rejoiced that evil had found him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For I have not given my mouth to sin, by wishing a curse to his soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>If the men of my tabernacle have not said: Who will give us of his flesh that we may be filled?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The stranger did not stay without, my door was open to the traveller.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>If as a man I have hid my sin, and have concealed my iniquity in my bosom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>If I have been afraid at a very great multitude, and the contempt of kinsmen hath terrified me: and I have not rather held my peace, and not gone out of the door.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Who would grant me a hearer, that the Almighty may hear my desire; and that he himself that judgeth would write a book,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>That I may carry it on my shoulder, and put it about me as a crown?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>At every step of mine I would pronounce it, and offer it as to a prince.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>If my land cry against me, and with it the furrows thereof mourn:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>If I have eaten the fruits thereof without money, and have afflicted the soul of the tillers thereof:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Let thistles grow up to me instead of wheat, and thorns instead of barley.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="32" preferred_title="Chapter 32">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So these three men ceased to answer Job, because he seemed just to himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Eliu the son of Barachel the Buzite, of the kindred of Ram, was angry and was moved to indignation: now he was angry against Job, because he said he was just before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And he was angry with his friends, because they had not found a reasonable answer, but only had condemned Job.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So Eliu waited while Job was speaking, because they were his elders that were speaking.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But when he saw that the three were not able to answer, he was exceedingly angry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then Eliu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered, and said: I am younger in days, and you are more ancient; therefore hanging down my head, I was afraid to shew you my opinion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For I hoped that greater age would speak, and that a multitude of years would teach wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But, as I see, there is a spirit in men, and the inspiration of the Almighty giveth understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They that are aged are not the wise men, neither do the ancients understand judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore I will speak: Hearken to me, I also will shew you my wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For I have waited for your words, I have given ear to your wisdom, as long as you were disputing in words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And as long as I thought you said some thing, I considered: but, as I see, there is none of you that can convince Job, and answer his words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Lest you should say: We have found wisdom, God hath cast him down, not man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He hath spoken nothing to me, and I will not answer him according to your words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>They were afraid, and answered no more, and they left off speaking.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore because I have waited, and they have not spoken: they stood, and answered no more:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I also will answer my part, and will shew my knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For I am full of matter to speak of, and the spirit of my bowels straiteneth me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Behold, my belly is as new wine which wanteth vent, which bursteth the new vessels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>I will speak and take breath a little: I will open my lips, and will answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I will not accept the person of man, and I will not level God with man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For I know not how long I shall continue, and whether after a while my Maker may take me away.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="33" preferred_title="Chapter 33">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hear therefore, O Job, my speeches, and hearken to all my words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Behold now I have opened my mouth, let my tongue speak within my jaws.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>My words are from my upright heart, and my lips shall speak a pure sentence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The spirit of God made me, and the breath of the Almighty gave me life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>If thou canst, answer me, and stand up against my face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Behold God hath made me as well as thee, and of the same clay I also was formed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But yet let not my wonder terrify thee, and let not my eloquence be burdensome to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now thou hast said in my hearing, and I have heard the voice of thy words:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I am clean, and without sin: I am unspotted, and there is no iniquity in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Because he hath found complaints against me, therefore he hath counted me for his enemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He hath put my feet in the stocks, he hath observed all my paths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now this is the thing in which thou art not justified: I will answer thee, that God is greater than man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Dost thou strive against him, because he hath not answered thee to all words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>God speaketh once, and repeateth not the selfsame thing the second time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>By a dream in a vision by night, when deep sleep falleth upon men, and they are sleeping in their beds:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then he openeth the ears of men, and teaching instructeth them in what they are to learn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>That he may withdraw a man from the things he is doing, and may deliver him from pride.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Rescuing his soul from corruption: and his life from passing to the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He rebuketh also by sorrow in the bed, and he maketh all his bones to wither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Bread becometh abominable to him in his life, and to his soul the meat which before he desired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>His flesh shall be consumed away, and his bones that were covered shall be made bare.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>His soul hath drawn near to corruption, and his life to the destroyers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If there shall be an angel speaking for him, one among thousands, to declare man&#8217;s uprightness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He shall have mercy on him, and shall say: Deliver him, that he may not go down to corruption: I have found wherein I may be merciful to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>His flesh is consumed with punishments, let him return to the days of his youth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He shall pray to God, and he will be gracious to him: and he shall see his face with joy, and he will render to man his justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He shall look upon men, and shall say: I have sinned, and indeed I have offended, and I have not received what I have deserved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>He hath delivered his soul from going into destruction, that it may live and see the light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Behold, all these things God worketh three times within every one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>That he may withdraw their souls from corruption, and enlighten them with the light of the living.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Attend, Job, and hearken to me: and hold thy peace, whilst I speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But if thou hast any thing to say, answer me, speak: for I would have thee to appear just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And if thou have not, hear me: hold thy peace, and I will teach thee wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="34" preferred_title="Chapter 34">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And Eliu continued his discourse, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear ye, wise men, my words, and ye learned, hearken to me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the ear trieth words, and the mouth discerneth meats by the taste.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let us choose to us judgment, and let us see among ourselves what is the best.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For Job hath said: I am just, and God hath overthrown my judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For in judging me there is a lie: my arrow is violent without any sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>What man is there like Job, who drinketh up scorning like water?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who goeth in company with them that work iniquity, and walketh with wicked men?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For he hath said: Man shall not please God, although he run with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore, ye men of understanding, hear me: far from God be wickedness, and iniquity from the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For he will render to a man his work, and according to the ways of every one he will reward them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For in very deed God will not condemn without cause, neither will the Almighty pervert judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>What other hath he appointed over the earth? or whom hath he set over the world which he made?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If he turn his heart to him, he shall draw his spirit and breath unto himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>All flesh shall perish together, and man shall return into ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If then thou hast understanding, hear what is said, and hearken to the voice of my words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Can he be healed that loveth not judgment? and how dost thou so far condemn him that is just?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Who saith to the king: Thou art an apostate: who calleth rulers ungodly:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Who accepteth not the persons of princes: nor hath regarded the tyrant, when he contended against the poor man: for all are the work of his hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>They shall suddenly die, and the people shall be troubled at midnight, and they shall pass, and take away the violent without hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For his eyes are upon the ways of men, and he considereth all their steps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>There is no darkness, and there is no shadow of death, where they may be hid who work iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For it is no longer in the power of man to enter into judgment with God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He shall break in pieces many and innumerable, and shall make others to stand in their stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For he knoweth their works: and therefore he shall bring night on them, and they shall be destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He hath struck them, as being wicked, in open sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Who as it were on purpose have revolted from him, and would not understand all his ways:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>So that they caused the cry of the needy to come to him, and he heard the voice of the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For when he granteth peace, who is there that can condemn? When he hideth his countenance, who is there that can behold him, whether it regard nations, or all men?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Who maketh a man that is a hypocrite to reign for the sins of the people?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Seeing then I have spoken of God, I will not hinder thee in thy turn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>If I have erred, teach thou me: if I have spoken iniquity, I will add no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Doth God require it of thee, because it hath displeased thee? for thou begannest to speak, and not I: but if thou know any thing better, speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Let men of understanding speak to me, and let a wise man hearken to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>But Job hath spoken foolishly, and his words sound not discipline.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>My father, let Job be tried even to the end: cease not from the man of iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Because he addeth blasphemy upon his sins, let him be tied fast in the mean time amongst us: and then let him provoke God to judgment with his speeches.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="35" preferred_title="Chapter 35">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Moreover Eliu spoke these words:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Doth thy thought seem right to thee, that thou shouldst say: I am more just than God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For thou saidst: That which is right doth not please thee: or what will it profit thee if I sin?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Therefore I will answer thy words, and thy friends with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Look up to heaven and see, and behold the sky, that it is higher than thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If thou sin, what shalt thou hurt him? and if thy iniquities be multiplied, what shalt thou do against him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And if thou do justly, what shalt thou give him, or what shall he receive of thy hand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thy wickedness may hurt a man that is like thee: and thy justice may help the son of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>By reason of the multitude of oppressors they shall cry out: and shall wail for the violence of the arm of tyrants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And he hath not said: Where is God, who made me, who hath given songs in the night?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Who teacheth us more than the beasts of the earth, and instructeth us more than the fowls of the air.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>There shall they cry, and he will not hear, because of the pride of evil men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>God therefore will not hear in vain, and the Almighty will look into the causes of every one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Yea when thou shalt say: He considereth not: be judged before him, and expect him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For he doth not now bring on his fury, neither doth he revenge wickedness exceedingly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore Job openeth his mouth in vain, and multiplieth words without knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="36" preferred_title="Chapter 36">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Eliu also proceeded, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Suffer me a little, and I will shewthee: for I have yet somewhat to speak in God&#8217;s behalf.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I will repeat my knowledge from the beginning, and I will prove my Maker just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For indeed my words are without a lie, and perfect knowledge shall be proved to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>God doth not cast away the mighty, whereas he himself also is mighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But he saveth not the wicked, and he giveth judgment to the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He will not take away his eyes from the just, and he placeth kings on the throne for ever, and they are exalted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And if they shall be in chains, and be bound with the cords of poverty:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He shall shew them their works, and their wicked deeds, because they have been violent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He also shall open their ear, to correct them: and shall speak, that they may return from iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If they shall hear and observe, they shall accomplish their days in good, and their years in glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But if they hear not, they shall pass by the sword, and shall be consumed in folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Dissemblers and crafty men prove the wrath of God, neither shall they cry when they are bound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Their soul shall die in a storm, and their life among the effeminate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He shall deliver the poor out of his distress, and shall open his ear in affliction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore he shall set thee at large out of the narrow mouth, and which hath no foundation under it: and the rest of thy table shall be full of fatness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thy cause hath been judged as that of the wicked, cause and judgment thou shalt recover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore let not anger overcome thee to oppress any man: neither let multitude of gifts turn thee aside.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Lay down thy greatness without tribulation, and all the mighty of strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Prolong not the night that people may come up for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Beware thou turn not aside to iniquity: for this thou hast begun to follow after misery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Behold, God is high in his strength, and none is like him among the lawgivers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Who can search out his ways? or who can say to him: Thou hast wrought iniquity?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Remember that thou knowest not his work, concerning which men have sung.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>All men see him, every one beholdeth afar off.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Behold, God is great, exceeding our knowledge: the number of his years is inestimable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He lifteth up the drops of rain, and poureth out showers like floods:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Which flow from the clouds that cover all above.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>If he will spread out clouds as his tent,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And lighten with his light from above, he shall cover also the ends of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For by these he judgeth people, and giveth food to many mortals.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>In his hands he hideth the light, and commandeth it to come again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He sheweth his friend concerning it, that it is his possession, and that he may come up to it.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="37" preferred_title="Chapter 37">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At this my heart trembleth, and is moved out of its place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear ye attentively the terror of his voice, and the sound that cometh out of his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He beholdeth under all the heavens, and his light is upon the ends of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>After it a noise shall roar, he shall thunder with the voice of his majesty, and shall not be found out, when his voice shall be heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>God shall thunder wonderfully with his voice, he that doth great and unsearchable things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He commandeth the snow to go down upon the earth, and the winter rain, and the shower of his strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He sealeth up the hand of all men, that every one may know his works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the beast shall go into his covert, and shall abide in his den.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Out of the inner parts shall a tempest come, and cold out of the north.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When God bloweth there cometh frost, and again the waters are poured out abundantly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Corn desireth clouds, and the clouds spread their light:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Which go round about, whithersoever the will of him that governeth them shall lead them, to whatsoever he shall command them upon the face of the whole earth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Whether in one tribe, or in his own land, or in what place soever of his mercy he shall command them to be found.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Hearken to these things, Job: Stand, and consider the wondrous works of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Dost thou know when God commanded the rains, to shew his light of his clouds?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Knowest thou the great paths of the clouds, and the perfect knowledges?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Are not thy garments hot, when the south wind blows upon the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thou perhaps hast made the heavens with him, which are most strong, as if they were of molten brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Shew us what we may say to him: for we are wrapped up in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Who shall tell him the things I speak? even if a man shall speak, he shall be swallowed up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But now they see not the light: the air on a sudden shall be thickened into clouds, and the wind shall pass and drive them away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Cold cometh out of the north, and to God praise with fear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>We cannot find him worthily: he is great in strength, and in judgment, and in justice, and he is ineffable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore men shall fear him, and all that seem to themselves to be wise, shall not dare to behold him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="38" preferred_title="Chapter 38">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord answered Job out of a whirlwind, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Who is this that wrappeth up sentences in unskilful words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Gird up thy loins like a man: I will ask thee, and answer thou me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Where wast thou when I laid the foundations of the earth? tell me if thou hast understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who hath laid the measures thereof, if thou knowest? or who hath stretched the line upon it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon what are its bases grounded? or who laid the corner stone thereof,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When the morning stars praised me together, and all the sons of God made a joyful melody?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who shut up the sea with doors, when it broke forth as issuing out of the womb:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When I made a cloud the garment thereof, and wrapped it in a mist as in swaddling bands?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I set my bounds around it, and made it bars and doors:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And I said: Hitherto thou shalt come, and shalt go no further, and here thou shalt break thy swelling waves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Didst thou since thy birth command the morning, and shew the dawning of the day its place?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And didst thou hold the extremities of the earth shaking them, and hast thou shaken the ungodly out of it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The seal shall be restored as clay, and shall stand as a garment:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>From the wicked their light shall be taken away, and the high arm shall be broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Hast thou entered into the depths of the sea, and walked in the lowest parts of the deep?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Have the gates of death been opened to thee, and hast thou seen the darksome doors?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Hast thou considered the breadth of the earth? tell me, if thou knowest all things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Where is the way where light dwelleth, and where is the place of darkness:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>That thou mayst bring every thing to its own bounds, and understand the paths of the house thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Didst thou know then that thou shouldst be born? and didst thou know the number of thy days?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Hast thou entered into the storehouses of the snow, or hast thou beheld the treasures of the hail:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Which I have prepared for the time of the enemy, against the day of battle and war?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>By what way is the light spread, and heat divided upon the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Who gave a course to violent showers, or a way for noisy thunder:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>That it should rain on the earth without man in the wilderness, where no mortal dwelleth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>That it should fill the desert and desolate land, and should bring forth green grass?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Who is the father of rain? or who begot the drops of dew?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Out of whose womb came the ice; and the frost from heaven who hath gendered it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The waters are hardened like a stone, and the surface of the deep is congealed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Shalt thou be able to join together the shining stars the Pleiades, or canst thou stop the turning about of Arcturus?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Canst thou bring forth the day star in its time, and make the evening star to rise upon the children of the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Dost thou know the order of heaven, and canst thou set down the reason thereof on the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Canst thou lift up thy voice to the clouds, that an abundance of waters may cover thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Canst thou send lightnings, and will they go, and will they return and say to thee: Here we are?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Who hath put wisdom in the heart of man? or who gave the cock understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Who can declare the order of the heavens, or who can make the harmony of heaven to sleep?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>When was the dust poured on the earth, and the clods fastened together?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Wilt thou take the prey for the lioness, and satisfy the appetite of her whelps,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>When they couch in the dens and lie in wait in holes?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Who provideth food for the raven, when her young ones cry to God, wandering about, because they have no meat?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="39" preferred_title="Chapter 39">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Knowest thou the time when the wild goats bring forth among the rocks, or hast thou observed the hinds when they fawn?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hast thou numbered the months of their conceiving, or knowest thou the time when they bring forth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They bow themselves to bring forth young, and they cast them, and send forth roarings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Their young are weaned and go to feed: they go forth, and return not to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who hath sent out the wild ass free, and who hath loosed his bonds?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>To whom I have given a house in the wilderness, and his dwellings in the barren land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He scorneth the multitude of the city, he heareth not the cry of the driver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He looketh round about the mountains of his pasture, and seeketh for every green thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Shall the rhinoceros be willing to serve thee, or will he stay at thy crib?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Canst thou bind the rhinoceros with thy thong to plough, or will he break the clods of the valleys after thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Wilt thou have confidence in his great strength, and leave thy labours to him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Wilt thou trust him that he will render thee the seed, and gather it into thy barnfloor?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The wing of the ostrich is like the wings of the heron, and of the hawk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When she leaveth her eggs on the earth, thou perhaps wilt warm them in the dust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>She forgetteth that the foot may tread upon them, or that the beasts of the field may break them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>She is hardened against her young ones, as though they were not hers, she hath laboured in vain, no fear constraining her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For God hath deprived her of wisdom, neither hath he given her understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When time shall be, she setteth up her wings on high: she scorneth the horse and his rider.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Wilt thou give strength to the horse, or clothe his neck with neighing?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Wilt thou lift him up like the locusts? the glory of his nostrils is terror.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He breaketh up the earth with his hoof, he pranceth boldly, he goeth forward to meet armed men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He despiseth fear, he turneth not his back to the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Above him shall the quiver rattle, the spear and shield shall glitter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Chasing and raging he swalloweth the ground, neither doth he make account when the noise of the trumpet soundeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When he heareth the trumpet he saith: Ha, ha: he smelleth the battle afar off, the encouraging of the captains, and the shouting of the army.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Doth the hawk wax feathered by thy wisdom, spreading her wings to the south?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Will the eagle mount up at thy command, and make her nest in high places?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>She abideth among the rocks, and dwelleth among cragged flints, and stony hills, where there is no access.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>From thence she looketh for the prey, and her eyes behold afar off.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Her young ones shall suck up blood: and wheresoever the carcass shall be, she is immediately there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And the Lord went on, and said to Job:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Shall he that contendeth with God be so easily silenced? surely he that reproveth God, ought to answer him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then Job answered the Lord, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>What can I answer, who hath spoken inconsiderately? I will lay my hand upon my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>One thing I have spoken, which I wish I had not said: and another, to which I will add no more.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="40" preferred_title="Chapter 40">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the Lord answering Job out of the whirlwind, said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Gird up thy loins like a man: I will ask thee, and do thou tell me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Wilt thou make void my judgment: and condemn me, that thou mayst be justified?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And hast thou an arm like God, and canst thou thunder with a voice like him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Clothe thyself with beauty, and set thyself up on high, and be glorious, and put on goodly garments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Scatter the proud in thy indignation, and behold every arrogant man, and humble him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Look on all that are proud, and confound them, and crush the wicked in their place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Hide them in the dust together, and plunge their faces into the pit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then I will confess that thy right hand is able to save thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Behold behemoth whom I made with thee, he eateth grass like an ox.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>His strength is in his loins, and his force in the navel of his belly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>He setteth up his tail like a cedar, the sinews of his testicles are wrapped together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>His bones are like pipes of brass, his gristle like plates of iron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He is the beginning of the ways of God, who made him, he will apply his sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>To him the mountains bring forth grass: there all the beasts of the field shall play.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He sleepeth under the shadow, in the covert of the reed, and in moist places.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The shades cover his shadow, the willows of the brook shall compass him about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold, he will drink up a river, and not wonder: and he trusteth that the Jordan may run into his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>In his eyes as with a hook he shall take him, and bore through his nostrils with stakes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Canst thou draw out the leviathan with a hook, or canst thou tie his tongue with a cord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Canst thou put a ring in his nose, or bore through his jaw with a buckle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Will he make many supplications to thee, or speak soft words to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Will he make a covenant with thee, and wilt thou take him to be a servant for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Shalt thou play with him as with a bird, or tie him up for thy handmaids?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Shall friends cut him in pieces, shall merchants divide him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Wilt thou fill nets with his skin, and the cabins of fishes with his head?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Lay thy hand upon him: remember the battle, and speak no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Behold his hope shall fail him, and in the sight of all he shall be cast down.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="41" preferred_title="Chapter 41">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I WILL not stir him up, like one that is cruel: for who can resist my countenance?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Who hath given me before that I should repay him? All things that are under heaven are mine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I will not spare him, nor his mighty words, and framed to make supplication.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Who can discover the face of his garment? or who can go into the midst of his mouth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who can open the doors of his face? his teeth are terrible round about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>His body is like molten shields, shut close up with scales pressing upon one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>One is joined to another, and not so much as any air can come between them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>They stick one to another and they hold one another fast, and shall not be separated.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>His sneezing is like the shining of fire, and his eyes like the eyelids of the morning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Out of his mouth go forth lamps, like torches of lighted fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Out of his nostrils goeth smoke, like that of a pot heated and boiling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>His breath kindleth coals, and a flame cometh forth out of his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In his neck strength shall dwell, and want goeth before his face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The members of his flesh cleave one to another: he shall send lightnings against him, and they shall not be carried to another place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>His heart shall be as hard as a stone, and as firm as a smith&#8217;s anvil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When he shall raise him up, the angels shall fear, and being affrighted shall purify themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When a sword shall lay at him, it shall not be able to hold, nor a spear, nor a breastplate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For he shall esteem iron as straw, and brass as rotten wood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The archer shall not put him to flight, the stones of the sling are to him like stubble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>As stubble will he esteem the hammer, and he will laugh him to scorn who shaketh the spear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The beams of the sun shall be under him, and he shall strew gold under him like mire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He shall make the deep sea to boil like a pot, and shall make it as when ointments boil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>A path shall shine after him, he shall esteem the deep as growing old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>There is no power upon earth that can be compared with him who was made to fear no one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He beholdeth every high thing, he is king over all the children of pride.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="42" preferred_title="Chapter 42">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Job answered the Lord, and said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I know that thou canst do all things, and no thought is hid from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Who is this that hideth counsel without knowledge? Therefore I have spoken unwisely, and things that above measure exceeded my knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hear, and I will speak: I will ask thee, and do thou tell me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>With the hearing of the ear, I have heard thee, but now my eye seeth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore I reprehend myself, and do penance in dust and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And after the Lord had spoken these words to Job, he said to Eliphaz the Themanite: My wrath is kindled against thee, and against thy two friends, because you have not spoken the thing that is right before me, as my servant Job hath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Take unto you therefore seven oxen, and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer for yourselves a holocaust: and my servant Job shall pray for you: his face I will accept, that folly be not imputed to you: for you have not spoken right things before me, as my servant Job hath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So Eliphaz the Themanite, and Baldad the Suhite, and Sophar the Naamathite went, and did as the Lord had spoken to them, and the Lord accepted the face of Job.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The Lord also was turned at the penance of Job, when he prayed for his friends. And the Lord gave Job twice as much as he had before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And all his brethren came to him, and all his sisters, and all that knew him before, and they ate bread with him in his house: and bemoaned him, and comforted him upon all the evil that God had brought upon him. And every man gave him one ewe, and one earring of gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the Lord blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning. And he had fourteen thousand sheep, and six thousand camels, and a thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand she asses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And he had seven sons, and three daughters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he called the name of one Dies, and the name of the second Cassia, and the name of the third Cornustibii.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And there were not found in all the earth women so beautiful as the daughters of Job: and their father gave them inheritance among their brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And Job lived after these things, a hundred and forty years, and he saw his children, and his children&#8217;s children, unto the fourth generation, and he died an old man, and full of days.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>