<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Chapter 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy, a brother: to Philemon, our beloved and fellow labourer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And to Appia, our dearest sister, and to Archippus, our fellow soldier, and to the church which is in thy house:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Grace to you and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I give thanks to my God, always making a remembrance of thee in my prayers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Hearing of thy charity and faith, which thou hast in the Lord Jesus, and towards all the saints:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>That the communication of thy faith may be made evident in the acknowledgment of every good work, that is in you in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For I have had great joy and consolation in thy charity, because the bowels of the saints have been refreshed by thee, brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Wherefore though I have much confidence in Christ Jesus, to command thee that which is to the purpose:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For charity sake I rather beseech, whereas thou art such a one, as Paul an old man, and now a prisoner also of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I beseech thee for my son, whom I have begotten in my bands, Onesimus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Who hath been heretofore unprofitable to thee, but now is profitable both to me and thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whom I have sent back to thee. And do thou receive him as my own bowels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Whom I would have retained with me, that in thy stead he might have ministered to me in the bands of the gospel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But without thy counsel I would do nothing: that thy good deed might not be as it were of necessity, but voluntary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For perhaps he therefore departed for a season from thee, that thou mightest receive him again for ever:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Not now as a servant, but instead of a servant, a most dear brother, especially to me: but how much more to thee both in the flesh and in the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If therefore thou count me a partner, receive him as myself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And if he hath wronged thee in any thing, or is in thy debt, put that to my account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I Paul have written it with my own hand: I will repay it: not to say to thee, that thou owest me thy own self also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Yea, brother. May I enjoy thee in the Lord. Refresh my bowels in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Trusting in thy obedience, I have written to thee: knowing that thou wilt also do more than I say.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But withal prepare me also a lodging. For I hope that through your prayers I shall be given unto you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>There salute thee Epaphras, my fellow prisoner in Christ Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke my fellow labourers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>