<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy </content>
            <content kind="EM">our</content>
            <content> brother, unto the church of God which is at Corinth, with all the saints which are in all Achaia:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Grace </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> to you and peace from God our Father, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">from</content>
            <content> the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Blessed </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comfort;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Who comforteth us in all our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort them which are in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith we ourselves are comforted of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For as the sufferings of Christ abound in us, so our consolation also aboundeth by Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And whether we be afflicted, </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> for your consolation and salvation, which is effectual in the enduring of the same sufferings which we also suffer: or whether we be comforted, </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> for your consolation and salvation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And our hope of you </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> stedfast, knowing, that as ye are partakers of the sufferings, so </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall ye be</content>
            <content> also of the consolation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For we would not, brethren, have you ignorant of our trouble which came to us in Asia, that we were pressed out of measure, above strength, insomuch that we despaired even of life:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>But we had the sentence of death in ourselves, that we should not trust in ourselves, but in God which raiseth the dead:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Who delivered us from so great a death, and doth deliver: in whom we trust that he will yet deliver </content>
            <content kind="EM">us</content>
            <content>;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Ye also helping together by prayer for us, that for the gift </content>
            <content kind="EM">bestowed</content>
            <content> upon us by the means of many persons thanks may be given by many on our behalf.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For our rejoicing is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in simplicity and godly sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our conversation in the world, and more abundantly to you-ward.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For we write none other things unto you, than what ye read or acknowledge; and I trust ye shall acknowledge even to the end;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>As also ye have acknowledged us in part, that we are your rejoicing, even as ye also </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> ours in the day of the Lord Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And in this confidence I was minded to come unto you before, that ye might have a second benefit;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And to pass by you into Macedonia, and to come again out of Macedonia unto you, and of you to be brought on my way toward Judaea.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>When I therefore was thus minded, did I use lightness? or the things that I purpose, do I purpose according to the flesh, that with me there should be yea yea, and nay nay?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> God </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> true, our word toward you was not yea and nay.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>For the Son of God, Jesus Christ, who was preached among you by us, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> by me and Silvanus and Timotheus, was not yea and nay, but in him was yea.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For all the promises of God in him </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> yea, and in him Amen, unto the glory of God by us.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Now he which stablisheth us with you in Christ, and hath anointed us, </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> God;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Who hath also sealed us, and given the earnest of the Spirit in our hearts.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Moreover I call God for a record upon my soul, that to spare you I came not as yet unto Corinth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Not for that we have dominion over your faith, but are helpers of your joy: for by faith ye stand.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>But I determined this with myself, that I would not come again to you in heaviness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>For if I make you sorry, who is he then that maketh me glad, but the same which is made sorry by me?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And I wrote this same unto you, lest, when I came, I should have sorrow from them of whom I ought to rejoice; having confidence in you all, that my joy is </content>
            <content kind="EM">the joy</content>
            <content> of you all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For out of much affliction and anguish of heart I wrote unto you with many tears; not that ye should be grieved, but that ye might know the love which I have more abundantly unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But if any have caused grief, he hath not grieved me, but in part: that I may not overcharge you all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Sufficient to such a man </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> this punishment, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">was inflicted</content>
            <content> of many.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>So that contrariwise ye </content>
            <content kind="EM">ought</content>
            <content> rather to forgive </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content>, and comfort </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content>, lest perhaps such a one should be swallowed up with overmuch sorrow.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Wherefore I beseech you that ye would confirm </content>
            <content kind="EM">your</content>
            <content> love toward him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For to this end also did I write, that I might know the proof of you, whether ye be obedient in all things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>To whom ye forgive any thing, I </content>
            <content kind="EM">forgive</content>
            <content> also: for if I forgave any thing, to whom I forgave </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>, for your sakes </content>
            <content kind="EM">forgave I it</content>
            <content> in the person of Christ;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Lest Satan should get an advantage of us: for we are not ignorant of his devices.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Furthermore, when I came to Troas to </content>
            <content kind="EM">preach</content>
            <content> Christ's gospel, and a door was opened unto me of the Lord,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>I had no rest in my spirit, because I found not Titus my brother: but taking my leave of them, I went from thence into Macedonia.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Now thanks </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> unto God, which always causeth us to triumph in Christ, and maketh manifest the savour of his knowledge by us in every place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>For we are unto God a sweet savour of Christ, in them that are saved, and in them that perish:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>To the one </content>
            <content kind="EM">we are</content>
            <content> the savour of death unto death; and to the other the savour of life unto life. And who </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> sufficient for these things?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>For we are not as many, which corrupt the word of God: but as of sincerity, but as of God, in the sight of God speak we in Christ.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Do we begin again to commend ourselves? or need we, as some </content>
            <content kind="EM">others</content>
            <content>, epistles of commendation to you, or </content>
            <content kind="EM">letters</content>
            <content> of commendation from you?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Ye are our epistle written in our hearts, known and read of all men:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content kind="EM">Forasmuch as ye are</content>
            <content> manifestly declared to be the epistle of Christ ministered by us, written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God; not in tables of stone, but in fleshy tables of the heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And such trust have we through Christ to God-ward:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Not that we are sufficient of ourselves to think any thing as of ourselves; but our sufficiency </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> of God;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Who also hath made us able ministers of the new testament; not of the letter, but of the spirit: for the letter killeth, but the spirit giveth life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But if the ministration of death, written </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> engraven in stones, was glorious, so that the children of Israel could not stedfastly behold the face of Moses for the glory of his countenance; which </content>
            <content kind="EM">glory</content>
            <content> was to be done away:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>How shall not the ministration of the spirit be rather glorious?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For if the ministration of condemnation </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> glory, much more doth the ministration of righteousness exceed in glory.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>For even that which was made glorious had no glory in this respect, by reason of the glory that excelleth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>For if that which is done away </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> glorious, much more that which remaineth </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> glorious.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Seeing then that we have such hope, we use great plainness of speech:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And not as Moses, </content>
            <content kind="EM">which</content>
            <content> put a vail over his face, that the children of Israel could not stedfastly look to the end of that which is abolished:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But their minds were blinded: for until this day remaineth the same vail untaken away in the reading of the old testament; which </content>
            <content kind="EM">vail</content>
            <content> is done away in Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>But even unto this day, when Moses is read, the vail is upon their heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Nevertheless when it shall turn to the Lord, the vail shall be taken away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Now the Lord is that Spirit: and where the Spirit of the Lord </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content>, there </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> liberty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But we all, with open face beholding as in a glass the glory of the Lord, are changed into the same image from glory to glory, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> as by the Spirit of the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Therefore seeing we have this ministry, as we have received mercy, we faint not;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>But have renounced the hidden things of dishonesty, not walking in craftiness, nor handling the word of God deceitfully; but by manifestation of the truth commending ourselves to every man's conscience in the sight of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>But if our gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>In whom the god of this world hath blinded the minds of them which believe not, lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ, who is the image of God, should shine unto them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For we preach not ourselves, but Christ Jesus the Lord; and ourselves your servants for Jesus' sake.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>For God, who commanded the light to shine out of darkness, hath shined in our hearts, to </content>
            <content kind="EM">give</content>
            <content> the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the excellency of the power may be of God, and not of us.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content kind="EM">We are</content>
            <content> troubled on every side, yet not distressed; </content>
            <content kind="EM">we are</content>
            <content> perplexed, but not in despair;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Persecuted, but not forsaken; cast down, but not destroyed;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Always bearing about in the body the dying of the Lord Jesus, that the life also of Jesus might be made manifest in our body.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>For we which live are alway delivered unto death for Jesus' sake, that the life also of Jesus might be made manifest in our mortal flesh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>So then death worketh in us, but life in you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>We having the same spirit of faith, according as it is written, I believed, and therefore have I spoken; we also believe, and therefore speak;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Knowing that he which raised up the Lord Jesus shall raise up us also by Jesus, and shall present </content>
            <content kind="EM">us</content>
            <content> with you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>For all things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> for your sakes, that the abundant grace might through the thanksgiving of many redound to the glory of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>For which cause we faint not; but though our outward man perish, yet the inward </content>
            <content kind="EM">man</content>
            <content> is renewed day by day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>For our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> eternal weight of glory;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>While we look not at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen: for the things which are seen </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> temporal; but the things which are not seen </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> eternal.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>For we know that if our earthly house of </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building of God, an house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>For in this we groan, earnestly desiring to be clothed upon with our house which is from heaven:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If so be that being clothed we shall not be found naked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For we that are in </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> tabernacle do groan, being burdened: not for that we would be unclothed, but clothed upon, that mortality might be swallowed up of life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Now he that hath wrought us for the selfsame thing </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> God, who also hath given unto us the earnest of the Spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Therefore </content>
            <content kind="EM">we are</content>
            <content> always confident, knowing that, whilst we are at home in the body, we are absent from the Lord:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>(For we walk by faith, not by sight:)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>We are confident, </content>
            <content kind="EM">I say</content>
            <content>, and willing rather to be absent from the body, and to be present with the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Wherefore we labour, that, whether present or absent, we may be accepted of him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>For we must all appear before the judgment seat of Christ; that every one may receive the things </content>
            <content kind="EM">done</content>
            <content> in </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> body, according to that he hath done, whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> good or bad.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Knowing therefore the terror of the Lord, we persuade men; but we are made manifest unto God; and I trust also are made manifest in your consciences.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For we commend not ourselves again unto you, but give you occasion to glory on our behalf, that ye may have somewhat to </content>
            <content kind="EM">answer</content>
            <content> them which glory in appearance, and not in heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For whether we be beside ourselves, </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> to God: or whether we be sober, </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> for your cause.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For the love of Christ constraineth us; because we thus judge, that if one died for all, then were all dead:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> he died for all, that they which live should not henceforth live unto themselves, but unto him which died for them, and rose again.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Wherefore henceforth know we no man after the flesh: yea, though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now henceforth know we </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> no more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Therefore if any man </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> in Christ, </content>
            <content kind="EM">he is</content>
            <content> a new creature: old things are passed away; behold, all things are become new.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And all things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> of God, who hath reconciled us to himself by Jesus Christ, and hath given to us the ministry of reconciliation;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>To wit, that God was in Christ, reconciling the world unto himself, not imputing their trespasses unto them; and hath committed unto us the word of reconciliation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Now then we are ambassadors for Christ, as though God did beseech </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content> by us: we pray </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content> in Christ's stead, be ye reconciled to God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For he hath made him </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content> sin for us, who knew no sin; that we might be made the righteousness of God in him.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>We then, </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> workers together </content>
            <content kind="EM">with him</content>
            <content>, beseech </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content> also that ye receive not the grace of God in vain.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>(For he saith, I have heard thee in a time accepted, and in the day of salvation have I succoured thee: behold, now </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the accepted time; behold, now </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the day of salvation.)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Giving no offence in any thing, that the ministry be not blamed:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>But in all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> approving ourselves as the ministers of God, in much patience, in afflictions, in necessities, in distresses,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>In stripes, in imprisonments, in tumults, in labours, in watchings, in fastings;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>By pureness, by knowledge, by longsuffering, by kindness, by the Holy Ghost, by love unfeigned,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>By the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteousness on the right hand and on the left,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>By honour and dishonour, by evil report and good report: as deceivers, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">yet</content>
            <content> true;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>As unknown, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">yet</content>
            <content> well known; as dying, and, behold, we live; as chastened, and not killed;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>As sorrowful, yet alway rejoicing; as poor, yet making many rich; as having nothing, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">yet</content>
            <content> possessing all things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>O </content>
            <content kind="EM">ye</content>
            <content> Corinthians, our mouth is open unto you, our heart is enlarged.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Ye are not straitened in us, but ye are straitened in your own bowels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Now for a recompence in the same, (I speak as unto </content>
            <content kind="EM">my</content>
            <content> children,) be ye also enlarged.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Be ye not unequally yoked together with unbelievers: for what fellowship hath righteousness with unrighteousness? and what communion hath light with darkness?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And what concord hath Christ with Belial? or what part hath he that believeth with an infidel?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And what agreement hath the temple of God with idols? for ye are the temple of the living God; as God hath said, I will dwell in them, and walk in </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content>; and I will be their God, and they shall be my people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye separate, saith the Lord, and touch not the unclean </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content>; and I will receive you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And will be a Father unto you, and ye shall be my sons and daughters, saith the Lord Almighty.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Having therefore these promises, dearly beloved, let us cleanse ourselves from all filthiness of the flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Receive us; we have wronged no man, we have corrupted no man, we have defrauded no man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I speak not </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> to condemn </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content>: for I have said before, that ye are in our hearts to die and live with </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Great </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> my boldness of speech toward you, great </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> my glorying of you: I am filled with comfort, I am exceeding joyful in all our tribulation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For, when we were come into Macedonia, our flesh had no rest, but we were troubled on every side; without </content>
            <content kind="EM">were</content>
            <content> fightings, within </content>
            <content kind="EM">were</content>
            <content> fears.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Nevertheless God, that comforteth those that are cast down, comforted us by the coming of Titus;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And not by his coming only, but by the consolation wherewith he was comforted in you, when he told us your earnest desire, your mourning, your fervent mind toward me; so that I rejoiced the more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For though I made you sorry with a letter, I do not repent, though I did repent: for I perceive that the same epistle hath made you sorry, though </content>
            <content kind="EM">it were</content>
            <content> but for a season.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Now I rejoice, not that ye were made sorry, but that ye sorrowed to repentance: for ye were made sorry after a godly manner, that ye might receive damage by us in nothing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>For godly sorrow worketh repentance to salvation not to be repented of: but the sorrow of the world worketh death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>For behold this selfsame thing, that ye sorrowed after a godly sort, what carefulness it wrought in you, yea, </content>
            <content kind="EM">what</content>
            <content> clearing of yourselves, yea, </content>
            <content kind="EM">what</content>
            <content> indignation, yea, </content>
            <content kind="EM">what</content>
            <content> fear, yea, </content>
            <content kind="EM">what</content>
            <content> vehement desire, yea, </content>
            <content kind="EM">what</content>
            <content> zeal, yea, </content>
            <content kind="EM">what</content>
            <content> revenge! In all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> ye have approved yourselves to be clear in this matter.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Wherefore, though I wrote unto you, </content>
            <content kind="EM">I did it</content>
            <content> not for his cause that had done the wrong, nor for his cause that suffered wrong, but that our care for you in the sight of God might appear unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Therefore we were comforted in your comfort: yea, and exceedingly the more joyed we for the joy of Titus, because his spirit was refreshed by you all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For if I have boasted any thing to him of you, I am not ashamed; but as we spake all things to you in truth, even so our boasting, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">I made</content>
            <content> before Titus, is found a truth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And his inward affection is more abundant toward you, whilst he remembereth the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling ye received him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I rejoice therefore that I have confidence in you in all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Moreover, brethren, we do you to wit of the grace of God bestowed on the churches of Macedonia;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>How that in a great trial of affliction the abundance of their joy and their deep poverty abounded unto the riches of their liberality.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>For to </content>
            <content kind="EM">their</content>
            <content> power, I bear record, yea, and beyond </content>
            <content kind="EM">their</content>
            <content> power </content>
            <content kind="EM">they were</content>
            <content> willing of themselves;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Praying us with much intreaty that we would receive the gift, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">take upon us</content>
            <content> the fellowship of the ministering to the saints.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">this they did</content>
            <content>, not as we hoped, but first gave their own selves to the Lord, and unto us by the will of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Insomuch that we desired Titus, that as he had begun, so he would also finish in you the same grace also.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Therefore, as ye abound in every </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing, in</content>
            <content> faith, and utterance, and knowledge, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> all diligence, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> your love to us, </content>
            <content kind="EM">see</content>
            <content> that ye abound in this grace also.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>I speak not by commandment, but by occasion of the forwardness of others, and to prove the sincerity of your love.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that, though he was rich, yet for your sakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might be rich.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And herein I give </content>
            <content kind="EM">my</content>
            <content> advice: for this is expedient for you, who have begun before, not only to do, but also to be forward a year ago.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Now therefore perform the doing </content>
            <content kind="EM">of it</content>
            <content>; that as </content>
            <content kind="EM">there was</content>
            <content> a readiness to will, so </content>
            <content kind="EM">there may be</content>
            <content> a performance also out of that which ye have.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For if there be first a willing mind, </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> accepted according to that a man hath, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> not according to that he hath not.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For </content>
            <content kind="EM">I mean</content>
            <content> not that other men be eased, and ye burdened:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But by an equality, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> now at this time your abundance </content>
            <content kind="EM">may be a supply</content>
            <content> for their want, that their abundance also may be </content>
            <content kind="EM">a supply</content>
            <content> for your want: that there may be equality:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>As it is written, He that </content>
            <content kind="EM">had gathered</content>
            <content> much had nothing over; and he that </content>
            <content kind="EM">had gathered</content>
            <content> little had no lack.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But thanks </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> to God, which put the same earnest care into the heart of Titus for you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>For indeed he accepted the exhortation; but being more forward, of his own accord he went unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And we have sent with him the brother, whose praise </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the gospel throughout all the churches;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And not </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> only, but who was also chosen of the churches to travel with us with this grace, which is administered by us to the glory of the same Lord, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">declaration of</content>
            <content> your ready mind:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Avoiding this, that no man should blame us in this abundance which is administered by us:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Providing for honest things, not only in the sight of the Lord, but also in the sight of men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And we have sent with them our brother, whom we have oftentimes proved diligent in many things, but now much more diligent, upon the great confidence which </content>
            <content kind="EM">I have</content>
            <content> in you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">any do enquire</content>
            <content> of Titus, </content>
            <content kind="EM">he is</content>
            <content> my partner and fellowhelper concerning you: or our brethren </content>
            <content kind="EM">be enquired of, they are</content>
            <content> the messengers of the churches, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the glory of Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Wherefore shew ye to them, and before the churches, the proof of your love, and of our boasting on your behalf.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>For as touching the ministering to the saints, it is superfluous for me to write to you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>For I know the forwardness of your mind, for which I boast of you to them of Macedonia, that Achaia was ready a year ago; and your zeal hath provoked very many.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Yet have I sent the brethren, lest our boasting of you should be in vain in this behalf; that, as I said, ye may be ready:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Lest haply if they of Macedonia come with me, and find you unprepared, we (that we say not, ye) should be ashamed in this same confident boasting.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Therefore I thought it necessary to exhort the brethren, that they would go before unto you, and make up beforehand your bounty, whereof ye had notice before, that the same might be ready, as </content>
            <content kind="EM">a matter of</content>
            <content> bounty, and not as </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> covetousness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>But this </content>
            <content kind="EM">I say</content>
            <content>, He which soweth sparingly shall reap also sparingly; and he which soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Every man according as he purposeth in his heart, </content>
            <content kind="EM">so let him give</content>
            <content>; not grudgingly, or of necessity: for God loveth a cheerful giver.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And God </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> able to make all grace abound toward you; that ye, always having all sufficiency in all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content>, may abound to every good work:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>(As it is written, He hath dispersed abroad; he hath given to the poor: his righteousness remaineth for ever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Now he that ministereth seed to the sower both minister bread for </content>
            <content kind="EM">your</content>
            <content> food, and multiply your seed sown, and increase the fruits of your righteousness;)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Being enriched in every thing to all bountifulness, which causeth through us thanksgiving to God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For the administration of this service not only supplieth the want of the saints, but is abundant also by many thanksgivings unto God;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Whiles by the experiment of this ministration they glorify God for your professed subjection unto the gospel of Christ, and for </content>
            <content kind="EM">your</content>
            <content> liberal distribution unto them, and unto all </content>
            <content kind="EM">men</content>
            <content>;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And by their prayer for you, which long after you for the exceeding grace of God in you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Thanks </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> unto God for his unspeakable gift.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Now I Paul myself beseech you by the meekness and gentleness of Christ, who in presence </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> base among you, but being absent am bold toward you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>But I beseech </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content>, that I may not be bold when I am present with that confidence, wherewith I think to be bold against some, which think of us as if we walked according to the flesh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>For though we walk in the flesh, we do not war after the flesh:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>(For the weapons of our warfare </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> not carnal, but mighty through God to the pulling down of strong holds;)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Casting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth itself against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And having in a readiness to revenge all disobedience, when your obedience is fulfilled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Do ye look on things after the outward appearance? If any man trust to himself that he is Christ's, let him of himself think this again, that, as he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> Christ's, even so </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> we Christ's.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For though I should boast somewhat more of our authority, which the Lord hath given us for edification, and not for your destruction, I should not be ashamed:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>That I may not seem as if I would terrify you by letters.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>For </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> letters, say they, </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> weighty and powerful; but </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> bodily presence </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> weak, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> speech contemptible.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Let such an one think this, that, such as we are in word by letters when we are absent, such </content>
            <content kind="EM">will we be</content>
            <content> also in deed when we are present.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For we dare not make ourselves of the number, or compare ourselves with some that commend themselves: but they measuring themselves by themselves, and comparing themselves among themselves, are not wise.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>But we will not boast of things without </content>
            <content kind="EM">our</content>
            <content> measure, but according to the measure of the rule which God hath distributed to us, a measure to reach even unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For we stretch not ourselves beyond </content>
            <content kind="EM">our measure</content>
            <content>, as though we reached not unto you: for we are come as far as to you also in </content>
            <content kind="EM">preaching</content>
            <content> the gospel of Christ:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Not boasting of things without </content>
            <content kind="EM">our</content>
            <content> measure, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that is</content>
            <content>, of other men's labours; but having hope, when your faith is increased, that we shall be enlarged by you according to our rule abundantly,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>To preach the gospel in the </content>
            <content kind="EM">regions</content>
            <content> beyond you, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> not to boast in another man's line of things made ready to our hand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For not he that commendeth himself is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Would to God ye could bear with me a little in </content>
            <content kind="EM">my</content>
            <content> folly: and indeed bear with me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>For I am jealous over you with godly jealousy: for I have espoused you to one husband, that I may present </content>
            <content kind="EM">you as</content>
            <content> a chaste virgin to Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>But I fear, lest by any means, as the serpent beguiled Eve through his subtilty, so your minds should be corrupted from the simplicity that is in Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For if he that cometh preacheth another Jesus, whom we have not preached, or </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> ye receive another spirit, which ye have not received, or another gospel, which ye have not accepted, ye might well bear with </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For I suppose I was not a whit behind the very chiefest apostles.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>But though </content>
            <content kind="EM">I be</content>
            <content> rude in speech, yet not in knowledge; but we have been throughly made manifest among you in all things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Have I committed an offence in abasing myself that ye might be exalted, because I have preached to you the gospel of God freely?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>I robbed other churches, taking wages </content>
            <content kind="EM">of them</content>
            <content>, to do you service.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And when I was present with you, and wanted, I was chargeable to no man: for that which was lacking to me the brethren which came from Macedonia supplied: and in all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> I have kept myself from being burdensome unto you, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">so</content>
            <content> will I keep </content>
            <content kind="EM">myself</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>As the truth of Christ is in me, no man shall stop me of this boasting in the regions of Achaia.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Wherefore? because I love you not? God knoweth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But what I do, that I will do, that I may cut off occasion from them which desire occasion; that wherein they glory, they may be found even as we.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For such </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> false apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into the apostles of Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And no marvel; for Satan himself is transformed into an angel of light.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Therefore </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> no great thing if his ministers also be transformed as the ministers of righteousness; whose end shall be according to their works.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I say again, Let no man think me a fool; if otherwise, yet as a fool receive me, that I may boast myself a little.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>That which I speak, I speak </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> not after the Lord, but as it were foolishly, in this confidence of boasting.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Seeing that many glory after the flesh, I will glory also.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>For ye suffer fools gladly, seeing ye </content>
            <content kind="EM">yourselves</content>
            <content> are wise.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For ye suffer, if a man bring you into bondage, if a man devour </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content>, if a man take </content>
            <content kind="EM">of you</content>
            <content>, if a man exalt himself, if a man smite you on the face.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>I speak as concerning reproach, as though we had been weak. Howbeit whereinsoever any is bold, (I speak foolishly,) I am bold also.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Are they Hebrews? so </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> I. Are they Israelites? so </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> I. Are they the seed of Abraham? so </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> I.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Are they ministers of Christ? (I speak as a fool) I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> more; in labours more abundant, in stripes above measure, in prisons more frequent, in deaths oft.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Of the Jews five times received I forty </content>
            <content kind="EM">stripes</content>
            <content> save one.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I stoned, thrice I suffered shipwreck, a night and a day I have been in the deep;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content kind="EM">In</content>
            <content> journeyings often, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils of waters, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils of robbers, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils by </content>
            <content kind="EM">mine own</content>
            <content> countrymen, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils by the heathen, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils in the city, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils in the wilderness, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils in the sea, </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> perils among false brethren;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>In weariness and painfulness, in watchings often, in hunger and thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Beside those things that are without, that which cometh upon me daily, the care of all the churches.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Who is weak, and I am not weak? who is offended, and I burn not?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>If I must needs glory, I will glory of the things which concern mine infirmities.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, which is blessed for evermore, knoweth that I lie not.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>In Damascus the governor under Aretas the king kept the city of the Damascenes with a garrison, desirous to apprehend me:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And through a window in a basket was I let down by the wall, and escaped his hands.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>It is not expedient for me doubtless to glory. I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I knew a man in Christ above fourteen years ago, (whether in the body, I cannot tell; or whether out of the body, I cannot tell: God knoweth;) such an one caught up to the third heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And I knew such a man, (whether in the body, or out of the body, I cannot tell: God knoweth;)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>How that he was caught up into paradise, and heard unspeakable words, which it is not lawful for a man to utter.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Of such an one will I glory: yet of myself I will not glory, but in mine infirmities.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>For though I would desire to glory, I shall not be a fool; for I will say the truth: but </content>
            <content kind="EM">now</content>
            <content> I forbear, lest any man should think of me above that which he seeth me </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content>, or </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> he heareth of me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And lest I should be exalted above measure through the abundance of the revelations, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, the messenger of Satan to buffet me, lest I should be exalted above measure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For this thing I besought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And he said unto me, </content>
            <wj>
                <content>My grace is sufficient for thee: for my strength is made perfect in weakness.</content>
            </wj>
            <content> Most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my infirmities, that the power of Christ may rest upon me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Therefore I take pleasure in infirmities, in reproaches, in necessities, in persecutions, in distresses for Christ's sake: for when I am weak, then am I strong.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>I am become a fool in glorying; ye have compelled me: for I ought to have been commended of you: for in nothing am I behind the very chiefest apostles, though I be nothing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Truly the signs of an apostle were wrought among you in all patience, in signs, and wonders, and mighty deeds.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For what is it wherein ye were inferior to other churches, except </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> that I myself was not burdensome to you? forgive me this wrong.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Behold, the third time I am ready to come to you; and I will not be burdensome to you: for I seek not yours, but you: for the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And I will very gladly spend and be spent for you; though the more abundantly I love you, the less I be loved.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But be it so, I did not burden you: nevertheless, being crafty, I caught you with guile.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Did I make a gain of you by any of them whom I sent unto you?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>I desired Titus, and with </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> I sent a brother. Did Titus make a gain of you? walked we not in the same spirit? </content>
            <content kind="EM">walked we</content>
            <content> not in the same steps?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Again, think ye that we excuse ourselves unto you? we speak before God in Christ: but </content>
            <content kind="EM">we do</content>
            <content> all things, dearly beloved, for your edifying.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For I fear, lest, when I come, I shall not find you such as I would, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> I shall be found unto you such as ye would not: lest </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> debates, envyings, wraths, strifes, backbitings, whisperings, swellings, tumults:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content kind="EM">And</content>
            <content> lest, when I come again, my God will humble me among you, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> I shall bewail many which have sinned already, and have not repented of the uncleanness and fornication and lasciviousness which they have committed.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the third </content>
            <content kind="EM">time</content>
            <content> I am coming to you. In the mouth of two or three witnesses shall every word be established.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I told you before, and foretell you, as if I were present, the second time; and being absent now I write to them which heretofore have sinned, and to all other, that, if I come again, I will not spare:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Since ye seek a proof of Christ speaking in me, which to you-ward is not weak, but is mighty in you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For though he was crucified through weakness, yet he liveth by the power of God. For we also are weak in him, but we shall live with him by the power of God toward you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Examine yourselves, whether ye be in the faith; prove your own selves. Know ye not your own selves, how that Jesus Christ is in you, except ye be reprobates?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>But I trust that ye shall know that we are not reprobates.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Now I pray to God that ye do no evil; not that we should appear approved, but that ye should do that which is honest, though we be as reprobates.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For we can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For we are glad, when we are weak, and ye are strong: and this also we wish, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> your perfection.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Therefore I write these things being absent, lest being present I should use sharpness, according to the power which the Lord hath given me to edification, and not to destruction.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Finally, brethren, farewell. Be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace; and the God of love and peace shall be with you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Greet one another with an holy kiss.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>All the saints salute you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the communion of the Holy Ghost, </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> with you all. Amen. (</content>
            <content kind="EM">The second epistle to the Corinthians was written from Philippi, a city of Macedonia, by Titus and Lucas.</content>
            <content>)</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
</book>
