<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD called unto Moses, and spake unto him out of the tabernacle of the congregation, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, If any man of you bring an offering unto the LORD, ye shall bring your offering of the cattle, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> of the herd, and of the flock.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If his offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> a burnt sacrifice of the herd, let him offer a male without blemish: he shall offer it of his own voluntary will at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And he shall put his hand upon the head of the burnt offering; and it shall be accepted for him to make atonement for him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And he shall kill the bullock before the LORD: and the priests, Aaron's sons, shall bring the blood, and sprinkle the blood round about upon the altar that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is by</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And he shall flay the burnt offering, and cut it into his pieces.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And the sons of Aaron the priest shall put fire upon the altar, and lay the wood in order upon the fire:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And the priests, Aaron's sons, shall lay the parts, the head, and the fat, in order upon the wood that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> on the fire which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the altar:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>But his inwards and his legs shall he wash in water: and the priest shall burn all on the altar, </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content> a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And if his offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> of the flocks, </content>
            <content kind="EM">namely</content>
            <content>, of the sheep, or of the goats, for a burnt sacrifice; he shall bring it a male without blemish.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And he shall kill it on the side of the altar northward before the LORD: and the priests, Aaron's sons, shall sprinkle his blood round about upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And he shall cut it into his pieces, with his head and his fat: and the priest shall lay them in order on the wood that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> on the fire which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the altar:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>But he shall wash the inwards and the legs with water: and the priest shall bring </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> all, and burn </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the altar: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And if the burnt sacrifice for his offering to the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> of fowls, then he shall bring his offering of turtledoves, or of young pigeons.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And the priest shall bring it unto the altar, and wring off his head, and burn </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> on the altar; and the blood thereof shall be wrung out at the side of the altar:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And he shall pluck away his crop with his feathers, and cast it beside the altar on the east part, by the place of the ashes:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And he shall cleave it with the wings thereof, </content>
            <content kind="EM">but</content>
            <content> shall not divide </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> asunder: and the priest shall burn it upon the altar, upon the wood that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the fire: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And when any will offer a meat offering unto the LORD, his offering shall be </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> fine flour; and he shall pour oil upon it, and put frankincense thereon:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And he shall bring it to Aaron's sons the priests: and he shall take thereout his handful of the flour thereof, and of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof; and the priest shall burn the memorial of it upon the altar, </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And the remnant of the meat offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> Aaron's and his sons': </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> a thing most holy of the offerings of the LORD made by fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And if thou bring an oblation of a meat offering baken in the oven, </content>
            <content kind="EM">it shall be</content>
            <content> unleavened cakes of fine flour mingled with oil, or unleavened wafers anointed with oil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And if thy oblation </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> a meat offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">baken</content>
            <content> in a pan, it shall be </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> fine flour unleavened, mingled with oil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Thou shalt part it in pieces, and pour oil thereon: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a meat offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And if thy oblation </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> a meat offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">baken</content>
            <content> in the fryingpan, it shall be made </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> fine flour with oil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And thou shalt bring the meat offering that is made of these things unto the LORD: and when it is presented unto the priest, he shall bring it unto the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And the priest shall take from the meat offering a memorial thereof, and shall burn </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the altar: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And that which is left of the meat offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> Aaron's and his sons': </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> a thing most holy of the offerings of the LORD made by fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>No meat offering, which ye shall bring unto the LORD, shall be made with leaven: for ye shall burn no leaven, nor any honey, in any offering of the LORD made by fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>As for the oblation of the firstfruits, ye shall offer them unto the LORD: but they shall not be burnt on the altar for a sweet savour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And every oblation of thy meat offering shalt thou season with salt; neither shalt thou suffer the salt of the covenant of thy God to be lacking from thy meat offering: with all thine offerings thou shalt offer salt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And if thou offer a meat offering of thy firstfruits unto the LORD, thou shalt offer for the meat offering of thy firstfruits green ears of corn dried by the fire, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> corn beaten out of full ears.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And thou shalt put oil upon it, and lay frankincense thereon: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a meat offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And the priest shall burn the memorial of it, </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> of the beaten corn thereof, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> of the oil thereof, with all the frankincense thereof: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And if his oblation </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> a sacrifice of peace offering, if he offer </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> of the herd; whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> a male or female, he shall offer it without blemish before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And he shall lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and kill it </content>
            <content kind="EM">at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and Aaron's sons the priests shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar round about.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And he shall offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering made by fire unto the LORD; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the inwards,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And the two kidneys, and the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> on them, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And Aaron's sons shall burn it on the altar upon the burnt sacrifice, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the wood that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> on the fire: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire, of a sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And if his offering for a sacrifice of peace offering unto the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> of the flock; male or female, he shall offer it without blemish.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>If he offer a lamb for his offering, then shall he offer it before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And he shall lay his hand upon the head of his offering, and kill it before the tabernacle of the congregation: and Aaron's sons shall sprinkle the blood thereof round about upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And he shall offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering an offering made by fire unto the LORD; the fat thereof, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the whole rump, it shall he take off hard by the backbone; and the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the inwards,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And the two kidneys, and the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon them, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And the priest shall burn it upon the altar: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> the food of the offering made by fire unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And if his offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> a goat, then he shall offer it before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And he shall lay his hand upon the head of it, and kill it before the tabernacle of the congregation: and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle the blood thereof upon the altar round about.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And he shall offer thereof his offering, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire unto the LORD; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the inwards,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And the two kidneys, and the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon them, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And the priest shall burn them upon the altar: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> the food of the offering made by fire for a sweet savour: all the fat </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the LORD'S.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content kind="EM">It shall be</content>
            <content> a perpetual statute for your generations throughout all your dwellings, that ye eat neither fat nor blood.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a soul shall sin through ignorance against any of the commandments of the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">concerning things</content>
            <content> which ought not to be done, and shall do against any of them:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If the priest that is anointed do sin according to the sin of the people; then let him bring for his sin, which he hath sinned, a young bullock without blemish unto the LORD for a sin offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And he shall bring the bullock unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation before the LORD; and shall lay his hand upon the bullock's head, and kill the bullock before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And the priest that is anointed shall take of the bullock's blood, and bring it to the tabernacle of the congregation:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And the priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle of the blood seven times before the LORD, before the vail of the sanctuary.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And the priest shall put </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> of the blood upon the horns of the altar of sweet incense before the LORD, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the tabernacle of the congregation; and shall pour all the blood of the bullock at the bottom of the altar of the burnt offering, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And he shall take off from it all the fat of the bullock for the sin offering; the fat that covereth the inwards, and all the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the inwards,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And the two kidneys, and the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon them, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> by the flanks, and the caul above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>As it was taken off from the bullock of the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the priest shall burn them upon the altar of the burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And the skin of the bullock, and all his flesh, with his head, and with his legs, and his inwards, and his dung,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Even the whole bullock shall he carry forth without the camp unto a clean place, where the ashes are poured out, and burn him on the wood with fire: where the ashes are poured out shall he be burnt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And if the whole congregation of Israel sin through ignorance, and the thing be hid from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done </content>
            <content kind="EM">somewhat against</content>
            <content> any of the commandments of the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">concerning things</content>
            <content> which should not be done, and are guilty;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>When the sin, which they have sinned against it, is known, then the congregation shall offer a young bullock for the sin, and bring him before the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And the elders of the congregation shall lay their hands upon the head of the bullock before the LORD: and the bullock shall be killed before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And the priest that is anointed shall bring of the bullock's blood to the tabernacle of the congregation:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And the priest shall dip his finger </content>
            <content kind="EM">in some</content>
            <content> of the blood, and sprinkle </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> seven times before the LORD, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> before the vail.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And he shall put </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> of the blood upon the horns of the altar which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> before the LORD, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the tabernacle of the congregation, and shall pour out all the blood at the bottom of the altar of the burnt offering, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And he shall take all his fat from him, and burn </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And he shall do with the bullock as he did with the bullock for a sin offering, so shall he do with this: and the priest shall make an atonement for them, and it shall be forgiven them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And he shall carry forth the bullock without the camp, and burn him as he burned the first bullock: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a sin offering for the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>When a ruler hath sinned, and done </content>
            <content kind="EM">somewhat</content>
            <content> through ignorance </content>
            <content kind="EM">against</content>
            <content> any of the commandments of the LORD his God </content>
            <content kind="EM">concerning things</content>
            <content> which should not be done, and is guilty;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Or if his sin, wherein he hath sinned, come to his knowledge; he shall bring his offering, a kid of the goats, a male without blemish:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the goat, and kill it in the place where they kill the burnt offering before the LORD: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a sin offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out his blood at the bottom of the altar of burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And he shall burn all his fat upon the altar, as the fat of the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the priest shall make an atonement for him as concerning his sin, and it shall be forgiven him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And if any one of the common people sin through ignorance, while he doeth </content>
            <content kind="EM">somewhat against</content>
            <content> any of the commandments of the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">concerning things</content>
            <content> which ought not to be done, and be guilty;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Or if his sin, which he hath sinned, come to his knowledge: then he shall bring his offering, a kid of the goats, a female without blemish, for his sin which he hath sinned.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering, and slay the sin offering in the place of the burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And the priest shall take of the blood thereof with his finger, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out all the blood thereof at the bottom of the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And he shall take away all the fat thereof, as the fat is taken away from off the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall burn </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the altar for a sweet savour unto the LORD; and the priest shall make an atonement for him, and it shall be forgiven him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And if he bring a lamb for a sin offering, he shall bring it a female without blemish.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And he shall lay his hand upon the head of the sin offering, and slay it for a sin offering in the place where they kill the burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>And the priest shall take of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the horns of the altar of burnt offering, and shall pour out all the blood thereof at the bottom of the altar:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>And he shall take away all the fat thereof, as the fat of the lamb is taken away from the sacrifice of the peace offerings; and the priest shall burn them upon the altar, according to the offerings made by fire unto the LORD: and the priest shall make an atonement for his sin that he hath committed, and it shall be forgiven him.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And if a soul sin, and hear the voice of swearing, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a witness, whether he hath seen or known </content>
            <content kind="EM">of it</content>
            <content>; if he do not utter </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>, then he shall bear his iniquity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Or if a soul touch any unclean thing, whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> a carcase of an unclean beast, or a carcase of unclean cattle, or the carcase of unclean creeping things, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> it be hidden from him; he also shall be unclean, and guilty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Or if he touch the uncleanness of man, whatsoever uncleanness </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> that a man shall be defiled withal, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth </content>
            <content kind="EM">of it</content>
            <content>, then he shall be guilty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Or if a soul swear, pronouncing with </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> lips to do evil, or to do good, whatsoever </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> that a man shall pronounce with an oath, and it be hid from him; when he knoweth </content>
            <content kind="EM">of it</content>
            <content>, then he shall be guilty in one of these.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And it shall be, when he shall be guilty in one of these </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content>, that he shall confess that he hath sinned in that </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content>:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the LORD for his sin which he hath sinned, a female from the flock, a lamb or a kid of the goats, for a sin offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for him concerning his sin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And if he be not able to bring a lamb, then he shall bring for his trespass, which he hath committed, two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, unto the LORD; one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And he shall bring them unto the priest, who shall offer </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> for the sin offering first, and wring off his head from his neck, but shall not divide </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> asunder:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And he shall sprinkle of the blood of the sin offering upon the side of the altar; and the rest of the blood shall be wrung out at the bottom of the altar: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a sin offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And he shall offer the second </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a burnt offering, according to the manner: and the priest shall make an atonement for him for his sin which he hath sinned, and it shall be forgiven him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>But if he be not able to bring two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, then he that sinned shall bring for his offering the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a sin offering; he shall put no oil upon it, neither shall he put </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> frankincense thereon: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a sin offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Then shall he bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his handful of it, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> a memorial thereof, and burn </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> on the altar, according to the offerings made by fire unto the LORD: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a sin offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And the priest shall make an atonement for him as touching his sin that he hath sinned in one of these, and it shall be forgiven him: and </content>
            <content kind="EM">the remnant</content>
            <content> shall be the priest's, as a meat offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>If a soul commit a trespass, and sin through ignorance, in the holy things of the LORD; then he shall bring for his trespass unto the LORD a ram without blemish out of the flocks, with thy estimation by shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for a trespass offering:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And he shall make amends for the harm that he hath done in the holy thing, and shall add the fifth part thereto, and give it unto the priest: and the priest shall make an atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering, and it shall be forgiven him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And if a soul sin, and commit any of these things which are forbidden to be done by the commandments of the LORD; though he wist </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> not, yet is he guilty, and shall bear his iniquity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And he shall bring a ram without blemish out of the flock, with thy estimation, for a trespass offering, unto the priest: and the priest shall make an atonement for him concerning his ignorance wherein he erred and wist </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> not, and it shall be forgiven him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>It </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a trespass offering: he hath certainly trespassed against the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>If a soul sin, and commit a trespass against the LORD, and lie unto his neighbour in that which was delivered him to keep, or in fellowship, or in a thing taken away by violence, or hath deceived his neighbour;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Or have found that which was lost, and lieth concerning it, and sweareth falsely; in any of all these that a man doeth, sinning therein:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Then it shall be, because he hath sinned, and is guilty, that he shall restore that which he took violently away, or the thing which he hath deceitfully gotten, or that which was delivered him to keep, or the lost thing which he found,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Or all that about which he hath sworn falsely; he shall even restore it in the principal, and shall add the fifth part more thereto, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> give it unto him to whom it appertaineth, in the day of his trespass offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the LORD, a ram without blemish out of the flock, with thy estimation, for a trespass offering, unto the priest:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And the priest shall make an atonement for him before the LORD: and it shall be forgiven him for any thing of all that he hath done in trespassing therein.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Command Aaron and his sons, saying, This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the burnt offering: It </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the burnt offering, because of the burning upon the altar all night unto the morning, and the fire of the altar shall be burning in it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And the priest shall put on his linen garment, and his linen breeches shall he put upon his flesh, and take up the ashes which the fire hath consumed with the burnt offering on the altar, and he shall put them beside the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And he shall put off his garments, and put on other garments, and carry forth the ashes without the camp unto a clean place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And the fire upon the altar shall be burning in it; it shall not be put out: and the priest shall burn wood on it every morning, and lay the burnt offering in order upon it; and he shall burn thereon the fat of the peace offerings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>The fire shall ever be burning upon the altar; it shall never go out.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the meat offering: the sons of Aaron shall offer it before the LORD, before the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And he shall take of it his handful, of the flour of the meat offering, and of the oil thereof, and all the frankincense which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the meat offering, and shall burn </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the altar </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sweet savour, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> the memorial of it, unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And the remainder thereof shall Aaron and his sons eat: with unleavened bread shall it be eaten in the holy place; in the court of the tabernacle of the congregation they shall eat it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>It shall not be baken with leaven. I have given it </content>
            <content kind="EM">unto them for</content>
            <content> their portion of my offerings made by fire; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy, as </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the sin offering, and as the trespass offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>All the males among the children of Aaron shall eat of it. </content>
            <content kind="EM">It shall be</content>
            <content> a statute for ever in your generations concerning the offerings of the LORD made by fire: every one that toucheth them shall be holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the offering of Aaron and of his sons, which they shall offer unto the LORD in the day when he is anointed; the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a meat offering perpetual, half of it in the morning, and half thereof at night.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>In a pan it shall be made with oil; </content>
            <content kind="EM">and when it is</content>
            <content> baken, thou shalt bring it in: </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the baken pieces of the meat offering shalt thou offer </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And the priest of his sons that is anointed in his stead shall offer it: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> a statute for ever unto the LORD; it shall be wholly burnt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>For every meat offering for the priest shall be wholly burnt: it shall not be eaten.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, saying, This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the sin offering: In the place where the burnt offering is killed shall the sin offering be killed before the LORD: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>The priest that offereth it for sin shall eat it: in the holy place shall it be eaten, in the court of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Whatsoever shall touch the flesh thereof shall be holy: and when there is sprinkled of the blood thereof upon any garment, thou shalt wash that whereon it was sprinkled in the holy place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>But the earthen vessel wherein it is sodden shall be broken: and if it be sodden in a brasen pot, it shall be both scoured, and rinsed in water.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>All the males among the priests shall eat thereof: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And no sin offering, whereof </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> of the blood is brought into the tabernacle of the congregation to reconcile </content>
            <content kind="EM">withal</content>
            <content> in the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>, shall be eaten: it shall be burnt in the fire.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Likewise this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the trespass offering: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>In the place where they kill the burnt offering shall they kill the trespass offering: and the blood thereof shall he sprinkle round about upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And he shall offer of it all the fat thereof; the rump, and the fat that covereth the inwards,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And the two kidneys, and the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> on them, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> by the flanks, and the caul </content>
            <content kind="EM">that is</content>
            <content> above the liver, with the kidneys, it shall he take away:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And the priest shall burn them upon the altar </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire unto the LORD: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a trespass offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Every male among the priests shall eat thereof: it shall be eaten in the holy place: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>As the sin offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content>, so </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the trespass offering: </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> one law for them: the priest that maketh atonement therewith shall have </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And the priest that offereth any man's burnt offering, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> the priest shall have to himself the skin of the burnt offering which he hath offered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And all the meat offering that is baken in the oven, and all that is dressed in the fryingpan, and in the pan, shall be the priest's that offereth it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And every meat offering, mingled with oil, and dry, shall all the sons of Aaron have, one </content>
            <content kind="EM">as much</content>
            <content> as another.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which he shall offer unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>If he offer it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer with the sacrifice of thanksgiving unleavened cakes mingled with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and cakes mingled with oil, of fine flour, fried.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Besides the cakes, he shall offer </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> his offering leavened bread with the sacrifice of thanksgiving of his peace offerings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And of it he shall offer one out of the whole oblation </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> an heave offering unto the LORD, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> it shall be the priest's that sprinkleth the blood of the peace offerings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving shall be eaten the same day that it is offered; he shall not leave any of it until the morning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But if the sacrifice of his offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> a vow, or a voluntary offering, it shall be eaten the same day that he offereth his sacrifice: and on the morrow also the remainder of it shall be eaten:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But the remainder of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burnt with fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings be eaten at all on the third day, it shall not be accepted, neither shall it be imputed unto him that offereth it: it shall be an abomination, and the soul that eateth of it shall bear his iniquity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And the flesh that toucheth any unclean </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content> shall not be eaten; it shall be burnt with fire: and as for the flesh, all that be clean shall eat thereof.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>But the soul that eateth </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">pertain</content>
            <content> unto the LORD, having his uncleanness upon him, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Moreover the soul that shall touch any unclean </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing, as</content>
            <content> the uncleanness of man, or </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> unclean beast, or any abominable unclean </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content>, and eat of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">pertain</content>
            <content> unto the LORD, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Ye shall eat no manner of fat, of ox, or of sheep, or of goat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And the fat of the beast that dieth of itself, and the fat of that which is torn with beasts, may be used in any other use: but ye shall in no wise eat of it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>For whosoever eateth the fat of the beast, of which men offer an offering made by fire unto the LORD, even the soul that eateth </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> shall be cut off from his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Moreover ye shall eat no manner of blood, </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether it be</content>
            <content> of fowl or of beast, in any of your dwellings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Whatsoever soul </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> that eateth any manner of blood, even that soul shall be cut off from his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, He that offereth the sacrifice of his peace offerings unto the LORD shall bring his oblation unto the LORD of the sacrifice of his peace offerings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>His own hands shall bring the offerings of the LORD made by fire, the fat with the breast, it shall he bring, that the breast may be waved </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And the priest shall burn the fat upon the altar: but the breast shall be Aaron's and his sons'.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And the right shoulder shall ye give unto the priest </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> an heave offering of the sacrifices of your peace offerings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>He among the sons of Aaron, that offereth the blood of the peace offerings, and the fat, shall have the right shoulder for </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> part.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>For the wave breast and the heave shoulder have I taken of the children of Israel from off the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and have given them unto Aaron the priest and unto his sons by a statute for ever from among the children of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is the portion</content>
            <content> of the anointing of Aaron, and of the anointing of his sons, out of the offerings of the LORD made by fire, in the day </content>
            <content kind="EM">when</content>
            <content> he presented them to minister unto the LORD in the priest's office;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Which the LORD commanded to be given them of the children of Israel, in the day that he anointed them, </content>
            <content kind="EM">by</content>
            <content> a statute for ever throughout their generations.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the burnt offering, of the meat offering, and of the sin offering, and of the trespass offering, and of the consecrations, and of the sacrifice of the peace offerings;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Which the LORD commanded Moses in mount Sinai, in the day that he commanded the children of Israel to offer their oblations unto the LORD, in the wilderness of Sinai.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments, and the anointing oil, and a bullock for the sin offering, and two rams, and a basket of unleavened bread;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And gather thou all the congregation together unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And Moses did as the LORD commanded him; and the assembly was gathered together unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And Moses said unto the congregation, This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the thing which the LORD commanded to be done.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And Moses brought Aaron and his sons, and washed them with water.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And he put upon him the coat, and girded him with the girdle, and clothed him with the robe, and put the ephod upon him, and he girded him with the curious girdle of the ephod, and bound </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> unto him therewith.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And he put the breastplate upon him: also he put in the breastplate the Urim and the Thummim.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And he put the mitre upon his head; also upon the mitre, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> upon his forefront, did he put the golden plate, the holy crown; as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> therein, and sanctified them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And he sprinkled thereof upon the altar seven times, and anointed the altar and all his vessels, both the laver and his foot, to sanctify them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And he poured of the anointing oil upon Aaron's head, and anointed him, to sanctify him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And Moses brought Aaron's sons, and put coats upon them, and girded them with girdles, and put bonnets upon them; as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And he brought the bullock for the sin offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the bullock for the sin offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And he slew </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>; and Moses took the blood, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the horns of the altar round about with his finger, and purified the altar, and poured the blood at the bottom of the altar, and sanctified it, to make reconciliation upon it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And he took all the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> upon the inwards, and the caul </content>
            <content kind="EM">above</content>
            <content> the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and Moses burned </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But the bullock, and his hide, his flesh, and his dung, he burnt with fire without the camp; as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And he brought the ram for the burnt offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And he killed </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>; and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And he cut the ram into pieces; and Moses burnt the head, and the pieces, and the fat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And he washed the inwards and the legs in water; and Moses burnt the whole ram upon the altar: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> a burnt sacrifice for a sweet savour, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire unto the LORD; as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And he brought the other ram, the ram of consecration: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands upon the head of the ram.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And he slew </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>; and Moses took of the blood of it, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the tip of Aaron's right ear, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And he brought Aaron's sons, and Moses put of the blood upon the tip of their right ear, and upon the thumbs of their right hands, and upon the great toes of their right feet: and Moses sprinkled the blood upon the altar round about.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And he took the fat, and the rump, and all the fat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> upon the inwards, and the caul </content>
            <content kind="EM">above</content>
            <content> the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and the right shoulder:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And out of the basket of unleavened bread, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> before the LORD, he took one unleavened cake, and a cake of oiled bread, and one wafer, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> on the fat, and upon the right shoulder:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And he put all upon Aaron's hands, and upon his sons' hands, and waved them </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And Moses took them from off their hands, and burnt </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> on the altar upon the burnt offering: they </content>
            <content kind="EM">were</content>
            <content> consecrations for a sweet savour: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And Moses took the breast, and waved it </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD: </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> of the ram of consecration it was Moses' part; as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And Moses took of the anointing oil, and of the blood which </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> upon the altar, and sprinkled </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon Aaron, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> upon his garments, and upon his sons, and upon his sons' garments with him; and sanctified Aaron, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> his garments, and his sons, and his sons' garments with him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And Moses said unto Aaron and to his sons, Boil the flesh </content>
            <content kind="EM">at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation: and there eat it with the bread that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the basket of consecrations, as I commanded, saying, Aaron and his sons shall eat it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And that which remaineth of the flesh and of the bread shall ye burn with fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And ye shall not go out of the door of the tabernacle of the congregation </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> seven days, until the days of your consecration be at an end: for seven days shall he consecrate you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>As he hath done this day, </content>
            <content kind="EM">so</content>
            <content> the LORD hath commanded to do, to make an atonement for you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>Therefore shall ye abide </content>
            <content kind="EM">at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation day and night seven days, and keep the charge of the LORD, that ye die not: for so I am commanded.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>So Aaron and his sons did all things which the LORD commanded by the hand of Moses.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And it came to pass on the eighth day, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> Moses called Aaron and his sons, and the elders of Israel;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And he said unto Aaron, Take thee a young calf for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering, without blemish, and offer </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And unto the children of Israel thou shalt speak, saying, Take ye a kid of the goats for a sin offering; and a calf and a lamb, </content>
            <content kind="EM">both</content>
            <content> of the first year, without blemish, for a burnt offering;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Also a bullock and a ram for peace offerings, to sacrifice before the LORD; and a meat offering mingled with oil: for to day the LORD will appear unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And they brought </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> which Moses commanded before the tabernacle of the congregation: and all the congregation drew near and stood before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And Moses said, This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the thing which the LORD commanded that ye should do: and the glory of the LORD shall appear unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And Moses said unto Aaron, Go unto the altar, and offer thy sin offering, and thy burnt offering, and make an atonement for thyself, and for the people: and offer the offering of the people, and make an atonement for them; as the LORD commanded.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Aaron therefore went unto the altar, and slew the calf of the sin offering, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> for himself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And the sons of Aaron brought the blood unto him: and he dipped his finger in the blood, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the horns of the altar, and poured out the blood at the bottom of the altar:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But the fat, and the kidneys, and the caul above the liver of the sin offering, he burnt upon the altar; as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And the flesh and the hide he burnt with fire without the camp.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And he slew the burnt offering; and Aaron's sons presented unto him the blood, which he sprinkled round about upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And they presented the burnt offering unto him, with the pieces thereof, and the head: and he burnt </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And he did wash the inwards and the legs, and burnt </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> upon the burnt offering on the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And he brought the people's offering, and took the goat, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> the sin offering for the people, and slew it, and offered it for sin, as the first.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And he brought the burnt offering, and offered it according to the manner.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And he brought the meat offering, and took an handful thereof, and burnt </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the altar, beside the burnt sacrifice of the morning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He slew also the bullock and the ram </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sacrifice of peace offerings, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> for the people: and Aaron's sons presented unto him the blood, which he sprinkled upon the altar round about,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And the fat of the bullock and of the ram, the rump, and that which covereth </content>
            <content kind="EM">the inwards</content>
            <content>, and the kidneys, and the caul </content>
            <content kind="EM">above</content>
            <content> the liver:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And they put the fat upon the breasts, and he burnt the fat upon the altar:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And the breasts and the right shoulder Aaron waved </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD; as Moses commanded.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And Aaron lifted up his hand toward the people, and blessed them, and came down from offering of the sin offering, and the burnt offering, and peace offerings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And Moses and Aaron went into the tabernacle of the congregation, and came out, and blessed the people: and the glory of the LORD appeared unto all the people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And there came a fire out from before the LORD, and consumed upon the altar the burnt offering and the fat: </content>
            <content kind="EM">which</content>
            <content> when all the people saw, they shouted, and fell on their faces.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, took either of them his censer, and put fire therein, and put incense thereon, and offered strange fire before the LORD, which he commanded them not.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And there went out fire from the LORD, and devoured them, and they died before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Then Moses said unto Aaron, This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is it</content>
            <content> that the LORD spake, saying, I will be sanctified in them that come nigh me, and before all the people I will be glorified. And Aaron held his peace.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said unto them, Come near, carry your brethren from before the sanctuary out of the camp.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>So they went near, and carried them in their coats out of the camp; as Moses had said.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And Moses said unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons, Uncover not your heads, neither rend your clothes; lest ye die, and lest wrath come upon all the people: but let your brethren, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which the LORD hath kindled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And ye shall not go out from the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, lest ye die: for the anointing oil of the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon you. And they did according to the word of Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Aaron, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Do not drink wine nor strong drink, thou, nor thy sons with thee, when ye go into the tabernacle of the congregation, lest ye die: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it shall be</content>
            <content> a statute for ever throughout your generations:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And that ye may put difference between holy and unholy, and between unclean and clean;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And that ye may teach the children of Israel all the statutes which the LORD hath spoken unto them by the hand of Moses.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And Moses spake unto Aaron, and unto Eleazar and unto Ithamar, his sons that were left, Take the meat offering that remaineth of the offerings of the LORD made by fire, and eat it without leaven beside the altar: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And ye shall eat it in the holy place, because it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy due, and thy sons' due, of the sacrifices of the LORD made by fire: for so I am commanded.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And the wave breast and heave shoulder shall ye eat in a clean place; thou, and thy sons, and thy daughters with thee: for </content>
            <content kind="EM">they be</content>
            <content> thy due, and thy sons' due, </content>
            <content kind="EM">which</content>
            <content> are given out of the sacrifices of peace offerings of the children of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The heave shoulder and the wave breast shall they bring with the offerings made by fire of the fat, to wave </content>
            <content kind="EM">it for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD; and it shall be thine, and thy sons' with thee, by a statute for ever; as the LORD hath commanded.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And Moses diligently sought the goat of the sin offering, and, behold, it was burnt: and he was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, the sons of Aaron </content>
            <content kind="EM">which were</content>
            <content> left </content>
            <content kind="EM">alive</content>
            <content>, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Wherefore have ye not eaten the sin offering in the holy place, seeing it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">God</content>
            <content> hath given it you to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before the LORD?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Behold, the blood of it was not brought in within the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>: ye should indeed have eaten it in the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>, as I commanded.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And Aaron said unto Moses, Behold, this day have they offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before the LORD; and such things have befallen me: and </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> I had eaten the sin offering to day, should it have been accepted in the sight of the LORD?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And when Moses heard </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content>, he was content.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying unto them,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, These </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> the beasts which ye shall eat among all the beasts that </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> on the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Whatsoever parteth the hoof, and is clovenfooted, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> cheweth the cud, among the beasts, that shall ye eat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Nevertheless these shall ye not eat of them that chew the cud, or of them that divide the hoof: </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> the camel, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And the coney, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And the hare, because he cheweth the cud, but divideth not the hoof; he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And the swine, though he divide the hoof, and be clovenfooted, yet he cheweth not the cud; he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Of their flesh shall ye not eat, and their carcase shall ye not touch; they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> unclean to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>These shall ye eat of all that </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> in the waters: whatsoever hath fins and scales in the waters, in the seas, and in the rivers, them shall ye eat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And all that have not fins and scales in the seas, and in the rivers, of all that move in the waters, and of any living thing which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the waters, they </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> an abomination unto you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>They shall be even an abomination unto you; ye shall not eat of their flesh, but ye shall have their carcases in abomination.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Whatsoever hath no fins nor scales in the waters, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> an abomination unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And these </content>
            <content kind="EM">are they which</content>
            <content> ye shall have in abomination among the fowls; they shall not be eaten, they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> an abomination: the eagle, and the ossifrage, and the ospray,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And the vulture, and the kite after his kind;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Every raven after his kind;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And the owl, and the night hawk, and the cuckow, and the hawk after his kind,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And the little owl, and the cormorant, and the great owl,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And the swan, and the pelican, and the gier eagle,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And the stork, the heron after her kind, and the lapwing, and the bat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>All fowls that creep, going upon </content>
            <content kind="EM">all</content>
            <content> four, </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> an abomination unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Yet these may ye eat of every flying creeping thing that goeth upon </content>
            <content kind="EM">all</content>
            <content> four, which have legs above their feet, to leap withal upon the earth;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content kind="EM">Even</content>
            <content> these of them ye may eat; the locust after his kind, and the bald locust after his kind, and the beetle after his kind, and the grasshopper after his kind.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>But all </content>
            <content kind="EM">other</content>
            <content> flying creeping things, which have four feet, </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> an abomination unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And for these ye shall be unclean: whosoever toucheth the carcase of them shall be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And whosoever beareth </content>
            <content kind="EM">ought</content>
            <content> of the carcase of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content kind="EM">The carcases</content>
            <content> of every beast which divideth the hoof, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> not clovenfooted, nor cheweth the cud, </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> unclean unto you: every one that toucheth them shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And whatsoever goeth upon his paws, among all manner of beasts that go on </content>
            <content kind="EM">all</content>
            <content> four, those </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> unclean unto you: whoso toucheth their carcase shall be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And he that beareth the carcase of them shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> unclean unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>These also </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> unclean unto you among the creeping things that creep upon the earth; the weasel, and the mouse, and the tortoise after his kind,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And the ferret, and the chameleon, and the lizard, and the snail, and the mole.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>These </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> unclean to you among all that creep: whosoever doth touch them, when they be dead, shall be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And upon whatsoever </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> of them, when they are dead, doth fall, it shall be unclean; whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> any vessel of wood, or raiment, or skin, or sack, whatsoever vessel </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content>, wherein </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> work is done, it must be put into water, and it shall be unclean until the even; so it shall be cleansed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And every earthen vessel, whereinto </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> of them falleth, whatsoever </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in it shall be unclean; and ye shall break it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Of all meat which may be eaten, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> on which </content>
            <content kind="EM">such</content>
            <content> water cometh shall be unclean: and all drink that may be drunk in every </content>
            <content kind="EM">such</content>
            <content> vessel shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>And every </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content> whereupon </content>
            <content kind="EM">any part</content>
            <content> of their carcase falleth shall be unclean; </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether it be</content>
            <content> oven, or ranges for pots, they shall be broken down: </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> unclean, and shall be unclean unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Nevertheless a fountain or pit, </content>
            <content kind="EM">wherein there is</content>
            <content> plenty of water, shall be clean: but that which toucheth their carcase shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">any part</content>
            <content> of their carcase fall upon any sowing seed which is to be sown, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>But if </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> water be put upon the seed, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">any part</content>
            <content> of their carcase fall thereon, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> unclean unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>And if any beast, of which ye may eat, die; he that toucheth the carcase thereof shall be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>And he that eateth of the carcase of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even: he also that beareth the carcase of it shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>And every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> an abomination; it shall not be eaten.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>Whatsoever goeth upon the belly, and whatsoever goeth upon </content>
            <content kind="EM">all</content>
            <content> four, or whatsoever hath more feet among all creeping things that creep upon the earth, them ye shall not eat; for they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> an abomination.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>Ye shall not make yourselves abominable with any creeping thing that creepeth, neither shall ye make yourselves unclean with them, that ye should be defiled thereby.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>For I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God: ye shall therefore sanctify yourselves, and ye shall be holy; for I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> holy: neither shall ye defile yourselves with any manner of creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>For I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD that bringeth you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: ye shall therefore be holy, for I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the beasts, and of the fowl, and of every living creature that moveth in the waters, and of every creature that creepeth upon the earth:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>To make a difference between the unclean and the clean, and between the beast that may be eaten and the beast that may not be eaten.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, If a woman have conceived seed, and born a man child: then she shall be unclean seven days; according to the days of the separation for her infirmity shall she be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And in the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And she shall then continue in the blood of her purifying three and thirty days; she shall touch no hallowed thing, nor come into the sanctuary, until the days of her purifying be fulfilled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But if she bear a maid child, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her separation: and she shall continue in the blood of her purifying threescore and six days.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And when the days of her purifying are fulfilled, for a son, or for a daughter, she shall bring a lamb of the first year for a burnt offering, and a young pigeon, or a turtledove, for a sin offering, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, unto the priest:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Who shall offer it before the LORD, and make an atonement for her; and she shall be cleansed from the issue of her blood. This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law for her that hath born a male or a female.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And if she be not able to bring a lamb, then she shall bring two turtles, or two young pigeons; the one for the burnt offering, and the other for a sin offering: and the priest shall make an atonement for her, and she shall be clean.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses and Aaron, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>When a man shall have in the skin of his flesh a rising, a scab, or bright spot, and it be in the skin of his flesh </content>
            <content kind="EM">like</content>
            <content> the plague of leprosy; then he shall be brought unto Aaron the priest, or unto one of his sons the priests:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And the priest shall look on the plague in the skin of the flesh: and </content>
            <content kind="EM">when</content>
            <content> the hair in the plague is turned white, and the plague in sight </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> deeper than the skin of his flesh, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a plague of leprosy: and the priest shall look on him, and pronounce him unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>If the bright spot </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> white in the skin of his flesh, and in sight </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> not deeper than the skin, and the hair thereof be not turned white; then the priest shall shut up </content>
            <content kind="EM">him that hath</content>
            <content> the plague seven days:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And the priest shall look on him the seventh day: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague in his sight be at a stay, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the plague spread not in the skin; then the priest shall shut him up seven days more:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And the priest shall look on him again the seventh day: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> somewhat dark, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the plague spread not in the skin, the priest shall pronounce him clean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is but</content>
            <content> a scab: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But if the scab spread much abroad in the skin, after that he hath been seen of the priest for his cleansing, he shall be seen of the priest again:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the priest see that, behold, the scab spreadeth in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a leprosy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>When the plague of leprosy is in a man, then he shall be brought unto the priest;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And the priest shall see </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content>: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the rising </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> white in the skin, and it have turned the hair white, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> quick raw flesh in the rising;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>It </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an old leprosy in the skin of his flesh, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean, and shall not shut him up: for he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And if a leprosy break out abroad in the skin, and the leprosy cover all the skin of </content>
            <content kind="EM">him that hath</content>
            <content> the plague from his head even to his foot, wheresoever the priest looketh;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then the priest shall consider: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the leprosy have covered all his flesh, he shall pronounce </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> clean </content>
            <content kind="EM">that hath</content>
            <content> the plague: it is all turned white: he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But when raw flesh appeareth in him, he shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And the priest shall see the raw flesh, and pronounce him to be unclean: </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> the raw flesh </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a leprosy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Or if the raw flesh turn again, and be changed unto white, he shall come unto the priest;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And the priest shall see him: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague be turned into white; then the priest shall pronounce </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> clean </content>
            <content kind="EM">that hath</content>
            <content> the plague: he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The flesh also, in which, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> in the skin thereof, was a boil, and is healed,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And in the place of the boil there be a white rising, or a bright spot, white, and somewhat reddish, and it be shewed to the priest;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And if, when the priest seeth it, behold, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> in sight lower than the skin, and the hair thereof be turned white; the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a plague of leprosy broken out of the boil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>But if the priest look on it, and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> no white hairs therein, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> not lower than the skin, but </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> somewhat dark; then the priest shall shut him up seven days:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And if it spread much abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a plague.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>But if the bright spot stay in his place, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> spread not, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a burning boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Or if there be </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> flesh, in the skin whereof </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> a hot burning, and the quick </content>
            <content kind="EM">flesh</content>
            <content> that burneth have a white bright spot, somewhat reddish, or white;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Then the priest shall look upon it: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the hair in the bright spot be turned white, and it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be in</content>
            <content> sight deeper than the skin; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a leprosy broken out of the burning: wherefore the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the plague of leprosy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>But if the priest look on it, and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> no white hair in the bright spot, and it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> no lower than the </content>
            <content kind="EM">other</content>
            <content> skin, but </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> somewhat dark; then the priest shall shut him up seven days:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And the priest shall look upon him the seventh day: </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> if it be spread much abroad in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the plague of leprosy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And if the bright spot stay in his place, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> spread not in the skin, but it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> somewhat dark; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a rising of the burning, and the priest shall pronounce him clean: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an inflammation of the burning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>If a man or woman have a plague upon the head or the beard;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Then the priest shall see the plague: and, behold, if it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> in sight deeper than the skin; </content>
            <content kind="EM">and there be</content>
            <content> in it a yellow thin hair; then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a dry scall, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> a leprosy upon the head or beard.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And if the priest look on the plague of the scall, and, behold, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> not in sight deeper than the skin, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">that there is</content>
            <content> no black hair in it; then the priest shall shut up </content>
            <content kind="EM">him that hath</content>
            <content> the plague of the scall seven days:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And in the seventh day the priest shall look on the plague: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the scall spread not, and there be in it no yellow hair, and the scall </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> not in sight deeper than the skin;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>He shall be shaven, but the scall shall he not shave; and the priest shall shut up </content>
            <content kind="EM">him that hath</content>
            <content> the scall seven days more:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>And in the seventh day the priest shall look on the scall: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the scall be not spread in the skin, nor </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> in sight deeper than the skin; then the priest shall pronounce him clean: and he shall wash his clothes, and be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>But if the scall spread much in the skin after his cleansing;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Then the priest shall look on him: and, behold, if the scall be spread in the skin, the priest shall not seek for yellow hair; he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>But if the scall be in his sight at a stay, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> there is black hair grown up therein; the scall is healed, he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> clean: and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>If a man also or a woman have in the skin of their flesh bright spots, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> white bright spots;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>Then the priest shall look: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the bright spots in the skin of their flesh </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> darkish white; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a freckled spot </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> groweth in the skin; he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>And the man whose hair is fallen off his head, he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> bald; </content>
            <content kind="EM">yet is</content>
            <content> he clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>And he that hath his hair fallen off from the part of his head toward his face, he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> forehead bald: </content>
            <content kind="EM">yet is</content>
            <content> he clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>And if there be in the bald head, or bald forehead, a white reddish sore; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a leprosy sprung up in his bald head, or his bald forehead.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>Then the priest shall look upon it: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the rising of the sore </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> white reddish in his bald head, or in his bald forehead, as the leprosy appeareth in the skin of the flesh;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>He is a leprous man, he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean: the priest shall pronounce him utterly unclean; his plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in his head.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>And the leper in whom the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content>, his clothes shall be rent, and his head bare, and he shall put a covering upon his upper lip, and shall cry, Unclean, unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>All the days wherein the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> in him he shall be defiled; he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean: he shall dwell alone; without the camp </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall</content>
            <content> his habitation </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>The garment also that the plague of leprosy is in, </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether it be</content>
            <content> a woollen garment, or a linen garment;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>Whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> in the warp, or woof; of linen, or of woollen; whether in a skin, or in any thing made of skin;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>And if the plague be greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the skin, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a plague of leprosy, and shall be shewed unto the priest:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>And the priest shall look upon the plague, and shut up </content>
            <content kind="EM">it that hath</content>
            <content> the plague seven days:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
            <content>And he shall look on the plague on the seventh day: if the plague be spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in a skin, </content>
            <content kind="EM">or</content>
            <content> in any work that is made of skin; the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a fretting leprosy; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
            <content>He shall therefore burn that garment, whether warp or woof, in woollen or in linen, or any thing of skin, wherein the plague is: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a fretting leprosy; it shall be burnt in the fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
            <content>And if the priest shall look, and, behold, the plague be not spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
            <content>Then the priest shall command that they wash </content>
            <content kind="EM">the thing</content>
            <content> wherein the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content>, and he shall shut it up seven days more:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
            <content>And the priest shall look on the plague, after that it is washed: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague have not changed his colour, and the plague be not spread; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean; thou shalt burn it in the fire; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> fret inward, </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether</content>
            <content> it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> bare within or without.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
            <content>And if the priest look, and, behold, the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> somewhat dark after the washing of it; then he shall rend it out of the garment, or out of the skin, or out of the warp, or out of the woof:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
            <content>And if it appear still in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in any thing of skin; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a spreading </content>
            <content kind="EM">plague</content>
            <content>: thou shalt burn that wherein the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> with fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="58">
            <content>And the garment, either warp, or woof, or whatsoever thing of skin </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content>, which thou shalt wash, if the plague be departed from them, then it shall be washed the second time, and shall be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="59">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of the plague of leprosy in a garment of woollen or linen, either in the warp, or woof, or any thing of skins, to pronounce it clean, or to pronounce it unclean.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>This shall be the law of the leper in the day of his cleansing: He shall be brought unto the priest:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And the priest shall go forth out of the camp; and the priest shall look, and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague of leprosy be healed in the leper;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Then shall the priest command to take for him that is to be cleansed two birds alive </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> clean, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And the priest shall command that one of the birds be killed in an earthen vessel over running water:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>As for the living bird, he shall take it, and the cedar wood, and the scarlet, and the hyssop, and shall dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird </content>
            <content kind="EM">that was</content>
            <content> killed over the running water:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And he shall sprinkle upon him that is to be cleansed from the leprosy seven times, and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird loose into the open field.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And he that is to be cleansed shall wash his clothes, and shave off all his hair, and wash himself in water, that he may be clean: and after that he shall come into the camp, and shall tarry abroad out of his tent seven days.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>But it shall be on the seventh day, that he shall shave all his hair off his head and his beard and his eyebrows, even all his hair he shall shave off: and he shall wash his clothes, also he shall wash his flesh in water, and he shall be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And on the eighth day he shall take two he lambs without blemish, and one ewe lamb of the first year without blemish, and three tenth deals of fine flour </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a meat offering, mingled with oil, and one log of oil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And the priest that maketh </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> clean shall present the man that is to be made clean, and those things, before the LORD, </content>
            <content kind="EM">at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And the priest shall take one he lamb, and offer him for a trespass offering, and the log of oil, and wave them </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And he shall slay the lamb in the place where he shall kill the sin offering and the burnt offering, in the holy place: for as the sin offering </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the priest's, </content>
            <content kind="EM">so is</content>
            <content> the trespass offering: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And the priest shall take </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> of the blood of the trespass offering, and the priest shall put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And the priest shall take </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> of the log of oil, and pour </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> into the palm of his own left hand:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And the priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in his left hand, and shall sprinkle of the oil with his finger seven times before the LORD:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And of the rest of the oil that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in his hand shall the priest put upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot, upon the blood of the trespass offering:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And the remnant of the oil that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the priest's hand he shall pour upon the head of him that is to be cleansed: and the priest shall make an atonement for him before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And the priest shall offer the sin offering, and make an atonement for him that is to be cleansed from his uncleanness; and afterward he shall kill the burnt offering:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the meat offering upon the altar: and the priest shall make an atonement for him, and he shall be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And if he </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> poor, and cannot get so much; then he shall take one lamb </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a trespass offering to be waved, to make an atonement for him, and one tenth deal of fine flour mingled with oil for a meat offering, and a log of oil;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, such as he is able to get; and the one shall be a sin offering, and the other a burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And he shall bring them on the eighth day for his cleansing unto the priest, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And the priest shall take the lamb of the trespass offering, and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And he shall kill the lamb of the trespass offering, and the priest shall take </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> of the blood of the trespass offering, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And the priest shall pour of the oil into the palm of his own left hand:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And the priest shall sprinkle with his right finger </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> of the oil that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in his left hand seven times before the LORD:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And the priest shall put of the oil that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in his hand upon the tip of the right ear of him that is to be cleansed, and upon the thumb of his right hand, and upon the great toe of his right foot, upon the place of the blood of the trespass offering:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And the rest of the oil that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the priest's hand he shall put upon the head of him that is to be cleansed, to make an atonement for him before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And he shall offer the one of the turtledoves, or of the young pigeons, such as he can get;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content kind="EM">Even</content>
            <content> such as he is able to get, the one </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sin offering, and the other </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a burnt offering, with the meat offering: and the priest shall make an atonement for him that is to be cleansed before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law </content>
            <content kind="EM">of him</content>
            <content> in whom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the plague of leprosy, whose hand is not able to get </content>
            <content kind="EM">that which pertaineth</content>
            <content> to his cleansing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses and unto Aaron, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>When ye be come into the land of Canaan, which I give to you for a possession, and I put the plague of leprosy in a house of the land of your possession;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>And he that owneth the house shall come and tell the priest, saying, It seemeth to me </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> as it were a plague in the house:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Then the priest shall command that they empty the house, before the priest go </content>
            <content kind="EM">into it</content>
            <content> to see the plague, that all that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the house be not made unclean: and afterward the priest shall go in to see the house:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>And he shall look on the plague, and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> in the walls of the house with hollow strakes, greenish or reddish, which in sight </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> lower than the wall;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Then the priest shall go out of the house to the door of the house, and shut up the house seven days:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>And the priest shall come again the seventh day, and shall look: and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague be spread in the walls of the house;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>Then the priest shall command that they take away the stones in which the plague </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content>, and they shall cast them into an unclean place without the city:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>And he shall cause the house to be scraped within round about, and they shall pour out the dust that they scrape off without the city into an unclean place:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>And they shall take other stones, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> in the place of those stones; and he shall take other morter, and shall plaister the house.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>And if the plague come again, and break out in the house, after that he hath taken away the stones, and after he hath scraped the house, and after it is plaistered;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>Then the priest shall come and look, and, behold, </content>
            <content kind="EM">if</content>
            <content> the plague be spread in the house, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a fretting leprosy in the house: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>And he shall break down the house, the stones of it, and the timber thereof, and all the morter of the house; and he shall carry </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> forth out of the city into an unclean place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>Moreover he that goeth into the house all the while that it is shut up shall be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>And he that lieth in the house shall wash his clothes; and he that eateth in the house shall wash his clothes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>And if the priest shall come in, and look </content>
            <content kind="EM">upon it</content>
            <content>, and, behold, the plague hath not spread in the house, after the house was plaistered: then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the plague is healed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>And he shall take to cleanse the house two birds, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>And he shall kill the one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
            <content>And he shall take the cedar wood, and the hyssop, and the scarlet, and the living bird, and dip them in the blood of the slain bird, and in the running water, and sprinkle the house seven times:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
            <content>And he shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird, and with the running water, and with the living bird, and with the cedar wood, and with the hyssop, and with the scarlet:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
            <content>But he shall let go the living bird out of the city into the open fields, and make an atonement for the house: and it shall be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law for all manner of plague of leprosy, and scall,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
            <content>And for the leprosy of a garment, and of a house,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
            <content>And for a rising, and for a scab, and for a bright spot:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
            <content>To teach when </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> unclean, and when </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> clean: this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of leprosy.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="15">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses and to Aaron, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When any man hath a running issue out of his flesh, </content>
            <content kind="EM">because of</content>
            <content> his issue he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And this shall be his uncleanness in his issue: whether his flesh run with his issue, or his flesh be stopped from his issue, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> his uncleanness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Every bed, whereon he lieth that hath the issue, is unclean: and every thing, whereon he sitteth, shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And whosoever toucheth his bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And he that sitteth on </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> thing whereon he sat that hath the issue shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And he that toucheth the flesh of him that hath the issue shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And if he that hath the issue spit upon him that is clean; then he shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And what saddle soever he rideth upon that hath the issue shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And whosoever toucheth any thing that was under him shall be unclean until the even: and he that beareth </content>
            <content kind="EM">any of</content>
            <content> those things shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And whomsoever he toucheth that hath the issue, and hath not rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And the vessel of earth, that he toucheth which hath the issue, shall be broken: and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And when he that hath an issue is cleansed of his issue; then he shall number to himself seven days for his cleansing, and wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in running water, and shall be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And on the eighth day he shall take to him two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, and come before the LORD unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and give them unto the priest:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And the priest shall offer them, the one </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sin offering, and the other </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a burnt offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for him before the LORD for his issue.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And if any man's seed of copulation go out from him, then he shall wash all his flesh in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And every garment, and every skin, whereon is the seed of copulation, shall be washed with water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The woman also with whom man shall lie </content>
            <content kind="EM">with</content>
            <content> seed of copulation, they shall </content>
            <content kind="EM">both</content>
            <content> bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">themselves</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And if a woman have an issue, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> her issue in her flesh be blood, she shall be put apart seven days: and whosoever toucheth her shall be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And every thing that she lieth upon in her separation shall be unclean: every thing also that she sitteth upon shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And whosoever toucheth her bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And whosoever toucheth any thing that she sat upon shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And if it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> on </content>
            <content kind="EM">her</content>
            <content> bed, or on any thing whereon she sitteth, when he toucheth it, he shall be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And if any man lie with her at all, and her flowers be upon him, he shall be unclean seven days; and all the bed whereon he lieth shall be unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And if a woman have an issue of her blood many days out of the time of her separation, or if it run beyond the time of her separation; all the days of the issue of her uncleanness shall be as the days of her separation: she </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Every bed whereon she lieth all the days of her issue shall be unto her as the bed of her separation: and whatsoever she sitteth upon shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her separation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And whosoever toucheth those things shall be unclean, and shall wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>But if she be cleansed of her issue, then she shall number to herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And on the eighth day she shall take unto her two turtles, or two young pigeons, and bring them unto the priest, to the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And the priest shall offer the one </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sin offering, and the other </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a burnt offering; and the priest shall make an atonement for her before the LORD for the issue of her uncleanness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Thus shall ye separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness; that they die not in their uncleanness, when they defile my tabernacle that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> among them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the law of him that hath an issue, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">of him</content>
            <content> whose seed goeth from him, and is defiled therewith;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And of her that is sick of her flowers, and of him that hath an issue, of the man, and of the woman, and of him that lieth with her that is unclean.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="16">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they offered before the LORD, and died;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And the LORD said unto Moses, Speak unto Aaron thy brother, that he come not at all times into the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content> within the vail before the mercy seat, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the ark; that he die not: for I will appear in the cloud upon the mercy seat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Thus shall Aaron come into the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>: with a young bullock for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>He shall put on the holy linen coat, and he shall have the linen breeches upon his flesh, and shall be girded with a linen girdle, and with the linen mitre shall he be attired: these </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> holy garments; therefore shall he wash his flesh in water, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">so</content>
            <content> put them on.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And he shall take of the congregation of the children of Israel two kids of the goats for a sin offering, and one ram for a burnt offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And Aaron shall offer his bullock of the sin offering, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> for himself, and make an atonement for himself, and for his house.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And he shall take the two goats, and present them before the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And Aaron shall cast lots upon the two goats; one lot for the LORD, and the other lot for the scapegoat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And Aaron shall bring the goat upon which the LORD'S lot fell, and offer him </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sin offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But the goat, on which the lot fell to be the scapegoat, shall be presented alive before the LORD, to make an atonement with him, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> to let him go for a scapegoat into the wilderness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And Aaron shall bring the bullock of the sin offering, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> for himself, and shall make an atonement for himself, and for his house, and shall kill the bullock of the sin offering which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> for himself:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And he shall take a censer full of burning coals of fire from off the altar before the LORD, and his hands full of sweet incense beaten small, and bring </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> within the vail:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And he shall put the incense upon the fire before the LORD, that the cloud of the incense may cover the mercy seat that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon the testimony, that he die not:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And he shall take of the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> with his finger upon the mercy seat eastward; and before the mercy seat shall he sprinkle of the blood with his finger seven times.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Then shall he kill the goat of the sin offering, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> for the people, and bring his blood within the vail, and do with that blood as he did with the blood of the bullock, and sprinkle it upon the mercy seat, and before the mercy seat:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And he shall make an atonement for the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>, because of the uncleanness of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions in all their sins: and so shall he do for the tabernacle of the congregation, that remaineth among them in the midst of their uncleanness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And there shall be no man in the tabernacle of the congregation when he goeth in to make an atonement in the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>, until he come out, and have made an atonement for himself, and for his household, and for all the congregation of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And he shall go out unto the altar that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> before the LORD, and make an atonement for it; and shall take of the blood of the bullock, and of the blood of the goat, and put </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> upon the horns of the altar round about.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And he shall sprinkle of the blood upon it with his finger seven times, and cleanse it, and hallow it from the uncleanness of the children of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And when he hath made an end of reconciling the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>, and the tabernacle of the congregation, and the altar, he shall bring the live goat:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And Aaron shall lay both his hands upon the head of the live goat, and confess over him all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions in all their sins, putting them upon the head of the goat, and shall send </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> away by the hand of a fit man into the wilderness:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And the goat shall bear upon him all their iniquities unto a land not inhabited: and he shall let go the goat in the wilderness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And Aaron shall come into the tabernacle of the congregation, and shall put off the linen garments, which he put on when he went into the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>, and shall leave them there:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And he shall wash his flesh with water in the holy place, and put on his garments, and come forth, and offer his burnt offering, and the burnt offering of the people, and make an atonement for himself, and for the people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And the fat of the sin offering shall he burn upon the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And he that let go the goat for the scapegoat shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward come into the camp.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And the bullock </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> the sin offering, and the goat </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the holy </content>
            <content kind="EM">place</content>
            <content>, shall </content>
            <content kind="EM">one</content>
            <content> carry forth without the camp; and they shall burn in the fire their skins, and their flesh, and their dung.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And he that burneth them shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> shall be a statute for ever unto you: </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> in the seventh month, on the tenth </content>
            <content kind="EM">day</content>
            <content> of the month, ye shall afflict your souls, and do no work at all, </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether it be</content>
            <content> one of your own country, or a stranger that sojourneth among you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>For on that day shall </content>
            <content kind="EM">the priest</content>
            <content> make an atonement for you, to cleanse you, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> ye may be clean from all your sins before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>It </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> a sabbath of rest unto you, and ye shall afflict your souls, by a statute for ever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And the priest, whom he shall anoint, and whom he shall consecrate to minister in the priest's office in his father's stead, shall make the atonement, and shall put on the linen clothes, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> the holy garments:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And he shall make an atonement for the holy sanctuary, and he shall make an atonement for the tabernacle of the congregation, and for the altar, and he shall make an atonement for the priests, and for all the people of the congregation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>And this shall be an everlasting statute unto you, to make an atonement for the children of Israel for all their sins once a year. And he did as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="17">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto Aaron, and unto his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them; This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the thing which the LORD hath commanded, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>What man soever </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> of the house of Israel, that killeth an ox, or lamb, or goat, in the camp, or that killeth </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> out of the camp,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And bringeth it not unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, to offer an offering unto the LORD before the tabernacle of the LORD; blood shall be imputed unto that man; he hath shed blood; and that man shall be cut off from among his people:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>To the end that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they offer in the open field, even that they may bring them unto the LORD, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, unto the priest, and offer them </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> peace offerings unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And the priest shall sprinkle the blood upon the altar of the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">at</content>
            <content> the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, and burn the fat for a sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And they shall no more offer their sacrifices unto devils, after whom they have gone a whoring. This shall be a statute for ever unto them throughout their generations.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And thou shalt say unto them, Whatsoever man </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> of the house of Israel, or of the strangers which sojourn among you, that offereth a burnt offering or sacrifice,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And bringeth it not unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, to offer it unto the LORD; even that man shall be cut off from among his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And whatsoever man </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> of the house of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among you, that eateth any manner of blood; I will even set my face against that soul that eateth blood, and will cut him off from among his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>For the life of the flesh </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the blood: and I have given it to you upon the altar to make an atonement for your souls: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the blood </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> maketh an atonement for the soul.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Therefore I said unto the children of Israel, No soul of you shall eat blood, neither shall any stranger that sojourneth among you eat blood.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And whatsoever man </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn among you, which hunteth and catcheth any beast or fowl that may be eaten; he shall even pour out the blood thereof, and cover it with dust.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> the life of all flesh; the blood of it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> for the life thereof: therefore I said unto the children of Israel, Ye shall eat the blood of no manner of flesh: for the life of all flesh </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the blood thereof: whosoever eateth it shall be cut off.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And every soul that eateth that which died </content>
            <content kind="EM">of itself</content>
            <content>, or that which was torn </content>
            <content kind="EM">with beasts, whether it be</content>
            <content> one of your own country, or a stranger, he shall both wash his clothes, and bathe </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> in water, and be unclean until the even: then shall he be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But if he wash </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> not, nor bathe his flesh; then he shall bear his iniquity.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="18">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, I am the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>After the doings of the land of Egypt, wherein ye dwelt, shall ye not do: and after the doings of the land of Canaan, whither I bring you, shall ye not do: neither shall ye walk in their ordinances.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Ye shall do my judgments, and keep mine ordinances, to walk therein: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Ye shall therefore keep my statutes, and my judgments: which if a man do, he shall live in them: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>None of you shall approach to any that is near of kin to him, to uncover </content>
            <content kind="EM">their</content>
            <content> nakedness: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The nakedness of thy father, or the nakedness of thy mother, shalt thou not uncover: she </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy mother; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The nakedness of thy father's wife shalt thou not uncover: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy father's nakedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The nakedness of thy sister, the daughter of thy father, or daughter of thy mother, </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether she be</content>
            <content> born at home, or born abroad, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> their nakedness thou shalt not uncover.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The nakedness of thy son's daughter, or of thy daughter's daughter, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> their nakedness thou shalt not uncover: for theirs </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thine own nakedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The nakedness of thy father's wife's daughter, begotten of thy father, she </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy sister, thou shalt not uncover her nakedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father's sister: she </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy father's near kinswoman.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother's sister: for she </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy mother's near kinswoman.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy father's brother, thou shalt not approach to his wife: she </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thine aunt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy daughter in law: she </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy son's wife; thou shalt not uncover her nakedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy brother's wife: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy brother's nakedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her daughter, neither shalt thou take her son's daughter, or her daughter's daughter, to uncover her nakedness; </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> her near kinswomen: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> wickedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Neither shalt thou take a wife to her sister, to vex </content>
            <content kind="EM">her</content>
            <content>, to uncover her nakedness, beside the other in her life </content>
            <content kind="EM">time</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Also thou shalt not approach unto a woman to uncover her nakedness, as long as she is put apart for her uncleanness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Moreover thou shalt not lie carnally with thy neighbour's wife, to defile thyself with her.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And thou shalt not let any of thy seed pass through </content>
            <content kind="EM">the fire</content>
            <content> to Molech, neither shalt thou profane the name of thy God: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Thou shalt not lie with mankind, as with womankind: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> abomination.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Neither shalt thou lie with any beast to defile thyself therewith: neither shall any woman stand before a beast to lie down thereto: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> confusion.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Defile not ye yourselves in any of these things: for in all these the nations are defiled which I cast out before you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And the land is defiled: therefore I do visit the iniquity thereof upon it, and the land itself vomiteth out her inhabitants.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Ye shall therefore keep my statutes and my judgments, and shall not commit </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> of these abominations; </content>
            <content kind="EM">neither</content>
            <content> any of your own nation, nor any stranger that sojourneth among you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>(For all these abominations have the men of the land done, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">were</content>
            <content> before you, and the land is defiled;)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>That the land spue not you out also, when ye defile it, as it spued out the nations that </content>
            <content kind="EM">were</content>
            <content> before you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>For whosoever shall commit any of these abominations, even the souls that commit </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> shall be cut off from among their people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Therefore shall ye keep mine ordinance, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">ye</content>
            <content> commit not </content>
            <content kind="EM">any one</content>
            <content> of these abominable customs, which were committed before you, and that ye defile not yourselves therein: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="19">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto all the congregation of the children of Israel, and say unto them, Ye shall be holy: for I the LORD your God </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Ye shall fear every man his mother, and his father, and keep my sabbaths: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Turn ye not unto idols, nor make to yourselves molten gods: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And if ye offer a sacrifice of peace offerings unto the LORD, ye shall offer it at your own will.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>It shall be eaten the same day ye offer it, and on the morrow: and if ought remain until the third day, it shall be burnt in the fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And if it be eaten at all on the third day, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> abominable; it shall not be accepted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Therefore </content>
            <content kind="EM">every one</content>
            <content> that eateth it shall bear his iniquity, because he hath profaned the hallowed thing of the LORD: and that soul shall be cut off from among his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not wholly reap the corners of thy field, neither shalt thou gather the gleanings of thy harvest.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And thou shalt not glean thy vineyard, neither shalt thou gather </content>
            <content kind="EM">every</content>
            <content> grape of thy vineyard; thou shalt leave them for the poor and stranger: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Ye shall not steal, neither deal falsely, neither lie one to another.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And ye shall not swear by my name falsely, neither shalt thou profane the name of thy God: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Thou shalt not defraud thy neighbour, neither rob </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content>: the wages of him that is hired shall not abide with thee all night until the morning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Thou shalt not curse the deaf, nor put a stumblingblock before the blind, but shalt fear thy God: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment: thou shalt not respect the person of the poor, nor honour the person of the mighty: </content>
            <content kind="EM">but</content>
            <content> in righteousness shalt thou judge thy neighbour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Thou shalt not go up and down </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> a talebearer among thy people: neither shalt thou stand against the blood of thy neighbour: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Thou shalt not hate thy brother in thine heart: thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy neighbour, and not suffer sin upon him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Thou shalt not avenge, nor bear any grudge against the children of thy people, but thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Ye shall keep my statutes. Thou shalt not let thy cattle gender with a diverse kind: thou shalt not sow thy field with mingled seed: neither shall a garment mingled of linen and woollen come upon thee.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And whosoever lieth carnally with a woman, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a bondmaid, betrothed to an husband, and not at all redeemed, nor freedom given her; she shall be scourged; they shall not be put to death, because she was not free.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And he shall bring his trespass offering unto the LORD, unto the door of the tabernacle of the congregation, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> a ram for a trespass offering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And the priest shall make an atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering before the LORD for his sin which he hath done: and the sin which he hath done shall be forgiven him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And when ye shall come into the land, and shall have planted all manner of trees for food, then ye shall count the fruit thereof as uncircumcised: three years shall it be as uncircumcised unto you: it shall not be eaten of.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>But in the fourth year all the fruit thereof shall be holy to praise the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">withal</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And in the fifth year shall ye eat of the fruit thereof, that it may yield unto you the increase thereof: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Ye shall not eat </content>
            <content kind="EM">any thing</content>
            <content> with the blood: neither shall ye use enchantment, nor observe times.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Ye shall not round the corners of your heads, neither shalt thou mar the corners of thy beard.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Ye shall not make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor print any marks upon you: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Do not prostitute thy daughter, to cause her to be a whore; lest the land fall to whoredom, and the land become full of wickedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Regard not them that have familiar spirits, neither seek after wizards, to be defiled by them: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Thou shalt rise up before the hoary head, and honour the face of the old man, and fear thy God: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And if a stranger sojourn with thee in your land, ye shall not vex him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content kind="EM">But</content>
            <content> the stranger that dwelleth with you shall be unto you as one born among you, and thou shalt love him as thyself; for ye were strangers in the land of Egypt: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>Ye shall do no unrighteousness in judgment, in meteyard, in weight, or in measure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Just balances, just weights, a just ephah, and a just hin, shall ye have: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Therefore shall ye observe all my statutes, and all my judgments, and do them: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="20">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Again, thou shalt say to the children of Israel, Whosoever </content>
            <content kind="EM">he be</content>
            <content> of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that sojourn in Israel, that giveth </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> of his seed unto Molech; he shall surely be put to death: the people of the land shall stone him with stones.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And I will set my face against that man, and will cut him off from among his people; because he hath given of his seed unto Molech, to defile my sanctuary, and to profane my holy name.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And if the people of the land do any ways hide their eyes from the man, when he giveth of his seed unto Molech, and kill him not:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Then I will set my face against that man, and against his family, and will cut him off, and all that go a whoring after him, to commit whoredom with Molech, from among their people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And the soul that turneth after such as have familiar spirits, and after wizards, to go a whoring after them, I will even set my face against that soul, and will cut him off from among his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be ye holy: for I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And ye shall keep my statutes, and do them: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD which sanctify you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For every one that curseth his father or his mother shall be surely put to death: he hath cursed his father or his mother; his blood </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> upon him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And the man that committeth adultery with </content>
            <content kind="EM">another</content>
            <content> man's wife, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even he</content>
            <content> that committeth adultery with his neighbour's wife, the adulterer and the adulteress shall surely be put to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And the man that lieth with his father's wife hath uncovered his father's nakedness: both of them shall surely be put to death; their blood </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> upon them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And if a man lie with his daughter in law, both of them shall surely be put to death: they have wrought confusion; their blood </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> upon them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>If a man also lie with mankind, as he lieth with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination: they shall surely be put to death; their blood </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> upon them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And if a man take a wife and her mother, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> wickedness: they shall be burnt with fire, both he and they; that there be no wickedness among you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And if a man lie with a beast, he shall surely be put to death: and ye shall slay the beast.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And if a woman approach unto any beast, and lie down thereto, thou shalt kill the woman, and the beast: they shall surely be put to death; their blood </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> upon them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And if a man shall take his sister, his father's daughter, or his mother's daughter, and see her nakedness, and she see his nakedness; it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a wicked thing; and they shall be cut off in the sight of their people: he hath uncovered his sister's nakedness; he shall bear his iniquity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And if a man shall lie with a woman having her sickness, and shall uncover her nakedness; he hath discovered her fountain, and she hath uncovered the fountain of her blood: and both of them shall be cut off from among their people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And thou shalt not uncover the nakedness of thy mother's sister, nor of thy father's sister: for he uncovereth his near kin: they shall bear their iniquity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And if a man shall lie with his uncle's wife, he hath uncovered his uncle's nakedness: they shall bear their sin; they shall die childless.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And if a man shall take his brother's wife, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an unclean thing: he hath uncovered his brother's nakedness; they shall be childless.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Ye shall therefore keep all my statutes, and all my judgments, and do them: that the land, whither I bring you to dwell therein, spue you not out.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And ye shall not walk in the manners of the nation, which I cast out before you: for they committed all these things, and therefore I abhorred them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>But I have said unto you, Ye shall inherit their land, and I will give it unto you to possess it, a land that floweth with milk and honey: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God, which have separated you from </content>
            <content kind="EM">other</content>
            <content> people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Ye shall therefore put difference between clean beasts and unclean, and between unclean fowls and clean: and ye shall not make your souls abominable by beast, or by fowl, or by any manner of living thing that creepeth on the ground, which I have separated from you as unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And ye shall be holy unto me: for I the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> holy, and have severed you from </content>
            <content kind="EM">other</content>
            <content> people, that ye should be mine.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>A man also or woman that hath a familiar spirit, or that is a wizard, shall surely be put to death: they shall stone them with stones: their blood </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> upon them.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="21">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD said unto Moses, Speak unto the priests the sons of Aaron, and say unto them, There shall none be defiled for the dead among his people:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>But for his kin, that is near unto him, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that is</content>
            <content>, for his mother, and for his father, and for his son, and for his daughter, and for his brother,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And for his sister a virgin, that is nigh unto him, which hath had no husband; for her may he be defiled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content kind="EM">But</content>
            <content> he shall not defile himself, </content>
            <content kind="EM">being</content>
            <content> a chief man among his people, to profane himself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>They shall not make baldness upon their head, neither shall they shave off the corner of their beard, nor make any cuttings in their flesh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>They shall be holy unto their God, and not profane the name of their God: for the offerings of the LORD made by fire, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the bread of their God, they do offer: therefore they shall be holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>They shall not take a wife </content>
            <content kind="EM">that is</content>
            <content> a whore, or profane; neither shall they take a woman put away from her husband: for he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> holy unto his God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Thou shalt sanctify him therefore; for he offereth the bread of thy God: he shall be holy unto thee: for I the LORD, which sanctify you, </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And the daughter of any priest, if she profane herself by playing the whore, she profaneth her father: she shall be burnt with fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">he that is</content>
            <content> the high priest among his brethren, upon whose head the anointing oil was poured, and that is consecrated to put on the garments, shall not uncover his head, nor rend his clothes;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Neither shall he go in to any dead body, nor defile himself for his father, or for his mother;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Neither shall he go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the crown of the anointing oil of his God </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> upon him: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And he shall take a wife in her virginity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>A widow, or a divorced woman, or profane, </content>
            <content kind="EM">or</content>
            <content> an harlot, these shall he not take: but he shall take a virgin of his own people to wife.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Neither shall he profane his seed among his people: for I the LORD do sanctify him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Speak unto Aaron, saying, Whosoever </content>
            <content kind="EM">he be</content>
            <content> of thy seed in their generations that hath </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> blemish, let him not approach to offer the bread of his God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For whatsoever man </content>
            <content kind="EM">he be</content>
            <content> that hath a blemish, he shall not approach: a blind man, or a lame, or he that hath a flat nose, or any thing superfluous,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Or a man that is brokenfooted, or brokenhanded,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Or crookbackt, or a dwarf, or that hath a blemish in his eye, or be scurvy, or scabbed, or hath his stones broken;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>No man that hath a blemish of the seed of Aaron the priest shall come nigh to offer the offerings of the LORD made by fire: he hath a blemish; he shall not come nigh to offer the bread of his God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>He shall eat the bread of his God, </content>
            <content kind="EM">both</content>
            <content> of the most holy, and of the holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Only he shall not go in unto the vail, nor come nigh unto the altar, because he hath a blemish; that he profane not my sanctuaries: for I the LORD do sanctify them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And Moses told </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="22">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto Aaron and to his sons, that they separate themselves from the holy things of the children of Israel, and that they profane not my holy name </content>
            <content kind="EM">in those things</content>
            <content> which they hallow unto me: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Say unto them, Whosoever </content>
            <content kind="EM">he be</content>
            <content> of all your seed among your generations, that goeth unto the holy things, which the children of Israel hallow unto the LORD, having his uncleanness upon him, that soul shall be cut off from my presence: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>What man soever of the seed of Aaron </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a leper, or hath a running issue; he shall not eat of the holy things, until he be clean. And whoso toucheth any thing </content>
            <content kind="EM">that is</content>
            <content> unclean </content>
            <content kind="EM">by</content>
            <content> the dead, or a man whose seed goeth from him;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Or whosoever toucheth any creeping thing, whereby he may be made unclean, or a man of whom he may take uncleanness, whatsoever uncleanness he hath;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The soul which hath touched any such shall be unclean until even, and shall not eat of the holy things, unless he wash his flesh with water.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And when the sun is down, he shall be clean, and shall afterward eat of the holy things; because it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> his food.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>That which dieth of itself, or is torn </content>
            <content kind="EM">with beasts</content>
            <content>, he shall not eat to defile himself therewith: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>They shall therefore keep mine ordinance, lest they bear sin for it, and die therefore, if they profane it: I the LORD do sanctify them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>There shall no stranger eat </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> the holy thing: a sojourner of the priest, or an hired servant, shall not eat </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> the holy thing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>But if the priest buy </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> soul with his money, he shall eat of it, and he that is born in his house: they shall eat of his meat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>If the priest's daughter also be </content>
            <content kind="EM">married</content>
            <content> unto a stranger, she may not eat of an offering of the holy things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>But if the priest's daughter be a widow, or divorced, and have no child, and is returned unto her father's house, as in her youth, she shall eat of her father's meat: but there shall no stranger eat thereof.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And if a man eat </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> the holy thing unwittingly, then he shall put the fifth </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> thereof unto it, and shall give </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> unto the priest with the holy thing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And they shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they offer unto the LORD;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Or suffer them to bear the iniquity of trespass, when they eat their holy things: for I the LORD do sanctify them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Speak unto Aaron, and to his sons, and unto all the children of Israel, and say unto them, Whatsoever </content>
            <content kind="EM">he be</content>
            <content> of the house of Israel, or of the strangers in Israel, that will offer his oblation for all his vows, and for all his freewill offerings, which they will offer unto the LORD for a burnt offering;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content kind="EM">Ye shall offer</content>
            <content> at your own will a male without blemish, of the beeves, of the sheep, or of the goats.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content kind="EM">But</content>
            <content> whatsoever hath a blemish, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> shall ye not offer: for it shall not be acceptable for you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And whosoever offereth a sacrifice of peace offerings unto the LORD to accomplish </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> vow, or a freewill offering in beeves or sheep, it shall be perfect to be accepted; there shall be no blemish therein.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Blind, or broken, or maimed, or having a wen, or scurvy, or scabbed, ye shall not offer these unto the LORD, nor make an offering by fire of them upon the altar unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Either a bullock or a lamb that hath any thing superfluous or lacking in his parts, that mayest thou offer </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a freewill offering; but for a vow it shall not be accepted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Ye shall not offer unto the LORD that which is bruised, or crushed, or broken, or cut; neither shall ye make </content>
            <content kind="EM">any offering thereof</content>
            <content> in your land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Neither from a stranger's hand shall ye offer the bread of your God of any of these; because their corruption </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in them, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> blemishes </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> in them: they shall not be accepted for you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>When a bullock, or a sheep, or a goat, is brought forth, then it shall be seven days under the dam; and from the eighth day and thenceforth it shall be accepted for an offering made by fire unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether it be</content>
            <content> cow or ewe, ye shall not kill it and her young both in one day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And when ye will offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving unto the LORD, offer </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> at your own will.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>On the same day it shall be eaten up; ye shall leave none of it until the morrow: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Therefore shall ye keep my commandments, and do them: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Neither shall ye profane my holy name; but I will be hallowed among the children of Israel: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD which hallow you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>That brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="23">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, </content>
            <content kind="EM">Concerning</content>
            <content> the feasts of the LORD, which ye shall proclaim </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content> holy convocations, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> these </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> my feasts.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Six days shall work be done: but the seventh day </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the sabbath of rest, an holy convocation; ye shall do no work </content>
            <content kind="EM">therein</content>
            <content>: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the sabbath of the LORD in all your dwellings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>These </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> the feasts of the LORD, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> holy convocations, which ye shall proclaim in their seasons.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>In the fourteenth </content>
            <content kind="EM">day</content>
            <content> of the first month at even </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the LORD'S passover.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And on the fifteenth day of the same month </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the feast of unleavened bread unto the LORD: seven days ye must eat unleavened bread.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>In the first day ye shall have an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work therein.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>But ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the LORD seven days: in the seventh day </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work </content>
            <content kind="EM">therein</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye be come into the land which I give unto you, and shall reap the harvest thereof, then ye shall bring a sheaf of the firstfruits of your harvest unto the priest:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And he shall wave the sheaf before the LORD, to be accepted for you: on the morrow after the sabbath the priest shall wave it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And ye shall offer that day when ye wave the sheaf an he lamb without blemish of the first year for a burnt offering unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And the meat offering thereof </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> two tenth deals of fine flour mingled with oil, an offering made by fire unto the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a sweet savour: and the drink offering thereof </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> of wine, the fourth </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> of an hin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And ye shall eat neither bread, nor parched corn, nor green ears, until the selfsame day that ye have brought an offering unto your God: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it shall be</content>
            <content> a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And ye shall count unto you from the morrow after the sabbath, from the day that ye brought the sheaf of the wave offering; seven sabbaths shall be complete:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Even unto the morrow after the seventh sabbath shall ye number fifty days; and ye shall offer a new meat offering unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Ye shall bring out of your habitations two wave loaves of two tenth deals: they shall be of fine flour; they shall be baken with leaven; </content>
            <content kind="EM">they are</content>
            <content> the firstfruits unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And ye shall offer with the bread seven lambs without blemish of the first year, and one young bullock, and two rams: they shall be </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a burnt offering unto the LORD, with their meat offering, and their drink offerings, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire, of sweet savour unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Then ye shall sacrifice one kid of the goats for a sin offering, and two lambs of the first year for a sacrifice of peace offerings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And the priest shall wave them with the bread of the firstfruits </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> a wave offering before the LORD, with the two lambs: they shall be holy to the LORD for the priest.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And ye shall proclaim on the selfsame day, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> it may be an holy convocation unto you: ye shall do no servile work </content>
            <content kind="EM">therein: it shall be</content>
            <content> a statute for ever in all your dwellings throughout your generations.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And when ye reap the harvest of your land, thou shalt not make clean riddance of the corners of thy field when thou reapest, neither shalt thou gather any gleaning of thy harvest: thou shalt leave them unto the poor, and to the stranger: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, In the seventh month, in the first </content>
            <content kind="EM">day</content>
            <content> of the month, shall ye have a sabbath, a memorial of blowing of trumpets, an holy convocation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Ye shall do no servile work </content>
            <content kind="EM">therein</content>
            <content>: but ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Also on the tenth </content>
            <content kind="EM">day</content>
            <content> of this seventh month </content>
            <content kind="EM">there shall be</content>
            <content> a day of atonement: it shall be an holy convocation unto you; and ye shall afflict your souls, and offer an offering made by fire unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And ye shall do no work in that same day: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a day of atonement, to make an atonement for you before the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>For whatsoever soul </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> that shall not be afflicted in that same day, he shall be cut off from among his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And whatsoever soul </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> that doeth any work in that same day, the same soul will I destroy from among his people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Ye shall do no manner of work: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it shall be</content>
            <content> a statute for ever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>It </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> unto you a sabbath of rest, and ye shall afflict your souls: in the ninth </content>
            <content kind="EM">day</content>
            <content> of the month at even, from even unto even, shall ye celebrate your sabbath.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, saying, The fifteenth day of this seventh month </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> the feast of tabernacles </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> seven days unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>On the first day </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> an holy convocation: ye shall do no servile work </content>
            <content kind="EM">therein</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Seven days ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the LORD: on the eighth day shall be an holy convocation unto you; and ye shall offer an offering made by fire unto the LORD: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a solemn assembly; </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> ye shall do no servile work </content>
            <content kind="EM">therein</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>These </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> the feasts of the LORD, which ye shall proclaim </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content> holy convocations, to offer an offering made by fire unto the LORD, a burnt offering, and a meat offering, a sacrifice, and drink offerings, every thing upon his day:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Beside the sabbaths of the LORD, and beside your gifts, and beside all your vows, and beside all your freewill offerings, which ye give unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>Also in the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when ye have gathered in the fruit of the land, ye shall keep a feast unto the LORD seven days: on the first day </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> a sabbath, and on the eighth day </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> a sabbath.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>And ye shall take you on the first day the boughs of goodly trees, branches of palm trees, and the boughs of thick trees, and willows of the brook; and ye shall rejoice before the LORD your God seven days.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>And ye shall keep it a feast unto the LORD seven days in the year. </content>
            <content kind="EM">It shall be</content>
            <content> a statute for ever in your generations: ye shall celebrate it in the seventh month.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>Ye shall dwell in booths seven days; all that are Israelites born shall dwell in booths:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>That your generations may know that I made the children of Israel to dwell in booths, when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>And Moses declared unto the children of Israel the feasts of the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="24">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Command the children of Israel, that they bring unto thee pure oil olive beaten for the light, to cause the lamps to burn continually.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Without the vail of the testimony, in the tabernacle of the congregation, shall Aaron order it from the evening unto the morning before the LORD continually: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it shall be</content>
            <content> a statute for ever in your generations.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>He shall order the lamps upon the pure candlestick before the LORD continually.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And thou shalt take fine flour, and bake twelve cakes thereof: two tenth deals shall be in one cake.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And thou shalt set them in two rows, six on a row, upon the pure table before the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And thou shalt put pure frankincense upon </content>
            <content kind="EM">each</content>
            <content> row, that it may be on the bread for a memorial, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> an offering made by fire unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Every sabbath he shall set it in order before the LORD continually, </content>
            <content kind="EM">being taken</content>
            <content> from the children of Israel by an everlasting covenant.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And it shall be Aaron's and his sons'; and they shall eat it in the holy place: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy unto him of the offerings of the LORD made by fire by a perpetual statute.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And the son of an Israelitish woman, whose father </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> an Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel: and this son of the Israelitish </content>
            <content kind="EM">woman</content>
            <content> and a man of Israel strove together in the camp;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And the Israelitish woman's son blasphemed the name </content>
            <content kind="EM">of the LORD</content>
            <content>, and cursed. And they brought him unto Moses: (and his mother's name </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan:)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And they put him in ward, that the mind of the LORD might be shewed them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Bring forth him that hath cursed without the camp; and let all that heard </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> lay their hands upon his head, and let all the congregation stone him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And thou shalt speak unto the children of Israel, saying, Whosoever curseth his God shall bear his sin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And he that blasphemeth the name of the LORD, he shall surely be put to death, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> all the congregation shall certainly stone him: as well the stranger, as he that is born in the land, when he blasphemeth the name </content>
            <content kind="EM">of the LORD</content>
            <content>, shall be put to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And he that killeth any man shall surely be put to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And he that killeth a beast shall make it good; beast for beast.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And if a man cause a blemish in his neighbour; as he hath done, so shall it be done to him;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth: as he hath caused a blemish in a man, so shall it be done to him </content>
            <content kind="EM">again</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And he that killeth a beast, he shall restore it: and he that killeth a man, he shall be put to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Ye shall have one manner of law, as well for the stranger, as for one of your own country: for I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And Moses spake to the children of Israel, that they should bring forth him that had cursed out of the camp, and stone him with stones. And the children of Israel did as the LORD commanded Moses.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="25">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses in mount Sinai, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When ye come into the land which I give you, then shall the land keep a sabbath unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Six years thou shalt sow thy field, and six years thou shalt prune thy vineyard, and gather in the fruit thereof;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>But in the seventh year shall be a sabbath of rest unto the land, a sabbath for the LORD: thou shalt neither sow thy field, nor prune thy vineyard.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>That which groweth of its own accord of thy harvest thou shalt not reap, neither gather the grapes of thy vine undressed: </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> it is a year of rest unto the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And the sabbath of the land shall be meat for you; for thee, and for thy servant, and for thy maid, and for thy hired servant, and for thy stranger that sojourneth with thee,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And for thy cattle, and for the beast that </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> in thy land, shall all the increase thereof be meat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And thou shalt number seven sabbaths of years unto thee, seven times seven years; and the space of the seven sabbaths of years shall be unto thee forty and nine years.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Then shalt thou cause the trumpet of the jubile to sound on the tenth </content>
            <content kind="EM">day</content>
            <content> of the seventh month, in the day of atonement shall ye make the trumpet sound throughout all your land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And ye shall hallow the fiftieth year, and proclaim liberty throughout </content>
            <content kind="EM">all</content>
            <content> the land unto all the inhabitants thereof: it shall be a jubile unto you; and ye shall return every man unto his possession, and ye shall return every man unto his family.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>A jubile shall that fiftieth year be unto you: ye shall not sow, neither reap that which groweth of itself in it, nor gather </content>
            <content kind="EM">the grapes</content>
            <content> in it of thy vine undressed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the jubile; it shall be holy unto you: ye shall eat the increase thereof out of the field.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>In the year of this jubile ye shall return every man unto his possession.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And if thou sell ought unto thy neighbour, or buyest </content>
            <content kind="EM">ought</content>
            <content> of thy neighbour's hand, ye shall not oppress one another:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>According to the number of years after the jubile thou shalt buy of thy neighbour, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> according unto the number of years of the fruits he shall sell unto thee:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>According to the multitude of years thou shalt increase the price thereof, and according to the fewness of years thou shalt diminish the price of it: for </content>
            <content kind="EM">according</content>
            <content> to the number </content>
            <content kind="EM">of the years</content>
            <content> of the fruits doth he sell unto thee.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Ye shall not therefore oppress one another; but thou shalt fear thy God: for I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Wherefore ye shall do my statutes, and keep my judgments, and do them; and ye shall dwell in the land in safety.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And the land shall yield her fruit, and ye shall eat your fill, and dwell therein in safety.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And if ye shall say, What shall we eat the seventh year? behold, we shall not sow, nor gather in our increase:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Then I will command my blessing upon you in the sixth year, and it shall bring forth fruit for three years.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And ye shall sow the eighth year, and eat </content>
            <content kind="EM">yet</content>
            <content> of old fruit until the ninth year; until her fruits come in ye shall eat </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> the old </content>
            <content kind="EM">store</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The land shall not be sold for ever: for the land </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> mine; for ye </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> strangers and sojourners with me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And in all the land of your possession ye shall grant a redemption for the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>If thy brother be waxen poor, and hath sold away </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> of his possession, and if any of his kin come to redeem it, then shall he redeem that which his brother sold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And if the man have none to redeem it, and himself be able to redeem it;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Then let him count the years of the sale thereof, and restore the overplus unto the man to whom he sold it; that he may return unto his possession.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>But if he be not able to restore </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> to him, then that which is sold shall remain in the hand of him that hath bought it until the year of jubile: and in the jubile it shall go out, and he shall return unto his possession.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And if a man sell a dwelling house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it is sold; </content>
            <content kind="EM">within</content>
            <content> a full year may he redeem it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And if it be not redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the walled city shall be established for ever to him that bought it throughout his generations: it shall not go out in the jubile.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>But the houses of the villages which have no wall round about them shall be counted as the fields of the country: they may be redeemed, and they shall go out in the jubile.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Notwithstanding the cities of the Levites, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the houses of the cities of their possession, may the Levites redeem at any time.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And if a man purchase of the Levites, then the house that was sold, and the city of his possession, shall go out in </content>
            <content kind="EM">the year of</content>
            <content> jubile: for the houses of the cities of the Levites </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> their possession among the children of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>But the field of the suburbs of their cities may not be sold; for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> their perpetual possession.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>And if thy brother be waxen poor, and fallen in decay with thee; then thou shalt relieve him: </content>
            <content kind="EM">yea, though he be</content>
            <content> a stranger, or a sojourner; that he may live with thee.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Take thou no usury of him, or increase: but fear thy God; that thy brother may live with thee.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Thou shalt not give him thy money upon usury, nor lend him thy victuals for increase.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God, which brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> to be your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>And if thy brother </content>
            <content kind="EM">that dwelleth</content>
            <content> by thee be waxen poor, and be sold unto thee; thou shalt not compel him to serve as a bondservant:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content kind="EM">But</content>
            <content> as an hired servant, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> as a sojourner, he shall be with thee, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> shall serve thee unto the year of jubile:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">then</content>
            <content> shall he depart from thee, </content>
            <content kind="EM">both</content>
            <content> he and his children with him, and shall return unto his own family, and unto the possession of his fathers shall he return.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>For they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> my servants, which I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: they shall not be sold as bondmen.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>Thou shalt not rule over him with rigour; but shalt fear thy God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>Both thy bondmen, and thy bondmaids, which thou shalt have, </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> of the heathen that are round about you; of them shall ye buy bondmen and bondmaids.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>Moreover of the children of the strangers that do sojourn among you, of them shall ye buy, and of their families that </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> with you, which they begat in your land: and they shall be your possession.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>And ye shall take them as an inheritance for your children after you, to inherit </content>
            <content kind="EM">them for</content>
            <content> a possession; they shall be your bondmen for ever: but over your brethren the children of Israel, ye shall not rule one over another with rigour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>And if a sojourner or stranger wax rich by thee, and thy brother </content>
            <content kind="EM">that dwelleth</content>
            <content> by him wax poor, and sell himself unto the stranger </content>
            <content kind="EM">or</content>
            <content> sojourner by thee, or to the stock of the stranger's family:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>After that he is sold he may be redeemed again; one of his brethren may redeem him:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>Either his uncle, or his uncle's son, may redeem him, or </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> that is nigh of kin unto him of his family may redeem him; or if he be able, he may redeem himself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>And he shall reckon with him that bought him from the year that he was sold to him unto the year of jubile: and the price of his sale shall be according unto the number of years, according to the time of an hired servant shall it be with him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
            <content>If </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> yet many years </content>
            <content kind="EM">behind</content>
            <content>, according unto them he shall give again the price of his redemption out of the money that he was bought for.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
            <content>And if there remain but few years unto the year of jubile, then he shall count with him, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> according unto his years shall he give him again the price of his redemption.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
            <content kind="EM">And</content>
            <content> as a yearly hired servant shall he be with him: </content>
            <content kind="EM">and the other</content>
            <content> shall not rule with rigour over him in thy sight.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
            <content>And if he be not redeemed in these </content>
            <content kind="EM">years</content>
            <content>, then he shall go out in the year of jubile, </content>
            <content kind="EM">both</content>
            <content> he, and his children with him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
            <content>For unto me the children of Israel </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> servants; they </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> my servants whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="26">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Ye shall make you no idols nor graven image, neither rear you up a standing image, neither shall ye set up </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> image of stone in your land, to bow down unto it: for I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Ye shall keep my sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If ye walk in my statutes, and keep my commandments, and do them;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Then I will give you rain in due season, and the land shall yield her increase, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And your threshing shall reach unto the vintage, and the vintage shall reach unto the sowing time: and ye shall eat your bread to the full, and dwell in your land safely.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And I will give peace in the land, and ye shall lie down, and none shall make </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content> afraid: and I will rid evil beasts out of the land, neither shall the sword go through your land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And ye shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall before you by the sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And five of you shall chase an hundred, and an hundred of you shall put ten thousand to flight: and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For I will have respect unto you, and make you fruitful, and multiply you, and establish my covenant with you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And ye shall eat old store, and bring forth the old because of the new.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And I will set my tabernacle among you: and my soul shall not abhor you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And I will walk among you, and will be your God, and ye shall be my people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD your God, which brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, that ye should not be their bondmen; and I have broken the bands of your yoke, and made you go upright.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But if ye will not hearken unto me, and will not do all these commandments;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And if ye shall despise my statutes, or if your soul abhor my judgments, so that ye will not do all my commandments, </content>
            <content kind="EM">but</content>
            <content> that ye break my covenant:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I also will do this unto you; I will even appoint over you terror, consumption, and the burning ague, that shall consume the eyes, and cause sorrow of heart: and ye shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And I will set my face against you, and ye shall be slain before your enemies: they that hate you shall reign over you; and ye shall flee when none pursueth you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And if ye will not yet for all this hearken unto me, then I will punish you seven times more for your sins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And I will break the pride of your power; and I will make your heaven as iron, and your earth as brass:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And your strength shall be spent in vain: for your land shall not yield her increase, neither shall the trees of the land yield their fruits.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And if ye walk contrary unto me, and will not hearken unto me; I will bring seven times more plagues upon you according to your sins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>I will also send wild beasts among you, which shall rob you of your children, and destroy your cattle, and make you few in number; and your </content>
            <content kind="EM">high</content>
            <content> ways shall be desolate.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And if ye will not be reformed by me by these things, but will walk contrary unto me;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Then will I also walk contrary unto you, and will punish you yet seven times for your sins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And I will bring a sword upon you, that shall avenge the quarrel of </content>
            <content kind="EM">my</content>
            <content> covenant: and when ye are gathered together within your cities, I will send the pestilence among you; and ye shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content kind="EM">And</content>
            <content> when I have broken the staff of your bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall deliver </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content> your bread again by weight: and ye shall eat, and not be satisfied.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And if ye will not for all this hearken unto me, but walk contrary unto me;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Then I will walk contrary unto you also in fury; and I, even I, will chastise you seven times for your sins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And ye shall eat the flesh of your sons, and the flesh of your daughters shall ye eat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And I will destroy your high places, and cut down your images, and cast your carcases upon the carcases of your idols, and my soul shall abhor you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And I will make your cities waste, and bring your sanctuaries unto desolation, and I will not smell the savour of your sweet odours.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And I will bring the land into desolation: and your enemies which dwell therein shall be astonished at it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And I will scatter you among the heathen, and will draw out a sword after you: and your land shall be desolate, and your cities waste.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Then shall the land enjoy her sabbaths, as long as it lieth desolate, and ye </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> in your enemies' land; </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> then shall the land rest, and enjoy her sabbaths.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>As long as it lieth desolate it shall rest; because it did not rest in your sabbaths, when ye dwelt upon it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>And upon them that are left </content>
            <content kind="EM">alive</content>
            <content> of you I will send a faintness into their hearts in the lands of their enemies; and the sound of a shaken leaf shall chase them; and they shall flee, as fleeing from a sword; and they shall fall when none pursueth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>And they shall fall one upon another, as it were before a sword, when none pursueth: and ye shall have no power to stand before your enemies.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>And ye shall perish among the heathen, and the land of your enemies shall eat you up.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>And they that are left of you shall pine away in their iniquity in your enemies' lands; and also in the iniquities of their fathers shall they pine away with them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>If they shall confess their iniquity, and the iniquity of their fathers, with their trespass which they trespassed against me, and that also they have walked contrary unto me;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> I also have walked contrary unto them, and have brought them into the land of their enemies; if then their uncircumcised hearts be humbled, and they then accept of the punishment of their iniquity:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>Then will I remember my covenant with Jacob, and also my covenant with Isaac, and also my covenant with Abraham will I remember; and I will remember the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>The land also shall be left of them, and shall enjoy her sabbaths, while she lieth desolate without them: and they shall accept of the punishment of their iniquity: because, even because they despised my judgments, and because their soul abhorred my statutes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>And yet for all that, when they be in the land of their enemies, I will not cast them away, neither will I abhor them, to destroy them utterly, and to break my covenant with them: for I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD their God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>But I will for their sakes remember the covenant of their ancestors, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt in the sight of the heathen, that I might be their God: I </content>
            <content kind="EM">am</content>
            <content> the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>These </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> the statutes and judgments and laws, which the LORD made between him and the children of Israel in mount Sinai by the hand of Moses.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="27">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And the LORD spake unto Moses, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Speak unto the children of Israel, and say unto them, When a man shall make a singular vow, the persons </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> for the LORD by thy estimation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And thy estimation shall be of the male from twenty years old even unto sixty years old, even thy estimation shall be fifty shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And if it </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> a female, then thy estimation shall be thirty shekels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> from five years old even unto twenty years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male twenty shekels, and for the female ten shekels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> from a month old even unto five years old, then thy estimation shall be of the male five shekels of silver, and for the female thy estimation </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> three shekels of silver.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> from sixty years old and above; if </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> a male, then thy estimation shall be fifteen shekels, and for the female ten shekels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>But if he be poorer than thy estimation, then he shall present himself before the priest, and the priest shall value him; according to his ability that vowed shall the priest value him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> a beast, whereof men bring an offering unto the LORD, all that </content>
            <content kind="EM">any man</content>
            <content> giveth of such unto the LORD shall be holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He shall not alter it, nor change it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good: and if he shall at all change beast for beast, then it and the exchange thereof shall be holy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> any unclean beast, of which they do not offer a sacrifice unto the LORD, then he shall present the beast before the priest:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And the priest shall value it, whether it be good or bad: as thou valuest it, </content>
            <content kind="EM">who art</content>
            <content> the priest, so shall it be.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>But if he will at all redeem it, then he shall add a fifth </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> thereof unto thy estimation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And when a man shall sanctify his house </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content> holy unto the LORD, then the priest shall estimate it, whether it be good or bad: as the priest shall estimate it, so shall it stand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And if he that sanctified it will redeem his house, then he shall add the fifth </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be his.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And if a man shall sanctify unto the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">some part</content>
            <content> of a field of his possession, then thy estimation shall be according to the seed thereof: an homer of barley seed </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be valued</content>
            <content> at fifty shekels of silver.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>If he sanctify his field from the year of jubile, according to thy estimation it shall stand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But if he sanctify his field after the jubile, then the priest shall reckon unto him the money according to the years that remain, even unto the year of the jubile, and it shall be abated from thy estimation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And if he that sanctified the field will in any wise redeem it, then he shall add the fifth </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> of the money of thy estimation unto it, and it shall be assured to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And if he will not redeem the field, or if he have sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed any more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>But the field, when it goeth out in the jubile, shall be holy unto the LORD, as a field devoted; the possession thereof shall be the priest's.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">a man</content>
            <content> sanctify unto the LORD a field which he hath bought, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> not of the fields of his possession;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Then the priest shall reckon unto him the worth of thy estimation, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> unto the year of the jubile: and he shall give thine estimation in that day, </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> a holy thing unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>In the year of the jubile the field shall return unto him of whom it was bought, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> to him to whom the possession of the land </content>
            <content kind="EM">did belong</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And all thy estimations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs shall be the shekel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Only the firstling of the beasts, which should be the LORD'S firstling, no man shall sanctify it; whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> ox, or sheep: it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the LORD'S.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And if </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> of an unclean beast, then he shall redeem </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> according to thine estimation, and shall add a fifth </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> of it thereto: or if it be not redeemed, then it shall be sold according to thy estimation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Notwithstanding no devoted thing, that a man shall devote unto the LORD of all that he hath, </content>
            <content kind="EM">both</content>
            <content> of man and beast, and of the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed: every devoted thing </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> most holy unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>None devoted, which shall be devoted of men, shall be redeemed; </content>
            <content kind="EM">but</content>
            <content> shall surely be put to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And all the tithe of the land, </content>
            <content kind="EM">whether</content>
            <content> of the seed of the land, </content>
            <content kind="EM">or</content>
            <content> of the fruit of the tree, </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the LORD'S: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> holy unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And if a man will at all redeem </content>
            <content kind="EM">ought</content>
            <content> of his tithes, he shall add thereto the fifth </content>
            <content kind="EM">part</content>
            <content> thereof.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And concerning the tithe of the herd, or of the flock, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> of whatsoever passeth under the rod, the tenth shall be holy unto the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>He shall not search whether it be good or bad, neither shall he change it: and if he change it at all, then both it and the change thereof shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>These </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> the commandments, which the LORD commanded Moses for the children of Israel in mount Sinai.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
</book>
