<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The vision of Obadiah. Thus saith the Lord GOD concerning Edom; We have heard a rumour from the LORD, and an ambassador is sent among the heathen, Arise ye, and let us rise up against her in battle.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Behold, I have made thee small among the heathen: thou art greatly despised.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>The pride of thine heart hath deceived thee, thou that dwellest in the clefts of the rock, whose habitation </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> high; that saith in his heart, Who shall bring me down to the ground?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Though thou exalt </content>
            <content kind="EM">thyself</content>
            <content> as the eagle, and though thou set thy nest among the stars, thence will I bring thee down, saith the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>If thieves came to thee, if robbers by night, (how art thou cut off!) would they not have stolen till they had enough? if the grapegatherers came to thee, would they not leave </content>
            <content kind="EM">some</content>
            <content> grapes?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>How are </content>
            <content kind="EM">the things</content>
            <content> of Esau searched out! </content>
            <content kind="EM">how</content>
            <content> are his hidden things sought up!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>All the men of thy confederacy have brought thee </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> to the border: the men that were at peace with thee have deceived thee, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> prevailed against thee; </content>
            <content kind="EM">they that eat</content>
            <content> thy bread have laid a wound under thee: </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> none understanding in him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Shall I not in that day, saith the LORD, even destroy the wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">men</content>
            <content> out of Edom, and understanding out of the mount of Esau?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And thy mighty </content>
            <content kind="EM">men</content>
            <content>, O Teman, shall be dismayed, to the end that every one of the mount of Esau may be cut off by slaughter.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>For </content>
            <content kind="EM">thy</content>
            <content> violence against thy brother Jacob shame shall cover thee, and thou shalt be cut off for ever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>In the day that thou stoodest on the other side, in the day that the strangers carried away captive his forces, and foreigners entered into his gates, and cast lots upon Jerusalem, even thou </content>
            <content kind="EM">wast</content>
            <content> as one of them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But thou shouldest not have looked on the day of thy brother in the day that he became a stranger; neither shouldest thou have rejoiced over the children of Judah in the day of their destruction; neither shouldest thou have spoken proudly in the day of distress.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Thou shouldest not have entered into the gate of my people in the day of their calamity; yea, thou shouldest not have looked on their affliction in the day of their calamity, nor have laid </content>
            <content kind="EM">hands</content>
            <content> on their substance in the day of their calamity;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Neither shouldest thou have stood in the crossway, to cut off those of his that did escape; neither shouldest thou have delivered up those of his that did remain in the day of distress.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>For the day of the LORD </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> near upon all the heathen: as thou hast done, it shall be done unto thee: thy reward shall return upon thine own head.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>For as ye have drunk upon my holy mountain, </content>
            <content kind="EM">so</content>
            <content> shall all the heathen drink continually, yea, they shall drink, and they shall swallow down, and they shall be as though they had not been.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But upon mount Zion shall be deliverance, and there shall be holiness; and the house of Jacob shall possess their possessions.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And the house of Jacob shall be a fire, and the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau for stubble, and they shall kindle in them, and devour them; and there shall not be </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> remaining of the house of Esau; for the LORD hath spoken </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">they of</content>
            <content> the south shall possess the mount of Esau; and </content>
            <content kind="EM">they of</content>
            <content> the plain the Philistines: and they shall possess the fields of Ephraim, and the fields of Samaria: and Benjamin </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall possess</content>
            <content> Gilead.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>And the captivity of this host of the children of Israel </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall possess</content>
            <content> that of the Canaanites, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> unto Zarephath; and the captivity of Jerusalem, which </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in Sepharad, shall possess the cities of the south.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And saviours shall come up on mount Zion to judge the mount of Esau; and the kingdom shall be the LORD'S.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
</book>
