<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Paul, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, and Timothy </content>
            <content kind="EM">our</content>
            <content> brother, unto Philemon our dearly beloved, and fellowlabourer,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And to </content>
            <content kind="EM">our</content>
            <content> beloved Apphia, and Archippus our fellowsoldier, and to the church in thy house:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Grace to you, and peace, from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>I thank my God, making mention of thee always in my prayers,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Hearing of thy love and faith, which thou hast toward the Lord Jesus, and toward all saints;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>That the communication of thy faith may become effectual by the acknowledging of every good thing which is in you in Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>For we have great joy and consolation in thy love, because the bowels of the saints are refreshed by thee, brother.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Wherefore, though I might be much bold in Christ to enjoin thee that which is convenient,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Yet for love's sake I rather beseech </content>
            <content kind="EM">thee</content>
            <content>, being such an one as Paul the aged, and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>I beseech thee for my son Onesimus, whom I have begotten in my bonds:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Which in time past was to thee unprofitable, but now profitable to thee and to me:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Whom I have sent again: thou therefore receive him, that is, mine own bowels:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Whom I would have retained with me, that in thy stead he might have ministered unto me in the bonds of the gospel:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But without thy mind would I do nothing; that thy benefit should not be as it were of necessity, but willingly.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>For perhaps he therefore departed for a season, that thou shouldest receive him for ever;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Not now as a servant, but above a servant, a brother beloved, specially to me, but how much more unto thee, both in the flesh, and in the Lord?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>If thou count me therefore a partner, receive him as myself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>If he hath wronged thee, or oweth </content>
            <content kind="EM">thee</content>
            <content> ought, put that on mine account;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>I Paul have written </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> with mine own hand, I will repay </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>: albeit I do not say to thee how thou owest unto me even thine own self besides.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Yea, brother, let me have joy of thee in the Lord: refresh my bowels in the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Having confidence in thy obedience I wrote unto thee, knowing that thou wilt also do more than I say.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But withal prepare me also a lodging: for I trust that through your prayers I shall be given unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>There salute thee Epaphras, my fellowprisoner in Christ Jesus;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Marcus, Aristarchus, Demas, Lucas, my fellowlabourers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> with your spirit. Amen.</content>
        </verse>
        <fragment>
            <content kind="EM">Written from Rome to Philemon, by Onesimus a servant.</content>
        </fragment>
    </chapter>
</book>
