<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Simon Peter, a servant and an apostle of Jesus Christ, to them that have obtained like precious faith with us through the righteousness of God and our Saviour Jesus Christ:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Grace and peace be multiplied unto you through the knowledge of God, and of Jesus our Lord,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>According as his divine power hath given unto us all things that </content>
            <content kind="EM">pertain</content>
            <content> unto life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises: that by these ye might be partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And beside this, giving all diligence, add to your faith virtue; and to virtue knowledge;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And to knowledge temperance; and to temperance patience; and to patience godliness;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And to godliness brotherly kindness; and to brotherly kindness charity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For if these things be in you, and abound, they make </content>
            <content kind="EM">you that ye shall</content>
            <content> neither </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>But he that lacketh these things is blind, and cannot see afar off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old sins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Wherefore the rather, brethren, give diligence to make your calling and election sure: for if ye do these things, ye shall never fall:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>For so an entrance shall be ministered unto you abundantly into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Wherefore I will not be negligent to put you always in remembrance of these things, though ye know </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content>, and be established in the present truth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Yea, I think it meet, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stir you up by putting </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
            <content> in remembrance;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Knowing that shortly I must put off </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> my tabernacle, even as our Lord Jesus Christ hath shewed me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Moreover I will endeavour that ye may be able after my decease to have these things always in remembrance.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>For we have not followed cunningly devised fables, when we made known unto you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were eyewitnesses of his majesty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>For he received from God the Father honour and glory, when there came such a voice to him from the excellent glory, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And this voice which came from heaven we heard, when we were with him in the holy mount.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>We have also a more sure word of prophecy; whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that shineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day star arise in your hearts:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Knowing this first, that no prophecy of the scripture is of any private interpretation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man: but holy men of God spake </content>
            <content kind="EM">as they were</content>
            <content> moved by the Holy Ghost.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>But there were false prophets also among the people, even as there shall be false teachers among you, who privily shall bring in damnable heresies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themselves swift destruction.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And many shall follow their pernicious ways; by reason of whom the way of truth shall be evil spoken of.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And through covetousness shall they with feigned words make merchandise of you: whose judgment now of a long time lingereth not, and their damnation slumbereth not.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For if God spared not the angels that sinned, but cast </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> down to hell, and delivered </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> into chains of darkness, to be reserved unto judgment;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>And spared not the old world, but saved Noah the eighth </content>
            <content kind="EM">person</content>
            <content>, a preacher of righteousness, bringing in the flood upon the world of the ungodly;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>And turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrha into ashes condemned </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> with an overthrow, making </content>
            <content kind="EM">them</content>
            <content> an ensample unto those that after should live ungodly;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And delivered just Lot, vexed with the filthy conversation of the wicked:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>(For that righteous man dwelling among them, in seeing and hearing, vexed </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> righteous soul from day to day with </content>
            <content kind="EM">their</content>
            <content> unlawful deeds;)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptations, and to reserve the unjust unto the day of judgment to be punished:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But chiefly them that walk after the flesh in the lust of uncleanness, and despise government. Presumptuous </content>
            <content kind="EM">are they</content>
            <content>, selfwilled, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Whereas angels, which are greater in power and might, bring not railing accusation against them before the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But these, as natural brute beasts, made to be taken and destroyed, speak evil of the things that they understand not; and shall utterly perish in their own corruption;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And shall receive the reward of unrighteousness, </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> they that count it pleasure to riot in the day time. Spots </content>
            <content kind="EM">they are</content>
            <content> and blemishes, sporting themselves with their own deceivings while they feast with you;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot cease from sin; beguiling unstable souls: an heart they have exercised with covetous practices; cursed children:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Which have forsaken the right way, and are gone astray, following the way of Balaam </content>
            <content kind="EM">the son</content>
            <content> of Bosor, who loved the wages of unrighteousness;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But was rebuked for his iniquity: the dumb ass speaking with man's voice forbad the madness of the prophet.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>These are wells without water, clouds that are carried with a tempest; to whom the mist of darkness is reserved for ever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For when they speak great swelling </content>
            <content kind="EM">words</content>
            <content> of vanity, they allure through the lusts of the flesh, </content>
            <content kind="EM">through much</content>
            <content> wantonness, those that were clean escaped from them who live in error.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>While they promise them liberty, they themselves are the servants of corruption: for of whom a man is overcome, of the same is he brought in bondage.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For if after they have escaped the pollutions of the world through the knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, they are again entangled therein, and overcome, the latter end is worse with them than the beginning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteousness, than, after they have known </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>, to turn from the holy commandment delivered unto them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But it is happened unto them according to the true proverb, The dog </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> turned to his own vomit again; and the sow that was washed to her wallowing in the mire.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>This second epistle, beloved, I now write unto you; in </content>
            <content kind="EM">both</content>
            <content> which I stir up your pure minds by way of remembrance:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>That ye may be mindful of the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets, and of the commandment of us the apostles of the Lord and Saviour:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Knowing this first, that there shall come in the last days scoffers, walking after their own lusts,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And saying, Where is the promise of his coming? for since the fathers fell asleep, all things continue as </content>
            <content kind="EM">they were</content>
            <content> from the beginning of the creation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For this they willingly are ignorant of, that by the word of God the heavens were of old, and the earth standing out of the water and in the water:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Whereby the world that then was, being overflowed with water, perished:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But the heavens and the earth, which are now, by the same word are kept in store, reserved unto fire against the day of judgment and perdition of ungodly men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>But, beloved, be not ignorant of this one thing, that one day </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> with the Lord as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The Lord is not slack concerning his promise, as some men count slackness; but is longsuffering to us-ward, not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night; in the which the heavens shall pass away with a great noise, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat, the earth also and the works that are therein shall be burned up.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content kind="EM">Seeing</content>
            <content> then </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> all these things shall be dissolved, what manner </content>
            <content kind="EM">of persons</content>
            <content> ought ye to be in </content>
            <content kind="EM">all</content>
            <content> holy conversation and godliness,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Looking for and hasting unto the coming of the day of God, wherein the heavens being on fire shall be dissolved, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Nevertheless we, according to his promise, look for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Wherefore, beloved, seeing that ye look for such things, be diligent that ye may be found of him in peace, without spot, and blameless.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>And account </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> the longsuffering of our Lord </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> salvation; even as our beloved brother Paul also according to the wisdom given unto him hath written unto you;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>As also in all </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> epistles, speaking in them of these things; in which are some things hard to be understood, which they that are unlearned and unstable wrest, as </content>
            <content kind="EM">they do</content>
            <content> also the other scriptures, unto their own destruction.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Ye therefore, beloved, seeing ye know </content>
            <content kind="EM">these things</content>
            <content> before, beware lest ye also, being led away with the error of the wicked, fall from your own stedfastness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But grow in grace, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. To him </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> glory both now and for ever. Amen.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
</book>
