<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Genealogy of Jesus Christ</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The book of the genealogy of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Abraham was the father of Isaac, Isaac was the father of Jacob, Jacob was the father of Judah and his brothers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Judah was the father of Perez and Zerah by Tamar, Perez was the father of Hezron, Hezron was the father of Ram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Ram was the father of Amminadab, Amminadab was the father of Nahshon, Nahshon was the father of Salmon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Salmon was the father of Boaz by Rahab, Boaz was the father of Obed by Ruth, Obed was the father of Jesse,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Jesse was the father of David the king. David the king was the father of Solomon by the wife of Uriah,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Solomon was the father of Rehoboam, Rehoboam was the father of Abijah, Abijah was the father of Asa,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Asa was the father of Jehoshaphat, Jehoshaphat was the father of Joram, Joram was the father of Uzziah,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Uzziah was the father of Jotham, Jotham was the father of Ahaz, Ahaz was the father of Hezekiah,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hezekiah was the father of Manasseh, Manasseh was the father of Amon, Amon was the father of Josiah,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Josiah was the father of Jechoniah and his brothers, at the time of the Babylonian resettlement.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>After the Babylonian resettlement, Jechoniah was the father of Shealtiel, Shealtiel was the father of Zerubbabel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Zerubbabel was the father of Abiud, Abiud was the father of Eliakim, Eliakim was the father of Azor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Azor was the father of Zadok, Zadok was the father of Achim, Achim was the father of Eliud,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Eliud was the father of Eleazar, Eleazar was the father of Matthan, Matthan was the father of Jacob,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Jacob was the father of Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So all the generations from Abraham to David are fourteen generations, and from David to the Babylonian resettlement fourteen generations, and from the Babylonian resettlement to the Christ fourteen generations.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Birth of Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now the birth of Jesus Christ took place in this way. When his mother Mary had been betrothed to Joseph, before they came together, she was found to be with child from the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Her husband Joseph, being righteous and not willing to shame her publicly, intended to send her away privately.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But as he thought about these things, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream and said, “Joseph, Son of David, do not be afraid to receive Mary as yoʋr wife, for the child that is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>She will give birth to a son, and yoʋ shall name him Jesus, for he will save his people from their sins.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>All this took place to fulfill what the Lord had spoken through the prophet:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>“Behold, the virgin will conceive and give birth to a son, and they will name him Immanuel” (which means, “God with us”).</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When Joseph awoke from his sleep, he did as the angel of the Lord commanded him. He took his wife,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but did not know her intimately until she had given birth to her firstborn son. And he named him Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Visit of the Wise Men</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judea, in the days of Herod the king, behold, wise men from the east arrived in Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>saying, “Where is the child who has been born king of the Jews? For we saw his star in the east and have come to worship him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When Herod the king heard this, he was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So he assembled all the chief priests and scribes of the people, and inquired of them where the Christ was to be born.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They told him, “In Bethlehem of Judea, for so it is written by the prophet,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>‘But yoʋ Bethlehem, land of Judah, are by no means least among the rulers of Judah; for from yoʋ will come a ruler who will shepherd my people Israel.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then Herod secretly called the wise men and ascertained from them what time the star had appeared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He sent them to Bethlehem and said, “Go search diligently for the child, and when you have found him, bring me word so that I too may come and worship him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They listened to the king and went on their way, and behold, the star that they had seen in the east went before them until it came and stopped over the place where the child was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When they saw the star, they rejoiced with exceedingly great joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>As they came into the house and saw the child with Mary his mother, they fell down and worshiped him. Then they opened their treasures and offered him gifts: gold, frankincense, and myrrh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And being warned in a dream not to return to Herod, they departed for their own country by another way.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Escape to Egypt</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>After they were gone, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to Joseph in a dream, saying, “Rise, take the child and his mother and flee to Egypt, and stay there until I tell yoʋ, for Herod is about to seek the child, to destroy him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So Joseph rose, took the child and his mother by night, and departed for Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>where he stayed until the death of Herod. This was to fulfill what the Lord had said through the prophet: “Out of Egypt I called my son.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Massacre of the Innocent Children</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When Herod saw that he had been fooled by the wise men, he was greatly enraged and sent men to kill all the boys in Bethlehem and in its vicinity who were two years old and under, according to the time that he had ascertained from the wise men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then what had been spoken by Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>“A voice was heard in Ramah, wailing, weeping, and great lamentation, Rachel weeping for her children, and she would not be comforted, because they are no more.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Return to Nazareth</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>After Herod died, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>saying, “Rise, take the child and his mother, and go to the land of Israel, for those who sought the life of the child are dead.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So Joseph rose, took the child and his mother, and went to the land of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But when he heard that Archelaus was reigning over Judea instead of his father Herod, he was afraid to go there. And being warned in a dream, he withdrew to the district of Galilee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and came and dwelt in a town called Nazareth, so that what had been spoken by the prophets might be fulfilled: “He will be called a Nazarene.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Preaching of John the Baptist</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In those days John the Baptist came preaching in the wilderness of Judea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>“Repent, for the kingdom of heaven has drawn near.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>This is the one who was spoken of by Isaiah the prophet, who said, “The voice of one crying out in the wilderness, ‘Prepare the way of the Lord; make his paths straight.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now John wore a garment of camel's hair and a leather belt around his waist, and his food was locusts and wild honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Jerusalem was going out to him, and so were all Judea and all the region around the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They were being baptized by him in the Jordan, confessing their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But when John saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to his baptism, he said to them, “You brood of vipers, who warned you to flee from the coming wrath?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Produce fruit consistent with repentance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And do not think that you can say to yourselves, ‘We have Abraham as our father,’ for I tell you that God is able from these stones to raise up children to Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Even now the axe is laid at the root of the trees. Every tree therefore that does not produce good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>“I baptize you with water for repentance, but he who is coming after me is mightier than I, whose sandals I am not worthy to carry. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>His winnowing fork is in his hand, and he will thoroughly clean out his threshing floor and gather his wheat into the barn, but the chaff he will burn up with unquenchable fire.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Baptism of Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Jesus came from Galilee to the Jordan to John, to be baptized by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But John tried to prevent him, saying, “I need to be baptized by yoʋ, and do yoʋ come to me?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But Jesus answered him, it for now, for thus it is fitting for us to fulfill all righteousness.” Then John permitted him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>After being baptized, Jesus immediately went up from the water. And behold, the heavens were opened to him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove and alighting on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And behold, a voice from heaven said, “This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Temptation of Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Jesus was led up into the wilderness by the Spirit to be tempted by the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>After fasting for forty days and forty nights, he was hungry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the tempter came up to him and said, “If yoʋ are the Son of God, command these stones to become bread.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But Jesus answered, It is written, Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that comes from the mouth of God.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then the devil took him to the holy city, set him on the pinnacle of the temple,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and said to him, “If yoʋ are the Son of God, throw yoʋrself down, for it is written, ‘He will command his angels concerning yoʋ,’ and, ‘In their hands they will lift yoʋ up, so that yoʋ do not strike yoʋr foot against a stone.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Jesus said to him, Again it is written, ‘Yoʋ shall not put the Lord yoʋr God to the test.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Again, the devil took him to a very high mountain and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he said to him, “All these things I will give yoʋ, if yoʋ will fall down and worship me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Jesus said to him, Get behind me, Satan! For it is written, shall worship the Lord yoʋr God, and him only shall yoʋ serve.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then the devil left him, and behold, angels came and ministered to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Begins His Ministry</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now when Jesus heard that John had been put in prison, he withdrew to Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And leaving Nazareth, he went and dwelt at Capernaum by the sea, in the region of Zebulun and Naphtali,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>so that what had been spoken by Isaiah the prophet might be fulfilled:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>“Land of Zebulun and land of Naphtali, way of the sea, beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the people sitting in darkness have seen a great light, and on those sitting in the region and shadow of death light has dawned.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>From that time Jesus began to preach, Repent, for the kingdom of heaven has drawn near.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Calls His First Disciples</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>As Jesus was walking by the Sea of Galilee, he saw two brothers, Simon (who is called Peter) and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea, for they were fishermen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Follow me, and I will make you fishers of men.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So they immediately left their nets and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Going on from there, he saw two other brothers, James the son of Zebedee and John his brother, in the boat with Zebedee their father, mending their nets, and he called them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So they immediately left the boat and their father and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Ministers to Great Crowds</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then Jesus went throughout all of Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing every disease and every sickness among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>So the news about him went out into all of Syria, and the people brought to him all who were sick with various diseases, those suffering severe pain, the demon-possessed, epileptics, and paralytics. And he healed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And large crowds followed him from Galilee, the Decapolis, Jerusalem, Judea, and from beyond the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Beatitudes</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus saw the crowds, he went up on the mountain. And when he sat down, his disciples came to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then he opened his mouth and taught them, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Blessed are those who mourn, for they will be comforted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Blessed are the meek, for they will inherit the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for righteousness, for they will be filled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Blessed are the merciful, for they will receive mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Blessed are the pure in heart, for they will see God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Blessed are the peacemakers, for they will be called sons of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Blessed are those who are persecuted for righteousness' sake, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Blessed are you when others reproach you, persecute you, and say all kinds of evil against you falsely on my account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Rejoice and be glad, for great is your reward in heaven; for in the same way they persecuted the prophets who were before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Salt and Light</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>You are the salt of the earth, but if salt loses its flavor, with what shall it be seasoned? It is no longer fit for anything but to be thrown out and trampled under people's feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>You are the light of the world. A city set on a hill cannot be hidden,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>nor do people light a lamp and put it under a basket, but on a lampstand, and it shines for all who are in the house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let your light shine before others in such a way that they may see your good works and glorify your Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Christ Fulfills the Law and the Prophets</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Do not think that I have come to abolish the Law or the Prophets. I have not come to abolish them, but to fulfill them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For truly I say to you, until heaven and earth pass away, not one letter or stroke of a letter will by any means pass from the law until all is accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore whoever does away with one of the least of these commandments and teaches others to do likewise will be called least in the kingdom of heaven, but whoever practices them and teaches them will be called great in the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For I tell you, unless your righteousness surpasses that of the scribes and Pharisees, you will certainly not enter the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Anger</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>You have heard that it was said to those of old, ‘Yoʋ shall not murder,’ and, ‘Whoever murders will be subject to judgment.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But I say to you that everyone who is angry with his brother will be subject to judgment. Whoever says to his brother, ‘Yoʋ idiot,’ will be subject to the Sanhedrin. And whoever says, ‘Yoʋ fool,’ will be subject to the fires of hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So if yoʋ are offering yoʋr gift at the altar and there remember that yoʋr brother has something against yoʋ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>gift there before the altar and go. First be reconciled to yoʋr brother, and then come and offer yoʋr gift.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Make friends with yoʋr adversary quickly while yoʋ are on the way with him, lest yoʋr adversary hand yoʋ over to the judge, and the judge hand yoʋ over to the guard, and yoʋ be thrown into prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I say to yoʋ, yoʋ will certainly not come out of there until yoʋ have paid the last penny.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Adultery</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>You have heard that it was said, ‘Yoʋ shall not commit adultery.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But I say to you that everyone who looks at a woman to lust after her has already committed adultery with her in his heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So if yoʋr right eye causes yoʋ to stumble, pluck it out and throw it away from yoʋ. For it is better for yoʋ to have one of yoʋr members perish, than for yoʋr whole body to be thrown into hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And if yoʋr right hand causes yoʋ to stumble, cut it off and throw it away from yoʋ. For it is better for yoʋ to have one of yoʋr members perish, than for yoʋr whole body to be thrown into hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Divorce</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>It was also said, ‘Whoever divorces his wife must give her a certificate of divorce.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But I say to you that whoever divorces his wife, apart from a matter of fornication, makes her commit adultery. And whoever marries a divorced woman commits adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Oaths</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Again, you have heard that it was said to those of old, ‘Yoʋ shall not break an oath, but shall keep yoʋr oaths to the Lord.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But I say to you, do not swear at all, neither by heaven, for it is the throne of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>nor by the earth, for it is the footstool of his feet; nor by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the great King.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Neither shall yoʋ swear by yoʋr head, for yoʋ cannot make one hair white or black.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>But let your ‘Yes’ be ‘Yes’ and your ‘No’ be ‘No’; for whatever is more than these is from the evil one.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Retaliation</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>You have heard that it was said, ‘An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But I say to you, do not resist one who is evil. Rather, if anyone slaps yoʋ on the right cheek, turn to him the other also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>If anyone wants to sue yoʋ and take away yoʋr tunic, let him have yoʋr cloak also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And if anyone presses yoʋ into service for one mile, go with him two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Give to him who asks of yoʋ, and do not turn away from him who wants to borrow from yoʋ.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Love for Enemies</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>You have heard that it was said, ‘Yoʋ shall love yoʋr neighbor and hate yoʋr enemy.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>But I say to you, love your enemies, those who curse you, do good to those who hate you, and pray for those who you and persecute you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>so that you may be sons of your Father in heaven. For he makes his sun rise on the evil and the good, and sends rain on the righteous and the unrighteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>For if you love those who love you, what reward do you have? Do not even the tax collectors do the same?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And if you greet only your what are you doing that is out of the ordinary? Do not even the do that?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>You therefore shall be perfect, just as your Father in heaven is perfect.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Giving to the Needy</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Be careful not to give to the needy in front of others to be seen by them, otherwise you have no reward with your Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So when yoʋ give to the needy, do not sound a trumpet before yoʋ, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, so that they may be praised by others. Truly I say to you, they have received their reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But when yoʋ give to the needy, do not let yoʋr left hand know what yoʋr right hand is doing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>so that yoʋr giving may be in secret. Then yoʋr Father who sees in secret will</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Prayer</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When pray, do not be like the hypocrites. For they love to pray standing in the synagogues and at the street corners so that they may be seen by others. Truly I say to you, they have received their reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But when yoʋ pray, go into yoʋr inner room, shut yoʋr door, and pray to yoʋr Father who is in secret. Then yoʋr Father who sees in secret will reward yoʋ</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when you pray, do not babble on repetitiously like the Gentiles do, for they think they will be heard because of their use of many words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Do not be like them, for your Father knows what you need before you ask him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Pray then like this: Our Father in heaven, be yoʋr name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>come. will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Give us this day our daily bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And forgive us our debts, as we our debtors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil. For yoʋrs is the kingdom and the power and the glory forever. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For if you forgive others their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But if you do not forgive others their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Fasting</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When you fast, do not be gloomy like the hypocrites, for they disfigure their faces so that they may be seen by others to be fasting. Truly I say to you, they have received their reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But when yoʋ fast, anoint yoʋr head and wash yoʋr face,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>so that yoʋ may not be seen by others to be fasting, but by yoʋr Father who is in secret. Then yoʋr Father who sees in secret will reward</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Lay Up Treasures in Heaven</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Do not lay up for yourselves treasures on earth, where moth and rust destroy, and where thieves break in and steal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust destroys, and where thieves do not break in or steal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Lamp of the Body</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The lamp of the body is the eye. If then yoʋr eye is clear, yoʋr whole body will be full of light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But if yoʋr eye is bad, yoʋr whole body will be full of darkness. If then the light within yoʋ is darkness, how great is the darkness!</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>You Cannot Serve Two Masters</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>No one can serve two masters, for either he will hate one and love the other, or he will be devoted to one and despise the other. You cannot serve God and money.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Anxiety</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Therefore I tell you, do not be anxious about your life, what you will eat and what you will drink, or about your body, what you will wear. Is not life more than food and the body more than clothing?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Look at the birds of the sky: They do not sow or reap or gather into barns, yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not of more value than they?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Which of you by being anxious can add a single moment to yoʋr span of life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And why are you anxious about clothing? Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow: They do not toil or spin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>yet I tell you that not even Solomon in all his glory was clothed like one of these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now if God so clothes the grass of the field, which is alive today and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, will he not much more clothe you, O you of little faith?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore do not be anxious, saying, ‘What will we eat?’ or, ‘What will we drink?’ or, ‘What will we wear?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For the Gentiles seek after all these things, and your heavenly Father knows that you need them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But seek first the kingdom of God and his righteousness, and all these things will be added to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Therefore do not be anxious about tomorrow, for tomorrow will be anxious about own matters. Sufficient for the day is its own trouble.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Judging Others</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Do not judge, so that you will not be judged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For with the judgment you pronounce you will be judged, and with the measure you use it will be measured to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Why do yoʋ see the speck in yoʋr brother's eye, but do not consider the beam in yoʋr own eye?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Or how will yoʋ say to yoʋr brother, ‘Let me take the speck out of yoʋr eye,’ when there is a beam in yoʋr own eye?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Hypocrite! First take the beam out of yoʋr own eye, and then yoʋ will see clearly to take the speck out of yoʋr brother's eye.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Do not give what is holy to dogs, and do not throw your pearls before pigs, lest they trample them with their feet, and then turn and tear you to pieces.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Ask, Seek, Knock</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and it will be given to you; seek, and you will find; knock, and it will be opened to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For everyone who asks receives, and he who seeks finds, and to him who knocks it will be opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Or what man is there among you, who, if his son asks him for bread, will give him a stone;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and if he asks for a fish, will give him a serpent?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If you then, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father in heaven give good things to those who ask him!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore whatever you wish that others would do to you, do the same also to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Narrow Gate</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Enter through the narrow gate, for wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leads to destruction, and there are many who enter through it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>How narrow is the gate, and restricted the way that leads to life, and there are few who find it!</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Beware of False Prophets</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Beware of false prophets, who come to you in sheep's clothing but inwardly are ravenous wolves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>By their fruits you will know them. Do people gather grapes from thorns, or figs from thistles?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>In the same way, every good tree produces good fruit, but a bad tree produces bad fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A good tree cannot produce bad fruit, neither can a bad tree produce good fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Every tree that does not produce good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>by their fruits you will know them.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>I Never Knew You</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Not everyone who says to me, ‘Lord, Lord,’ will enter the kingdom of heaven, but only he who does the will of my Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Many will say to me on that day, ‘Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy in yoʋr name, and in yoʋr name cast out demons, and in yoʋr name do many miracles?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then I will declare to them, ‘I never knew you; depart from me, you who practice lawlessness.’</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Two Foundations</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Everyone then who hears these words of mine and does them I will compare to a wise man who built his house on the rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The rain fell, the floods came, and the winds blew and beat on that house, but it did not fall, for it was founded on the rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But everyone who hears these words of mine and does not do them will be compared to a foolish man who built his house on the sand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The rain fell, the floods came, and the winds blew and beat against that house, and it fell, and great was its fall.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When Jesus finished saying these things, the crowds were astonished at his teaching,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>because he was teaching them as one who had authority, and not as the scribes.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Cleanses a Man with Leprosy</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus came down from the mountain, large crowds followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And behold, a leper came and bowed down before him, saying, “Lord, if yoʋ are willing, yoʋ can make me clean.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So Jesus stretched out his hand and touched him, saying, I am willing; be made clean.” Immediately his leprosy was cleansed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Jesus said to him, Be sure not to tell anyone about this, but go show yoʋrself to the priest, and offer the gift that Moses commanded, as a testimony to them.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals a Centurion's Servant</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When Jesus entered Capernaum, a centurion came to him and pleaded with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>saying, “Lord, my servant is lying paralyzed at home, suffering terribly.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Jesus said to him, I will come and heal him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But the centurion replied, “Lord, I am not worthy to have yoʋ enter under my roof, but just say the word, and my servant will be healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For I too am a man under authority, with soldiers under me. I say to this one, ‘Go,’ and he goes; and to another, ‘Come,’ and he comes; and to my servant, ‘Do this,’ and he does it.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When Jesus heard this, he was amazed and said to those who were following him, Truly I say to you, not even in Israel have I found such great faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I tell you that many will come from east and west, and recline with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob at the banquet table in the kingdom of heaven,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>but the sons of the kingdom will be cast into the outer darkness; in that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Jesus said to the centurion, Go; it will be done for you just as yoʋ have believed.” And his servant was healed in that hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals Many</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When Jesus came into Peter's house, he saw Peter's mother-in-law lying in bed with a fever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So he touched her hand, and the fever left her. Then she rose and began to serve him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When evening came, many who were possessed by demons were brought to him, and he cast out the spirits with a word and healed all who were sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This was to fulfill what had been spoken by Isaiah the prophet: “He took our infirmities and bore our diseases.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Would-Be Followers of Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When Jesus saw the large crowds around him, he gave orders to depart to the other side of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then a scribe came up and said to him, “Teacher, I will follow yoʋ wherever yoʋ go.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Jesus said to him, have holes, and the birds of the sky have nests, but the Son of Man has nowhere to lay his head.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then another of his disciples said to him, “Lord, let me first go and bury my father.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But Jesus said to him, Follow me, and let the dead bury their own dead.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Calms a Storm</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then he got into the boat, and his disciples followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And behold, a great storm arose on the sea, so that the boat was being swamped by the waves. But Jesus was asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So the disciples came to him and woke him, saying, “Lord, save us! We are perishing!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But he said to them, Why are you afraid, O you of little faith?” Then he rose and rebuked the winds and the sea, and there was a great calm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the men were amazed, saying, “What kind of man is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him?”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals Two Demon-Possessed Men</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When Jesus came to the other side of the sea, to the region of the Gergesenes, two demon-possessed men met him, coming out of the tombs. They were so fierce that no one could pass by that way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And behold, they cried out, “What do yoʋ have to do with us, Jesus, Son of God? Have yoʋ come here to torment us before the appointed time?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now at a distance from them there was a herd of many pigs feeding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So the demons begged Jesus, “If yoʋ cast us out, let us go into the herd of pigs.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>He said to them, Go.” So they came out and went into the herd of pigs, and behold, the whole herd of pigs rushed down the steep bank into the sea and died in the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Those who had been feeding the pigs then ran off, went into the city, and reported everything, including what had happened to the demon-possessed men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And behold, the whole city went out to meet Jesus. And when they saw him, they begged him to depart from their region.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals a Paralytic</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After getting into the boat, Jesus went back across the sea and came to his own city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And behold, some men brought to him a paralytic lying on a bed. When Jesus saw their faith, he said to the paralytic, Take courage, son; yoʋr sins are forgiven</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And behold, some of the scribes said to themselves, “This man is blaspheming.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Perceiving their thoughts, Jesus said, Why are you thinking evil things in your hearts?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Which is easier, to say, ‘Yoʋr sins are or to say, ‘Rise and walk’?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But so that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins”—then he said to the paralytic—Rise, pick up yoʋr bed, and go to yoʋr house.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So he rose and went to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When the crowds saw it, they were amazed and glorified God, who had given such authority to men.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Calls Matthew</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As Jesus went on from there, he saw a man named Matthew sitting at the tax booth. Jesus said to him, me,” so Matthew rose and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Later, as Jesus reclined at the table in Matthew's house, behold, many tax collectors and sinners came and reclined with him and his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When the Pharisees saw this, they said to his disciples, “Why is your teacher eating with tax collectors and sinners?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When Jesus heard this, he said to them, It is not the healthy who have need of a physician, but the sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Go and learn what this means: ‘I desire mercy and not sacrifice,’ for I did not come to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>A Question About Fasting</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the disciples of John came to Jesus and said, “Why is it that we and the Pharisees fast often, but yoʋr disciples do not fast?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Can the bridegroom's attendants mourn as long as the bridegroom is with them? But the days are coming when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and then they will fast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>No one puts a piece of unshrunk cloth on an old garment, for the patch would pull away from the garment, and a worse tear would be made.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Neither do people put new wine into old wineskins. For the wineskins would burst, spilling the wine and ruining the wineskins. But new wine is put into new wineskins, and both are preserved.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>A Girl Restored to Life and a Woman Healed</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>As he said these things to them, behold, a ruler came and bowed down before him, saying, “My daughter has just now died, but come and lay yoʋr hand on her, and she will live.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So Jesus rose and followed him, and so did his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And behold, a woman who had suffered from a flow of blood for twelve years came up behind him and touched the fringe of his garment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For she said to herself, “If only I touch his garment, I will be healed.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But when Jesus turned around and saw her, he said, Take courage, daughter; yoʋr faith has healed yoʋ.” And the woman was healed from that hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>When Jesus came to the house of the ruler and saw the flute players and the crowd making a commotion,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>he said to them, Go away, for the girl is not dead but sleeping.” And they began laughing at him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But when the crowd had been put outside, he went in and took hold of the girl's hand, and she arose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And news of this spread throughout that entire region.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals Two Blind Men</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>As Jesus went on from there, two blind men followed him, crying out, “Have mercy on us, Son of David!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When he went into the house, the blind men came to him, and Jesus said to them, Do you believe that I am able to do this?” They said to him, “Yes, Lord.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then he touched their eyes, saying, Let it be done for yoʋ according to your faith.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And their eyes were opened. Then Jesus sternly warned them, Make sure no one finds out about this.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But they went out and spread the news about him throughout that entire region.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals a Mute Man</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>As they were going away, behold, a mute man possessed by a demon was brought to Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>When the demon was cast out, the mute man spoke, and the crowds were amazed, saying, “Such a thing has never been seen in Israel.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But the Pharisees said, “By the ruler of demons he casts out demons.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Compassion of Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then Jesus went throughout all the cities and villages, teaching in their synagogues, preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing every disease and every sickness among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>When he saw the crowds, he was moved with compassion for them, because they were harassed and helpless, like sheep without a shepherd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then he said to his disciples, The harvest is plentiful, but the workers are few.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Therefore ask the Lord of the harvest to send out workers into his harvest.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Twelve Apostles</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Jesus summoned his twelve disciples and gave them authority to cast out unclean spirits and to heal every disease and every sickness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now these are the names of the twelve apostles: first, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother; James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Philip and Bartholomew; Thomas and Matthew the tax collector; James the son of Alphaeus, and Lebbaeus, who was given the name Thaddaeus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Simon the Cananite, and Judas Iscariot, who betrayed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Sends Out the Twelve Apostles</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>These twelve Jesus sent out, instructing them, Do not go anywhere among the Gentiles, and do not enter any town of the Samaritans,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but go rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>As you go, preach that the kingdom of heaven has drawn near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Heal the sick, cleanse lepers, and cast out demons. Freely you have received; freely give.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Take no gold, silver, or copper in your belts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>no knapsack for your journey, no extra tunic, sandals, or for the worker is worthy of his food.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>you enter a town or village, inquire who in it is worthy, and stay there until you leave that place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>As you enter the house, greet the people who live there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If the household is worthy, let your peace come upon it; but if it is not worthy, let your peace return to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If anyone will not receive you or listen to your words, shake off the dust from your feet as you go out from that house or town.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Truly I say to you, it will be more tolerable on the day of judgment for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah than for that town.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Persecutions Will Come</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Behold, I am sending you out like sheep in the midst of wolves, so be as wise as serpents and as innocent as doves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But beware of men, for they will deliver you up to councils and flog you in their synagogues.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For my sake you will even be brought before governors and kings as witnesses to them and to the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When they hand you over, do not be anxious about how to speak or what to say, for what you are to say will be given to you in that hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For it will not be you speaking, but the Spirit of your Father speaking through you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>will deliver up brother to death, and a father his child, and children will rise up against their parents and have them put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>You will be hated by all because of my name, but he who endures to the end will be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>When they persecute you in one town, flee to another, for truly I say to you, you will certainly not finish going through the towns of Israel before the Son of Man comes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>A disciple is not above his teacher, nor is a servant above his master.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>It is sufficient for a disciple to be like his teacher and for a servant to be like his master. If they have called the master of the house how much more will they malign the members of his household?</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Fear God Alone</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So do not be afraid of them, for there is nothing covered that will not be revealed, and nothing hidden that will not be made known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>What I tell you in the darkness, speak in the light; and what you hear whispered in your ear, proclaim on the housetops.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Do not be afraid of those who kill the body but cannot kill the soul, but rather fear him who can destroy both the soul and the body in hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Are not two sparrows sold for a penny? Yet not one of them will fall to the ground without your Father's consent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And even the hairs of your head are all numbered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So do not be afraid; you are of more value than many sparrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Acknowledging Christ</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Therefore everyone who acknowledges me before men, I will also acknowledge before my Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But whoever denies me before men, I will also deny before my Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Not Peace, but a Sword</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Do not think that I have come to bring peace to the earth. I have not come to bring peace, but a sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>For I have come to set a man against his father, a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And a man's enemies will be the members of his own household.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Whoever loves his father or mother more than me is not worthy of me; whoever loves his son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And whoever does not take up his cross and follow me is not worthy of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Whoever finds his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life for my sake will find it.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Rewards</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Whoever receives you receives me, and whoever receives me receives him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Whoever receives a prophet in the name of a prophet will receive a prophet's reward; whoever receives a righteous person in the name of a righteous person will receive a righteous person's reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And whoever gives one of these little ones even a cup of cold water to drink in the name of a disciple, truly I say to you, he will certainly not lose his reward.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus had finished instructing his twelve disciples, he departed from there to teach and preach in their cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Messengers from John the Baptist</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now when John heard in prison about the works Christ had done, he sent two of his disciples</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>to ask him, “Are yoʋ the one who is to come, or should we wait for another?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Jesus answered them, Go tell John what you hear and see:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The blind receive their sight and the lame walk, lepers are made clean and the deaf hear, the dead are raised and the poor have good news preached to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And blessed is anyone who does not take offense at me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>As these men went away, Jesus began to speak to the crowds about John: What did you go out into the wilderness to see? A reed shaken by the wind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>What then did you go out to see? A man clothed in soft garments? Behold, those who wear soft garments are in the palaces of kings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But what did you go out to see? A prophet? Yes, I tell you, and more than a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For this is the one of whom it is written, Behold, I am sending my messenger ahead of yoʋ, who will prepare yoʋr way before yoʋ.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Truly I say to you, among those born of women there has arisen no one greater than John the Baptist, but whoever is least in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>From the days of John the Baptist until now the kingdom of heaven has been suffering violence, and the violent try to take it by force.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For all the prophets and the law prophesied until John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And if you are willing to accept it, he is Elijah who is to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He who has ears to hear, let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But to what should I compare this generation? It is like children sitting in the and calling out to their companions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>We played the flute for you, but you did not dance; we sang a lament for you, but you did not mourn.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, ‘He has a demon.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The Son of Man came eating and drinking, and they say, ‘Behold, a glutton and a drunkard, a friend of tax collectors and sinners!’ Yet wisdom is justified by her children.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Woe to the Unrepentant</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then Jesus began to reproach the cities in which most of his miracles had been done, because they did not repent:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Woe to yoʋ, Chorazin! Woe to yoʋ, Bethsaida! For if the miracles that were done in you had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But I tell you, it will be more tolerable on the day of judgment for Tyre and Sidon than for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And yoʋ, Capernaum, who have been exalted to heaven, will be brought down to Hades. For if the miracles that were done in yoʋ had been done in Sodom, it would have remained until this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But I tell you, it will be more tolerable on the day of judgment for the land of Sodom than for yoʋ.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Come to Me, and I Will Give You Rest</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>At that time Jesus said, I praise yoʋ, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because yoʋ have hidden these things from the wise and intelligent, and revealed them to infants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Yes, Father, for so it was well-pleasing in yoʋr sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>All things have been delivered to me by my Father. No one knows the Son except the Father, and no one knows the Father except the Son, and anyone to whom the Son chooses to reveal him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Come to me, all of you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Take my yoke upon you and learn from me, for I am gentle and lowly in heart, and you will find rest for your souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Is Lord of the Sabbath</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time Jesus went through the grainfields on the Sabbath. His disciples were hungry and began to pluck heads of grain and eat them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When the Pharisees saw this, they said to him, “Behold, yoʋr disciples are doing what is not lawful to do on the Sabbath.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He said to them, Have you not read what David did when he was hungry, he and those who were with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>how he entered the house of God and ate the bread of the Presence, which was not lawful for him or those who were with him to eat, but only for the priests?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Or have you not read in the law that on the Sabbath the priests in the temple profane the Sabbath and yet are guiltless?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But I tell you that something greater than the temple is here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But if you had known what this means: ‘I desire mercy and not sacrifice,’ you would not have condemned the guiltless.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals a Man with a Withered Hand</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then he departed from there and went into their synagogue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And behold, there was a man who had a withered hand. In order to accuse Jesus, the Pharisees asked him, “Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He said to them, What man among you who has a sheep that falls into a pit on the Sabbath will not take hold of it and lift it out?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Of how much more value is a person than a sheep! So then, it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then he said to the man, Stretch out yoʋr hand.” So he stretched it out, and it was restored, as sound as the other.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But the Pharisees went out and took counsel against Jesus as to how they might destroy him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>God's Chosen Servant</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Aware of this, Jesus withdrew from there. Large crowds followed him, and he healed them all</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and warned them not to make him known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This was to fulfill what had been spoken through Isaiah the prophet:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>“Behold, my servant whom I have chosen, my beloved, in whom my soul is well pleased. I will put my Spirit upon him, and he will declare justice to the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He will not quarrel or cry out, nor will anyone hear his voice in the streets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>A bruised reed he will not break, and a smoldering wick he will not extinguish, until he brings justice to victory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And in his name the Gentiles will hope.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus and Beelzebul</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then a demon-possessed man who was blind and mute was brought to him, and Jesus healed him, so that the man who was blind and mute could speak and see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>All the crowds were amazed and said, “Can this be the Son of David?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But when the Pharisees heard this, they said, “It is only by Beelzebul, the ruler of demons, that this man casts out demons.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Knowing their thoughts, Jesus said to them, Every kingdom divided against itself is laid waste, and no city or house divided against itself will stand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So if Satan casts out Satan, he is divided against himself. How then will his kingdom stand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And if I cast out demons by Beelzebul, by whom do your followers cast them out? Therefore they will be your judges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But if I cast out demons by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God has come upon you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Or how can anyone enter the house of a strong man and plunder his goods unless he first binds the strong man? Then he will plunder his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Whoever is not with me is against me, and whoever does not gather with me scatters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore I tell you, people will be forgiven for every sin and blasphemy, but they will not be forgiven for blasphemy against the Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Whoever speaks a word against the Son of Man will be forgiven, but whoever speaks against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven, neither in the present age nor in the age to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>A Tree Is Known by Its Fruit</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>A tree is known by its fruit. If a tree is good, its fruit will also be good. If a tree is bad, its fruit will also be bad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>You brood of vipers, how can you speak good things, when you are evil? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The good person brings good things out of his good treasure, and the evil person brings evil things out of his evil treasure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But I tell you, on the day of judgment people will give an account for every idle word they speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For by yoʋr words yoʋ will be justified, and by yoʋr words yoʋ will be condemned.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Sign of Jonah</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then some of the scribes and Pharisees responded, “Teacher, we want to see a sign from yoʋ.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But Jesus answered them, An evil and adulterous generation asks for a sign, but no sign will be given to it except the sign of Jonah the prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For just as Jonah was in the belly of the great sea creature for three days and three nights, so will the Son of Man be in the heart of the earth for three days and three nights.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The men of Nineveh will rise up at the judgment with this generation and condemn it, for they repented at the preaching of Jonah, and behold, something greater than Jonah is here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>The queen of the South will rise up at the judgment with this generation and condemn it, for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon, and behold, something greater than Solomon is here.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>An Unclean Spirit Returns</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>When an unclean spirit has gone out of a person, it goes through waterless places seeking rest, but does not find any.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Then it says, ‘I will return to the house I left.’ When it arrives, it finds the house unoccupied, swept, and put in order.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Then it goes and takes with it seven other spirits more evil than itself, and they go in and dwell there, and the last state of that person becomes worse than the first. So will it be with this evil generation also.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus' Mother and Brothers</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>While Jesus was still speaking to the crowds, behold, his mother and his brothers stood outside, asking to speak to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Then someone said to him, “Behold, yoʋr mother and yoʋr brothers are standing outside, asking to speak to yoʋ.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>But he replied to the one who spoke to him, Who is my mother, and who are my brothers?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>And stretching out his hand toward his disciples, he said, Behold, my mother and my brothers!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>For whoever does the will of my Father in heaven is my brother and sister and mother.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Sower</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>On that day Jesus went out of the house and sat by the sea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and large crowds gathered around him. So he got into the boat and sat down, while the entire crowd stood on the shore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then he told them many things in parables, saying, Behold, a sower went out to sow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>As he sowed, some seeds fell along the path, and the birds came and devoured them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Other seeds fell on rocky ground, where they did not have much soil, and they sprang up immediately because they had no depth of soil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But when the sun rose, they were scorched. And because they had no root, they withered away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Other seeds fell among the thorns, and the thorns grew up and choked them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But other seeds fell on good soil and produced fruit, some a hundred, some sixty, and some thirty times more than what was sown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He who has ears to hear, let him hear.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Purpose of Parables</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then the disciples came and said to him, “Why do yoʋ speak to the people in parables?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Jesus answered them, To you it has been given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to them it has not been given.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For whoever has will be given more, and he will have an abundance. But whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>That is why I speak to them in parables, because ‘they see but do not perceive, and they hear but do not listen or understand.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>In them is fulfilled the prophecy of Isaiah, which says, will hear but never understand, and you will see but never perceive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For the heart of this people has become dull; with their ears they have barely heard, and their eyes they have closed, lest they should see with their eyes, with their ears, and understand with their heart and turn back, and I would heal them.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But blessed are your eyes because they see, and your ears because they hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For truly I say to you, many prophets and righteous people desired to see the things you see but did not see them, and to hear the things you hear but did not hear them.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Sower Explained</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>then the parable of the sower:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When anyone hears the word of the kingdom and does not understand it, the evil one comes and what was sown in his heart. This is the seed sown along the path.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The seed sown on rocky ground is he who hears the word and immediately receives it with joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Yet he has no root in himself, but is only temporary. When tribulation or persecution arises on account of the word, he immediately falls away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The seed sown among the thorns is he who hears the word, but the cares of this world and the deceitfulness of riches choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But the seed sown on the good soil is he who hears the word and understands it, who bears fruit and produces a hundred, sixty, or thirty times more than what was sown.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Wheat and the Tares</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Jesus presented another parable to them, saying, The kingdom of heaven may be compared to a person who sowed good seed in his field,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but while people were sleeping, his enemy came and sowed tares among the wheat, and then went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>When the plants sprouted and produced grain, the tares also appeared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So the servants of the master of the house came and said to him, ‘Master, did yoʋ not sow good seed in yoʋr field? How then does it have tares?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>He said to them, ‘An enemy has done this.’ So the servants said to him, ‘Do yoʋ want us to go and gather them up?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He said, ‘No, lest in gathering the tares you uproot the wheat with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Let them both grow together until the harvest, and at the time of the harvest I will say to the reapers, “Gather the tares first and bind them into bundles to burn them up, but gather the wheat into my barn.” ’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Mustard Seed</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>He presented another parable to them, saying, The kingdom of heaven is like a grain of mustard seed that a man took and sowed in his field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Although it is the smallest of all seeds, it grows larger than the other garden plants and becomes a tree, and the birds of the sky come and nest in its branches.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Leaven</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He spoke to them another parable: The kingdom of heaven is like leaven that a woman took and mixed into three measures of flour until it had all been leavened.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Use of Parables</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>All these things Jesus spoke to the crowds in parables; he did not speak to them without using a parable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>This was to fulfill what had been spoken through the prophet: “I will open my mouth in parables; I will declare things hidden from the foundation of the world.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Wheat and the Tares Explained</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then Jesus left the crowds and went into the house, and his disciples came to him and said, “Explain to us the parable of the tares of the field.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>So he said to them in response, He who sows the good seed is the Son of Man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>The field is the world, and the good seeds are the sons of the kingdom. The tares are the sons of the evil one,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and the enemy who sowed them is the devil. The harvest is the end of the age, and the reapers are angels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Therefore, just as the tares are gathered and burned with fire, so it will be at the end of this age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The Son of Man will send his angels, and they will gather out of his kingdom all stumbling blocks and those who practice lawlessness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>They will throw them into the fiery furnace. In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father. He who has ears to hear, let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Hidden Treasure</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a treasure hidden in a field, which a man found and hid again, and in his joy he went and sold all that he had and bought that field.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Pearl of Great Price</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a merchant seeking fine pearls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>When he found one pearl of great price, he went and sold all that he had and bought it.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Dragnet</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a dragnet that was cast into the sea, catching all kinds of fish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>When it was full, the fishermen drew it to shore. Then they sat down and put the good fish into containers, but the bad ones they threw away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>So it will be at the end of the age. The angels will come and separate the evil from the righteous</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>and throw them into the fiery furnace. In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>New and Old Treasures</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Have you understood all these things?” They said to him, “Yes, Lord.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Then he said to them, Every scribe that has been trained as a disciple for the kingdom of heaven is like a master of a house who brings out of his treasure things new and old.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Rejected at Nazareth</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>When Jesus had finished these parables, he departed from there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Then he went to his hometown and taught the people in their synagogue. They were astonished and said, “Where did this man get this wisdom and these miraculous powers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Is this not the carpenter's son? Is not his mother's name Mary, and are not his brothers James, Joses, Simon, and Judas?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Are not all his sisters with us? Where then did this man get all these things?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>And they took offense at him. Then Jesus said to them, A prophet is not without honor except in his hometown and in his own household.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>And he did not do many miracles there because of their unbelief.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Death of John the Baptist</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time Herod the tetrarch heard the report about Jesus</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and said to his servants, “This is John the Baptist; he has been raised from the dead, and that is why these mighty powers are at work in him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For Herod had arrested John, bound him, and put him in prison on account of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For John had been saying to him, “It is not lawful for yoʋ to have her.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Although Herod wanted to kill John, he was afraid of the crowd, because they regarded John as a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But when Herod's birthday was celebrated, the daughter of Herodias danced before the guests and pleased Herod.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So he promised with an oath to give her whatever she might ask.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Prompted by her mother, she said, “Give me here on a platter the head of John the Baptist.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The king was grieved, but because of his oaths and his guests, he commanded it to be given</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and sent orders to have John beheaded in the prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>John's head was brought on a platter and given to the girl, and she brought it to her mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Later, John's disciples came and took his body and buried it. Then they went and brought word to Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Feeding of the Five Thousand</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When Jesus heard this, he withdrew from there in a boat to a desolate place by himself. But the crowds heard about it and followed him on foot from the towns.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when Jesus went ashore and saw a large crowd, he was moved with compassion for them and healed their sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>As evening approached, his disciples came to him and said, “This place is desolate, and the hour is now late. Send the crowds away so that they may go into the villages and buy themselves some food.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But Jesus said to them, They have no need to go away; you give them something to eat.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They said to him, “We have here only five loaves and two fish.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He said, Bring them here to me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then he commanded the crowds to sit down on the grass, and taking the five loaves and the two fish, he looked up to heaven and said the blessing. Then he broke the loaves and gave them to the disciples, and the disciples gave them to the crowds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>They all ate and were filled, and the disciples picked up what was left over of the broken pieces, twelve baskets full.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now those who had eaten were about five thousand men, besides women and children.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Walks on Water</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Immediately Jesus compelled the disciples to get into the boat and go ahead of him to the other side of the sea, while he sent the crowds away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>After sending the crowds away, he went up on the mountain by himself to pray. When evening came, he was there alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Meanwhile, the boat was already in the middle of the sea, being tossed by the waves, for the wind was against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And in the fourth watch of the night Jesus went to them, walking on the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>When the disciples saw him walking on the sea, they were terrified and said, “It is a ghost!” And they cried out in fear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But Jesus immediately said to them, Take courage! It is I; do not be afraid.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In response Peter said to him, “Lord, if it is yoʋ, command me to come to yoʋ on the water.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So he said, Come.” Then Peter got down from the boat and walked on the water to go to Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But when he saw the strong wind, he became frightened, and beginning to sink, he cried out, “Lord, save me!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Immediately Jesus reached out his hand, took hold of him, and said to him, of little faith, why did yoʋ doubt?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And when they had gotten into the boat, the wind ceased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then those who were in the boat came and worshiped him, saying, “Truly yoʋ are the Son of God.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals the Sick in Gennesaret</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>When they had crossed the sea, they came to the land of Gennesaret.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when the men of that place recognized Jesus, they sent word into that entire surrounding region, and people brought to him all who were sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>They begged him to let the sick touch even the fringe of his garment, and all who touched it were completely healed.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Traditions of the Elders</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the scribes and Pharisees from Jerusalem came to Jesus and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>“Why do yoʋr disciples break the tradition of the elders? For they do not wash their hands when they eat bread.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He answered them, And why do you break the commandment of God for the sake of your tradition?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For God commanded, ‘Honor yoʋr father and yoʋr mother,’ and, ‘Whoever speaks evil of his father or mother must surely die.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But you say, ‘If anyone says to his father or mother, “Whatever benefit yoʋ might have received from me is now a gift devoted to God,” then he certainly need not honor his father or his mother.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>You have nullified the commandment of God for the sake of your tradition.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Hypocrites! Isaiah prophesied rightly about you when he said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>This people to me with their mouth and honors me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They worship me in vain, teaching as doctrines the commandments of men.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Jesus called the crowd over and said to them, and understand:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>It is not what goes into the mouth that defiles a person; it is what comes out of the mouth that defiles a person.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then his disciples came and said to him, “Do yoʋ know that the Pharisees were offended when they heard this statement?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Jesus answered, Every plant that my heavenly Father has not planted will be uprooted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>them be; they are blind guides of the blind. And if one blind person guides another, both will fall into a pit.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Peter said to him in response, “Explain this parable to us.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesus said, Are you also still without understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Do you not yet understand that everything that goes into the mouth passes into the stomach and is expelled into the latrine?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But the things that come out of the mouth come from the heart, and these defile a person.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For from the heart come evil thoughts, murder, adultery, fornication, theft, false testimony, and slander.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>These are what defile a person, but to eat with unwashed hands does not defile a person.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>A Canaanite Woman's Faith</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Jesus went away from there and withdrew to the district of Tyre and Sidon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And behold, a Canaanite woman from that region came and cried out to him, “Have mercy on me, Lord, Son of David! My daughter is severely demon-possessed.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But he did not respond to her at all. So his disciples came to him and urged him, “Send her away, for she is crying out after us.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>In response Jesus said, I was sent only to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But she came and bowed down before him, saying, “Lord, help me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He replied, It is not good to take the children's bread and throw it to the dogs.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>She said, “Yes, Lord, yet even the dogs eat the crumbs that fall from the table of their masters.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Jesus answered her, O woman, great is yoʋr faith; it will be done for yoʋ as yoʋ wish.” And her daughter was healed from that hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals Many</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Departing from there, Jesus went along the Sea of Galilee. Then he went up on the mountain and sat down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Large crowds came to him, having with them the lame, blind, mute, crippled, and many others. They put them at the feet of Jesus, and he healed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So the crowds were amazed when they saw the mute speaking, the crippled made well, the lame walking, and the blind seeing. And they glorified the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Feeding of the Four Thousand</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then Jesus called his disciples over and said, I have compassion on the crowd because they have stayed with me now for three days and have nothing to eat. I do not want to send them away without having eaten, lest they faint on the way.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>His disciples said to him, “Where can we get so many loaves in such a desolate place to fill such a large crowd?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus said to them, How many loaves do you have?” They said, “Seven, and a few small fish.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>So he commanded the crowds to sit down on the ground,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and taking the seven loaves and the fish, he gave thanks, broke them, and gave them to his disciples, and the disciples gave them to the crowd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>They all ate and were filled, and the disciples picked up what was left over of the broken pieces, seven baskets full.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Besides women and children, there were four thousand men who had eaten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>After sending the crowds away, Jesus got into the boat and went to the region of Magdala.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Pharisees and Sadducees Ask For a Sign</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the Pharisees and Sadducees came and tested Jesus, asking him to show them a sign from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But he answered them, When evening comes you say, ‘It will be fair weather, for the sky is red.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And in the morning you say, ‘There will be a storm today, for the sky is red and threatening.’ You know how to discern the appearance of the sky, but you cannot discern the signs of the times?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>An evil and adulterous generation asks for a sign, but no sign will be given to it except the sign of Jonah the prophet.” Then he left them and went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When his disciples reached the other side of the sea, they realized that they had forgotten to bring bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them, Watch out and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So they discussed this among themselves, saying, “He must have said this because we brought no bread.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Aware of this, Jesus said to them, Why are you discussing among yourselves, O you of little faith, the fact that you brought no bread?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Do you not yet understand? Do you not remember the five loaves for the five thousand, and how many baskets you collected?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Or the seven loaves for the four thousand, and how many baskets you collected?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>How could you not understand that I was not talking about bread when I told you to beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then they understood that he had not told them to beware of the leaven of bread, but of the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Peter Declares That Jesus Is the Christ</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now when Jesus came into the district of Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, Who do people say that I, the Son of Man, am?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>They said, “Some say John the Baptist, others say Elijah, and others say that yoʋ are Jeremiah or one of the prophets.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He said to them, But who do you say that I am?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Simon Peter answered, “Yoʋ are the Christ, the Son of the living God.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Jesus answered him, Blessed are yoʋ, Simon Bar-Jonah, for flesh and blood has not revealed this to yoʋ, but my Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And I tell yoʋ that yoʋ are Peter, and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of Hades shall not prevail against it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I will give yoʋ the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever yoʋ bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever yoʋ loose on earth will be loosed in heaven.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then he commanded his disciples to tell no one that he was Jesus the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>From that time Jesus began to show his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many things at the hands of the elders, chief priests, and scribes, and that he must be killed and on the third day be raised up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So Peter took him aside and began to rebuke him, saying, “God forbid, Lord! This shall certainly not happen to yoʋ.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But he turned around and said to Peter, Get behind me, Satan! Yoʋ are a stumbling block to me, for yoʋ are not thinking about the things of God, but the things of men.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then Jesus said to his disciples, If anyone wants to come after me, he must deny himself, take up his cross, and follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For whoever wants to save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life for my sake will find it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For what does it benefit a person if he gains the whole world but forfeits his soul? Or what can a person give in exchange for his soul?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For the Son of Man will come with his angels in the glory of his Father, and then he will repay each person according to what he has done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Truly I say to you, there are some standing here who will certainly not taste death until they see the Son of Man coming in his kingdom.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Transfiguration</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After six days Jesus took Peter, James, and John the brother of James, and led them up on a high mountain by themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>There he was transfigured before them; his face shone like the sun, and his garments became as white as light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And behold, Moses and Elijah appeared to them, talking with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So Peter said to Jesus, “Lord, it is good for us to be here. If yoʋ wish, we will make three shelters here, one for yoʋ, one for Moses, and one for Elijah.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>While he was still speaking, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them, and a voice from the cloud said, “This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased; listen to him!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>When the disciples heard this, they fell on their faces and were utterly afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But Jesus came over and touched them, saying, Rise; do not be afraid.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And lifting up their eyes, they saw no one but Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As they were coming down from the mountain, Jesus commanded them, Do not tell anyone about the vision you saw until the Son of Man has risen from the dead.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then his disciples asked him, “Why do the scribes say that Elijah must come first?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Jesus answered them, Elijah does indeed come first, and he will restore all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But I tell you that Elijah has already come, and they did not recognize him, but did to him whatever they wished. Even so the Son of Man is about to suffer at their hands.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then the disciples understood that he was speaking to them about John the Baptist.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals a Demon-Possessed Boy</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When they came to the crowd, a man approached Jesus, kneeling before him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and saying, “Lord, have mercy on my son, for he is an epileptic and suffers terribly. For often he falls into the fire, and often into the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I brought him to yoʋr disciples, but they could not heal him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Jesus answered, O faithless and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you? How long shall I bear with you? Bring him here to me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then Jesus rebuked the demon, and it came out of the boy, and he was healed from that hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Afterward the disciples came to Jesus privately and said, “Why could we not cast it out?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Because of your For truly I say to you, if you have faith like a grain of mustard seed, you will say to this mountain, ‘Move from here to there,’ and it will move. Nothing will be impossible for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content />
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Second Time</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>While they were traveling around in Galilee, Jesus said to them, The Son of Man is about to be delivered up into the hands of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>They will kill him, and on the third day he will be raised up.” And the disciples were greatly distressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Paying the Temple Tax</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When they came to Capernaum, the collectors of the two-drachma tax came to Peter and said, “Your teacher pays the two-drachma tax, doesn't he?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He said, “Yes.” And when Peter came into the house, Jesus spoke to him first, saying, What do yoʋ think, Simon? From whom do the kings of the earth receive toll or tax? From their own sons or from strangers?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Peter said to him, “From strangers.” And Jesus said to him, Then the sons are free.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But so that we may not offend them, go to the sea, cast a hook, and take the first fish that comes up. When yoʋ open its mouth, yoʋ will find a stater coin. Take it and give it to them for yoʋ and me.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>True Greatness</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In that hour the disciples came to Jesus and said, “Who is greater in the kingdom of heaven?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So Jesus called over a little child, placed him among them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and said, I say to you, unless you change and become like little children, you will certainly not enter the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Therefore whoever humbles himself like this little child is greater in the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And whoever receives one little child such as this in my name receives me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but if anyone causes one of these little ones who believe in me to stumble, it would be better for him to have a heavy millstone hung around his neck and to be drowned in the depth of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Temptations to Sin</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Woe to the world because of stumbling blocks! It is necessary that stumbling blocks come, yet woe to that man through whom the stumbling block comes!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>If yoʋr hand or yoʋr foot causes yoʋ to stumble, cut them off and throw them away from yoʋ. It is better for yoʋ to enter life lame or crippled than to have two hands or two feet and be thrown into the eternal fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And if yoʋr eye causes yoʋ to stumble, pluck it out and throw it away from yoʋ. It is better for yoʋ to enter life with one eye than to have two eyes and be thrown into the fires of hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Lost Sheep</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Be careful not to despise one of these little ones, for I tell you that their angels in heaven continually see the face of my Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content />
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>What do you think? If a man has a hundred sheep, and one of them goes astray, does he not leave the other ninety-nine and go seek on the mountains the one that has gone astray?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And if he happens to find it, truly I say to you, he rejoices more over it than over the ninety-nine that have not gone astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>In the same way, it is not the will of your Father in heaven that one of these little ones should perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Restoring a Brother Who Sins Against Yoʋ</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If yoʋr brother sins against yoʋ, go show him his fault between yoʋ and him alone. If he listens to yoʋ, yoʋ have gained yoʋr brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But if he does not listen, take one or two others with yoʋ, so that every matter may be established by the mouth of two or three witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the church. And if he refuses to listen even to the church, treat him as you would a pagan or a tax collector.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Truly I say to you, whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Again, truly I say to you, if two of you agree on earth about anything you ask, it will be done for you by my Father in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For where two or three are gathered together in my name, I am there among them.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Unforgiving Servant</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Peter came to Jesus and said, “Lord, how many times must I forgive my brother when he sins against me? Up to seven times?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Jesus said to him, Not, I tell yoʋ, up to seven times, but up to seventy times seven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For this reason the kingdom of heaven may be compared to a king who wished to settle accounts with his servants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>As he began to settle accounts, one servant who had a debt of ten thousand talents was brought to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But since he did not have anything with which to repay the debt, his master commanded him to be sold along with his wife, his children, and all that he had, so that the debt could be repaid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So the servant fell down and bowed before him, saying, ‘be patient with me, and I will repay yoʋ all that I owe.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Moved with compassion, the master of that servant released him and forgave him the debt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But that servant went out and found one of his fellow servants who owed him a hundred denarii. He grabbed him and began to choke him, saying, ‘Repay me what yoʋ owe.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So his fellow servant fell down at his feet and begged him, ‘Be patient with me, and I will repay</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But he was not willing to do so. Instead, he went and threw him into prison until he should repay what was owed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When his fellow servants saw what had taken place, they were greatly distressed and went and reported to their master all that had happened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then the master summoned the servant and said to him, ‘Yoʋ evil servant! I forgave yoʋ all that debt because yoʋ begged me to do so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Should yoʋ not also have had mercy on yoʋr fellow servant, even as I had mercy on yoʋ?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And in anger his master handed him over to the jailers to be tortured until he should repay all that was owed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>My heavenly Father will also do the same to you if each one of you, from your hearts, does not forgive his brother for his trespasses.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Questions About Divorce</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus had finished saying these things, he departed from Galilee and came into the region of Judea beyond the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Large crowds followed him, and he healed them there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the Pharisees came up to Jesus and tested him by asking him, “Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife for any reason?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He answered them, Have you not read that he who made them from the beginning ‘made them male and female,’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and said, ‘For this reason a man will leave his father and mother and be joined to his wife, and the two will become one flesh’?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So then, they are no longer two, but one flesh. Therefore what God has joined together, let no man separate.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They said to him, “Why then did Moses command us to give her a certificate of divorce and send her away?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He said to them, Because of your hardness of heart Moses allowed you to divorce your wives, but from the beginning it was not so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I tell you that whoever divorces his wife, except for fornication, and marries another, commits adultery. And whoever marries a divorced woman commits adultery.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>His disciples said to him, “If such is the case of a man with his wife, it is better not to marry.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But Jesus said to them, Not all men can accept this statement, but only those to whom it is given.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For there are eunuchs who were born that way from their mother's womb, and there are eunuchs who have been made eunuchs by men, and there are eunuchs who have made themselves eunuchs for the sake of the kingdom of heaven. Whoever is able to accept this should accept it.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Let the Little Children Come to Me</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then little children were brought to Jesus so that he might lay his hands on them and pray, but the disciples rebuked those who brought them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Yet Jesus said, Let the little children come to me and do not hinder them, for the kingdom of heaven belongs to such as these.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And after laying his hands on them, he departed from there.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Rich Young Ruler</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And behold, a man came and said to him, “Good Teacher, what good thing must I do to have eternal life?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Jesus said to him, Why do yoʋ call me good? No one is good except God alone. But if yoʋ wish to enter life, keep the commandments.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The man said to him, “Which ones?” Jesus said, shall not murder, Yoʋ shall not commit adultery, Yoʋ shall not steal, Yoʋ shall not give false testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Honor yoʋr father and yoʋr mother, and, Yoʋ shall love yoʋr neighbor as yoʋrself.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The young man said to him, “All these I have kept from my youth; what do I still lack?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Jesus said to him, If yoʋ wish to be perfect, go sell what yoʋ have and give to the poor, and yoʋ will have treasure in heaven; then come follow me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But when the young man heard this, he went away sorrowful, for he had many possessions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then Jesus said to his disciples, Truly I say to you, only with difficulty will a rich person enter the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Again I say to you, it is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich person to enter the kingdom of God.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When his disciples heard this, they were greatly astonished and said, “Who then can be saved?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus looked at them and said to them, With men it is impossible, but with God all things are possible.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then Peter said to him in response, “Behold, we have left everything and followed yoʋ; what then will there be for us?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Truly I say to you, when all things are made new and the Son of Man sits on his throne of glory, you who have followed me will also sit on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And everyone who has left houses, brothers, sisters, father, mother, wife, children, or fields for my name's sake, will receive a hundred times more and will inherit eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But many who are first will be last, and many who are last will be first.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Workers in the Vineyard</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For the kingdom of heaven is like a master of a house who went out early in the morning to hire workers for his vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>After agreeing with the workers that they would each receive a denarius for the day, he sent them into his vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>About the third hour he went out and saw others standing idle in the marketplace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He said to them, ‘You go into my vineyard as well, and I will give you whatever is right.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So they went. He went out again about the sixth hour and the ninth hour and did likewise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>About the eleventh hour he went out and found others standing and said to them, ‘Why have you been standing here idle all day?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They said to him, ‘Because no one has hired us.’ He said to them, ‘You go into my vineyard as well, and you will receive whatever is right.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When evening came, the owner of the vineyard said to his foreman, ‘Call the workers and pay them their wages, beginning with the last and going on to the first.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When those who had been hired about the eleventh hour came, they each received a denarius.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So when those who had been hired first came, they thought they would receive more, but they also each received a denarius.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When they received it, they grumbled against the master of the house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>saying, ‘These last men worked for one hour, and yoʋ have made them equal to us, who have borne the burden of the day and the scorching heat.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But he replied to one of them, ‘Friend, I am doing yoʋ no wrong. Did yoʋ not agree with me to work for a denarius?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Take what is yoʋrs and go. I wish to give to this last man just as I gave to yoʋ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Or is it not lawful for me to do what I wish with what is mine? Are yoʋ envious because I am good?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So the last will be first, and the first will be last. For many are called, but few are chosen.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Predicts His Death and Resurrection a Third Time</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>As Jesus was going up to Jerusalem, he took the twelve disciples aside privately on the way and said to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be delivered up to the chief priests and scribes. They will condemn him to death</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and hand him over to the Gentiles to be mocked, flogged, and crucified. But on the third day he will rise again.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Request of the Mother of James and John</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then the mother of the sons of Zebedee came with her sons to Jesus, and bowing down she asked him for a favor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So he said to her, What do yoʋ want?” She said to him, “Say that these two sons of mine may sit, one on yoʋr right and one on yoʋr left, in yoʋr kingdom.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Jesus answered, You do not know what you are asking. Are you able to drink the cup that I am about to drink, or to be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with?” The two brothers said to him, “We are able.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So he said to them, You will indeed drink my cup and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with, but to sit on my right and on my left is not mine to give, but it is for those for whom it has been prepared by my Father.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When the ten heard this, they were indignant with the two brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So Jesus called them over and said, You know that the rulers of the Gentiles lord it over them, and their great men exercise authority over them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But it shall not be so among you. Instead, whoever wants to be great among you must be your servant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and whoever wants to be first among you must be your slave,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>just as the Son of Man came not to be served but to serve, and to give his life as a ransom for many.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Heals Two Blind Men</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>As they went out from Jericho, a large crowd followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And behold, there were two blind men sitting by the road. When they heard that Jesus was passing by, they cried out, “Have mercy on us, Lord, Son of David!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But the crowd rebuked them, telling them to be silent. Yet they cried out even more loudly, “Have mercy on us, Lord, Son of David!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>So Jesus stopped, called them over, and said, What do you want me to do for you?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>They said to him, “Lord, let our eyes be opened.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Moved with compassion, Jesus touched their eyes, and immediately their eyes received sight, and they followed him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Triumphal Entry</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When they drew near to Jerusalem and came to Bethsphage, at the Mount of Olives, Jesus sent two disciples ahead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>telling them, Go into the village ahead of you, and immediately you will find a donkey tied there and a colt with it. Untie them and bring them to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>If anyone says anything to you, say, ‘The Lord has need of them.’ And immediately he will send them.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now all this took place to fulfill what the Lord had spoken through the prophet:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>“Say to the daughter of Zion, ‘Behold, yoʋr king is coming to yoʋ, humble and mounted on a donkey, and a colt, the foal of a beast of burden.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So the disciples went and did just as Jesus had directed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They brought the donkey and the colt and laid on them their garments, and Jesus sat on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>A very large crowd spread their garments on the road, and others cut down branches from the trees and also spread them on the road.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The crowds that went ahead of him and those that followed were crying out, “Hosanna to the Son of David! Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord! Hosanna in the highest!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>As he came into Jerusalem, the whole city was stirred up, saying, “Who is this?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So the crowds were saying, “This is Jesus the prophet, who is from Nazareth of Galilee.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Cleanses the Temple</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Jesus entered the courts of God's temple and drove out all who were selling and buying there. He overturned the tables of the money changers and the seats of those who were selling doves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And he said to them, It is written, ‘My house shall be called a house of prayer,’ but you have made it a den of robbers.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the lame and the blind came to him in the temple courts, and he healed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But when the chief priests and the scribes saw the wonderful things that he did and the children crying out in the temple courts, “Hosanna to the Son of David,” they were indignant</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and said to him, “Do yoʋ hear what these children are saying?” Jesus said to them, Yes, have you never read, Out of the mouths of babies and nursing infants have prepared praise’?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And leaving them, he went out of the city to Bethany and spent the night there.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Curses the Fig Tree</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Early in the morning, as Jesus was returning to the city, he was hungry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Seeing a lone fig tree by the road, he came to it and found nothing on it but leaves. Then he said to it, May there never be any fruit from yoʋ again.” And at once the fig tree withered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When the disciples saw it, they were amazed, saying, “How did the fig tree wither all at once?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Jesus answered them, Truly I say to you, if you have faith and do not doubt, not only will you do what has been done to the fig tree, but even if you say to this mountain, ‘Be taken up and thrown into the sea,’ it will happen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And if you have faith, you will receive whatever you ask for in prayer.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Authority of Jesus Questioned</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>When he entered the temple courts, the chief priests and the elders of the people came up to him as he was teaching and said, “By what authority are yoʋ doing these things? And who gave yoʋ this authority?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Jesus answered them, I will also ask you one question. If you tell me the answer, I will also tell you by what authority I am doing these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Where did John's authority to baptize come from? From heaven or from men?” So they discussed it among themselves, saying, “If we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will say to us, ‘Why then did you not believe him?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But we are afraid of what the crowd might do if we say, ‘From men,’ for everyone regards John as a prophet.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So they answered Jesus, “We do not know.” Then he said to them, Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Two Sons</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But what do you think? A man had two sons. He went to his first son and said, ‘Son, go work today in my vineyard.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>His son answered, ‘I will not,’ but afterward he changed his mind and went.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then the man went to his second son and said the same thing. His second son answered, ‘I will go, sir,’ but he did not go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Which of the two did the will of his father?” They said to him, “The first.” Jesus said to them, I say to you, tax collectors and prostitutes are entering the kingdom of God ahead of you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For John came to you in the way of righteousness, and you did not believe him, but tax collectors and prostitutes believed him. Yet even after you saw it, you did not change your minds and believe him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Vineyard Owner</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>to another parable: There was a master of a house who planted a vineyard, put a fence around it, dug a winepress in it, built a tower, leased it to farmers, and left the country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>When the season for fruit drew near, he sent his servants to the farmers to receive his fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>But the farmers took his servants; they beat one, killed another, and stoned yet another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Again he sent other servants, more than the first. But the farmers treated them in the same way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Last of all, he sent them his son, saying, ‘They will have respect for my son.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But when the farmers saw the son, they said among themselves, ‘This is the heir. Come, let us kill him and take possession of his inheritance.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>So they took him, threw him out of the vineyard, and killed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Now when the owner of the vineyard comes, what will he do to those farmers?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>They said to him, “He will bring those wretches to a wretched end and lease the vineyard to other farmers who will give him the fruits in their seasons.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Have you never read in the Scriptures, The stone that the builders rejected has become the cornerstone; this was the Lord's doing, and it is amazing in our eyes’?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Therefore I tell you that the kingdom of God will be taken away from you and given to a people who will produce its fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>He who falls on this stone will be broken to pieces, but anyone on whom it falls will be crushed.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>When the chief priests and the Pharisees heard Jesus' parables, they knew he was speaking about them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Although they were looking for a way to arrest him, they were afraid of the crowds, because the people regarded him as a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Wedding Feast</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Once again Jesus spoke to them in parables, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The kingdom of heaven can be compared to a king who prepared a wedding feast for his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He sent his servants to call those who had been invited to the wedding feast, but they would not come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Again he sent other servants, saying, ‘Tell those who are invited, “Behold, I have prepared my dinner, my oxen and the fattened cattle have been slaughtered, and everything is ready. Come to the wedding feast.” ’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But they paid no attention and went away, one to his own field and another to his business.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The rest seized his servants, mistreated them, and killed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When the king heard about it, he was furious. So he sent his armies, who destroyed those murderers and burned down their city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then he said to his servants, ‘The wedding feast is ready, but those who were invited were not worthy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Go therefore to where the roads exit the city and invite to the wedding feast anyone you find.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So the servants went out to the roads and gathered together all whom they found, both evil and good, and the wedding feast was filled with guests.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But when the king came in to see the guests, he saw a man there who was not clothed with a wedding garment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So he said to him, ‘Friend, how did yoʋ come in here without a wedding garment?’ But the man was speechless.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then the king said to the servants, ‘Bind his feet and hands, take him away, and throw him into the outer darkness. In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For many are called, but few are chosen.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Question About Paying Taxes to Caesar</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then the Pharisees went and took counsel as to how they might ensnare Jesus in what he said.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They sent their disciples to him, along with the Herodians, saying, “Teacher, we know that yoʋ are true and teach the way of God in truth and defer to no one, for yoʋ do not show partiality.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Tell us then, what do yoʋ think? Is it lawful to pay taxes to Caesar or not?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But Jesus knew their evil intent and said, Why are you testing me, you hypocrites?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Show me the coin for the tax.” So they brought him a denarius.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then he said to them, Whose image and inscription is this?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They said to him, “Caesar's.” So he said to them, Then render to Caesar the things that are Caesar's, and to God the things that are God's.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When they heard this, they were amazed. So they left him and went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Sadducees Ask About the Resurrection</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>On that day some Sadducees (who say there is no resurrection) came to Jesus and asked him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>“Teacher, Moses said, ‘If a man dies without having children, his brother must marry the widow and raise up offspring for him.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now there were seven brothers among us. The first married and died, and having no offspring, he left his wife to his brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The same thing happened to the second and to the third, down to the seventh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Last of all, the woman also died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In the resurrection, therefore, which of the seven will she be the wife of? For they all had her.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Jesus answered them, You are in error because you know neither the Scriptures nor the power of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For in the resurrection people neither marry nor are they given in marriage. Instead, they are like angels of God in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But as for the resurrection of the dead, have you not read what God said to you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob’? He is not the God of the dead, but of the living.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And when the crowds heard this, they were astonished at his teaching.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Greatest Commandment</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Now when the Pharisees heard that Jesus had silenced the Sadducees, they gathered together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And one of them, a lawyer, asked Jesus a question to test him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>“Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the law?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Jesus said to him, shall love the Lord yoʋr God with all yoʋr heart, with all yoʋr soul, and with all yoʋr mind.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>This is the important and greatest commandment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And a second is like it: ‘Yoʋ shall love yoʋr neighbor as yoʋrself.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>All the Law and the Prophets hang on these two commandments.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Whose Son Is the Christ?</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>While the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus asked them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>What do you think about the Christ? Whose son is he?” They said to him, “David's.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>He said to them, How is it then that David, in the Spirit, calls him ‘Lord,’ saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>The Lord said to my Lord, Sit at my right hand until I make yoʋr enemies a footstool for yoʋr feet” ’?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>If David calls him ‘Lord,’ how is he his son?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>No one was able to say anything in reply, nor did anyone dare to ask him questions anymore from that day forward.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Woe to the Scribes and Pharisees</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Jesus said to the crowds and to his disciples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The scribes and the Pharisees sit on Moses' seat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore observe and do all that they tell you to observe. But do not do what they do, for they say things and do not do them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They bind burdens that are heavy and hard to bear and lay them on people's shoulders, but they themselves are not willing to lift a finger to move them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They do all their works to be seen by others. They make their phylacteries wide and the fringes of their garments long.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They love the place of honor at banquets, the best seats in the synagogues,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>in the marketplaces, and when others call them ‘Rabbi, Rabbi.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But you are not to be called ‘Rabbi,’ for there is one who is your the Christ, and you are all brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And do not call anyone on earth your father, for there is one who is your Father, he who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Neither are you to be called instructors, for there is one who is your instructor, the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But he who is greater among you must be your servant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you and for a pretense make long prayers. Therefore you will receive a more severe judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content />
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you cross sea and land to make a single convert, and when he has become one, you make him twice as much a son of hell as yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Woe to you, blind guides, who say, ‘If anyone swears by the temple, it is nothing; but if anyone swears by the gold of the temple, he is bound by his oath.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>You fools and blind men! Which is greater, the gold or the temple that the gold sacred?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>You also say, ‘If anyone swears by the altar, it is nothing; but if anyone swears by the gift on the altar, he is bound by his oath.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>You and blind men! Which is greater, the gift or the altar that makes the gift sacred?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Therefore, whoever swears by the altar swears by it and by everything on it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And whoever swears by the temple swears by it and by him who dwells in it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And whoever swears by heaven swears by the throne of God and by him who sits upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you tithe mint, dill, and cumin, yet you have neglected the weightier matters of the law: justice, mercy, and faith. These you ought to have done without neglecting the others.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>You blind guides, who strain out a gnat but swallow a camel!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you cleanse the outside of the cup and the dish, but inside they are full of plunder and</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>blind Pharisee! First clean the inside of the cup and the dish, and then the outside of them will also be clean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you are like whitewashed tombs, which appear beautiful on the outside, but inside they are full of the bones of the dead and all uncleanness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In the same way, you also appear righteous to others on the outside, but inside you are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you build the tombs of the prophets and adorn the graves of the righteous,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and you say, ‘If we had been alive in the days of our fathers, we would not have been participants with them in shedding the blood of the prophets.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore you bear witness against yourselves that you are the sons of those who murdered the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Fill up, then, the measure of your fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>You serpents, you brood of vipers! How will you escape being sentenced to hell?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Therefore, behold, I am sending you prophets, sages, and scribes. Some of them you will kill and crucify, and some of them you will flog in your synagogues and persecute from town to town.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>As a result, all the righteous blood that has been shed on earth will come upon you, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zechariah son of Barachiah, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Truly I say to you, all these things will come upon this generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Lament over Jerusalem</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Jerusalem, Jerusalem, the city that kills the prophets and stones those who are sent to yoʋ! How often I have wanted to gather yoʋr children together as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, but you were not willing!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Behold, your house is left to you desolate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>For I tell you, from now on you will certainly not see me until you say, ‘Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Predicts the Destruction of the Temple</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>As Jesus came out from the temple courts and was walking away, his disciples came to him to show him the buildings of the temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But Jesus said to them, You see all these things, do you not? Truly I say to you, there will certainly not be left here one stone upon another that will not be thrown down.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Signs of the End of the Age</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Later, as Jesus was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples came to him privately and said, “Tell us, when will these things happen? And what will be the sign of yoʋr coming and of the end of the age?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Jesus answered them, Make sure no one leads you astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For many will come in my name, saying, ‘I am the Christ,’ and they will lead many astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>You will of wars and rumors of wars. Do not be alarmed, for all these things must take place, but the end is not yet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For nation will rise up against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will be famines, plagues, and earthquakes in various places.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But all these things are the beginning of the labor pains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then they will deliver you up to tribulation and kill you, and you will be hated by all nations because of my name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Many will fall away and will betray one another and hate one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Many false prophets will rise up and lead many astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Because lawlessness will be increased, the love of many will grow cold,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>but he who endures to the end will be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And this gospel of the kingdom will be proclaimed in the whole world as a testimony to all nations, and then the end will come.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Great Tribulation</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So when you see the abomination of desolation, which was spoken of by Daniel the prophet, standing in the holy place” (let the reader understand),</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>then those who are in Judea must flee to the mountains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He who is on the housetop must not come down to get anything out of his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And he who is in the field must not turn back to get his garments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Woe to those who are with child and to those who are nursing infants in those days!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Pray that your flight will not happen in winter or on a Sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For at that time there will be a great tribulation unlike any other from the beginning of the world until now, and it will never be equaled again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>If those days had not been cut short, no flesh would be saved. But for the sake of the chosen those days will be cut short.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If anyone says to you at that time, ‘Behold, here is the Christ!’ or, ‘Here he is!’ do not believe him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For false christs and false prophets will rise up and perform great signs and wonders so as to lead astray, if possible, even the chosen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Behold, I have told you in advance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So if they say to you, ‘Behold, he is in the wilderness,’ do not go out, or, ‘Behold, he is in the inner rooms,’ do not believe it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For just as lightning comes from the east and shines to the west, so will be the coming of the Son of Man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For where the carcass is, there the vultures will be gathered together.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Coming of the Son of Man</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>But immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light. The stars will fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in the heavens, and all the tribes of the earth will mourn when they see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And he will send his angels with a loud trumpet call, and they will gather together his chosen from the four winds, from one end of the heavens to the other.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Lesson of the Fig Tree</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now learn this lesson from the fig tree: As soon as its branches become tender and put out leaves, you know that summer is near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So also, when you see all these things, know that he is near, at the very gates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>I say to you, this generation will certainly not pass away until all these things have taken place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will certainly not pass away.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Be Ready</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>No one knows about that day and hour, not even the angels of heaven, but only my Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>As were the days of Noah, so will be the coming of the Son of Man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For in the days before the flood, people were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day when Noah went into the ark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>They knew nothing about what would happen until the flood came and took them all away. So will it be at the coming of the Son of Man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Two men will be in the field; one will be taken and one will be left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Two women will be grinding grain at the mill; one will be taken and one will be left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Therefore keep watch, for you do not know in what hour your Lord is coming.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>But know this: If the master of the house had known at what time of night the thief was coming, he would have kept watch and not allowed his house to be broken into.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Therefore you also must be ready, for the Son of Man is coming at an hour when you do not expect him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Who then is the faithful and wise servant, whom his master has set over his household, to give them their food at the proper time?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Blessed is that servant whom his master finds so doing when he comes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Truly I say to you, he will set him over all his possessions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>But if that evil servant says in his heart, ‘My master is delayed in coming,’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>and begins to beat his fellow servants and to eat and drink with the drunkards,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>the master of that servant will come on a day when he does not expect him and at an hour he does not foresee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>and will cut him in two and assign his portion to be with the hypocrites. In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Ten Virgins</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time the kingdom of heaven will be like ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Five of them were wise, and five were foolish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When those who were foolish took their lamps, they did not take oil with them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>but the wise took oil in their flasks along with their lamps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When the bridegroom was delayed, they all became drowsy and slept.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But in the middle of the night there was a shout: ‘Behold, the bridegroom is coming! Come out to meet him.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then all the virgins rose and trimmed their lamps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the foolish ones said to the wise, ‘Give us some of your oil, for our lamps are going out.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But the wise replied, ‘No, there will not be enough for us and for you. Instead, go to those who sell oil and buy some for yourselves.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But while they were on their way to buy it, the bridegroom came, and those who were ready went in with him to the wedding feast. Then the door was shut.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Afterward the other virgins also came, saying, ‘Lord, Lord, open the door for us.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But he answered, ‘Truly I say to you, I do not know you.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Therefore keep watch, for you do not know the day or the hour in which the Son of Man is coming.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Parable of the Talents</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For it is just like a man about to go on a journey, who called his servants and entrusted his possessions to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>To one he gave five talents, to another two talents, and to another one talent, to each according to his ability. And he immediately went on his journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The man who had received the five talents went and traded with them, and made five more talents.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>In the same way, the man who had received the two talents two more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But the man who had received the one talent went and dug a hole in the ground and hid his master's money.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>After a long time the master of those servants came and settled accounts with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The man who had received the five talents came to him and brought the other five talents, saying, ‘Master, yoʋ entrusted me with five talents; behold, I have earned five more talents besides them.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>His master said to him, ‘Well done, good and faithful servant! Yoʋ have been faithful over a few things; I will set yoʋ over many things. Enter into the joy of yoʋr master.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The man who had received the two talents also came to him and said, ‘Master, yoʋ entrusted me with two talents; behold, I have earned two more talents besides them.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>His master said to him, ‘Well done, good and faithful servant! Yoʋ have been faithful over a few things; I will set yoʋ over many things. Enter into the joy of yoʋr master.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then the man who had received the one talent came to him and said, ‘Master, I knew that yoʋ were a hard man, reaping where yoʋ did not sow and gathering where yoʋ scattered no seed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So I was afraid and went and hid yoʋr talent in the ground. Behold, yoʋ have what is yoʋrs.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But his master answered him, ‘Yoʋ evil and lazy servant! Yoʋ knew, did yoʋ, that I reap where I did not sow and gather where I scattered no seed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then yoʋ should have deposited my money with the bankers, and when I came I would have received what is mine with interest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Therefore take the talent from him and give it to the one who has ten talents.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For everyone who has will be given more, and he will have an abundance. But the one who does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And throw that worthless servant into the outer darkness. In that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.’</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Final Judgment</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When the Son of Man comes in his glory, and all the with him, he will sit down on his throne of glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate them from one another as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He will set the sheep on his right and the goats on his left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then the King will say to those on his right, ‘Come, you who are blessed by my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>For I was hungry, and you gave me something to eat; I was thirsty, and you gave me something to drink; I was a stranger, and you took me in;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>I was naked, and you clothed me; I was sick, and you looked after me; I was in prison, and you came to visit me.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then the righteous will answer him, ‘Lord, when did we see yoʋ hungry and feed yoʋ, or thirsty and give yoʋ something to drink?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>When did we see yoʋ as a stranger and take yoʋ in, or naked and clothe yoʋ?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>When did we see yoʋ sick or in prison and come to visit yoʋ?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>The King will answer them, ‘Truly I say to you, inasmuch as you did it to one of the least of these my brothers, you did it to me.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then he will say to those on his left, ‘Depart from me, you who are accursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>For I was hungry, and you did not give me anything to eat; I was thirsty, and you did not give me anything to drink;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>I was a stranger, and you did not take me in; I was naked, and you did not clothe me; I was sick and in prison, and you did not look after me.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Then they too will Lord, when did we see yoʋ hungry or thirsty or as a stranger or naked or sick or in prison, and not take care of yoʋ?’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>He will answer them, ‘Truly I say to you, inasmuch as you did not do it to one of the least of these, neither did you do it to me.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And these will go away into eternal punishment, but the righteous into eternal life.”</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Plot to Kill Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus had finished saying all these things, he said to his disciples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You know that after two days the Passover is coming, and the Son of Man will be delivered up to be crucified.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the chief priests, the scribes, and the elders of the people were gathered together in the courtyard of the high priest, whose name was Caiaphas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and they plotted together to arrest Jesus by stealth and kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But they said, “Not during the feast, lest there be a riot among the people.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Anointed at Bethany</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now when Jesus was in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>a woman came to him with an alabaster jar of very expensive ointment, and she poured it out on his head as he reclined at the table.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When his disciples saw it, they were indignant and said, “For what purpose is this waste?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>This ointment could have been sold for a large sum, and the money could have been given to the poor.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Aware of this, Jesus said to them, Why are you causing trouble for this woman? For she has done a good deed to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>You always have the poor with you, but you do not always have me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>She has put this ointment on my body to prepare me for burial.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Truly I say to you, wherever this gospel is preached in the whole world, what this woman has done will also be spoken of as a memorial to her.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Judas Agrees to Betray Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then one of the twelve, the one called Judas Iscariot, went to the chief priests</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and said, “What are you willing to give me if I deliver him up to you?” So they set out for him thirty pieces of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And from then on he was looking for an opportunity to betray Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Passover with the Disciples</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>On the first day of the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the disciples came to Jesus and said to him, “Where do yoʋ want us to make preparations for yoʋ to eat the Passover?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He said, Go into the city to a certain man and say to him, ‘The Teacher says, “My time is near. I am going to keep the Passover with yoʋ, along with my disciples.” ’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So the disciples did as Jesus had directed them and prepared the Passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When evening came, Jesus was reclining at the table with the twelve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>As they were eating, he said, I say to you, one of you will betray me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Greatly distressed, they began to say to him one after another, “Surely not I, Lord?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus answered, The one who has dipped his hand with me in the dish will betray me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The Son of Man indeed goes just as it is written of him, but woe to that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed! It would have been better for that man if he had not been born.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then Judas, who betrayed him, replied, “Surely not I, Rabbi?” Jesus said to him, have said it yoʋrself.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Institution of the Lord's Supper</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>As they were eating, Jesus took the bread, and when he had given thanks, he broke it, gave it to the disciples, and said, Take and eat this bread; this is my body.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then he took the cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave it to them, saying, Drink of it, all of you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>for this is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many for the remission of sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>But I tell you, from this point forward I will certainly not drink again from this fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it with you anew in the kingdom of my Father.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And after singing a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Predicts Peter's Denial</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them, All of you will fall away because of me this night. For it is written, ‘I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But after I have been raised up, I will go ahead of you to Galilee.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Peter answered him, “Even if everyone else falls away because of yoʋ, I will never fall away.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus said to him, Truly I say to yoʋ that on this night, before a rooster crows, yoʋ will deny me three times.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>But Peter said to him, “Even if I must die with yoʋ, I will certainly not deny yoʋ.” And all the disciples said the same thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Prays in the Garden of Gethsemane</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then Jesus went with them to a place called Gethsemane, and he said to the disciples, Sit here while I go over there and pray.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And taking with him Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, he began to be sorrowful and distressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them, My soul is very sorrowful, even to the point of death; stay here and keep watch with me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And going a little farther, he fell on his face and prayed, My Father, if possible, let this cup pass from me; nevertheless, not as I will, but as yoʋ will.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Then he came to the disciples and found them sleeping, and said to Peter, So you could not keep watch with me for one hour?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Keep watch and pray, lest you enter into temptation. The spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Again, he went away for a second time and prayed, My Father, if this cup cannot pass from me unless I drink it, may yoʋr will be done.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then he came and found them sleeping again, for their eyes were heavy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>So he left them and went away again and prayed for a third time, saying the same thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Then he came to his disciples and said to them, Sleep on now and take your rest! Behold, the hour has drawn near, and the Son of Man is delivered up into the hands of sinners.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Rise, let us go. Behold, my betrayer has drawn near.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Arrested</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>While he was still speaking, behold, Judas, one of the twelve, came. With him was a large crowd with swords and clubs, sent from the chief priests and elders of the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Now his betrayer had given them a sign, saying, “Whomever I kiss, he is the one; arrest him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Immediately he went up to Jesus and said, “Greetings, Rabbi!” And he kissed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Jesus said to him, Friend, for what purpose have yoʋ come?” Then they came forward, took hold of Jesus, and arrested him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And behold, one of the men with Jesus stretched out his hand and drew his sword. He struck the servant of the high priest and cut off his ear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Then Jesus said to him, Put yoʋr sword back into its place, for all who take the sword will by the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Or do yoʋ think that I cannot call on my Father right now, and he will provide me with more than twelve legions of angels?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>How then would the Scriptures be fulfilled that say it must happen this way?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>In that hour Jesus said to the crowds, Have you come out to arrest me with swords and clubs as you would against a robber? I sat daily with you, teaching in the temple courts, and you did not arrest me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>But all this has taken place so that the Scriptures of the prophets would be fulfilled.” Then all the disciples left him and fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Faces the Sanhedrin</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>Now those who had arrested Jesus led him away to Caiaphas the high priest, where the scribes and the elders were assembled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>But Peter was following him at a distance, coming as far as the courtyard of the high priest. After going inside, he sat with the officers to see the outcome.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>Now the chief priests, the elders, and the whole Sanhedrin were seeking false testimony against Jesus, so that they could put him to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>but they did not find any. Even though many false witnesses came forward, they did not find any.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>But at last two false witnesses came forward and declared, “This man said, ‘I am able to destroy the temple of God and rebuild it in three days.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>So the high priest stood up and said to him, “Do yoʋ make no answer? What are these men testifying against yoʋ?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>But Jesus was silent. Then the high priest said to him, “I adjure yoʋ by the living God to tell us if yoʋ are the Christ, the Son of God.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>Jesus said to him, have said it yoʋrself. Nevertheless I say to you, from now on you will see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of Power and coming on the clouds of heaven.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>Then the high priest tore his garments and said, “He has blasphemed! What further need do we have of witnesses? Behold, you have now heard his blasphemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>What do you think?” They answered, “He deserves death.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>Then they spit in his face and struck him. Others slapped him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>saying, “Prophesy to us, yoʋ Christ! Who is it that struck yoʋ?”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Peter Denies Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>Now Peter was sitting outside in the courtyard, and a servant girl came to him and said, “Yoʋ also were with Jesus the Galilean.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>But he denied it before them all, saying, “I do not know what yoʋ are talking about!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>Then he went out to the gateway, and another servant girl saw him and said to those who were there, “This man also was with Jesus of Nazareth.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>But again he denied it with an oath: “I do not know the man.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="73">
      <content>After a little while, those who were standing there came up and said to Peter, “Truly yoʋ also are one of them, for even yoʋr accent gives yoʋ away.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="74">
      <content>Then he began to invoke curses and to swear: “I do not know the man.” And immediately a rooster crowed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="75">
      <content>Then Peter remembered what Jesus had said to him: Before a rooster crows, yoʋ will deny me three times.” And he went out and wept bitterly.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Handed Over to Pontius Pilate</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when morning came, all the chief priests and the elders of the people took counsel against Jesus to put him to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>They bound him, led him away, and handed him over to Pontius Pilate, the governor.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Judas Hangs Himself</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When Judas, who had betrayed him, saw that Jesus had been condemned, he regretted what he had done and returned the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and the elders,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>saying, “I have sinned by betraying innocent blood.” But they said, “What is that to us? See to it yoʋrself.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So he threw the pieces of silver into the temple and departed. Then he went away and hanged himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The chief priests took the pieces of silver and said, “It is not lawful to put them into the temple treasury, since they are a price paid for blood.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So they took counsel and used the money to buy the potter's field as a burial place for foreigners.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore that field has been called the Field of Blood to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then what was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled: “They took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of him on whom a price had been set, on whom some of the sons of Israel had set a price,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and they gave them for the potter's field, as the Lord directed me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Jesus Faces Pilate</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Meanwhile, Jesus stood before the governor, and the governor asked him, “Are yoʋ the king of the Jews?” Jesus said to him, have said it yoʋrself.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But when he was accused by the chief priests and the elders, he made no answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Pilate said to him, “Do yoʋ not hear all the things they are testifying against yoʋ?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But he gave him no answer, not even to a single charge, so the governor was greatly amazed.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Crowd Calls For Jesus' Crucifixion</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now at the feast the governor was accustomed to release one prisoner for the crowd, whomever they wanted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>At that time they had a notorious prisoner named Barabbas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So when the crowds were gathered together, Pilate said to them, “Whom do you want me to release for you? Barabbas, or Jesus, who is called Christ?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>(For he knew they had handed Jesus over out of envy.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>While Pilate was sitting on the judgment seat, his wife sent him this message: “Have nothing to do with that righteous man, for I have suffered a great deal today in a dream because of him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But the chief priests and the elders persuaded the crowds to ask for Barabbas to be released and for Jesus to be executed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>In response the governor said to them, “Which of the two do you want me to release for you?” They said, “Barabbas.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So Pilate said to them, “What then shall I do with Jesus, who is called Christ?” They all said to him, “Let him be crucified!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then the governor said, “Why? What evil has he done?” But they cried out all the more, “Let him be crucified!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When Pilate saw that he was achieving nothing and that a riot was breaking out, he took water and washed his hands before the crowd, saying, “I am innocent of the blood of this righteous man. See to it yourselves.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>All the people answered, “His blood be on us and on our children!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then he released for them Barabbas, but he scourged Jesus and handed him over to be crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Soldiers Mock Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then the governor's soldiers took Jesus with them into the governor's headquarters and gathered against him the entire cohort of soldiers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>They stripped him, put a scarlet robe on him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>twisted together a crown of thorns, and put it on his head. They put a reed in his right hand, and kneeling before him, they mocked him, saying, “Hail, King of the Jews!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then they spit on him, took the reed, and beat him repeatedly on his head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When they had finished mocking him, they stripped him of the robe and put his own garments back on him. Then they led him away to crucify him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Crucifixion</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>As they went out, they found a Cyrenian man named Simon. They pressed him into service, forcing him to carry Jesus' cross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>When they came to a place called Golgotha (which means, “Place of the Skull”),</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>they gave Jesus sour wine to drink mixed with gall. But when he tasted it, he refused to drink it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>After crucifying him, they divided his garments among themselves by casting lots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then they sat down and kept watch over him there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Over his head they placed the written charge against him, which read, “This is Jesus, the King of the Jews.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then two robbers were crucified with him, one on his right and one on his left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Those who passed by reviled him, shaking their heads</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and saying, “Yoʋ who would destroy the temple and build it in three days, save yoʋrself. If yoʋ are the Son of God, come down from the cross!”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>In the same way the chief priests also, along with the scribes, elders, and Pharisees, were mocking him, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>“He saved others, but he cannot save himself. If he is the king of Israel, let him come down now from the cross, and we will believe in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>He has put his trust in God; let God deliver him now if he wants him, for he said, ‘I am the Son of God.’ ”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>The robbers who were crucified with him were also reviling him in the same way.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Death of Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>From the sixth hour until the ninth hour, there was darkness over the whole land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And about the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a loud voice, Eli, Eli, sabachthani?” that is, My God, my God, why have yoʋ forsaken me?”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>When some of those standing there heard this, they said, “This man is calling for Elijah.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Immediately one of them ran, got a sponge, filled it with sour wine, put it on a reed, and gave it to him to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>But the rest said, “Leave him alone. Let us see if Elijah comes to save him.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Then Jesus cried out again with a loud voice and gave up his spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And behold, the veil of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom. The earth was shaken, and the rocks were split.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>The tombs were opened, and the bodies of many saints who had fallen asleep were raised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>(They came out of the tombs, and after his resurrection they went into the holy city and appeared to many.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Now when the centurion and those who were keeping watch with him over Jesus saw the earthquake and the things that had happened, they became very frightened and said, “Truly this man was the Son of God.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Many women who had followed Jesus from Galilee and provided for him were there looking on from a distance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>among whom were Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Burial of Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>When it was evening, there came a rich man from Arimathea named Joseph, who was himself also a disciple of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>He went to Pilate and asked for Jesus' body. So Pilate commanded that the body be given to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>Joseph took the body, wrapped it in a clean linen cloth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>and laid it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn in the rock. Then he rolled a large stone against the entrance of the tomb and went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>Mary Magdalene was there, and so was the other Mary, sitting across from the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Guard at the Tomb</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>The next day (that is, after the day of Preparation), the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered together before Pilate</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>and said, “Sir, we remember that while he was still alive that deceiver said, ‘After three days I will rise again.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>Therefore command that the tomb be secured until the third day, lest his disciples come by night, steal him away, and say to the people, ‘He has been raised from the dead.’ This last deception would be worse than the first.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>Pilate said to them, “You have a guard of soldiers. Go and make it as secure as you know how.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>So they went and secured the tomb by sealing the stone and posting the guard of soldiers.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Resurrection</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After the Sabbath, at dawn on the first day of the week, Mary Magdalene came to see the tomb along with the other Mary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And behold, there was a great earthquake, for an angel of the Lord descended from heaven and came and rolled away the stone from the entrance and sat on it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>His appearance was like lightning, and his clothing was as white as snow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The guards were so afraid of him that they trembled and became like dead men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then the angel said to the women, “Do not be afraid, for I know that you are looking for Jesus, who has been crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He is not here, for he is risen, just as he said. Come see the place where the Lord lay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And now go quickly and tell his disciples that he is risen from the dead. And behold, he is going ahead of you to Galilee; there you will see him. Listen to what I have told you.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So they went out quickly from the tomb with fear and great joy, and ran to tell his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As they went to tell his disciples, behold, Jesus met them and said, Greetings!” So they came up, took hold of his feet, and worshiped him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them, Do not be afraid; go tell my brothers to go to Galilee, and there they will see me.”</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Soldiers Bribed to Lie</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>As they went, behold, some of the guards went into the city and brought word to the chief priests of all that had taken place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>After the chief priests had assembled with the elders and taken counsel, they gave a large sum of money to the soldiers</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and said, “Tell people, ‘His disciples came by night and stole him away while we were sleeping.’</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If this matter is heard before the governor, we will persuade him and keep you free from concern.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So they took the money and did as they had been instructed. And this story is still being spread among the Jews today.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Great Commission</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Meanwhile, the eleven disciples went to Galilee, to the mountain where Jesus had directed them to go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When they saw him, they worshiped him, but some doubted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then Jesus came and said to them, All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Go and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>teaching them to obey everything I have commanded you. And behold, I am with you always, even to the end of the age.” Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>