<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Greeting</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ according to the command of God our Savior and the Lord Jesus Christ our hope,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to Timothy, my true child in the faith: Grace, mercy, and peace from God our Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Warning Against False Teachers</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Just as I urged yoʋ when I was going to Macedonia, remain in Ephesus so that yoʋ may charge certain people not to teach different doctrines</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>or to occupy themselves with myths and endless genealogies, which promote disputes rather than the plan of God that operates by faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The goal of our instruction is love from a pure heart, from a good conscience, and from sincere faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Some have strayed from these and have turned aside to meaningless talk,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>desiring to be teachers of the law, although they do not understand what they are talking about or what they so confidently affirm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now we know that the law is good, if one uses it lawfully.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>We know that the law is not laid down for the righteous, but for the lawless and rebellious, for the ungodly and sinners, for the unholy and profane, for those who kill their father or mother, for murderers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>fornicators, homosexuals, slave traders, liars, perjurers, and whatever else is opposed to the sound teaching</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>that conforms to the gospel of the glory of the blessed God, which has been entrusted to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Paul's Testimony of God's Mercy</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I give thanks to Christ Jesus our Lord, who has given me strength, because he considered me to be faithful and appointed me to serve him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>even though I was formerly a blasphemer, a persecutor, and an insolent man. But I received mercy because I had ignorantly acted in unbelief,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and the grace of our Lord abounded to me greatly with the faith and love that are in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>This saying is trustworthy and deserving of full acceptance: Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am the foremost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But I received mercy for this reason, that in me, as the foremost sinner, Jesus Christ might show complete patience, making me an example for those who would come to believe in him for eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now to the King of the ages, immortal, invisible, the only wise God, be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>This charge I entrust to yoʋ, Timothy, my child, according to the prophecies once made about yoʋ, so that by them yoʋ may fight the good fight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>having faith and a good conscience. By rejecting this, some have shipwrecked their faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Among them are Hymenaeus and Alexander, whom I have handed over to Satan so that they may learn not to blaspheme.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Instruction About Prayer</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I urge then, first of all, that supplications, prayers, intercessions, and thanksgivings be made for all people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for kings and all who are in authority, so that we may lead quiet and peaceful lives in all godliness and dignity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For this is good and acceptable before God our Savior,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>who wants all people to be saved and to come to the knowledge of the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For there is one God and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>who gave himself as a ransom for all, which is the testimony given at the proper time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For this testimony I was appointed to be a preacher, an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and truth. (I am speaking the truth in Christ; I am not lying.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore I want the men in every place to pray, lifting up holy hands without anger or argument.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Likewise, I want the women to adorn themselves in respectable apparel, with modesty and discretion, not with elaborately braided hair, gold, pearls, or expensive clothing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but with good works, which is proper for women who profess godly reverence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>A woman should learn quietly with full submission.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I do not permit a woman to teach or to have authority over a man; rather, she is to remain quiet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For Adam was formed first, then Eve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And Adam was not the one who was deceived; it was the woman who was deceived and fell into transgression.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Nevertheless, women will be saved through childbearing, if they continue in faith, love, and holiness, with self-control.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Qualifications for Overseers</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>This saying is trustworthy: If anyone aspires to the office of overseer, he desires a good work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Therefore the overseer must be above reproach, the husband of one wife, sober-minded, sensible, respectable, hospitable, able to teach,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>not given to wine, not violent, not greedy for sordid gain, but gentle, not contentious, and not a lover of money.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He must lead his own household well, keeping his children in submission with all dignity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>(For if a man does not know how to lead his own household, how will he take care of God's church?)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He must not be a new convert, or he might become puffed up and fall into the condemnation of the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He must also have a good reputation among outsiders, so that he does not fall into the reproach and snare of the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Qualifications for Deacons</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Deacons likewise must be dignified, not double-tongued, not given to much wine, and not greedy for sordid gain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They must hold the mystery of the faith with a clear conscience.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They must first be tested; if they are above reproach, let them serve as deacons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Their wives likewise must be dignified, not slanderers, but sober-minded and faithful in all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A deacon must be the husband of one wife and must lead his children and his own household well.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For those who have served well as deacons obtain a good standing for themselves along with great boldness in the faith that is in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>The Mystery of Godliness</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I am writing these things to yoʋ, hoping to come to yoʋ soon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But if I delay, I am writing so that yoʋ may know how one ought to conduct himself in the household of God, which is the church of the living God, a pillar and foundation of the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Beyond all question, great is the mystery of godliness: God was revealed in the flesh, vindicated by the Spirit, seen by angels, preached among nations, believed on in the world, and taken up in glory.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Some Will Fall Away from the Faith</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the Spirit expressly says that in latter times some will fall away from the faith and occupy themselves with deceitful spirits and the teachings of demons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>being influenced by the hypocrisy of liars who are seared in their own consciences.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They forbid marriage and demand abstinence from foods that God created to be received with thanksgiving by those who believe and know the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For everything created by God is good, and nothing is to be rejected when it is received with thanksgiving,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>since it is sanctified through the word of God and prayer.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>A Good Servant of Jesus Christ</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If yoʋ point these things out to the brothers, yoʋ will be a good servant of Jesus Christ, nourished by the words of the faith and the sound doctrine that yoʋ have closely followed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Have nothing to do with profane myths and old wives' tales. Rather train yoʋrself for godliness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For bodily training is beneficial to a certain extent, but godliness is beneficial in every way, since it holds promises for both the present life and the life to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>This saying is trustworthy and deserving of full acceptance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For this is why we labor and suffer reproach, because we have put our hope in the living God, who is the Savior of all people, and especially of those who believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Command and teach these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let no one despise yoʋ because yoʋ are young, but set an example for the believers in yoʋr speech, conduct, love, spirit, faith, and purity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Until I come, give attention to the public reading of Scripture, to exhortation, and to teaching.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Do not neglect the gift that is in yoʋ, which was given to yoʋ through prophecy when the council of elders laid their hands on yoʋ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Attend to these things and immerse yourself in them, so that yoʋr progress may be evident to all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Watch yoʋr life and doctrine closely. Persevere in these things, for as yoʋ do this, yoʋ will save both yoʋrself and those who listen to yoʋ.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Instructions for the Church</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Do not rebuke an older man, but appeal to him as you would to a father. Speak to younger men as brothers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>older women as mothers, and younger women as sisters, in all purity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Honor widows who are truly widows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But if any widow has children or grandchildren, they should first learn to show godliness toward their own household and to make some repayment to their parents, for this is good and acceptable in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now a woman who is truly a widow and left all alone has put her hope in God and continues night and day in her supplications and prayers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But she who lives in self-indulgence is dead even while she lives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Give these commands as well, so that no one will be open to blame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But if anyone does not provide for his own relatives, and especially for those of his own household, he has denied the faith and is worse than an unbeliever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>A widow may be put on the list to receive support if she is at least sixty years old, has been the wife of one husband,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and has a reputation for good works, that is, if she has brought up children, shown hospitality, washed the feet of the saints, helped the afflicted, and devoted herself to every good work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But reject younger widows, for when their sensual desires draw them away from Christ, they wish to marry,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>thus bringing judgment on themselves because they have broken their previous pledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>At the same time, they learn to be idle, wandering about from house to house. And they are not only idle, but also gossips and busybodies, saying things they should not say.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So I advise the younger widows to marry, bear children, and manage their households, so as to give the adversary no opportunity to revile us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For some have already turned away to follow Satan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If any believing man or woman has relatives who are widows, they must help them; the church should not be burdened, so that it may help those who are truly widows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Elders who lead well should be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who labor in preaching and teaching.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For the Scripture says, “Yoʋ shall not muzzle an ox while it is threshing,” and, “The worker is worthy of his wages.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Do not accept an accusation against an elder unless it is confirmed by two or three witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>As for those who sin, reprove them in the presence of all, so that others will be afraid to follow their example.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I solemnly charge yoʋ before God and the Lord Jesus Christ and the chosen angels to observe these things without partiality, doing nothing out of favoritism.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Do not lay hands on anyone hastily, and do not take part in the sins of others; keep yoʋrself pure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>(No longer drink only water, but use a little wine for the sake of yoʋr stomach and yoʋr frequent illnesses.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The sins of some are obvious, going before them to judgment, but the sins of others trail along behind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>In the same way, good works are obvious, and even those that are not obvious cannot remain hidden.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>All who are under the yoke of slavery must regard their own masters as worthy of all honor, so that no one will revile God's name or his doctrine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2-">
      <content>Slaves who have believing masters must not despise them, for they are brothers; rather they must serve them, because those who benefit from their good service are faithful and beloved.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>False Teachers and the Love of Money</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="-2">
      <content>Teach and encourage these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>If anyone teaches a different doctrine and does not agree with the sound words of our Lord Jesus Christ and the teaching that is in accordance with godliness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>he is puffed up and understands nothing. Moreover, he has an unhealthy desire for controversies and quarrels about words, from which come envy, strife, slanderous words, evil suspicions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and constant disagreement among people who are depraved in mind and deprived of the truth, supposing that godliness is a means of gain. Keep away from such people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But godliness with contentment is great gain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For we brought nothing into the world, and it is clear that we cannot bring anything out either,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but if we have food and clothing, we will be content with that.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But those who wish to be rich fall into temptation and a snare, and into many senseless and harmful desires that sink people into ruin and destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For the love of money is the root of all kinds of evil, and in their eagerness to become rich some have wandered away from the faith, piercing themselves with many sorrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Fight the Good Fight</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But as for yoʋ, O man of God, flee from these things, and pursue righteousness, godliness, faithfulness, love, endurance, and gentleness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Fight the good fight of faith. Take hold of the eternal life to which yoʋ were called and concerning which yoʋ made the good confession in the presence of many witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I charge yoʋ before God, who gives life to all things, and before Christ Jesus, who made the good confession in his testimony before Pontius Pilate,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>that yoʋ obey what has been commanded without fault or reproach until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>which God will reveal in his own time. He is the blessed and only Sovereign, the King of kings and Lord of lords,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>who alone has immortality, dwelling in unapproachable light, whom no man has ever seen or is able to see. To him be honor and eternal power. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Command those who are rich in this present age not to be haughty or to put their hope in the uncertainty of riches, but in the living God, who richly provides us with everything for our enjoyment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Command them to do good, to be rich in good works, and to be generous and willing to share,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>treasuring up for themselves a good foundation for the time to come, so that they may take hold of eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>O Timothy, guard what has been entrusted to yoʋ and avoid the profane chatter and counterarguments of what is falsely called “knowledge.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>By professing it, some have strayed from the faith. Grace be with yoʋ. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>