<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Greeting</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God according to the promise of life that is in Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to Timothy, my beloved child: Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Paul's Charge to Timothy</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I thank God, whom I serve with a clear conscience as my forefathers did, as night and day I constantly remember yoʋ in my prayers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Recalling yoʋr tears, I long to see yoʋ so that I may be filled with joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I am reminded of the sincere faith that is in yoʋ, which dwelt first in yoʋr grandmother Lois and in yoʋr mother Eunice, and now, I am sure, dwells in yoʋ also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore I remind yoʋ to rekindle the gift of God that is in yoʋ through the laying on of my hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For God did not give us a spirit of timidity, but a spirit of power, love, and sound judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore do not be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord or of me his prisoner. Rather, join with me in suffering for the gospel as you rely on the power of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He saved us and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace. This grace was given to us in Christ Jesus before time began,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but has now been revealed through the appearing of our Savior Jesus Christ, who abolished death and brought life and immortality to light through the gospel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For this gospel I was appointed to be a preacher, an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>That is why I am suffering these things. But I am not ashamed, for I know whom I have believed, and I am persuaded that he is able to guard what has been entrusted to me until that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Hold to the pattern of sound teaching that yoʋ have heard from me, in the faith and love that are in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>By the Holy Spirit who dwells within us, guard the good deposit that has been entrusted to yoʋ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Yoʋ know that everyone in Asia has turned away from me, including Phygelus and Hermogenes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>May the Lord give mercy to the household of Onesiphorus, because he often refreshed me and was not ashamed of my chains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>On the contrary, when he arrived in Rome, he sought me out very diligently and found me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>May the Lord grant him to find mercy from the Lord on that day! Yoʋ know very well all the ways he helped me in Ephesus.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>A Good Soldier of Christ Jesus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Yoʋ then, my child, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Entrust what yoʋ have heard from me in the presence of many witnesses to faithful men who will be competent to teach others also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Endure hardship as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>No one serving as a soldier entangles himself in the affairs of civilian life, since he seeks to please the one who enlisted him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Similarly, an athlete is not crowned unless he competes according to the rules.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The hardworking farmer ought to receive the first share of the crops.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Think about what I am saying. May the Lord give yoʋ understanding in everything.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Remember Jesus Christ, the offspring of David, who was raised from the dead according to my gospel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For this gospel I suffer to the point of being chained like a criminal, but the word of God is not chained.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore I endure everything for the sake of the chosen, so that they too may obtain the salvation that is in Christ Jesus, with eternal glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This saying is trustworthy: If we died with him, we will also live with him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>if we endure, we will also reign with him; if we deny him, he will also deny us;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>if we are unfaithful, he remains faithful; he cannot deny himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>A Faithful Workman of God</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Remind the people of these things, solemnly charging them before the Lord not to quarrel about words, which does no good but only leads to the ruin of those who are listening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Be diligent to present yoʋrself to God as a proven worker who does not need to be ashamed and who correctly teaches the word of truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Avoid profane chatter, for those who engage in such talk will stray further and further into ungodliness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and their message will spread like gangrene. Among them are Hymenaeus and Philetus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>who have strayed from the truth, saying that the resurrection has already happened. They are undermining the faith of some.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Nevertheless, the foundation of God stands firm, having this seal: “The Lord knows those who are his,” and, “Everyone who calls upon the name of the Lord must depart from unrighteousness.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now in a large house there are not only vessels of gold and silver, but also of wood and clay; some are for honorable use and some for dishonorable use.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, if anyone cleanses himself from what is dishonorable, he will be a vessel for honorable use, set apart as holy, useful to the master, and prepared for every good work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Flee youthful lusts and pursue righteousness, faithfulness, love, and peace, along with those who call upon the Lord from a pure heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Have nothing to do with foolish and ignorant controversies, knowing that they breed quarrels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>A servant of the Lord ought not to quarrel, but to be kind to everyone, able to teach, and patient,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>instructing his opponents with gentleness. Perhaps God will grant them repentance leading to the knowledge of the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then they will come to their senses and escape from the snare of the devil, who has taken them captive to do his will.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Hard Times in the Last Days</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But know this: Hard times will come in the last days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For people will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boasters, proud, blasphemous, disobedient to parents, ungrateful, unholy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>without natural affection, irreconcilable, slanderous, without self-control, brutal, having no love for what is good,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>traitors, reckless, puffed up, and lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>having a form of godliness but denying its power. Avoid such people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Among them are those who worm their way into houses and captivate vulnerable women who are overwhelmed with sins and swayed by various evil desires.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Such women are always learning yet never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Just as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so these false teachers also oppose the truth. They are corrupted in mind and have proven themselves to be unqualified with respect to the faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But they will not make any further progress, for their folly will become obvious to everyone, just like the folly of Jannes and Jambres.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Continue in What You Have Learned</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Yoʋ, however, have closely followed my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, patience, love, and endurance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Yoʋ know how much persecution and suffering I endured in Antioch, Iconium, and Lystra. Yet the Lord rescued me from it all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Indeed, everyone who wants to live a godly life in Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But evil people and imposters will become worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But as for yoʋ, continue in what yoʋ have learned and firmly believed, knowing from whom yoʋ have learned it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and how from childhood yoʋ have known the sacred writings, which are able to give yoʋ wisdom for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>All Scripture is inspired by God and is beneficial for teaching, reproof, correction, and instruction in righteousness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>so that the man of God may be complete, fully equipped for every good work.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Preach the Word</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I solemnly charge yoʋ therefore in the presence of God and the Lord Jesus Christ, who will judge the living and the dead when he appears with his kingdom:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Preach the word, be prepared whether the time is favorable or not, reprove, rebuke, and encourage, with complete patience and careful instruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For a time is coming when people will not tolerate sound doctrine, but having itching ears they will surround themselves with teachers to suit their own desires.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They will turn their ears away from the truth and be turned aside to myths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But as for yoʋ, be sober-minded in all things, endure hardship, do the work of an evangelist, and fulfill yoʋr ministry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For I am already being poured out like a drink offering, and the time of my departure is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>I have fought the good fight, I have finished the race, I have kept the faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>There is now laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will give to me on that day, and not only to me, but also to all who have longed for his appearing.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Personal Instructions</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Make every effort to come to me soon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For Demas, who is in love with this present world, has deserted me and gone to Thessalonica. Crescens has gone to Galatia, and Titus to Dalmatia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Luke alone is with me. Get Mark and bring him with yoʋ, for he is useful to me for ministry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Tychicus I have sent to Ephesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When yoʋ come, bring the cloak that I left with Carpus in Troas, as well as my scrolls, especially the parchments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Alexander the coppersmith did me great harm. May the Lord repay him according to his works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Yoʋ yoʋrself should be on guard against him, for he has vehemently opposed our message.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>At my first defense no one came to stand by me; instead, they all deserted me. May it not be counted against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But the Lord stood by me and strengthened me, so that through me the proclamation might be fully made and all the Gentiles might hear. And I was rescued from the lion's mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the Lord will rescue me from every evil deed and preserve me for his heavenly kingdom. To him be the glory forever and ever. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Final Greetings</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Greet Prisca and Aquila and the household of Onesiphorus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Erastus stayed in Corinth, and Trophimus, who was sick, I left in Miletus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Make every effort to come before winter. Eubulus greets yoʋ, and so do Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and all the brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The Lord Jesus Christ be with yoʋr spirit. Grace be with you. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>