<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Greeting</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, a servant of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ, appointed to further the faith of God's chosen ones and the knowledge of the truth that is in accordance with godliness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>in the hope of eternal life, which God, who does not lie, promised before time began;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>in his own time he revealed his word through the preaching with which I was entrusted by the command of God our Savior;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>to Titus, my true child in our common faith: Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ our Savior.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Qualifications for Elders</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The reason I left yoʋ in Crete was for yoʋ to put in order what remained to be done and to appoint elders in every town, as I directed yoʋ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>An elder must be above reproach, the husband of one wife, with faithful children who are not rebellious and cannot be accused of debauchery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For an overseer, as God's steward, must be above reproach, not self-willed, not quick-tempered, not given to wine, not violent, not greedy for sordid gain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but hospitable, a lover of goodness, sensible, just, holy, and self-controlled,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>holding firmly to the trustworthy message as it has been taught, so that he can encourage others with sound doctrine and refute those who contradict it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For there are many rebellious people, full of meaningless talk and deception, especially those of the circumcision faction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>They must be silenced, because they are ruining entire households by teaching what they ought not to teach, for the sake of sordid gain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>One of their very own prophets said, “Cretans are always liars, evil beasts, and lazy gluttons.”</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>This testimony is true. Therefore rebuke them sharply, so that they may become sound in the faith,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>not paying any attention to Jewish myths or the commandments of men who turn away from the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>To the pure, all things are pure; but to those who are defiled and do not believe, nothing is pure. In fact, both their minds and their consciences are defiled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They profess to know God, but by their works they deny him. They are detestable, disobedient, and have proven themselves to be unqualified for any good work.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Teach Sound Doctrine</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But as for yoʋ, teach what is consistent with sound doctrine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Elderly men are to be sober-minded, dignified, sensible, and sound in faith, love, and endurance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Elderly women likewise are to be reverent in behavior, not slanderous or enslaved to much wine, but teaching what is good,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>so that they can admonish the young women to be loving to their husbands, loving to their children,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>sensible, pure, homemakers, kind, and submissive to their own husbands, so that the word of God may not be discredited.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In the same way, urge the younger men to be of sound mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Show yoʋrself to be a model of good works in every way, and in yoʋr teaching show integrity, dignity, incorruptibility,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and sound speech that is above reproach, so that any opponent may be put to shame because he has nothing bad to say about us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Slaves are to be submissive to their own masters and well-pleasing in everything, not talking back,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>not pilfering, but showing all good faith, so that in every way they may adorn the teaching of God our Savior.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the saving grace of God has appeared to all people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>instructing us to deny ungodliness and worldly lusts and to live in a sensible, righteous, and godly manner in the present age,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>as we wait for the blessed hope—the appearing of the glory of our great God and Savior, Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He gave himself for us to redeem us from all lawlessness and to purify for himself a people for his own possession, zealous for good works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Declare these things; encourage and rebuke with all authority. Let no one despise yoʋ.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Be Ready for Every Good Work</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Remind the people to be subject to rulers and authorities, to be obedient, to be ready for every good work,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to slander no one, and to be peaceable and considerate, always showing gentleness toward everyone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For we ourselves were once foolish, disobedient, led astray, and enslaved to various lusts and pleasures. Living in wickedness and envy, we were loathsome and hated one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But when the kindness of God our Savior and his love for mankind appeared,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>he saved us, not because of any righteous works we had done, but according to his mercy, through the washing of regeneration and the renewal of the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He richly poured out his Spirit upon us through Jesus Christ our Savior,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>so that, having been justified by his grace, we might become heirs according to the hope of eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>This saying is trustworthy. I want yoʋ to insist on these things, so that those who have put their trust in God may be careful to devote themselves to good works. These things are good and beneficial for people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But avoid foolish controversies, genealogies, quarrels, and disputes about the law, for they are unprofitable and futile.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Reject a divisive person after a first and second warning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For yoʋ know that such a person is corrupted and sinful; he is self-condemned.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Final Instructions and Greetings</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When I send Artemas to yoʋ, or Tychicus, make every effort to come to me at Nicopolis, for I have decided to spend the winter there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Do everything yoʋ can to help Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their way, and make sure they lack nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Our people must learn to devote themselves to good works in order to meet pressing needs, so that they will not be unfruitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>All who are with me greet yoʋ. Greet those who love us in the faith. Grace be with you all. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>