<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Greeting</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, a prisoner for Christ Jesus, and Timothy our brother, to Philemon, our beloved friend and fellow worker,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and also to the beloved Apphia, to Archippus our fellow soldier, and to the church that meets in yoʋr house:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Philemon's Love and Faith</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I give thanks to my God, always making mention of yoʋ in my prayers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>because I hear of yoʋr love for all the saints and the faith that yoʋ have toward the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I pray that yoʋr fellowship with us in the faith may be effective in deepening yoʋr understanding of every blessing that we have in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>We are very thankful for the comfort we have received from yoʋr love, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed through yoʋ, brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Paul's Appeal for Onesimus</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore, although I am bold enough in Christ to command yoʋ to do what is right,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I would rather appeal to yoʋ on the basis of love. I, Paul, an old man and now a prisoner for Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>appeal to yoʋ on behalf of my child, Onesimus, whose father I have become during my imprisonment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Once he was useless to yoʋ, but now he is useful both to yoʋ and to me. I am sending him back,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and I ask yoʋ to receive him, that is, my very own heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I wanted to keep him with me so that he could serve me in yoʋr place during my imprisonment for the gospel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But I did not want to do anything without yoʋr consent, so that yoʋr good deed would not be done out of compulsion, but of yoʋr own free will.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Perhaps the reason he was separated from yoʋ for an hour was so that yoʋ might have him back forever,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>no longer as a slave, but more than a slave, as a beloved brother, especially to me, but even more so to yoʋ, both in the flesh and in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So if yoʋ consider me to be a partner, receive him as yoʋ would receive me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If he has wronged yoʋ in any way or owes yoʋ anything, charge it to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I, Paul, write this with my own hand: I will repay it (not to mention that yoʋ owe me yoʋr very own life).</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Yes, brother, let me have some benefit from yoʋ in the Lord. Refresh my heart in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Trusting in yoʋr obedience, I write to yoʋ, knowing that yoʋ will do even more than I ask.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>At the same time, I want yoʋ to prepare a guest room for me, for I hope that through your prayers I will be restored to you soon.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Final Greetings</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Epaphras, my fellow prisoner in Christ Jesus greets yoʋ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and so do Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, my fellow workers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>