<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Greeting</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The elder to the beloved Gaius, whom I love in the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Beloved, I pray that in all respects yoʋ may prosper and be in good health, even as yoʋr soul prospers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For I was overjoyed when the brothers came and testified about yoʋr faithfulness to the truth and how yoʋ walk in the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I have no greater joy than to hear that my children are walking in the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Gaius Commended</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Beloved, yoʋ are acting faithfully in whatever yoʋ do for the brothers and for those who are strangers to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They have testified of yoʋr love before the church, and yoʋ will do well to send them on their way in a manner worthy of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For they went out for the sake of the Name, receiving nothing from the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore we ought to receive men like them, so that we may be fellow workers for the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Diotrephes Denounced</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I wrote to the church, but Diotrephes, who loves to put himself first, does not acknowledge us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So if I come, I will call attention to what he is doing and the evil accusations of nonsense that he is making against us. And he is not satisfied with that! He not only refuses to receive the brothers, but also stops those who want to do so and throws them out of the church.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Demetrius Commended</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Beloved, do not imitate what is evil, but what is good. Whoever does good is of God; whoever does evil has not seen God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Demetrius is well spoken of by everyone—and even by the truth itself. We also speak well of him, and you know that our testimony is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment kind="HEADING">
      <content>Final Greetings</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I have much to write, but I do not want to write to yoʋ with pen and ink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I hope to see yoʋ soon, and we will speak face to face. Peace be with yoʋ. The friends greet yoʋ. Greet the friends by name.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>