<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The proverbs of Solomon son of David, king of Israel:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>for attaining wisdom and discipline; for understanding words of insight;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>for acquiring a disciplined and prudent life, doing what is right and just and fair;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>for giving prudence to the simple, knowledge and discretion to the young--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>let the wise listen and add to their learning, and let the discerning get guidance--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>for understanding proverbs and parables, the sayings and riddles of the wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The fear of the LORD is the beginning of knowledge, but fools </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> despise wisdom and discipline. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Listen, my son, to your father's instruction and do not forsake your mother's teaching.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>They will be a garland to grace your head and a chain to adorn your neck. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>My son, if sinners entice you, do not give in to them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>If they say, "Come along with us; let's lie in wait for someone's blood, let's waylay some harmless soul;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>let's swallow them alive, like the grave, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> and whole, like those who go down to the pit;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>we will get all sorts of valuable things and fill our houses with plunder;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>throw in your lot with us, and we will share a common purse"--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>my son, do not go along with them, do not set foot on their paths;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>for their feet rush into sin, they are swift to shed blood.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>How useless to spread a net in full view of all the birds!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>These men lie in wait for their own blood; they waylay only themselves!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Such is the end of all who go after ill-gotten gain; it takes away the lives of those who get it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Wisdom calls aloud in the street, she raises her voice in the public squares;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>at the head of the noisy streets </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> she cries out, in the gateways of the city she makes her speech: </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"How long will you simple ones </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> love your simple ways? How long will mockers delight in mockery and fools hate knowledge?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>If you had responded to my rebuke, I would have poured out my heart to you and made my thoughts known to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>But since you rejected me when I called and no one gave heed when I stretched out my hand,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>since you ignored all my advice and would not accept my rebuke,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>I in turn will laugh at your disaster; I will mock when calamity overtakes you--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>when calamity overtakes you like a storm, when disaster sweeps over you like a whirlwind, when distress and trouble overwhelm you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"Then they will call to me but I will not answer; they will look for me but will not find me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Since they hated knowledge and did not choose to fear the LORD,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>since they would not accept my advice and spurned my rebuke,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>they will eat the fruit of their ways and be filled with the fruit of their schemes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>For the waywardness of the simple will kill them, and the complacency of fools will destroy them;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>but whoever listens to me will live in safety and be at ease, without fear of harm." </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> The Hebrew words rendered </content>
            <content kind="EM">fool</content>
            <content> in Proverbs, and often elsewhere in the Old Testament, denote one who is morally deficient.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Hebrew; Septuagint </content>
            <content kind="EM">/ on the tops of the walls</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> The Hebrew word rendered </content>
            <content kind="EM">simple</content>
            <content> in Proverbs generally denotes one without moral direction and inclined to evil.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>My son, if you accept my words and store up my commands within you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>turning your ear to wisdom and applying your heart to understanding,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>and if you call out for insight and cry aloud for understanding,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>and if you look for it as for silver and search for it as for hidden treasure,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>then you will understand the fear of the LORD and find the knowledge of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>For the LORD gives wisdom, and from his mouth come knowledge and understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>He holds victory in store for the upright, he is a shield to those whose walk is blameless,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>for he guards the course of the just and protects the way of his faithful ones. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Then you will understand what is right and just and fair--every good path.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>For wisdom will enter your heart, and knowledge will be pleasant to your soul.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Discretion will protect you, and understanding will guard you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Wisdom will save you from the ways of wicked men, from men whose words are perverse,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>who leave the straight paths to walk in dark ways,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>who delight in doing wrong and rejoice in the perverseness of evil,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>whose paths are crooked and who are devious in their ways. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>It will save you also from the adulteress, from the wayward wife with her seductive words,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>who has left the partner of her youth and ignored the covenant she made before God. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For her house leads down to death and her paths to the spirits of the dead.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>None who go to her return or attain the paths of life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Thus you will walk in the ways of good men and keep to the paths of the righteous.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For the upright will live in the land, and the blameless will remain in it;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>but the wicked will be cut off from the land, and the unfaithful will be torn from it. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">covenant of her God</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>My son, do not forget my teaching, but keep my commands in your heart,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>for they will prolong your life many years and bring you prosperity. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Let love and faithfulness never leave you; bind them around your neck, write them on the tablet of your heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Then you will win favor and a good name in the sight of God and man. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Trust in the LORD with all your heart and lean not on your own understanding;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>in all your ways acknowledge him, and he will make your paths straight. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Do not be wise in your own eyes; fear the LORD and shun evil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>This will bring health to your body and nourishment to your bones. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Honor the LORD with your wealth, with the firstfruits of all your crops;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>then your barns will be filled to overflowing, and your vats will brim over with new wine. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>My son, do not despise the LORD's discipline and do not resent his rebuke,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>because the LORD disciplines those he loves, as a father </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> the son he delights in. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Blessed is the man who finds wisdom, the man who gains understanding,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>for she is more profitable than silver and yields better returns than gold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>She is more precious than rubies; nothing you desire can compare with her.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Long life is in her right hand; in her left hand are riches and honor.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Her ways are pleasant ways, and all her paths are peace.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>She is a tree of life to those who embrace her; those who lay hold of her will be blessed. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>By wisdom the LORD laid the earth's foundations, by understanding he set the heavens in place;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>by his knowledge the deeps were divided, and the clouds let drop the dew. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>My son, preserve sound judgment and discernment, do not let them out of your sight;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>they will be life for you, an ornament to grace your neck.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Then you will go on your way in safety, and your foot will not stumble;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>when you lie down, you will not be afraid; when you lie down, your sleep will be sweet.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Have no fear of sudden disaster or of the ruin that overtakes the wicked,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>for the LORD will be your confidence and will keep your foot from being snared. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Do not withhold good from those who deserve it, when it is in your power to act.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Do not say to your neighbor, "Come back later; I'll give it tomorrow"-- when you now have it with you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Do not plot harm against your neighbor, who lives trustfully near you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Do not accuse a man for no reason-- when he has done you no harm. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Do not envy a violent man or choose any of his ways,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>for the LORD detests a perverse man but takes the upright into his confidence. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>The LORD's curse is on the house of the wicked, but he blesses the home of the righteous.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>He mocks proud mockers but gives grace to the humble.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>The wise inherit honor, but fools he holds up to shame. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">will direct your paths</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> Hebrew; Septuagint </content>
            <content kind="EM">/ and he punishes</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Listen, my sons, to a father's instruction; pay attention and gain understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I give you sound learning, so do not forsake my teaching.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>When I was a boy in my father's house, still tender, and an only child of my mother,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>he taught me and said, "Lay hold of my words with all your heart; keep my commands and you will live.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Get wisdom, get understanding; do not forget my words or swerve from them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Do not forsake wisdom, and she will protect you; love her, and she will watch over you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Wisdom is supreme; therefore get wisdom. Though it cost all you have, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> get understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Esteem her, and she will exalt you; embrace her, and she will honor you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>She will set a garland of grace on your head and present you with a crown of splendor." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Listen, my son, accept what I say, and the years of your life will be many.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>I guide you in the way of wisdom and lead you along straight paths.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>When you walk, your steps will not be hampered; when you run, you will not stumble.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Hold on to instruction, do not let it go; guard it well, for it is your life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Do not set foot on the path of the wicked or walk in the way of evil men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Avoid it, do not travel on it; turn from it and go on your way.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>For they cannot sleep till they do evil; they are robbed of slumber till they make someone fall.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>They eat the bread of wickedness and drink the wine of violence. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The path of the righteous is like the first gleam of dawn, shining ever brighter till the full light of day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>But the way of the wicked is like deep darkness; they do not know what makes them stumble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>My son, pay attention to what I say; listen closely to my words.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Do not let them out of your sight, keep them within your heart;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>for they are life to those who find them and health to a man's whole body.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Above all else, guard your heart, for it is the wellspring of life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Put away perversity from your mouth; keep corrupt talk far from your lips.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Let your eyes look straight ahead, fix your gaze directly before you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Make level </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> paths for your feet and take only ways that are firm.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Do not swerve to the right or the left; keep your foot from evil. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Whatever else you get</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">26</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Consider the</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>My son, pay attention to my wisdom, listen well to my words of insight,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>that you may maintain discretion and your lips may preserve knowledge.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>For the lips of an adulteress drip honey, and her speech is smoother than oil;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>but in the end she is bitter as gall, sharp as a double-edged sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Her feet go down to death; her steps lead straight to the grave. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>She gives no thought to the way of life; her paths are crooked, but she knows it not. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Now then, my sons, listen to me; do not turn aside from what I say.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Keep to a path far from her, do not go near the door of her house,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>lest you give your best strength to others and your years to one who is cruel,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>lest strangers feast on your wealth and your toil enrich another man's house.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>At the end of your life you will groan, when your flesh and body are spent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>You will say, "How I hated discipline! How my heart spurned correction!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>I would not obey my teachers or listen to my instructors.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>I have come to the brink of utter ruin in the midst of the whole assembly." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Drink water from your own cistern, running water from your own well.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Should your springs overflow in the streets, your streams of water in the public squares?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Let them be yours alone, never to be shared with strangers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>May your fountain be blessed, and may you rejoice in the wife of your youth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>A loving doe, a graceful deer-- may her breasts satisfy you always, may you ever be captivated by her love.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Why be captivated, my son, by an adulteress? Why embrace the bosom of another man's wife? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For a man's ways are in full view of the LORD, and he examines all his paths.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>The evil deeds of a wicked man ensnare him; the cords of his sin hold him fast.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>He will die for lack of discipline, led astray by his own great folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>My son, if you have put up security for your neighbor, if you have struck hands in pledge for another,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>if you have been trapped by what you said, ensnared by the words of your mouth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>then do this, my son, to free yourself, since you have fallen into your neighbor's hands: Go and humble yourself; press your plea with your neighbor!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Allow no sleep to your eyes, no slumber to your eyelids.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Free yourself, like a gazelle from the hand of the hunter, like a bird from the snare of the fowler. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Go to the ant, you sluggard; consider its ways and be wise!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>It has no commander, no overseer or ruler,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>yet it stores its provisions in summer and gathers its food at harvest. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>How long will you lie there, you sluggard? When will you get up from your sleep?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to rest--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>and poverty will come on you like a bandit and scarcity like an armed man. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>A scoundrel and villain, who goes about with a corrupt mouth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>who winks with his eye, signals with his feet and motions with his fingers,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>who plots evil with deceit in his heart-- he always stirs up dissension.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Therefore disaster will overtake him in an instant; he will suddenly be destroyed--without remedy. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>There are six things the LORD hates, seven that are detestable to him:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>haughty eyes, a lying tongue, hands that shed innocent blood,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>a heart that devises wicked schemes, feet that are quick to rush into evil,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>a false witness who pours out lies and a man who stirs up dissension among brothers. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>My son, keep your father's commands and do not forsake your mother's teaching.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Bind them upon your heart forever; fasten them around your neck.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>When you walk, they will guide you; when you sleep, they will watch over you; when you awake, they will speak to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>For these commands are a lamp, this teaching is a light, and the corrections of discipline are the way to life,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>keeping you from the immoral woman, from the smooth tongue of the wayward wife.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Do not lust in your heart after her beauty or let her captivate you with her eyes,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>for the prostitute reduces you to a loaf of bread, and the adulteress preys upon your very life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Can a man scoop fire into his lap without his clothes being burned?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Can a man walk on hot coals without his feet being scorched?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>So is he who sleeps with another man's wife; no one who touches her will go unpunished. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Men do not despise a thief if he steals to satisfy his hunger when he is starving.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Yet if he is caught, he must pay sevenfold, though it costs him all the wealth of his house.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>But a man who commits adultery lacks judgment; whoever does so destroys himself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Blows and disgrace are his lot, and his shame will never be wiped away;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>for jealousy arouses a husband's fury, and he will show no mercy when he takes revenge.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>He will not accept any compensation; he will refuse the bribe, however great it is. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">like a vagrant / and scarcity like a beggar</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>My son, keep my words and store up my commands within you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Keep my commands and you will live; guard my teachings as the apple of your eye.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Bind them on your fingers; write them on the tablet of your heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Say to wisdom, "You are my sister," and call understanding your kinsman;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>they will keep you from the adulteress, from the wayward wife with her seductive words. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>At the window of my house I looked out through the lattice.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>I saw among the simple, I noticed among the young men, a youth who lacked judgment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He was going down the street near her corner, walking along in the direction of her house</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>at twilight, as the day was fading, as the dark of night set in. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Then out came a woman to meet him, dressed like a prostitute and with crafty intent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>(She is loud and defiant, her feet never stay at home;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>now in the street, now in the squares, at every corner she lurks.)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>She took hold of him and kissed him and with a brazen face she said: </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"I have fellowship offerings </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> at home; today I fulfilled my vows.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>So I came out to meet you; I looked for you and have found you!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I have covered my bed with colored linens from Egypt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes and cinnamon.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Come, let's drink deep of love till morning; let's enjoy ourselves with love!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>My husband is not at home; he has gone on a long journey.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>He took his purse filled with money and will not be home till full moon." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>With persuasive words she led him astray; she seduced him with her smooth talk.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>All at once he followed her like an ox going to the slaughter, like a deer </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> stepping into a noose </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>till an arrow pierces his liver, like a bird darting into a snare, little knowing it will cost him his life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Now then, my sons, listen to me; pay attention to what I say.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Do not let your heart turn to her ways or stray into her paths.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Many are the victims she has brought down; her slain are a mighty throng.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Her house is a highway to the grave, </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> leading down to the chambers of death. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">14</content>
            <content> Traditionally </content>
            <content kind="EM">peace offerings</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Syriac (see also Septuagint); Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">fool</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this line is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">27</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Does not wisdom call out? Does not understanding raise her voice?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>On the heights along the way, where the paths meet, she takes her stand;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>beside the gates leading into the city, at the entrances, she cries aloud:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"To you, O men, I call out; I raise my voice to all mankind.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>You who are simple, gain prudence; you who are foolish, gain understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Listen, for I have worthy things to say; I open my lips to speak what is right.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>My mouth speaks what is true, for my lips detest wickedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>All the words of my mouth are just; none of them is crooked or perverse.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>To the discerning all of them are right; they are faultless to those who have knowledge.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Choose my instruction instead of silver, knowledge rather than choice gold,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>for wisdom is more precious than rubies, and nothing you desire can compare with her. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"I, wisdom, dwell together with prudence; I possess knowledge and discretion.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>To fear the LORD is to hate evil; I hate pride and arrogance, evil behavior and perverse speech.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Counsel and sound judgment are mine; I have understanding and power.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>By me kings reign and rulers make laws that are just;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>by me princes govern, and all nobles who rule on earth. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>I love those who love me, and those who seek me find me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>With me are riches and honor, enduring wealth and prosperity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>My fruit is better than fine gold; what I yield surpasses choice silver.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>I walk in the way of righteousness, along the paths of justice,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>bestowing wealth on those who love me and making their treasuries full. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"The LORD brought me forth as the first of his works, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> before his deeds of old;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>I was appointed </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> from eternity, from the beginning, before the world began.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>When there were no oceans, I was given birth, when there were no springs abounding with water;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>before the mountains were settled in place, before the hills, I was given birth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>before he made the earth or its fields or any of the dust of the world.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>I was there when he set the heavens in place, when he marked out the horizon on the face of the deep,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>when he established the clouds above and fixed securely the fountains of the deep,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>when he gave the sea its boundary so the waters would not overstep his command, and when he marked out the foundations of the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Then I was the craftsman at his side. I was filled with delight day after day, rejoicing always in his presence,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>rejoicing in his whole world and delighting in mankind. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>"Now then, my sons, listen to me; blessed are those who keep my ways.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Listen to my instruction and be wise; do not ignore it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Blessed is the man who listens to me, watching daily at my doors, waiting at my doorway.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>For whoever finds me finds life and receives favor from the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>But whoever fails to find me harms himself; all who hate me love death." </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">16</content>
            <content> Many Hebrew manuscripts and Septuagint; most Hebrew manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">and nobles--all righteous rulers</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">way</content>
            <content>; or </content>
            <content kind="EM">dominion</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">The LORD possessed me at the beginning of his work</content>
            <content>; or </content>
            <content kind="EM">The LORD brought me forth at the beginning of his work</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">23</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">fashioned</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Wisdom has built her house; she has hewn out its seven pillars.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>She has prepared her meat and mixed her wine; she has also set her table.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>She has sent out her maids, and she calls from the highest point of the city.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Let all who are simple come in here!" she says to those who lack judgment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"Come, eat my food and drink the wine I have mixed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Leave your simple ways and you will live; walk in the way of understanding. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Whoever corrects a mocker invites insult; whoever rebukes a wicked man incurs abuse.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Do not rebuke a mocker or he will hate you; rebuke a wise man and he will love you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Instruct a wise man and he will be wiser still; teach a righteous man and he will add to his learning. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"The fear of the LORD is the beginning of wisdom, and knowledge of the Holy One is understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>For through me your days will be many, and years will be added to your life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>If you are wise, your wisdom will reward you; if you are a mocker, you alone will suffer." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>The woman Folly is loud; she is undisciplined and without knowledge.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>She sits at the door of her house, on a seat at the highest point of the city,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>calling out to those who pass by, who go straight on their way.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"Let all who are simple come in here!" she says to those who lack judgment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Stolen water is sweet; food eaten in secret is delicious!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But little do they know that the dead are there, that her guests are in the depths of the grave. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The proverbs of Solomon: A wise son brings joy to his father, but a foolish son grief to his mother. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Ill-gotten treasures are of no value, but righteousness delivers from death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>The LORD does not let the righteous go hungry but he thwarts the craving of the wicked. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Lazy hands make a man poor, but diligent hands bring wealth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>He who gathers crops in summer is a wise son, but he who sleeps during harvest is a disgraceful son. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Blessings crown the head of the righteous, but violence overwhelms the mouth of the wicked. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The memory of the righteous will be a blessing, but the name of the wicked will rot. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The wise in heart accept commands, but a chattering fool comes to ruin. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The man of integrity walks securely, but he who takes crooked paths will be found out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He who winks maliciously causes grief, and a chattering fool comes to ruin. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The mouth of the righteous is a fountain of life, but violence overwhelms the mouth of the wicked. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Hatred stirs up dissension, but love covers over all wrongs. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Wisdom is found on the lips of the discerning, but a rod is for the back of him who lacks judgment. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Wise men store up knowledge, but the mouth of a fool invites ruin. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The wealth of the rich is their fortified city, but poverty is the ruin of the poor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>The wages of the righteous bring them life, but the income of the wicked brings them punishment. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>He who heeds discipline shows the way to life, but whoever ignores correction leads others astray. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He who conceals his hatred has lying lips, and whoever spreads slander is a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>When words are many, sin is not absent, but he who holds his tongue is wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>The tongue of the righteous is choice silver, but the heart of the wicked is of little value. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>The lips of the righteous nourish many, but fools die for lack of judgment. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>The blessing of the LORD brings wealth, and he adds no trouble to it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A fool finds pleasure in evil conduct, but a man of understanding delights in wisdom. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>What the wicked dreads will overtake him; what the righteous desire will be granted. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>When the storm has swept by, the wicked are gone, but the righteous stand firm forever. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>As vinegar to the teeth and smoke to the eyes, so is a sluggard to those who send him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The fear of the LORD adds length to life, but the years of the wicked are cut short. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>The prospect of the righteous is joy, but the hopes of the wicked come to nothing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>The way of the LORD is a refuge for the righteous, but it is the ruin of those who do evil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>The righteous will never be uprooted, but the wicked will not remain in the land. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>The mouth of the righteous brings forth wisdom, but a perverse tongue will be cut out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>The lips of the righteous know what is fitting, but the mouth of the wicked only what is perverse. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">but the mouth of the wicked conceals violence</content>
            <content>; also in verse 11</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The LORD abhors dishonest scales, but accurate weights are his delight. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>When pride comes, then comes disgrace, but with humility comes wisdom. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>The integrity of the upright guides them, but the unfaithful are destroyed by their duplicity. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Wealth is worthless in the day of wrath, but righteousness delivers from death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The righteousness of the blameless makes a straight way for them, but the wicked are brought down by their own wickedness. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The righteousness of the upright delivers them, but the unfaithful are trapped by evil desires. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>When a wicked man dies, his hope perishes; all he expected from his power comes to nothing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The righteous man is rescued from trouble, and it comes on the wicked instead. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>With his mouth the godless destroys his neighbor, but through knowledge the righteous escape. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>When the righteous prosper, the city rejoices; when the wicked perish, there are shouts of joy. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Through the blessing of the upright a city is exalted, but by the mouth of the wicked it is destroyed. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>A man who lacks judgment derides his neighbor, but a man of understanding holds his tongue. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>A gossip betrays a confidence, but a trustworthy man keeps a secret. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For lack of guidance a nation falls, but many advisers make victory sure. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>He who puts up security for another will surely suffer, but whoever refuses to strike hands in pledge is safe. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>A kindhearted woman gains respect, but ruthless men gain only wealth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>A kind man benefits himself, but a cruel man brings trouble on himself. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The wicked man earns deceptive wages, but he who sows righteousness reaps a sure reward. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>The truly righteous man attains life, but he who pursues evil goes to his death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>The LORD detests men of perverse heart but he delights in those whose ways are blameless. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Be sure of this: The wicked will not go unpunished, but those who are righteous will go free. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Like a gold ring in a pig's snout is a beautiful woman who shows no discretion. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The desire of the righteous ends only in good, but the hope of the wicked only in wrath. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>One man gives freely, yet gains even more; another withholds unduly, but comes to poverty. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>A generous man will prosper; he who refreshes others will himself be refreshed. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>People curse the man who hoards grain, but blessing crowns him who is willing to sell. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>He who seeks good finds goodwill, but evil comes to him who searches for it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Whoever trusts in his riches will fall, but the righteous will thrive like a green leaf. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>He who brings trouble on his family will inherit only wind, and the fool will be servant to the wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life, and he who wins souls is wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>If the righteous receive their due on earth, how much more the ungodly and the sinner! </content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Whoever loves discipline loves knowledge, but he who hates correction is stupid. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A good man obtains favor from the LORD, but the LORD condemns a crafty man. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A man cannot be established through wickedness, but the righteous cannot be uprooted. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>A wife of noble character is her husband's crown, but a disgraceful wife is like decay in his bones. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The plans of the righteous are just, but the advice of the wicked is deceitful. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The words of the wicked lie in wait for blood, but the speech of the upright rescues them. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Wicked men are overthrown and are no more, but the house of the righteous stands firm. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>A man is praised according to his wisdom, but men with warped minds are despised. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Better to be a nobody and yet have a servant than pretend to be somebody and have no food. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>A righteous man cares for the needs of his animal, but the kindest acts of the wicked are cruel. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He who works his land will have abundant food, but he who chases fantasies lacks judgment. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The wicked desire the plunder of evil men, but the root of the righteous flourishes. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>An evil man is trapped by his sinful talk, but a righteous man escapes trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>From the fruit of his lips a man is filled with good things as surely as the work of his hands rewards him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The way of a fool seems right to him, but a wise man listens to advice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>A fool shows his annoyance at once, but a prudent man overlooks an insult. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>A truthful witness gives honest testimony, but a false witness tells lies. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Reckless words pierce like a sword, but the tongue of the wise brings healing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Truthful lips endure forever, but a lying tongue lasts only a moment. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>There is deceit in the hearts of those who plot evil, but joy for those who promote peace. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>No harm befalls the righteous, but the wicked have their fill of trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>The LORD detests lying lips, but he delights in men who are truthful. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A prudent man keeps his knowledge to himself, but the heart of fools blurts out folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Diligent hands will rule, but laziness ends in slave labor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>An anxious heart weighs a man down, but a kind word cheers him up. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>A righteous man is cautious in friendship, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> but the way of the wicked leads them astray. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The lazy man does not roast </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> his game, but the diligent man prizes his possessions. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>In the way of righteousness there is life; along that path is immortality. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">26</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">man is a guide to his neighbor</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">27</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>A wise son heeds his father's instruction, but a mocker does not listen to rebuke. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>From the fruit of his lips a man enjoys good things, but the unfaithful have a craving for violence. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>He who guards his lips guards his life, but he who speaks rashly will come to ruin. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The sluggard craves and gets nothing, but the desires of the diligent are fully satisfied. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The righteous hate what is false, but the wicked bring shame and disgrace. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Righteousness guards the man of integrity, but wickedness overthrows the sinner. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>One man pretends to be rich, yet has nothing; another pretends to be poor, yet has great wealth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>A man's riches may ransom his life, but a poor man hears no threat. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The light of the righteous shines brightly, but the lamp of the wicked is snuffed out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Pride only breeds quarrels, but wisdom is found in those who take advice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Dishonest money dwindles away, but he who gathers money little by little makes it grow. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Hope deferred makes the heart sick, but a longing fulfilled is a tree of life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>He who scorns instruction will pay for it, but he who respects a command is rewarded. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The teaching of the wise is a fountain of life, turning a man from the snares of death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Good understanding wins favor, but the way of the unfaithful is hard. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Every prudent man acts out of knowledge, but a fool exposes his folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>A wicked messenger falls into trouble, but a trustworthy envoy brings healing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He who ignores discipline comes to poverty and shame, but whoever heeds correction is honored. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>A longing fulfilled is sweet to the soul, but fools detest turning from evil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>He who walks with the wise grows wise, but a companion of fools suffers harm. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Misfortune pursues the sinner, but prosperity is the reward of the righteous. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>A good man leaves an inheritance for his children's children, but a sinner's wealth is stored up for the righteous. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A poor man's field may produce abundant food, but injustice sweeps it away. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>He who spares the rod hates his son, but he who loves him is careful to discipline him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The righteous eat to their hearts' content, but the stomach of the wicked goes hungry. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">unfaithful does not endure</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The wise woman builds her house, but with her own hands the foolish one tears hers down. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He whose walk is upright fears the LORD, but he whose ways are devious despises him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A fool's talk brings a rod to his back, but the lips of the wise protect them. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Where there are no oxen, the manger is empty, but from the strength of an ox comes an abundant harvest. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>A truthful witness does not deceive, but a false witness pours out lies. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The mocker seeks wisdom and finds none, but knowledge comes easily to the discerning. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Stay away from a foolish man, for you will not find knowledge on his lips. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The wisdom of the prudent is to give thought to their ways, but the folly of fools is deception. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Fools mock at making amends for sin, but goodwill is found among the upright. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Each heart knows its own bitterness, and no one else can share its joy. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The house of the wicked will be destroyed, but the tent of the upright will flourish. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>There is a way that seems right to a man, but in the end it leads to death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Even in laughter the heart may ache, and joy may end in grief. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The faithless will be fully repaid for their ways, and the good man rewarded for his. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>A simple man believes anything, but a prudent man gives thought to his steps. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>A wise man fears the LORD and shuns evil, but a fool is hotheaded and reckless. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>A quick-tempered man does foolish things, and a crafty man is hated. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The simple inherit folly, but the prudent are crowned with knowledge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Evil men will bow down in the presence of the good, and the wicked at the gates of the righteous. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>The poor are shunned even by their neighbors, but the rich have many friends. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>He who despises his neighbor sins, but blessed is he who is kind to the needy. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Do not those who plot evil go astray? But those who plan what is good find </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> love and faithfulness. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>All hard work brings a profit, but mere talk leads only to poverty. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>The wealth of the wise is their crown, but the folly of fools yields folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>A truthful witness saves lives, but a false witness is deceitful. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>He who fears the LORD has a secure fortress, and for his children it will be a refuge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The fear of the LORD is a fountain of life, turning a man from the snares of death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>A large population is a king's glory, but without subjects a prince is ruined. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>A patient man has great understanding, but a quick-tempered man displays folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>A heart at peace gives life to the body, but envy rots the bones. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>He who oppresses the poor shows contempt for their Maker, but whoever is kind to the needy honors God. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>When calamity comes, the wicked are brought down, but even in death the righteous have a refuge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Wisdom reposes in the heart of the discerning and even among fools she lets herself be known. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Righteousness exalts a nation, but sin is a disgrace to any people. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>A king delights in a wise servant, but a shameful servant incurs his wrath. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">show</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Hebrew; Septuagint and Syriac </content>
            <content kind="EM">/ but in the heart of fools she is not known</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="15">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>A gentle answer turns away wrath, but a harsh word stirs up anger. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>The tongue of the wise commends knowledge, but the mouth of the fool gushes folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>The eyes of the LORD are everywhere, keeping watch on the wicked and the good. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The tongue that brings healing is a tree of life, but a deceitful tongue crushes the spirit. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>A fool spurns his father's discipline, but whoever heeds correction shows prudence. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The house of the righteous contains great treasure, but the income of the wicked brings them trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The lips of the wise spread knowledge; not so the hearts of fools. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The LORD detests the sacrifice of the wicked, but the prayer of the upright pleases him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The LORD detests the way of the wicked but he loves those who pursue righteousness. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Stern discipline awaits him who leaves the path; he who hates correction will die. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Death and Destruction </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> lie open before the LORD-- how much more the hearts of men! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>A mocker resents correction; he will not consult the wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>A happy heart makes the face cheerful, but heartache crushes the spirit. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The discerning heart seeks knowledge, but the mouth of a fool feeds on folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>All the days of the oppressed are wretched, but the cheerful heart has a continual feast. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Better a little with the fear of the LORD than great wealth with turmoil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Better a meal of vegetables where there is love than a fattened calf with hatred. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>A hot-tempered man stirs up dissension, but a patient man calms a quarrel. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>The way of the sluggard is blocked with thorns, but the path of the upright is a highway. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>A wise son brings joy to his father, but a foolish man despises his mother. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Folly delights a man who lacks judgment, but a man of understanding keeps a straight course. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Plans fail for lack of counsel, but with many advisers they succeed. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A man finds joy in giving an apt reply-- and how good is a timely word! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>The path of life leads upward for the wise to keep him from going down to the grave. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The LORD tears down the proud man's house but he keeps the widow's boundaries intact. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>The LORD detests the thoughts of the wicked, but those of the pure are pleasing to him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>A greedy man brings trouble to his family, but he who hates bribes will live. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>The heart of the righteous weighs its answers, but the mouth of the wicked gushes evil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>The LORD is far from the wicked but he hears the prayer of the righteous. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>A cheerful look brings joy to the heart, and good news gives health to the bones. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>He who listens to a life-giving rebuke will be at home among the wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>He who ignores discipline despises himself, but whoever heeds correction gains understanding. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>The fear of the LORD teaches a man wisdom, </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> and humility comes before honor. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol and Abaddon</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Wisdom teaches the fear of the LORD</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="16">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>To man belong the plans of the heart, but from the LORD comes the reply of the tongue. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>All a man's ways seem innocent to him, but motives are weighed by the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Commit to the LORD whatever you do, and your plans will succeed. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The LORD works out everything for his own ends-- even the wicked for a day of disaster. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The LORD detests all the proud of heart. Be sure of this: They will not go unpunished. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Through love and faithfulness sin is atoned for; through the fear of the LORD a man avoids evil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>When a man's ways are pleasing to the LORD, he makes even his enemies live at peace with him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Better a little with righteousness than much gain with injustice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>In his heart a man plans his course, but the LORD determines his steps. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The lips of a king speak as an oracle, and his mouth should not betray justice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Honest scales and balances are from the LORD; all the weights in the bag are of his making. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Kings detest wrongdoing, for a throne is established through righteousness. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Kings take pleasure in honest lips; they value a man who speaks the truth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>A king's wrath is a messenger of death, but a wise man will appease it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>When a king's face brightens, it means life; his favor is like a rain cloud in spring. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>How much better to get wisdom than gold, to choose understanding rather than silver! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>The highway of the upright avoids evil; he who guards his way guards his life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Pride goes before destruction, a haughty spirit before a fall. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Better to be lowly in spirit and among the oppressed than to share plunder with the proud. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Whoever gives heed to instruction prospers, and blessed is he who trusts in the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>The wise in heart are called discerning, and pleasant words promote instruction.</content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Understanding is a fountain of life to those who have it, but folly brings punishment to fools. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A wise man's heart guides his mouth, and his lips promote instruction.</content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Pleasant words are a honeycomb, sweet to the soul and healing to the bones. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>There is a way that seems right to a man, but in the end it leads to death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>The laborer's appetite works for him; his hunger drives him on. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>A scoundrel plots evil, and his speech is like a scorching fire. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>A perverse man stirs up dissension, and a gossip separates close friends. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>A violent man entices his neighbor and leads him down a path that is not good. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>He who winks with his eye is plotting perversity; he who purses his lips is bent on evil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Gray hair is a crown of splendor; it is attained by a righteous life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Better a patient man than a warrior, a man who controls his temper than one who takes a city. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>The lot is cast into the lap, but its every decision is from the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">words make a man persuasive</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">23</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">mouth / and makes his lips persuasive</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="17">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Better a dry crust with peace and quiet than a house full of feasting, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> with strife. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A wise servant will rule over a disgraceful son, and will share the inheritance as one of the brothers. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>The crucible for silver and the furnace for gold, but the LORD tests the heart. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>A wicked man listens to evil lips; a liar pays attention to a malicious tongue. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>He who mocks the poor shows contempt for their Maker; whoever gloats over disaster will not go unpunished. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Children's children are a crown to the aged, and parents are the pride of their children. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Arrogant </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> lips are unsuited to a fool-- how much worse lying lips to a ruler! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>A bribe is a charm to the one who gives it; wherever he turns, he succeeds. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>He who covers over an offense promotes love, but whoever repeats the matter separates close friends. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>A rebuke impresses a man of discernment more than a hundred lashes a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>An evil man is bent only on rebellion; a merciless official will be sent against him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Better to meet a bear robbed of her cubs than a fool in his folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>If a man pays back evil for good, evil will never leave his house. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Starting a quarrel is like breaching a dam; so drop the matter before a dispute breaks out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Acquitting the guilty and condemning the innocent-- the LORD detests them both. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Of what use is money in the hand of a fool, since he has no desire to get wisdom? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>A friend loves at all times, and a brother is born for adversity. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>A man lacking in judgment strikes hands in pledge and puts up security for his neighbor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He who loves a quarrel loves sin; he who builds a high gate invites destruction. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>A man of perverse heart does not prosper; he whose tongue is deceitful falls into trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>To have a fool for a son brings grief; there is no joy for the father of a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>A cheerful heart is good medicine, but a crushed spirit dries up the bones. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A wicked man accepts a bribe in secret to pervert the course of justice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>A discerning man keeps wisdom in view, but a fool's eyes wander to the ends of the earth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>A foolish son brings grief to his father and bitterness to the one who bore him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>It is not good to punish an innocent man, or to flog officials for their integrity. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>A man of knowledge uses words with restraint, and a man of understanding is even-tempered. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Even a fool is thought wise if he keeps silent, and discerning if he holds his tongue. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">sacrifices</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Eloquent</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="18">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>An unfriendly man pursues selfish ends; he defies all sound judgment. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A fool finds no pleasure in understanding but delights in airing his own opinions. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>When wickedness comes, so does contempt, and with shame comes disgrace. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The words of a man's mouth are deep waters, but the fountain of wisdom is a bubbling brook. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>It is not good to be partial to the wicked or to deprive the innocent of justice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>A fool's lips bring him strife, and his mouth invites a beating. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>A fool's mouth is his undoing, and his lips are a snare to his soul. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The words of a gossip are like choice morsels; they go down to a man's inmost parts. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>One who is slack in his work is brother to one who destroys. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The name of the LORD is a strong tower; the righteous run to it and are safe. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The wealth of the rich is their fortified city; they imagine it an unscalable wall. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Before his downfall a man's heart is proud, but humility comes before honor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>He who answers before listening-- that is his folly and his shame. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>A man's spirit sustains him in sickness, but a crushed spirit who can bear? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The heart of the discerning acquires knowledge; the ears of the wise seek it out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>A gift opens the way for the giver and ushers him into the presence of the great. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>The first to present his case seems right, till another comes forward and questions him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Casting the lot settles disputes and keeps strong opponents apart. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>An offended brother is more unyielding than a fortified city, and disputes are like the barred gates of a citadel. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>From the fruit of his mouth a man's stomach is filled; with the harvest from his lips he is satisfied. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>The tongue has the power of life and death, and those who love it will eat its fruit. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>He who finds a wife finds what is good and receives favor from the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A poor man pleads for mercy, but a rich man answers harshly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>A man of many companions may come to ruin, but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother. </content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="19">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Better a poor man whose walk is blameless than a fool whose lips are perverse. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>It is not good to have zeal without knowledge, nor to be hasty and miss the way. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A man's own folly ruins his life, yet his heart rages against the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Wealth brings many friends, but a poor man's friend deserts him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>A false witness will not go unpunished, and he who pours out lies will not go free. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Many curry favor with a ruler, and everyone is the friend of a man who gives gifts. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>A poor man is shunned by all his relatives-- how much more do his friends avoid him! Though he pursues them with pleading, they are nowhere to be found. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He who gets wisdom loves his own soul; he who cherishes understanding prospers. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>A false witness will not go unpunished, and he who pours out lies will perish. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>It is not fitting for a fool to live in luxury-- how much worse for a slave to rule over princes! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>A man's wisdom gives him patience; it is to his glory to overlook an offense. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>A king's rage is like the roar of a lion, but his favor is like dew on the grass. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>A foolish son is his father's ruin, and a quarrelsome wife is like a constant dripping. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Houses and wealth are inherited from parents, but a prudent wife is from the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Laziness brings on deep sleep, and the shiftless man goes hungry. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>He who obeys instructions guards his life, but he who is contemptuous of his ways will die. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>He who is kind to the poor lends to the LORD, and he will reward him for what he has done. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Discipline your son, for in that there is hope; do not be a willing party to his death. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>A hot-tempered man must pay the penalty; if you rescue him, you will have to do it again. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Listen to advice and accept instruction, and in the end you will be wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Many are the plans in a man's heart, but it is the LORD's purpose that prevails. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>What a man desires is unfailing love </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> ; better to be poor than a liar. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The fear of the LORD leads to life: Then one rests content, untouched by trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>The sluggard buries his hand in the dish; he will not even bring it back to his mouth! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Flog a mocker, and the simple will learn prudence; rebuke a discerning man, and he will gain knowledge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>He who robs his father and drives out his mother is a son who brings shame and disgrace. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Stop listening to instruction, my son, and you will stray from the words of knowledge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>A corrupt witness mocks at justice, and the mouth of the wicked gulps down evil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Penalties are prepared for mockers, and beatings for the backs of fools. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this sentence is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">A man's greed is his shame</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="20">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Wine is a mocker and beer a brawler; whoever is led astray by them is not wise. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A king's wrath is like the roar of a lion; he who angers him forfeits his life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>It is to a man's honor to avoid strife, but every fool is quick to quarrel. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>A sluggard does not plow in season; so at harvest time he looks but finds nothing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The purposes of a man's heart are deep waters, but a man of understanding draws them out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Many a man claims to have unfailing love, but a faithful man who can find? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The righteous man leads a blameless life; blessed are his children after him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>When a king sits on his throne to judge, he winnows out all evil with his eyes. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Who can say, "I have kept my heart pure; I am clean and without sin"? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Differing weights and differing measures-- the LORD detests them both. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Even a child is known by his actions, by whether his conduct is pure and right. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Ears that hear and eyes that see-- the LORD has made them both. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Do not love sleep or you will grow poor; stay awake and you will have food to spare. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"It's no good, it's no good!" says the buyer; then off he goes and boasts about his purchase. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Gold there is, and rubies in abundance, but lips that speak knowledge are a rare jewel. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Take the garment of one who puts up security for a stranger; hold it in pledge if he does it for a wayward woman. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Food gained by fraud tastes sweet to a man, but he ends up with a mouth full of gravel. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Make plans by seeking advice; if you wage war, obtain guidance. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>A gossip betrays a confidence; so avoid a man who talks too much. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>If a man curses his father or mother, his lamp will be snuffed out in pitch darkness. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>An inheritance quickly gained at the beginning will not be blessed at the end. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Do not say, "I'll pay you back for this wrong!" Wait for the LORD, and he will deliver you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The LORD detests differing weights, and dishonest scales do not please him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>A man's steps are directed by the LORD. How then can anyone understand his own way? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>It is a trap for a man to dedicate something rashly and only later to consider his vows. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>A wise king winnows out the wicked; he drives the threshing wheel over them. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The lamp of the LORD searches the spirit of a man </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ; it searches out his inmost being. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Love and faithfulness keep a king safe; through love his throne is made secure. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>The glory of young men is their strength, gray hair the splendor of the old. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Blows and wounds cleanse away evil, and beatings purge the inmost being. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">27</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">The spirit of man is the LORD's lamp</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="21">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The king's heart is in the hand of the LORD; he directs it like a watercourse wherever he pleases. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>All a man's ways seem right to him, but the LORD weighs the heart. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>To do what is right and just is more acceptable to the LORD than sacrifice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Haughty eyes and a proud heart, the lamp of the wicked, are sin! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The plans of the diligent lead to profit as surely as haste leads to poverty. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>A fortune made by a lying tongue is a fleeting vapor and a deadly snare. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The violence of the wicked will drag them away, for they refuse to do what is right. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The way of the guilty is devious, but the conduct of the innocent is upright. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Better to live on a corner of the roof than share a house with a quarrelsome wife. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The wicked man craves evil; his neighbor gets no mercy from him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>When a mocker is punished, the simple gain wisdom; when a wise man is instructed, he gets knowledge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The Righteous One </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> takes note of the house of the wicked and brings the wicked to ruin. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>If a man shuts his ears to the cry of the poor, he too will cry out and not be answered. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>A gift given in secret soothes anger, and a bribe concealed in the cloak pacifies great wrath. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>When justice is done, it brings joy to the righteous but terror to evildoers. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>A man who strays from the path of understanding comes to rest in the company of the dead. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>He who loves pleasure will become poor; whoever loves wine and oil will never be rich. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The wicked become a ransom for the righteous, and the unfaithful for the upright. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Better to live in a desert than with a quarrelsome and ill-tempered wife. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>In the house of the wise are stores of choice food and oil, but a foolish man devours all he has. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>He who pursues righteousness and love finds life, prosperity </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> and honor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>A wise man attacks the city of the mighty and pulls down the stronghold in which they trust. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>He who guards his mouth and his tongue keeps himself from calamity. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>The proud and arrogant man--"Mocker" is his name; he behaves with overweening pride. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The sluggard's craving will be the death of him, because his hands refuse to work.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>All day long he craves for more, but the righteous give without sparing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The sacrifice of the wicked is detestable-- how much more so when brought with evil intent! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>A false witness will perish, and whoever listens to him will be destroyed forever. </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>A wicked man puts up a bold front, but an upright man gives thought to his ways. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>There is no wisdom, no insight, no plan that can succeed against the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>The horse is made ready for the day of battle, but victory rests with the LORD. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Some Hebrew manuscripts, Septuagint and Vulgate; most Hebrew manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">vapor for those who seek death</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">The righteous man</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">righteousness</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">28</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">/ but the words of an obedient man will live on</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="22">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>A good name is more desirable than great riches; to be esteemed is better than silver or gold. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Rich and poor have this in common: The LORD is the Maker of them all. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A prudent man sees danger and takes refuge, but the simple keep going and suffer for it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Humility and the fear of the LORD bring wealth and honor and life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>In the paths of the wicked lie thorns and snares, but he who guards his soul stays far from them. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Train </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> a child in the way he should go, and when he is old he will not turn from it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The rich rule over the poor, and the borrower is servant to the lender. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He who sows wickedness reaps trouble, and the rod of his fury will be destroyed. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>A generous man will himself be blessed, for he shares his food with the poor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Drive out the mocker, and out goes strife; quarrels and insults are ended. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He who loves a pure heart and whose speech is gracious will have the king for his friend. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The eyes of the LORD keep watch over knowledge, but he frustrates the words of the unfaithful. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>The sluggard says, "There is a lion outside!" or, "I will be murdered in the streets!" </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The mouth of an adulteress is a deep pit; he who is under the LORD's wrath will fall into it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Folly is bound up in the heart of a child, but the rod of discipline will drive it far from him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>He who oppresses the poor to increase his wealth and he who gives gifts to the rich--both come to poverty. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Pay attention and listen to the sayings of the wise; apply your heart to what I teach,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>for it is pleasing when you keep them in your heart and have all of them ready on your lips.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>So that your trust may be in the LORD, I teach you today, even you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Have I not written thirty </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> sayings for you, sayings of counsel and knowledge,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>teaching you true and reliable words, so that you can give sound answers to him who sent you? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Do not exploit the poor because they are poor and do not crush the needy in court,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>for the LORD will take up their case and will plunder those who plunder them. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Do not make friends with a hot-tempered man, do not associate with one easily angered,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>or you may learn his ways and get yourself ensnared. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Do not be a man who strikes hands in pledge or puts up security for debts;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>if you lack the means to pay, your very bed will be snatched from under you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Do not move an ancient boundary stone set up by your forefathers. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Do you see a man skilled in his work? He will serve before kings; he will not serve before obscure men. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Start</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">20</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">not formerly written</content>
            <content>; or </content>
            <content kind="EM">not written excellent</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="23">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>When you sit to dine with a ruler, note well what </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> is before you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>and put a knife to your throat if you are given to gluttony.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Do not crave his delicacies, for that food is deceptive. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Do not wear yourself out to get rich; have the wisdom to show restraint.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Cast but a glance at riches, and they are gone, for they will surely sprout wings and fly off to the sky like an eagle. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Do not eat the food of a stingy man, do not crave his delicacies;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>for he is the kind of man who is always thinking about the cost. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> "Eat and drink," he says to you, but his heart is not with you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>You will vomit up the little you have eaten and will have wasted your compliments. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Do not speak to a fool, for he will scorn the wisdom of your words. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Do not move an ancient boundary stone or encroach on the fields of the fatherless,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>for their Defender is strong; he will take up their case against you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Apply your heart to instruction and your ears to words of knowledge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Do not withhold discipline from a child; if you punish him with the rod, he will not die.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Punish him with the rod and save his soul from death. </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>My son, if your heart is wise, then my heart will be glad;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>my inmost being will rejoice when your lips speak what is right. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Do not let your heart envy sinners, but always be zealous for the fear of the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>There is surely a future hope for you, and your hope will not be cut off. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Listen, my son, and be wise, and keep your heart on the right path.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Do not join those who drink too much wine or gorge themselves on meat,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>for drunkards and gluttons become poor, and drowsiness clothes them in rags. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Listen to your father, who gave you life, and do not despise your mother when she is old.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Buy the truth and do not sell it; get wisdom, discipline and understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>The father of a righteous man has great joy; he who has a wise son delights in him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>May your father and mother be glad; may she who gave you birth rejoice! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>My son, give me your heart and let your eyes keep to my ways,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>for a prostitute is a deep pit and a wayward wife is a narrow well.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Like a bandit she lies in wait, and multiplies the unfaithful among men. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Who has woe? Who has sorrow? Who has strife? Who has complaints? Who has needless bruises? Who has bloodshot eyes?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Those who linger over wine, who go to sample bowls of mixed wine.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Do not gaze at wine when it is red, when it sparkles in the cup, when it goes down smoothly!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>In the end it bites like a snake and poisons like a viper.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Your eyes will see strange sights and your mind imagine confusing things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>You will be like one sleeping on the high seas, lying on top of the rigging.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>"They hit me," you will say, "but I'm not hurt! They beat me, but I don't feel it! When will I wake up so I can find another drink?" </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">who</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">for as he thinks within himself, / so he is</content>
            <content>; or </content>
            <content kind="EM">for as he puts on a feast, / so he is</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">14</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="24">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Do not envy wicked men, do not desire their company;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>for their hearts plot violence, and their lips talk about making trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>By wisdom a house is built, and through understanding it is established;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>through knowledge its rooms are filled with rare and beautiful treasures. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>A wise man has great power, and a man of knowledge increases strength;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>for waging war you need guidance, and for victory many advisers. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Wisdom is too high for a fool; in the assembly at the gate he has nothing to say. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He who plots evil will be known as a schemer.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The schemes of folly are sin, and men detest a mocker. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>If you falter in times of trouble, how small is your strength! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Rescue those being led away to death; hold back those staggering toward slaughter.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>If you say, "But we knew nothing about this," does not he who weighs the heart perceive it? Does not he who guards your life know it? Will he not repay each person according to what he has done? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Eat honey, my son, for it is good; honey from the comb is sweet to your taste.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Know also that wisdom is sweet to your soul; if you find it, there is a future hope for you, and your hope will not be cut off. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Do not lie in wait like an outlaw against a righteous man's house, do not raid his dwelling place;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>for though a righteous man falls seven times, he rises again, but the wicked are brought down by calamity. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Do not gloat when your enemy falls; when he stumbles, do not let your heart rejoice,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>or the LORD will see and disapprove and turn his wrath away from him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Do not fret because of evil men or be envious of the wicked,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>for the evil man has no future hope, and the lamp of the wicked will be snuffed out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Fear the LORD and the king, my son, and do not join with the rebellious,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>for those two will send sudden destruction upon them, and who knows what calamities they can bring?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>These also are sayings of the wise: To show partiality in judging is not good:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Whoever says to the guilty, "You are innocent"-- peoples will curse him and nations denounce him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>But it will go well with those who convict the guilty, and rich blessing will come upon them. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>An honest answer is like a kiss on the lips. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Finish your outdoor work and get your fields ready; after that, build your house. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Do not testify against your neighbor without cause, or use your lips to deceive.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Do not say, "I'll do to him as he has done to me; I'll pay that man back for what he did." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>I went past the field of the sluggard, past the vineyard of the man who lacks judgment;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>thorns had come up everywhere, the ground was covered with weeds, and the stone wall was in ruins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>I applied my heart to what I observed and learned a lesson from what I saw:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to rest--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>and poverty will come on you like a bandit and scarcity like an armed man. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">34</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">like a vagrant / and scarcity like a beggar</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="25">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>These are more proverbs of Solomon, copied by the men of Hezekiah king of Judah:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>It is the glory of God to conceal a matter; to search out a matter is the glory of kings. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>As the heavens are high and the earth is deep, so the hearts of kings are unsearchable. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Remove the dross from the silver, and out comes material for </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> the silversmith;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>remove the wicked from the king's presence, and his throne will be established through righteousness. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Do not exalt yourself in the king's presence, and do not claim a place among great men;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>it is better for him to say to you, "Come up here," than for him to humiliate you before a nobleman. What you have seen with your eyes</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>do not bring </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> hastily to court, for what will you do in the end if your neighbor puts you to shame? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>If you argue your case with a neighbor, do not betray another man's confidence,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>or he who hears it may shame you and you will never lose your bad reputation. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>A word aptly spoken is like apples of gold in settings of silver. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Like an earring of gold or an ornament of fine gold is a wise man's rebuke to a listening ear. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Like the coolness of snow at harvest time is a trustworthy messenger to those who send him; he refreshes the spirit of his masters. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Like clouds and wind without rain is a man who boasts of gifts he does not give. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Through patience a ruler can be persuaded, and a gentle tongue can break a bone. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>If you find honey, eat just enough-- too much of it, and you will vomit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Seldom set foot in your neighbor's house-- too much of you, and he will hate you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Like a club or a sword or a sharp arrow is the man who gives false testimony against his neighbor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Like a bad tooth or a lame foot is reliance on the unfaithful in times of trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Like one who takes away a garment on a cold day, or like vinegar poured on soda, is one who sings songs to a heavy heart. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>If your enemy is hungry, give him food to eat; if he is thirsty, give him water to drink.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>In doing this, you will heap burning coals on his head, and the LORD will reward you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>As a north wind brings rain, so a sly tongue brings angry looks. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Better to live on a corner of the roof than share a house with a quarrelsome wife. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Like cold water to a weary soul is good news from a distant land. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Like a muddied spring or a polluted well is a righteous man who gives way to the wicked. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>It is not good to eat too much honey, nor is it honorable to seek one's own honor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Like a city whose walls are broken down is a man who lacks self-control. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">comes a vessel from</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7,8</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">nobleman / on whom you had set your eyes. / </content>
            <content kind="EM">[8]</content>
            <content kind="EM"> Do not go</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="26">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Like snow in summer or rain in harvest, honor is not fitting for a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Like a fluttering sparrow or a darting swallow, an undeserved curse does not come to rest. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A whip for the horse, a halter for the donkey, and a rod for the backs of fools! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Do not answer a fool according to his folly, or you will be like him yourself. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Answer a fool according to his folly, or he will be wise in his own eyes. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Like cutting off one's feet or drinking violence is the sending of a message by the hand of a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Like a lame man's legs that hang limp is a proverb in the mouth of a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Like tying a stone in a sling is the giving of honor to a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Like a thornbush in a drunkard's hand is a proverb in the mouth of a fool. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Like an archer who wounds at random is he who hires a fool or any passer-by. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>As a dog returns to its vomit, so a fool repeats his folly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Do you see a man wise in his own eyes? There is more hope for a fool than for him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>The sluggard says, "There is a lion in the road, a fierce lion roaming the streets!" </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>As a door turns on its hinges, so a sluggard turns on his bed. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The sluggard buries his hand in the dish; he is too lazy to bring it back to his mouth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>The sluggard is wiser in his own eyes than seven men who answer discreetly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Like one who seizes a dog by the ears is a passer-by who meddles in a quarrel not his own. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Like a madman shooting firebrands or deadly arrows</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>is a man who deceives his neighbor and says, "I was only joking!" </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Without wood a fire goes out; without gossip a quarrel dies down. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>As charcoal to embers and as wood to fire, so is a quarrelsome man for kindling strife. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>The words of a gossip are like choice morsels; they go down to a man's inmost parts. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Like a coating of glaze </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> over earthenware are fervent lips with an evil heart. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>A malicious man disguises himself with his lips, but in his heart he harbors deceit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Though his speech is charming, do not believe him, for seven abominations fill his heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>His malice may be concealed by deception, but his wickedness will be exposed in the assembly. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>If a man digs a pit, he will fall into it; if a man rolls a stone, it will roll back on him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>A lying tongue hates those it hurts, and a flattering mouth works ruin. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">23</content>
            <content> With a different word division of the Hebrew; Masoretic Text </content>
            <content kind="EM">of silver dross</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="27">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Do not boast about tomorrow, for you do not know what a day may bring forth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Let another praise you, and not your own mouth; someone else, and not your own lips. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Stone is heavy and sand a burden, but provocation by a fool is heavier than both. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Anger is cruel and fury overwhelming, but who can stand before jealousy? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Better is open rebuke than hidden love. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Wounds from a friend can be trusted, but an enemy multiplies kisses. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>He who is full loathes honey, but to the hungry even what is bitter tastes sweet. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Like a bird that strays from its nest is a man who strays from his home. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Perfume and incense bring joy to the heart, and the pleasantness of one's friend springs from his earnest counsel. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Do not forsake your friend and the friend of your father, and do not go to your brother's house when disaster strikes you-- better a neighbor nearby than a brother far away. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Be wise, my son, and bring joy to my heart; then I can answer anyone who treats me with contempt. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The prudent see danger and take refuge, but the simple keep going and suffer for it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Take the garment of one who puts up security for a stranger; hold it in pledge if he does it for a wayward woman. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>If a man loudly blesses his neighbor early in the morning, it will be taken as a curse. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>A quarrelsome wife is like a constant dripping on a rainy day;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>restraining her is like restraining the wind or grasping oil with the hand. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>As iron sharpens iron, so one man sharpens another. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He who tends a fig tree will eat its fruit, and he who looks after his master will be honored. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>As water reflects a face, so a man's heart reflects the man. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Death and Destruction </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> are never satisfied, and neither are the eyes of man. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>The crucible for silver and the furnace for gold, but man is tested by the praise he receives. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Though you grind a fool in a mortar, grinding him like grain with a pestle, you will not remove his folly from him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Be sure you know the condition of your flocks, give careful attention to your herds;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>for riches do not endure forever, and a crown is not secure for all generations.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>When the hay is removed and new growth appears and the grass from the hills is gathered in,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>the lambs will provide you with clothing, and the goats with the price of a field.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>You will have plenty of goats' milk to feed you and your family and to nourish your servant girls. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">20</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol and Abaddon</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="28">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The wicked man flees though no one pursues, but the righteous are as bold as a lion. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>When a country is rebellious, it has many rulers, but a man of understanding and knowledge maintains order. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A ruler </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> who oppresses the poor is like a driving rain that leaves no crops. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Those who forsake the law praise the wicked, but those who keep the law resist them. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Evil men do not understand justice, but those who seek the LORD understand it fully. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Better a poor man whose walk is blameless than a rich man whose ways are perverse. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>He who keeps the law is a discerning son, but a companion of gluttons disgraces his father. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He who increases his wealth by exorbitant interest amasses it for another, who will be kind to the poor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>If anyone turns a deaf ear to the law, even his prayers are detestable. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He who leads the upright along an evil path will fall into his own trap, but the blameless will receive a good inheritance. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>A rich man may be wise in his own eyes, but a poor man who has discernment sees through him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>When the righteous triumph, there is great elation; but when the wicked rise to power, men go into hiding. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>He who conceals his sins does not prosper, but whoever confesses and renounces them finds mercy. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Blessed is the man who always fears the LORD, but he who hardens his heart falls into trouble. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Like a roaring lion or a charging bear is a wicked man ruling over a helpless people. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>A tyrannical ruler lacks judgment, but he who hates ill-gotten gain will enjoy a long life. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>A man tormented by the guilt of murder will be a fugitive till death; let no one support him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He whose walk is blameless is kept safe, but he whose ways are perverse will suddenly fall. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He who works his land will have abundant food, but the one who chases fantasies will have his fill of poverty. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>A faithful man will be richly blessed, but one eager to get rich will not go unpunished. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>To show partiality is not good-- yet a man will do wrong for a piece of bread. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>A stingy man is eager to get rich and is unaware that poverty awaits him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>He who rebukes a man will in the end gain more favor than he who has a flattering tongue. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>He who robs his father or mother and says, "It's not wrong"-- he is partner to him who destroys. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>A greedy man stirs up dissension, but he who trusts in the LORD will prosper. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>He who trusts in himself is a fool, but he who walks in wisdom is kept safe. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>He who gives to the poor will lack nothing, but he who closes his eyes to them receives many curses. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>When the wicked rise to power, people go into hiding; but when the wicked perish, the righteous thrive. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">3</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">A poor man</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="29">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>A man who remains stiff-necked after many rebukes will suddenly be destroyed--without remedy. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>When the righteous thrive, the people rejoice; when the wicked rule, the people groan. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A man who loves wisdom brings joy to his father, but a companion of prostitutes squanders his wealth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>By justice a king gives a country stability, but one who is greedy for bribes tears it down. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Whoever flatters his neighbor is spreading a net for his feet. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>An evil man is snared by his own sin, but a righteous one can sing and be glad. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The righteous care about justice for the poor, but the wicked have no such concern. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Mockers stir up a city, but wise men turn away anger. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>If a wise man goes to court with a fool, the fool rages and scoffs, and there is no peace. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Bloodthirsty men hate a man of integrity and seek to kill the upright. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>A fool gives full vent to his anger, but a wise man keeps himself under control. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>If a ruler listens to lies, all his officials become wicked. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>The poor man and the oppressor have this in common: The LORD gives sight to the eyes of both. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>If a king judges the poor with fairness, his throne will always be secure. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The rod of correction imparts wisdom, but a child left to himself disgraces his mother. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>When the wicked thrive, so does sin, but the righteous will see their downfall. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Discipline your son, and he will give you peace; he will bring delight to your soul. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Where there is no revelation, the people cast off restraint; but blessed is he who keeps the law. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>A servant cannot be corrected by mere words; though he understands, he will not respond. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Do you see a man who speaks in haste? There is more hope for a fool than for him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>If a man pampers his servant from youth, he will bring grief </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> in the end. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>An angry man stirs up dissension, and a hot-tempered one commits many sins. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>A man's pride brings him low, but a man of lowly spirit gains honor. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>The accomplice of a thief is his own enemy; he is put under oath and dare not testify. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Fear of man will prove to be a snare, but whoever trusts in the LORD is kept safe. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Many seek an audience with a ruler, but it is from the LORD that man gets justice. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The righteous detest the dishonest; the wicked detest the upright.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="30">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The sayings of Agur son of Jakeh--an oracle </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> : This man declared to Ithiel, to Ithiel and to Ucal: </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"I am the most ignorant of men; I do not have a man's understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I have not learned wisdom, nor have I knowledge of the Holy One.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Who has gone up to heaven and come down? Who has gathered up the wind in the hollow of his hands? Who has wrapped up the waters in his cloak? Who has established all the ends of the earth? What is his name, and the name of his son? Tell me if you know! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"Every word of God is flawless; he is a shield to those who take refuge in him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Do not add to his words, or he will rebuke you and prove you a liar. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Two things I ask of you, O LORD; do not refuse me before I die:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Keep falsehood and lies far from me; give me neither poverty nor riches, but give me only my daily bread.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Otherwise, I may have too much and disown you and say, `Who is the LORD?' Or I may become poor and steal, and so dishonor the name of my God. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"Do not slander a servant to his master, or he will curse you, and you will pay for it. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"There are those who curse their fathers and do not bless their mothers;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>those who are pure in their own eyes and yet are not cleansed of their filth;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>those whose eyes are ever so haughty, whose glances are so disdainful;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>those whose teeth are swords and whose jaws are set with knives to devour the poor from the earth, the needy from among mankind. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"The leech has two daughters. `Give! Give!' they cry. "There are three things that are never satisfied, four that never say, `Enough!':</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>the grave, </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> the barren womb, land, which is never satisfied with water, and fire, which never says, `Enough!' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"The eye that mocks a father, that scorns obedience to a mother, will be pecked out by the ravens of the valley, will be eaten by the vultures. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"There are three things that are too amazing for me, four that I do not understand:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>the way of an eagle in the sky, the way of a snake on a rock, the way of a ship on the high seas, and the way of a man with a maiden. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"This is the way of an adulteress: She eats and wipes her mouth and says, `I've done nothing wrong.' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Under three things the earth trembles, under four it cannot bear up:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>a servant who becomes king, a fool who is full of food,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>an unloved woman who is married, and a maidservant who displaces her mistress. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"Four things on earth are small, yet they are extremely wise:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Ants are creatures of little strength, yet they store up their food in the summer;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>coneys </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> are creatures of little power, yet they make their home in the crags;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>locusts have no king, yet they advance together in ranks;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>a lizard can be caught with the hand, yet it is found in kings' palaces. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"There are three things that are stately in their stride, four that move with stately bearing:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>a lion, mighty among beasts, who retreats before nothing;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>a strutting rooster, a he-goat, and a king with his army around him. </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>"If you have played the fool and exalted yourself, or if you have planned evil, clap your hand over your mouth!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>For as churning the milk produces butter, and as twisting the nose produces blood, so stirring up anger produces strife."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Jakeh of Massa</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Masoretic Text; with a different word division of the Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">declared, "I am weary, O God; / I am weary, O God, and faint.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">16</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">26</content>
            <content> That is, the hyrax or rock badger</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">31</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">king secure against revolt</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="31">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The sayings of King Lemuel--an oracle </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> his mother taught him:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"O my son, O son of my womb, O son of my vows, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>do not spend your strength on women, your vigor on those who ruin kings. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"It is not for kings, O Lemuel-- not for kings to drink wine, not for rulers to crave beer,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>lest they drink and forget what the law decrees, and deprive all the oppressed of their rights.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Give beer to those who are perishing, wine to those who are in anguish;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>let them drink and forget their poverty and remember their misery no more. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Speak up for those who cannot speak for themselves, for the rights of all who are destitute.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Speak up and judge fairly; defend the rights of the poor and needy." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content> </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> A wife of noble character who can find? She is worth far more than rubies.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Her husband has full confidence in her and lacks nothing of value.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>She brings him good, not harm, all the days of her life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>She selects wool and flax and works with eager hands.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>She is like the merchant ships, bringing her food from afar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>She gets up while it is still dark; she provides food for her family and portions for her servant girls.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>She considers a field and buys it; out of her earnings she plants a vineyard.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>She sets about her work vigorously; her arms are strong for her tasks.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>She sees that her trading is profitable, and her lamp does not go out at night.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>In her hand she holds the distaff and grasps the spindle with her fingers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>She opens her arms to the poor and extends her hands to the needy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>When it snows, she has no fear for her household; for all of them are clothed in scarlet.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>She makes coverings for her bed; she is clothed in fine linen and purple.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Her husband is respected at the city gate, where he takes his seat among the elders of the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>She makes linen garments and sells them, and supplies the merchants with sashes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>She is clothed with strength and dignity; she can laugh at the days to come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>She speaks with wisdom, and faithful instruction is on her tongue.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>She watches over the affairs of her household and does not eat the bread of idleness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Her children arise and call her blessed; her husband also, and he praises her:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"Many women do noble things, but you surpass them all."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Charm is deceptive, and beauty is fleeting; but a woman who fears the LORD is to be praised.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Give her the reward she has earned, and let her works bring her praise at the city gate.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">of Lemuel king of Massa, which</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">/ the answer to my prayers</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> Verses 10-31 are an acrostic, each verse beginning with a successive letter of the Hebrew alphabet.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
</book>
