<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, according to the promise of life that is in Christ Jesus, </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>To Timothy, my dear son: Grace, mercy and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I thank God, whom I serve, as my forefathers did, with a clear conscience, as night and day I constantly remember you in my prayers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Recalling your tears, I long to see you, so that I may be filled with joy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>I have been reminded of your sincere faith, which first lived in your grandmother Lois and in your mother Eunice and, I am persuaded, now lives in you also.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>For this reason I remind you to fan into flame the gift of God, which is in you through the laying on of my hands.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>For God did not give us a spirit of timidity, but a spirit of power, of love and of self-discipline.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>So do not be ashamed to testify about our Lord, or ashamed of me his prisoner. But join with me in suffering for the gospel, by the power of God,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>who has saved us and called us to a holy life--not because of anything we have done but because of his own purpose and grace. This grace was given us in Christ Jesus before the beginning of time,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>but it has now been revealed through the appearing of our Savior, Christ Jesus, who has destroyed death and has brought life and immortality to light through the gospel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And of this gospel I was appointed a herald and an apostle and a teacher.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>That is why I am suffering as I am. Yet I am not ashamed, because I know whom I have believed, and am convinced that he is able to guard what I have entrusted to him for that day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>What you heard from me, keep as the pattern of sound teaching, with faith and love in Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Guard the good deposit that was entrusted to you--guard it with the help of the Holy Spirit who lives in us.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>You know that everyone in the province of Asia has deserted me, including Phygelus and Hermogenes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>May the Lord show mercy to the household of Onesiphorus, because he often refreshed me and was not ashamed of my chains.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>On the contrary, when he was in Rome, he searched hard for me until he found me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>May the Lord grant that he will find mercy from the Lord on that day! You know very well in how many ways he helped me in Ephesus.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>You then, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And the things you have heard me say in the presence of many witnesses entrust to reliable men who will also be qualified to teach others.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Endure hardship with us like a good soldier of Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>No one serving as a soldier gets involved in civilian affairs--he wants to please his commanding officer.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Similarly, if anyone competes as an athlete, he does not receive the victor's crown unless he competes according to the rules.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The hardworking farmer should be the first to receive a share of the crops.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Reflect on what I am saying, for the Lord will give you insight into all this.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Remember Jesus Christ, raised from the dead, descended from David. This is my gospel,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>for which I am suffering even to the point of being chained like a criminal. But God's word is not chained.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Therefore I endure everything for the sake of the elect, that they too may obtain the salvation that is in Christ Jesus, with eternal glory.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Here is a trustworthy saying: If we died with him, we will also live with him;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>if we endure, we will also reign with him. If we disown him, he will also disown us;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>if we are faithless, he will remain faithful, for he cannot disown himself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Keep reminding them of these things. Warn them before God against quarreling about words; it is of no value, and only ruins those who listen.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Do your best to present yourself to God as one approved, a workman who does not need to be ashamed and who correctly handles the word of truth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Avoid godless chatter, because those who indulge in it will become more and more ungodly.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Their teaching will spread like gangrene. Among them are Hymenaeus and Philetus,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>who have wandered away from the truth. They say that the resurrection has already taken place, and they destroy the faith of some.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Nevertheless, God's solid foundation stands firm, sealed with this inscription: "The Lord knows those who are his," </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and, "Everyone who confesses the name of the Lord must turn away from wickedness."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>In a large house there are articles not only of gold and silver, but also of wood and clay; some are for noble purposes and some for ignoble.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>If a man cleanses himself from the latter, he will be an instrument for noble purposes, made holy, useful to the Master and prepared to do any good work.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Flee the evil desires of youth, and pursue righteousness, faith, love and peace, along with those who call on the Lord out of a pure heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Don't have anything to do with foolish and stupid arguments, because you know they produce quarrels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And the Lord's servant must not quarrel; instead, he must be kind to everyone, able to teach, not resentful.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Those who oppose him he must gently instruct, in the hope that God will grant them repentance leading them to a knowledge of the truth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>and that they will come to their senses and escape from the trap of the devil, who has taken them captive to do his will.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Num. 16:5 (see Septuagint)</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>But mark this: There will be terrible times in the last days.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>People will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, proud, abusive, disobedient to their parents, ungrateful, unholy,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>without love, unforgiving, slanderous, without self-control, brutal, not lovers of the good,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>treacherous, rash, conceited, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>having a form of godliness but denying its power. Have nothing to do with them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>They are the kind who worm their way into homes and gain control over weak-willed women, who are loaded down with sins and are swayed by all kinds of evil desires,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>always learning but never able to acknowledge the truth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Just as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses, so also these men oppose the truth--men of depraved minds, who, as far as the faith is concerned, are rejected.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>But they will not get very far because, as in the case of those men, their folly will be clear to everyone.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>You, however, know all about my teaching, my way of life, my purpose, faith, patience, love, endurance,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>persecutions, sufferings--what kinds of things happened to me in Antioch, Iconium and Lystra, the persecutions I endured. Yet the Lord rescued me from all of them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>In fact, everyone who wants to live a godly life in Christ Jesus will be persecuted,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>while evil men and impostors will go from bad to worse, deceiving and being deceived.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But as for you, continue in what you have learned and have become convinced of, because you know those from whom you learned it,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>and how from infancy you have known the holy Scriptures, which are able to make you wise for salvation through faith in Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>All Scripture is God-breathed and is useful for teaching, rebuking, correcting and training in righteousness,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>so that the man of God may be thoroughly equipped for every good work.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>In the presence of God and of Christ Jesus, who will judge the living and the dead, and in view of his appearing and his kingdom, I give you this charge:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Preach the Word; be prepared in season and out of season; correct, rebuke and encourage--with great patience and careful instruction.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>For the time will come when men will not put up with sound doctrine. Instead, to suit their own desires, they will gather around them a great number of teachers to say what their itching ears want to hear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>They will turn their ears away from the truth and turn aside to myths.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But you, keep your head in all situations, endure hardship, do the work of an evangelist, discharge all the duties of your ministry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>For I am already being poured out like a drink offering, and the time has come for my departure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>I have fought the good fight, I have finished the race, I have kept the faith.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Now there is in store for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, will award to me on that day--and not only to me, but also to all who have longed for his appearing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Do your best to come to me quickly,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>for Demas, because he loved this world, has deserted me and has gone to Thessalonica. Crescens has gone to Galatia, and Titus to Dalmatia.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Only Luke is with me. Get Mark and bring him with you, because he is helpful to me in my ministry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>I sent Tychicus to Ephesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>When you come, bring the cloak that I left with Carpus at Troas, and my scrolls, especially the parchments.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Alexander the metalworker did me a great deal of harm. The Lord will repay him for what he has done.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>You too should be on your guard against him, because he strongly opposed our message.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>At my first defense, no one came to my support, but everyone deserted me. May it not be held against them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But the Lord stood at my side and gave me strength, so that through me the message might be fully proclaimed and all the Gentiles might hear it. And I was delivered from the lion's mouth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The Lord will rescue me from every evil attack and will bring me safely to his heavenly kingdom. To him be glory for ever and ever. Amen. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Greet Priscilla </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and Aquila and the household of Onesiphorus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Erastus stayed in Corinth, and I left Trophimus sick in Miletus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Do your best to get here before winter. Eubulus greets you, and so do Pudens, Linus, Claudia and all the brothers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>The Lord be with your spirit. Grace be with you. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">Prisca</content>
            <content>, a variant of </content>
            <content kind="EM">Priscilla</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
</book>
