<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, and Timothy our brother, to Philemon, our dear helper in the faith,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And to Apphia, our sister, and to Archippus, our brother in God's army, and to the church in your house:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I give praise to God at all times and make prayer for you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Hearing of the love and the faith which you have to the Lord Jesus and to all the saints;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>That the faith which you have in common with them may be working with power, in the knowledge of every good thing in you, for Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For I had great joy and comfort in your love, because the hearts of the saints have been made strong again through you, brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And so, though I might, in the name of Christ, give you orders to do what is right,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Still, because of love, in place of an order, I make a request to you, I, Paul, an old man and now a prisoner of Christ Jesus:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>My request is for my child Onesimus, the child of my chains,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Who in the past was of no profit to you, but now is of profit to you and to me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whom I have sent back to you, him who is my very heart:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Though my desire was to keep him with me, to be my servant in the chains of the good news, in your place:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But without your approval I would do nothing; so that your good works might not be forced, but done freely from your heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For it is possible that for this reason he was parted from you for a time, so that you might have him for ever;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>No longer as a servant, but more than a servant, a brother, very dear to me specially, but much more to you, in the flesh as well as in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If then you take me to be your friend and brother, take him in as myself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If he has done you any wrong or is in debt to you for anything, put it to my account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I, Paul, writing this myself, say, I will make payment to you: and I do not say to you that you are in debt to me even for your life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So brother, let me have joy of you in the Lord: give new life to my heart in Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Being certain that you will do my desire, I am writing to you, in the knowledge that you will do even more than I say.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And make a room ready for me; for I am hoping that through your prayers I will be given to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Epaphras, my brother-prisoner in Christ Jesus, sends you his love;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And so do Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, my brother-workers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. So be it.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>