<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher, vanity of vanities; all </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>What profit hath a man of all his labour which he taketh under the sun?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content kind="EM">One</content>
            <content> generation passeth away, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">another</content>
            <content> generation cometh: but the earth abideth for ever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The sun also ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to his place where he arose.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The wind goeth toward the south, and turneth about unto the north; it whirleth about continually, and the wind returneth again according to his circuits.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>All the rivers run into the sea; yet the sea </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> not full; unto the place from whence the rivers come, thither they return again.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>All things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> full of labour; man cannot utter </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>: the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The thing that hath been, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is that</content>
            <content> which shall be; and that which is done </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> that which shall be done: and </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> no new </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content> under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Is there </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> thing whereof it may be said, See, this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> new? it hath been already of old time, which was before us.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content kind="EM">There is</content>
            <content> no remembrance of former </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content>; neither shall there be </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> remembrance of </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> that are to come with </content>
            <content kind="EM">those</content>
            <content> that shall come after.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And I gave my heart to seek and search out by wisdom concerning all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> that are done under heaven: this sore travail hath God given to the sons of man to be exercised therewith.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity and vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content kind="EM">That which is</content>
            <content> crooked cannot be made straight: and that which is wanting cannot be numbered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I am come to great estate, and have gotten more wisdom than all </content>
            <content kind="EM">they</content>
            <content> that have been before me in Jerusalem: yea, my heart had great experience of wisdom and knowledge.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And I gave my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also is vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For in much wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> much grief: and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>I said in mine heart, Go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I said of laughter, </content>
            <content kind="EM">It is</content>
            <content> mad: and of mirth, What doeth it?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I sought in mine heart to give myself unto wine, yet acquainting mine heart with wisdom; and to lay hold on folly, till I might see what </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> that good for the sons of men, which they should do under the heaven all the days of their life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>I made me gardens and orchards, and I planted trees in them of all </content>
            <content kind="EM">kind of</content>
            <content> fruits:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>I made me pools of water, to water therewith the wood that bringeth forth trees:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>I got </content>
            <content kind="EM">me</content>
            <content> servants and maidens, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of great and small cattle above all that were in Jerusalem before me:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>I gathered me also silver and gold, and the peculiar treasure of kings and of the provinces: I gat me men singers and women singers, and the delights of the sons of men, </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> musical instruments, and that of all sorts.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them, I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced in all my labour: and this was my portion of all my labour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do: and, behold, all </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> vanity and vexation of spirit, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">there was</content>
            <content> no profit under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what </content>
            <content kind="EM">can</content>
            <content> the man </content>
            <content kind="EM">do</content>
            <content> that cometh after the king? </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> that which hath been already done.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The wise man's eyes </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> in his head; but the fool walketh in darkness: and I myself perceived also that one event happeneth to them all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so it happeneth even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then I said in my heart, that this also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>For </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> no remembrance of the wise more than of the fool for ever; seeing that which now </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the days to come shall all be forgotten. And how dieth the wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">man</content>
            <content>? as the fool.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Therefore I hated life; because the work that is wrought under the sun </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> grievous unto me: for all </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity and vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Yea, I hated all my labour which I had taken under the sun: because I should leave it unto the man that shall be after me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And who knoweth whether he shall be a wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">man</content>
            <content> or a fool? yet shall he have rule over all my labour wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have shewed myself wise under the sun. This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> also vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Therefore I went about to cause my heart to despair of all the labour which I took under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For there is a man whose labour </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in wisdom, and in knowledge, and in equity; yet to a man that hath not laboured therein shall he leave it </content>
            <content kind="EM">for</content>
            <content> his portion. This also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity and a great evil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>For what hath man of all his labour, and of the vexation of his heart, wherein he hath laboured under the sun?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>For all his days </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> sorrows, and his travail grief; yea, his heart taketh not rest in the night. This is also vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content kind="EM">There is</content>
            <content> nothing better for a man, </content>
            <content kind="EM">than</content>
            <content> that he should eat and drink, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> he should make his soul enjoy good in his labour. This also I saw, that it </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> from the hand of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>For who can eat, or who else can hasten </content>
            <content kind="EM">hereunto</content>
            <content>, more than I?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>For </content>
            <content kind="EM">God</content>
            <content> giveth to a man that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> good in his sight wisdom, and knowledge, and joy: but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to </content>
            <content kind="EM">him that is</content>
            <content> good before God. This also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity and vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>To every </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing there is</content>
            <content> a season, and a time to every purpose under the heaven:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A time to be born, and a time to die; a time to plant, and a time to pluck up </content>
            <content kind="EM">that which is</content>
            <content> planted;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>A time to kill, and a time to heal; a time to break down, and a time to build up;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>A time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to dance;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>A time to cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together; a time to embrace, and a time to refrain from embracing;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>A time to get, and a time to lose; a time to keep, and a time to cast away;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>A time to rend, and a time to sew; a time to keep silence, and a time to speak;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>A time to love, and a time to hate; a time of war, and a time of peace.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboureth?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>I have seen the travail, which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised in it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He hath made every </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content> beautiful in his time: also he hath set the world in their heart, so that no man can find out the work that God maketh from the beginning to the end.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>I know that </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> no good in them, but for </content>
            <content kind="EM">a man</content>
            <content> to rejoice, and to do good in his life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy the good of all his labour, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the gift of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it: and God doeth </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">men</content>
            <content> should fear before him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>That which hath been is now; and that which is to be hath already been; and God requireth that which is past.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And moreover I saw under the sun the place of judgment, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> wickedness </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> there; and the place of righteousness, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> iniquity </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> there.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>I said in mine heart, God shall judge the righteous and the wicked: for </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> a time there for every purpose and for every work.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>I said in mine heart concerning the estate of the sons of men, that God might manifest them, and that they might see that they themselves are beasts.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one breath; so that a man hath no preeminence above a beast: for all </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Who knoweth the spirit of man that goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast that goeth downward to the earth?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Wherefore I perceive that </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his own works; for that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> his portion: for who shall bring him to see what shall be after him?</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>So I returned, and considered all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and behold the tears of </content>
            <content kind="EM">such as were</content>
            <content> oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors </content>
            <content kind="EM">there was</content>
            <content> power; but they had no comforter.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Wherefore I praised the dead which are already dead more than the living which are yet alive.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Yea, better </content>
            <content kind="EM">is he</content>
            <content> than both they, which hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Again, I considered all travail, and every right work, that for this a man is envied of his neighbour. This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> also vanity and vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Better </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an handful </content>
            <content kind="EM">with</content>
            <content> quietness, than both the hands full </content>
            <content kind="EM">with</content>
            <content> travail and vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Then I returned, and I saw vanity under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>There is one </content>
            <content kind="EM">alone</content>
            <content>, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> not a second; yea, he hath neither child nor brother: yet </content>
            <content kind="EM">is there</content>
            <content> no end of all his labour; neither is his eye satisfied with riches; neither </content>
            <content kind="EM">saith he</content>
            <content>, For whom do I labour, and bereave my soul of good? This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> also vanity, yea, it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a sore travail.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Two </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> better than one; because they have a good reward for their labour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow: but woe to him </content>
            <content kind="EM">that is</content>
            <content> alone when he falleth; for </content>
            <content kind="EM">he hath</content>
            <content> not another to help him up.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Again, if two lie together, then they have heat: but how can one be warm </content>
            <content kind="EM">alone</content>
            <content>?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And if one prevail against him, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Better </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a poor and a wise child than an old and foolish king, who will no more be admonished.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For out of prison he cometh to reign; whereas also </content>
            <content kind="EM">he that is</content>
            <content> born in his kingdom becometh poor.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>I considered all the living which walk under the sun, with the second child that shall stand up in his stead.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content kind="EM">There is</content>
            <content> no end of all the people, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> of all that have been before them: they also that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity and vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God, and be more ready to hear, than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they consider not that they do evil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be hasty to utter </content>
            <content kind="EM">any</content>
            <content> thing before God: for God </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be few.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>For a dream cometh through the multitude of business; and a fool's voice </content>
            <content kind="EM">is known</content>
            <content> by multitude of words.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for </content>
            <content kind="EM">he hath</content>
            <content> no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou hast vowed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Better </content>
            <content kind="EM">is it</content>
            <content> that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the angel, that it </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thine hands?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>For in the multitude of dreams and many words </content>
            <content kind="EM">there are</content>
            <content> also </content>
            <content kind="EM">divers</content>
            <content> vanities: but fear thou God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and violent perverting of judgment and justice in a province, marvel not at the matter: for </content>
            <content kind="EM">he that is</content>
            <content> higher than the highest regardeth; and </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> higher than they.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king </content>
            <content kind="EM">himself</content>
            <content> is served by the field.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance with increase: this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> also vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>When goods increase, they are increased that eat them: and what good </content>
            <content kind="EM">is there</content>
            <content> to the owners thereof, saving the beholding </content>
            <content kind="EM">of them</content>
            <content> with their eyes?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The sleep of a labouring man </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> sweet, whether he eat little or much: but the abundance of the rich will not suffer him to sleep.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>There is a sore evil </content>
            <content kind="EM">which</content>
            <content> I have seen under the sun, </content>
            <content kind="EM">namely</content>
            <content>, riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But those riches perish by evil travail: and he begetteth a son, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> nothing in his hand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>As he came forth of his mother's womb, naked shall he return to go as he came, and shall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away in his hand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>And this also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a sore evil, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> in all points as he came, so shall he go: and what profit hath he that hath laboured for the wind?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>All his days also he eateth in darkness, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">he hath</content>
            <content> much sorrow and wrath with his sickness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Behold </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> which I have seen: </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> good and comely </content>
            <content kind="EM">for one</content>
            <content> to eat and to drink, and to enjoy the good of all his labour that he taketh under the sun all the days of his life, which God giveth him: for it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> his portion.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labour; this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the gift of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content> in the joy of his heart.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> common among men:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A man to whom God hath given riches, wealth, and honour, so that he wanteth nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a stranger eateth it: this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity, and it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an evil disease.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If a man beget an hundred </content>
            <content kind="EM">children</content>
            <content>, and live many years, so that the days of his years be many, and his soul be not filled with good, and also </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> he have no burial; I say, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> an untimely birth </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> better than he.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For he cometh in with vanity, and departeth in darkness, and his name shall be covered with darkness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Moreover he hath not seen the sun, nor known </content>
            <content kind="EM">any thing</content>
            <content>: this hath more rest than the other.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Yea, though he live a thousand years twice </content>
            <content kind="EM">told</content>
            <content>, yet hath he seen no good: do not all go to one place?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>All the labour of man </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For what hath the wise more than the fool? what hath the poor, that knoweth to walk before the living?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Better </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the sight of the eyes than the wandering of the desire: this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> also vanity and vexation of spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>That which hath been is named already, and it is known that it </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> man: neither may he contend with him that is mightier than he.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Seeing there be many things that increase vanity, what </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> man the better?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For who knoweth what </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> good for man in </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> life, all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun?</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>A good name </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> better than precious ointment; and the day of death than the day of one's birth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content kind="EM">It is</content>
            <content> better to go to the house of mourning, than to go to the house of feasting: for that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the end of all men; and the living will lay </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> to his heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Sorrow </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> better than laughter: for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made better.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The heart of the wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in the house of mirth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content kind="EM">It is</content>
            <content> better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the laughter of the fool: this also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Surely oppression maketh a wise man mad; and a gift destroyeth the heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Better </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the end of a thing than the beginning thereof: </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> the patient in spirit </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> better than the proud in spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry: for anger resteth in the bosom of fools.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Say not thou, What is </content>
            <content kind="EM">the cause</content>
            <content> that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not enquire wisely concerning this.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> good with an inheritance: and </content>
            <content kind="EM">by it there is</content>
            <content> profit to them that see the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a defence, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> money </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a defence: but the excellency of knowledge </content>
            <content kind="EM">is, that</content>
            <content> wisdom giveth life to them that have it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Consider the work of God: for who can make </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> straight, which he hath made crooked?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>In the day of prosperity be joyful, but in the day of adversity consider: God also hath set the one over against the other, to the end that man should find nothing after him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>All </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> have I seen in the days of my vanity: there is a just </content>
            <content kind="EM">man</content>
            <content> that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked </content>
            <content kind="EM">man</content>
            <content> that prolongeth </content>
            <content kind="EM">his life</content>
            <content> in his wickedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Be not righteous over much; neither make thyself over wise: why shouldest thou destroy thyself?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Be not over much wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die before thy time?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content kind="EM">It is</content>
            <content> good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from this withdraw not thine hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth of them all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Wisdom strengtheneth the wise more than ten mighty </content>
            <content kind="EM">men</content>
            <content> which are in the city.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> not a just man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Also take no heed unto all words that are spoken; lest thou hear thy servant curse thee:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>For oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>All this have I proved by wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> far from me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>That which is far off, and exceeding deep, who can find it out?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>I applied mine heart to know, and to search, and to seek out wisdom, and the reason </content>
            <content kind="EM">of things</content>
            <content>, and to know the wickedness of folly, even of foolishness </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> madness:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And I find more bitter than death the woman, whose heart </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> snares and nets, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> her hands </content>
            <content kind="EM">as</content>
            <content> bands: whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Behold, this have I found, saith the preacher, </content>
            <content kind="EM">counting</content>
            <content> one by one, to find out the account:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Which yet my soul seeketh, but I find not: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Lo, this only have I found, that God hath made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Who </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> as the wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">man</content>
            <content>? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? a man's wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the boldness of his face shall be changed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I </content>
            <content kind="EM">counsel thee</content>
            <content> to keep the king's commandment, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> in regard of the oath of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Be not hasty to go out of his sight: stand not in an evil thing; for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Where the word of a king </content>
            <content kind="EM">is, there is</content>
            <content> power: and who may say unto him, What doest thou?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Whoso keepeth the commandment shall feel no evil thing: and a wise man's heart discerneth both time and judgment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Because to every purpose there is time and judgment, therefore the misery of man </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> great upon him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>For he knoweth not that which shall be: for who can tell him when it shall be?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content kind="EM">There is</content>
            <content> no man that hath power over the spirit to retain the spirit; neither </content>
            <content kind="EM">hath he</content>
            <content> power in the day of death: and </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> no discharge in </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> war; neither shall wickedness deliver those that are given to it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> a time wherein one man ruleth over another to his own hurt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And so I saw the wicked buried, who had come and gone from the place of the holy, and they were forgotten in the city where they had so done: this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> also vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Though a sinner do evil an hundred times, and his </content>
            <content kind="EM">days</content>
            <content> be prolonged, yet surely I know that it shall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>But it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> days, </content>
            <content kind="EM">which are</content>
            <content> as a shadow; because he feareth not before God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>There is a vanity which is done upon the earth; that there be just </content>
            <content kind="EM">men</content>
            <content>, unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there be wicked </content>
            <content kind="EM">men</content>
            <content>, to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be merry: for that shall abide with him of his labour the days of his life, which God giveth him under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>When I applied mine heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done upon the earth: (for also </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is that</content>
            <content> neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes:)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Then I beheld all the work of God, that a man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because though a man labour to seek </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> out, yet he shall not find </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>; yea further; though a wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">man</content>
            <content> think to know </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>, yet shall he not be able to find </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>For all this I considered in my heart even to declare all this, that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> in the hand of God: no man knoweth either love or hatred </content>
            <content kind="EM">by</content>
            <content> all </content>
            <content kind="EM">that is</content>
            <content> before them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>All </content>
            <content kind="EM">things come</content>
            <content> alike to all: </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> one event to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not: as </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the good, so </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the sinner; </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> he that sweareth, as </content>
            <content kind="EM">he</content>
            <content> that feareth an oath.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>This </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> an evil among all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> that are done under the sun, that </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> one event unto all: yea, also the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in their heart while they live, and after that </content>
            <content kind="EM">they go</content>
            <content> to the dead.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For to him that is joined to all the living there is hope: for a living dog is better than a dead lion.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not any thing, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Also their love, and their hatred, and their envy, is now perished; neither have they any more a portion for ever in any </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing</content>
            <content> that is done under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God now accepteth thy works.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Let thy garments be always white; and let thy head lack no ointment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of the life of thy vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all the days of thy vanity: for that </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> thy portion in </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> life, and in thy labour which thou takest under the sun.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> with thy might; for </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in the grave, whither thou goest.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare; so </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>This wisdom have I seen also under the sun, and it </content>
            <content kind="EM">seemed</content>
            <content> great unto me:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content kind="EM">There was</content>
            <content> a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Then said I, Wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> better than strength: nevertheless the poor man's wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> despised, and his words are not heard.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>The words of wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">men are</content>
            <content> heard in quiet more than the cry of him that ruleth among fools.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> better than weapons of war: but one sinner destroyeth much good.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Dead flies cause the ointment of the apothecary to send forth a stinking savour: </content>
            <content kind="EM">so doth</content>
            <content> a little folly him that is in reputation for wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> honour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A wise man's heart </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> at his right hand; but a fool's heart at his left.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Yea also, when he that is a fool walketh by the way, his wisdom faileth </content>
            <content kind="EM">him</content>
            <content>, and he saith to every one </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> he </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a fool.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for yielding pacifieth great offences.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>There is an evil </content>
            <content kind="EM">which</content>
            <content> I have seen under the sun, as an error </content>
            <content kind="EM">which</content>
            <content> proceedeth from the ruler:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Folly is set in great dignity, and the rich sit in low place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking as servants upon the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh an hedge, a serpent shall bite him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Whoso removeth stones shall be hurt therewith; </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> he that cleaveth wood shall be endangered thereby.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>If the iron be blunt, and he do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> profitable to direct.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Surely the serpent will bite without enchantment; and a babbler is no better.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The words of a wise man's mouth </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>The beginning of the words of his mouth </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> foolishness: and the end of his talk </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> mischievous madness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>A fool also is full of words: a man cannot tell what shall be; and what shall be after him, who can tell him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The labour of the foolish wearieth every one of them, because he knoweth not how to go to the city.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Woe to thee, O land, when thy king </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a child, and thy princes eat in the morning!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Blessed </content>
            <content kind="EM">art</content>
            <content> thou, O land, when thy king </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>By much slothfulness the building decayeth; and through idleness of the hands the house droppeth through.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh merry: but money answereth all </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content>.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Curse not the king, no not in thy thought; and curse not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the air shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Cast thy bread upon the waters: for thou shalt find it after many days.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Give a portion to seven, and also to eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If the clouds be full of rain, they empty </content>
            <content kind="EM">themselves</content>
            <content> upon the earth: and if the tree fall toward the south, or toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there it shall be.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>As thou knowest not what </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the way of the spirit, </content>
            <content kind="EM">nor</content>
            <content> how the bones </content>
            <content kind="EM">do grow</content>
            <content> in the womb of her that is with child: even so thou knowest not the works of God who maketh all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thine hand: for thou knowest not whether shall prosper, either this or that, or whether they both </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> alike good.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Truly the light </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> sweet, and a pleasant </content>
            <content kind="EM">thing it is</content>
            <content> for the eyes to behold the sun:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>But if a man live many years, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> rejoice in them all; yet let him remember the days of darkness; for they shall be many. All that cometh </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the sight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all these </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> God will bring thee into judgment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Therefore remove sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh: for childhood and youth </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>While the sun, or the light, or the moon, or the stars, be not darkened, nor the clouds return after the rain:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>In the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows be darkened,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>And the doors shall be shut in the streets, when the sound of the grinding is low, and he shall rise up at the voice of the bird, and all the daughters of musick shall be brought low;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Also </content>
            <content kind="EM">when</content>
            <content> they shall be afraid of </content>
            <content kind="EM">that which is</content>
            <content> high, and fears </content>
            <content kind="EM">shall be</content>
            <content> in the way, and the almond tree shall flourish, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail: because man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go about the streets:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Or ever the silver cord be loosed, or the golden bowl be broken, or the pitcher be broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Then shall the dust return to the earth as it was: and the spirit shall return unto God who gave it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Vanity of vanities, saith the preacher; all </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> vanity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And moreover, because the preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he gave good heed, and sought out, </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> set in order many proverbs.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The preacher sought to find out acceptable words: and </content>
            <content kind="EM">that which was</content>
            <content> written </content>
            <content kind="EM">was</content>
            <content> upright, </content>
            <content kind="EM">even</content>
            <content> words of truth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The words of the wise </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> as goads, and as nails fastened </content>
            <content kind="EM">by</content>
            <content> the masters of assemblies, </content>
            <content kind="EM">which</content>
            <content> are given from one shepherd.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And further, by these, my son, be admonished: of making many books </content>
            <content kind="EM">there is</content>
            <content> no end; and much study </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> a weariness of the flesh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Let us hear the conclusion of the whole matter: Fear God, and keep his commandments: for this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the whole </content>
            <content kind="EM">duty</content>
            <content> of man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For God shall bring every work into judgment, with every secret thing, whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> good, or whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> evil.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
</book>
