<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Paul and Timotheus, the servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus which are at Philippi, with the bishops and deacons:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Grace </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">from</content>
            <content> the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I thank my God upon every remembrance of you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Always in every prayer of mine for you all making request with joy,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For your fellowship in the gospel from the first day until now;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Being confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work in you will perform </content>
            <content kind="EM">it</content>
            <content> until the day of Jesus Christ:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Even as it is meet for me to think this of you all, because I have you in my heart; inasmuch as both in my bonds, and in the defence and confirmation of the gospel, ye all are partakers of my grace.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For God is my record, how greatly I long after you all in the bowels of Jesus Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in knowledge and </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
            <content> all judgment;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>That ye may approve things that are excellent; that ye may be sincere and without offence till the day of Christ;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Being filled with the fruits of righteousness, which are by Jesus Christ, unto the glory and praise of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But I would ye should understand, brethren, that the things </content>
            <content kind="EM">which happened</content>
            <content> unto me have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the gospel;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>So that my bonds in Christ are manifest in all the palace, and in all other </content>
            <content kind="EM">places</content>
            <content>;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And many of the brethren in the Lord, waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to speak the word without fear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Some indeed preach Christ even of envy and strife; and some also of good will:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>The one preach Christ of contention, not sincerely, supposing to add affliction to my bonds:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But the other of love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the gospel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>What then? notwithstanding, every way, whether in pretence, or in truth, Christ is preached; and I therein do rejoice, yea, and will rejoice.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>For I know that this shall turn to my salvation through your prayer, and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>According to my earnest expectation and </content>
            <content kind="EM">my</content>
            <content> hope, that in nothing I shall be ashamed, but </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> with all boldness, as always, </content>
            <content kind="EM">so</content>
            <content> now also Christ shall be magnified in my body, whether </content>
            <content kind="EM">it be</content>
            <content> by life, or by death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For to me to live </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> Christ, and to die </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> gain.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But if I live in the flesh, this </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> the fruit of my labour: yet what I shall choose I wot not.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>For I am in a strait betwixt two, having a desire to depart, and to be with Christ; which is far better:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Nevertheless to abide in the flesh </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> more needful for you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>And having this confidence, I know that I shall abide and continue with you all for your furtherance and joy of faith;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>That your rejoicing may be more abundant in Jesus Christ for me by my coming to you again.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Only let your conversation be as it becometh the gospel of Christ: that whether I come and see you, or else be absent, I may hear of your affairs, that ye stand fast in one spirit, with one mind striving together for the faith of the gospel;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And in nothing terrified by your adversaries: which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of salvation, and that of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>For unto you it is given in the behalf of Christ, not only to believe on him, but also to suffer for his sake;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Having the same conflict which ye saw in me, and now hear </content>
            <content kind="EM">to be</content>
            <content> in me.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>If </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> therefore any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be likeminded, having the same love, </content>
            <content kind="EM">being</content>
            <content> of one accord, of one mind.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content kind="EM">Let</content>
            <content> nothing </content>
            <content kind="EM">be done</content>
            <content> through strife or vainglory; but in lowliness of mind let each esteem other better than themselves.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Look not every man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Let this mind be in you, which was also in Christ Jesus:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Who, being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a servant, and was made in the likeness of men:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>And being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the cross.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Wherefore God also hath highly exalted him, and given him a name which is above every name:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>That at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> in heaven, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> in earth, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">things</content>
            <content> under the earth;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>And </content>
            <content kind="EM">that</content>
            <content> every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> Lord, to the glory of God the Father.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Wherefore, my beloved, as ye have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For it is God which worketh in you both to will and to do of </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content> good pleasure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Do all things without murmurings and disputings:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>That ye may be blameless and harmless, the sons of God, without rebuke, in the midst of a crooked and perverse nation, among whom ye shine as lights in the world;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Holding forth the word of life; that I may rejoice in the day of Christ, that I have not run in vain, neither laboured in vain.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Yea, and if I be offered upon the sacrifice and service of your faith, I joy, and rejoice with you all.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For the same cause also do ye joy, and rejoice with me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>But I trust in the Lord Jesus to send Timotheus shortly unto you, that I also may be of good comfort, when I know your state.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For I have no man likeminded, who will naturally care for your state.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For all seek their own, not the things which are Jesus Christ's.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But ye know the proof of him, that, as a son with the father, he hath served with me in the gospel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Him therefore I hope to send presently, so soon as I shall see how it will go with me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>But I trust in the Lord that I also myself shall come shortly.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Yet I supposed it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother, and companion in labour, and fellowsoldier, but your messenger, and he that ministered to my wants.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>For he longed after you all, and was full of heaviness, because that ye had heard that he had been sick.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>For indeed he was sick nigh unto death: but God had mercy on him; and not on him only, but on me also, lest I should have sorrow upon sorrow.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>I sent him therefore the more carefully, that, when ye see him again, ye may rejoice, and that I may be the less sorrowful.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Receive him therefore in the Lord with all gladness; and hold such in reputation:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Because for the work of Christ he was nigh unto death, not regarding his life, to supply your lack of service toward me.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write the same things to you, to me indeed </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> not grievous, but for you </content>
            <content kind="EM">it is</content>
            <content> safe.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Beware of dogs, beware of evil workers, beware of the concision.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>For we are the circumcision, which worship God in the spirit, and rejoice in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Though I might also have confidence in the flesh. If any other man thinketh that he hath whereof he might trust in the flesh, I more:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, </content>
            <content kind="EM">of</content>
            <content> the tribe of Benjamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrews; as touching the law, a Pharisee;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Concerning zeal, persecuting the church; touching the righteousness which is in the law, blameless.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But what things were gain to me, those I counted loss for Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Yea doubtless, and I count all things </content>
            <content kind="EM">but</content>
            <content> loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord: for whom I have suffered the loss of all things, and do count them </content>
            <content kind="EM">but</content>
            <content> dung, that I may win Christ,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And be found in him, not having mine own righteousness, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteousness which is of God by faith:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>That I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being made conformable unto his death;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>If by any means I might attain unto the resurrection of the dead.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Not as though I had already attained, either were already perfect: but I follow after, if that I may apprehend that for which also I am apprehended of Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Brethren, I count not myself to have apprehended: but </content>
            <content kind="EM">this</content>
            <content> one thing </content>
            <content kind="EM">I do</content>
            <content>, forgetting those things which are behind, and reaching forth unto those things which are before,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>I press toward the mark for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Let us therefore, as many as be perfect, be thus minded: and if in any thing ye be otherwise minded, God shall reveal even this unto you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Nevertheless, whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the same rule, let us mind the same thing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Brethren, be followers together of me, and mark them which walk so as ye have us for an ensample.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>(For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, </content>
            <content kind="EM">that they are</content>
            <content> the enemies of the cross of Christ:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Whose end </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> destruction, whose God </content>
            <content kind="EM">is their</content>
            <content> belly, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">whose</content>
            <content> glory </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> in their shame, who mind earthly things.)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For our conversation is in heaven; from whence also we look for the Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Who shall change our vile body, that it may be fashioned like unto his glorious body, according to the working whereby he is able even to subdue all things unto himself.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Therefore, my brethren dearly beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, </content>
            <content kind="EM">my</content>
            <content> dearly beloved.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I beseech Euodias, and beseech Syntyche, that they be of the same mind in the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And I intreat thee also, true yokefellow, help those women which laboured with me in the gospel, with Clement also, and </content>
            <content kind="EM">with</content>
            <content> other my fellowlabourers, whose names </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> in the book of life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Rejoice in the Lord alway: </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
            <content> again I say, Rejoice.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Let your moderation be known unto all men. The Lord </content>
            <content kind="EM">is</content>
            <content> at hand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Be careful for nothing; but in every thing by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving let your requests be made known unto God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding, shall keep your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> honest, whatsoever things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> just, whatsoever things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> pure, whatsoever things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> lovely, whatsoever things </content>
            <content kind="EM">are</content>
            <content> of good report; if </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> any virtue, and if </content>
            <content kind="EM">there be</content>
            <content> any praise, think on these things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Those things, which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me, do: and the God of peace shall be with you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly, that now at the last your care of me hath flourished again; wherein ye were also careful, but ye lacked opportunity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Not that I speak in respect of want: for I have learned, in whatsoever state I am, </content>
            <content kind="EM">therewith</content>
            <content> to be content.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>I know both how to be abased, and I know how to abound: every where and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>I can do all things through Christ which strengtheneth me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Notwithstanding ye have well done, that ye did communicate with my affliction.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Now ye Philippians know also, that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving, but ye only.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>For even in Thessalonica ye sent once and again unto my necessity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Not because I desire a gift: but I desire fruit that may abound to your account.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But I have all, and abound: I am full, having received of Epaphroditus the things </content>
            <content kind="EM">which were sent</content>
            <content> from you, an odour of a sweet smell, a sacrifice acceptable, wellpleasing to God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>But my God shall supply all your need according to his riches in glory by Christ Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Now unto God and our Father </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> glory for ever and ever. Amen.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren which are with me greet you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>All the saints salute you, chiefly they that are of Caesar's household.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ </content>
            <content kind="EM">be</content>
            <content> with you all. Amen.</content>
        </verse>
        <fragment>
            <content kind="EM">To the Philippians written from Rome, by Epaphroditus.</content>
        </fragment>
    </chapter>
</book>
