<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The word of the LORD came to Jonah son of Amittai:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Go to the great city of Nineveh and preach against it, because its wickedness has come up before me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>But Jonah ran away from the LORD and headed for Tarshish. He went down to Joppa, where he found a ship bound for that port. After paying the fare, he went aboard and sailed for Tarshish to flee from the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Then the LORD sent a great wind on the sea, and such a violent storm arose that the ship threatened to break up.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>All the sailors were afraid and each cried out to his own god. And they threw the cargo into the sea to lighten the ship. But Jonah had gone below deck, where he lay down and fell into a deep sleep.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The captain went to him and said, "How can you sleep? Get up and call on your god! Maybe he will take notice of us, and we will not perish."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Then the sailors said to each other, "Come, let us cast lots to find out who is responsible for this calamity." They cast lots and the lot fell on Jonah.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>So they asked him, "Tell us, who is responsible for making all this trouble for us? What do you do? Where do you come from? What is your country? From what people are you?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>He answered, "I am a Hebrew and I worship the LORD, the God of heaven, who made the sea and the land."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>This terrified them and they asked, "What have you done?" (They knew he was running away from the LORD, because he had already told them so.)</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The sea was getting rougher and rougher. So they asked him, "What should we do to you to make the sea calm down for us?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"Pick me up and throw me into the sea," he replied, "and it will become calm. I know that it is my fault that this great storm has come upon you."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Instead, the men did their best to row back to land. But they could not, for the sea grew even wilder than before.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Then they cried to the LORD, "O LORD, please do not let us die for taking this man's life. Do not hold us accountable for killing an innocent man, for you, O LORD, have done as you pleased."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Then they took Jonah and threw him overboard, and the raging sea grew calm.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>At this the men greatly feared the LORD, and they offered a sacrifice to the LORD and made vows to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But the LORD provided a great fish to swallow Jonah, and Jonah was inside the fish three days and three nights.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>From inside the fish Jonah prayed to the LORD his God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He said: "In my distress I called to the LORD, and he answered me. From the depths of the grave </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> I called for help, and you listened to my cry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>You hurled me into the deep, into the very heart of the seas, and the currents swirled about me; all your waves and breakers swept over me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>I said, `I have been banished from your sight; yet I will look again toward your holy temple.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The engulfing waters threatened me, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> the deep surrounded me; seaweed was wrapped around my head.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>To the roots of the mountains I sank down; the earth beneath barred me in forever. But you brought my life up from the pit, O LORD my God. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"When my life was ebbing away, I remembered you, LORD, and my prayer rose to you, to your holy temple. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Those who cling to worthless idols forfeit the grace that could be theirs.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>But I, with a song of thanksgiving, will sacrifice to you. What I have vowed I will make good. Salvation comes from the LORD."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>And the LORD commanded the fish, and it vomited Jonah onto dry land.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">waters were at my throat</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then the word of the LORD came to Jonah a second time:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Go to the great city of Nineveh and proclaim to it the message I give you."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Jonah obeyed the word of the LORD and went to Nineveh. Now Nineveh was a very important city--a visit required three days.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>On the first day, Jonah started into the city. He proclaimed: "Forty more days and Nineveh will be overturned."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The Ninevites believed God. They declared a fast, and all of them, from the greatest to the least, put on sackcloth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>When the news reached the king of Nineveh, he rose from his throne, took off his royal robes, covered himself with sackcloth and sat down in the dust.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Then he issued a proclamation in Nineveh: "By the decree of the king and his nobles: Do not let any man or beast, herd or flock, taste anything; do not let them eat or drink.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>But let man and beast be covered with sackcloth. Let everyone call urgently on God. Let them give up their evil ways and their violence.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Who knows? God may yet relent and with compassion turn from his fierce anger so that we will not perish." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>When God saw what they did and how they turned from their evil ways, he had compassion and did not bring upon them the destruction he had threatened.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>But Jonah was greatly displeased and became angry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He prayed to the LORD, "O LORD, is this not what I said when I was still at home? That is why I was so quick to flee to Tarshish. I knew that you are a gracious and compassionate God, slow to anger and abounding in love, a God who relents from sending calamity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Now, O LORD, take away my life, for it is better for me to die than to live."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>But the LORD replied, "Have you any right to be angry?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Jonah went out and sat down at a place east of the city. There he made himself a shelter, sat in its shade and waited to see what would happen to the city.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Then the LORD God provided a vine and made it grow up over Jonah to give shade for his head to ease his discomfort, and Jonah was very happy about the vine.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But at dawn the next day God provided a worm, which chewed the vine so that it withered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>When the sun rose, God provided a scorching east wind, and the sun blazed on Jonah's head so that he grew faint. He wanted to die, and said, "It would be better for me to die than to live."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>But God said to Jonah, "Do you have a right to be angry about the vine?" "I do," he said. "I am angry enough to die."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But the LORD said, "You have been concerned about this vine, though you did not tend it or make it grow. It sprang up overnight and died overnight.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>But Nineveh has more than a hundred and twenty thousand people who cannot tell their right hand from their left, and many cattle as well. Should I not be concerned about that great city?" </content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
</book>
