<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>A record of the genealogy of Jesus Christ the son of David, the son of Abraham: </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Abraham was the father of Isaac, Isaac the father of Jacob, Jacob the father of Judah and his brothers,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Judah the father of Perez and Zerah, whose mother was Tamar, Perez the father of Hezron, Hezron the father of Ram,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Ram the father of Amminadab, Amminadab the father of Nahshon, Nahshon the father of Salmon,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Salmon the father of Boaz, whose mother was Rahab, Boaz the father of Obed, whose mother was Ruth, Obed the father of Jesse,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>and Jesse the father of King David. David was the father of Solomon, whose mother had been Uriah's wife,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Solomon the father of Rehoboam, Rehoboam the father of Abijah, Abijah the father of Asa,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Asa the father of Jehoshaphat, Jehoshaphat the father of Jehoram, Jehoram the father of Uzziah,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Uzziah the father of Jotham, Jotham the father of Ahaz, Ahaz the father of Hezekiah,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Hezekiah the father of Manasseh, Manasseh the father of Amon, Amon the father of Josiah,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>and Josiah the father of Jeconiah </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and his brothers at the time of the exile to Babylon. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>After the exile to Babylon: Jeconiah was the father of Shealtiel, Shealtiel the father of Zerubbabel,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Zerubbabel the father of Abiud, Abiud the father of Eliakim, Eliakim the father of Azor,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Azor the father of Zadok, Zadok the father of Akim, Akim the father of Eliud,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Eliud the father of Eleazar, Eleazar the father of Matthan, Matthan the father of Jacob,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>and Jacob the father of Joseph, the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Thus there were fourteen generations in all from Abraham to David, fourteen from David to the exile to Babylon, and fourteen from the exile to the Christ. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>This is how the birth of Jesus Christ came about: His mother Mary was pledged to be married to Joseph, but before they came together, she was found to be with child through the Holy Spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Because Joseph her husband was a righteous man and did not want to expose her to public disgrace, he had in mind to divorce her quietly.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>But after he had considered this, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream and said, "Joseph son of David, do not be afraid to take Mary home as your wife, because what is conceived in her is from the Holy Spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>She will give birth to a son, and you are to give him the name Jesus, </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> because he will save his people from their sins."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>All this took place to fulfill what the Lord had said through the prophet:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"The virgin will be with child and will give birth to a son, and they will call him Immanuel" </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> --which means, "God with us."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>When Joseph woke up, he did what the angel of the Lord had commanded him and took Mary home as his wife.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>But he had no union with her until she gave birth to a son. And he gave him the name Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> That is, Jehoiachin; also in verse 12</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Messiah.</content>
            <content> "The Christ" (Greek) and "the Messiah" (Hebrew) both mean "the Anointed One."</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> </content>
            <content kind="EM">Jesus</content>
            <content> is the Greek form of </content>
            <content kind="EM">Joshua,</content>
            <content> which means </content>
            <content kind="EM">the LORD saves.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">23</content>
            <content> Isaiah 7:14</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>After Jesus was born in Bethlehem in Judea, during the time of King Herod, Magi </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> from the east came to Jerusalem</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>and asked, "Where is the one who has been born king of the Jews? We saw his star in the east </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> and have come to worship him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>When King Herod heard this he was disturbed, and all Jerusalem with him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>When he had called together all the people's chief priests and teachers of the law, he asked them where the Christ </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> was to be born.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"In Bethlehem in Judea," they replied, "for this is what the prophet has written:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"`But you, Bethlehem, in the land of Judah, are by no means least among the rulers of Judah; for out of you will come a ruler who will be the shepherd of my people Israel.' </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Then Herod called the Magi secretly and found out from them the exact time the star had appeared.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He sent them to Bethlehem and said, "Go and make a careful search for the child. As soon as you find him, report to me, so that I too may go and worship him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>After they had heard the king, they went on their way, and the star they had seen in the east </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> went ahead of them until it stopped over the place where the child was.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>When they saw the star, they were overjoyed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>On coming to the house, they saw the child with his mother Mary, and they bowed down and worshiped him. Then they opened their treasures and presented him with gifts of gold and of incense and of myrrh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>And having been warned in a dream not to go back to Herod, they returned to their country by another route.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>When they had gone, an angel of the Lord appeared to Joseph in a dream. "Get up," he said, "take the child and his mother and escape to Egypt. Stay there until I tell you, for Herod is going to search for the child to kill him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>So he got up, took the child and his mother during the night and left for Egypt,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>where he stayed until the death of Herod. And so was fulfilled what the Lord had said through the prophet: "Out of Egypt I called my son." </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>When Herod realized that he had been outwitted by the Magi, he was furious, and he gave orders to kill all the boys in Bethlehem and its vicinity who were two years old and under, in accordance with the time he had learned from the Magi.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Then what was said through the prophet Jeremiah was fulfilled:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"A voice is heard in Ramah, weeping and great mourning, Rachel weeping for her children and refusing to be comforted, because they are no more." </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>After Herod died, an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>and said, "Get up, take the child and his mother and go to the land of Israel, for those who were trying to take the child's life are dead."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>So he got up, took the child and his mother and went to the land of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But when he heard that Archelaus was reigning in Judea in place of his father Herod, he was afraid to go there. Having been warned in a dream, he withdrew to the district of Galilee,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>and he went and lived in a town called Nazareth. So was fulfilled what was said through the prophets: "He will be called a Nazarene."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Traditionally </content>
            <content kind="EM">Wise Men</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">star when it rose</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Messiah</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Micah 5:2</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">9</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">seen when it rose</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Hosea 11:1</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Jer. 31:15</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>In those days John the Baptist came, preaching in the Desert of Judea</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>and saying, "Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is near."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>This is he who was spoken of through the prophet Isaiah: "A voice of one calling in the desert, `Prepare the way for the Lord, make straight paths for him.'" </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>John's clothes were made of camel's hair, and he had a leather belt around his waist. His food was locusts and wild honey.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>People went out to him from Jerusalem and all Judea and the whole region of the Jordan.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Confessing their sins, they were baptized by him in the Jordan River.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But when he saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to where he was baptizing, he said to them: "You brood of vipers! Who warned you to flee from the coming wrath?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Produce fruit in keeping with repentance.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And do not think you can say to yourselves, `We have Abraham as our father.' I tell you that out of these stones God can raise up children for Abraham.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The ax is already at the root of the trees, and every tree that does not produce good fruit will be cut down and thrown into the fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"I baptize you with </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> water for repentance. But after me will come one who is more powerful than I, whose sandals I am not fit to carry. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and with fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>His winnowing fork is in his hand, and he will clear his threshing floor, gathering his wheat into the barn and burning up the chaff with unquenchable fire."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then Jesus came from Galilee to the Jordan to be baptized by John.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But John tried to deter him, saying, "I need to be baptized by you, and do you come to me?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Jesus replied, "Let it be so now; it is proper for us to do this to fulfill all righteousness." Then John consented.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>As soon as Jesus was baptized, he went up out of the water. At that moment heaven was opened, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove and lighting on him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And a voice from heaven said, "This is my Son, whom I love; with him I am well pleased."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">3</content>
            <content> Isaiah 40:3</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">in</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Jesus was led by the Spirit into the desert to be tempted by the devil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>After fasting forty days and forty nights, he was hungry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>The tempter came to him and said, "If you are the Son of God, tell these stones to become bread."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Jesus answered, "It is written: `Man does not live on bread alone, but on every word that comes from the mouth of God.' </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Then the devil took him to the holy city and had him stand on the highest point of the temple.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"If you are the Son of God," he said, "throw yourself down. For it is written: "`He will command his angels concerning you, and they will lift you up in their hands, so that you will not strike your foot against a stone.' </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Jesus answered him, "It is also written: `Do not put the Lord your God to the test.' </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Again, the devil took him to a very high mountain and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their splendor.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"All this I will give you," he said, "if you will bow down and worship me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Jesus said to him, "Away from me, Satan! For it is written: `Worship the Lord your God, and serve him only.' </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Then the devil left him, and angels came and attended him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>When Jesus heard that John had been put in prison, he returned to Galilee.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Leaving Nazareth, he went and lived in Capernaum, which was by the lake in the area of Zebulun and Naphtali--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>to fulfill what was said through the prophet Isaiah:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"Land of Zebulun and land of Naphtali, the way to the sea, along the Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>the people living in darkness have seen a great light; on those living in the land of the shadow of death a light has dawned." </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>From that time on Jesus began to preach, "Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is near."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>As Jesus was walking beside the Sea of Galilee, he saw two brothers, Simon called Peter and his brother Andrew. They were casting a net into the lake, for they were fishermen.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"Come, follow me," Jesus said, "and I will make you fishers of men."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>At once they left their nets and followed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Going on from there, he saw two other brothers, James son of Zebedee and his brother John. They were in a boat with their father Zebedee, preparing their nets. Jesus called them,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>and immediately they left the boat and their father and followed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Jesus went throughout Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, preaching the good news of the kingdom, and healing every disease and sickness among the people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>News about him spread all over Syria, and people brought to him all who were ill with various diseases, those suffering severe pain, the demon-possessed, those having seizures, and the paralyzed, and he healed them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Large crowds from Galilee, the Decapolis, </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> Jerusalem, Judea and the region across the Jordan followed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Deut. 8:3</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Psalm 91:11,12</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> Deut. 6:16</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> Deut. 6:13</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">16</content>
            <content> Isaiah 9:1,2</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">25</content>
            <content> That is, the Ten Cities</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Now when he saw the crowds, he went up on a mountainside and sat down. His disciples came to him,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>and he began to teach them, saying:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>"Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Blessed are those who mourn, for they will be comforted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Blessed are the meek, for they will inherit the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for righteousness, for they will be filled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Blessed are the merciful, for they will be shown mercy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Blessed are the pure in heart, for they will see God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Blessed are the peacemakers, for they will be called sons of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Blessed are those who are persecuted because of righteousness, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"Blessed are you when people insult you, persecute you and falsely say all kinds of evil against you because of me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Rejoice and be glad, because great is your reward in heaven, for in the same way they persecuted the prophets who were before you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"You are the salt of the earth. But if the salt loses its saltiness, how can it be made salty again? It is no longer good for anything, except to be thrown out and trampled by men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"You are the light of the world. A city on a hill cannot be hidden.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Neither do people light a lamp and put it under a bowl. Instead they put it on its stand, and it gives light to everyone in the house.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>In the same way, let your light shine before men, that they may see your good deeds and praise your Father in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Do not think that I have come to abolish the Law or the Prophets; I have not come to abolish them but to fulfill them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>I tell you the truth, until heaven and earth disappear, not the smallest letter, not the least stroke of a pen, will by any means disappear from the Law until everything is accomplished.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Anyone who breaks one of the least of these commandments and teaches others to do the same will be called least in the kingdom of heaven, but whoever practices and teaches these commands will be called great in the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For I tell you that unless your righteousness surpasses that of the Pharisees and the teachers of the law, you will certainly not enter the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"You have heard that it was said to the people long ago, `Do not murder, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and anyone who murders will be subject to judgment.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But I tell you that anyone who is angry with his brother </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> will be subject to judgment. Again, anyone who says to his brother, `Raca, </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> ' is answerable to the Sanhedrin. But anyone who says, `You fool!' will be in danger of the fire of hell.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"Therefore, if you are offering your gift at the altar and there remember that your brother has something against you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>leave your gift there in front of the altar. First go and be reconciled to your brother; then come and offer your gift.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>"Settle matters quickly with your adversary who is taking you to court. Do it while you are still with him on the way, or he may hand you over to the judge, and the judge may hand you over to the officer, and you may be thrown into prison.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>I tell you the truth, you will not get out until you have paid the last penny. </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"You have heard that it was said, `Do not commit adultery.' </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>But I tell you that anyone who looks at a woman lustfully has already committed adultery with her in his heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>If your right eye causes you to sin, gouge it out and throw it away. It is better for you to lose one part of your body than for your whole body to be thrown into hell.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And if your right hand causes you to sin, cut it off and throw it away. It is better for you to lose one part of your body than for your whole body to go into hell.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>"It has been said, `Anyone who divorces his wife must give her a certificate of divorce.' </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>But I tell you that anyone who divorces his wife, except for marital unfaithfulness, causes her to become an adulteress, and anyone who marries the divorced woman commits adultery.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>"Again, you have heard that it was said to the people long ago, `Do not break your oath, but keep the oaths you have made to the Lord.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>But I tell you, Do not swear at all: either by heaven, for it is God's throne;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>or by the earth, for it is his footstool; or by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the Great King.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>And do not swear by your head, for you cannot make even one hair white or black.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Simply let your `Yes' be `Yes,' and your `No,' `No'; anything beyond this comes from the evil one.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>"You have heard that it was said, `Eye for eye, and tooth for tooth.' </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>But I tell you, Do not resist an evil person. If someone strikes you on the right cheek, turn to him the other also.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>And if someone wants to sue you and take your tunic, let him have your cloak as well.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>If someone forces you to go one mile, go with him two miles.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>Give to the one who asks you, and do not turn away from the one who wants to borrow from you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>"You have heard that it was said, `Love your neighbor </content>
            <note_ref>8</note_ref>
            <content> and hate your enemy.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>But I tell you: Love your enemies </content>
            <note_ref>9</note_ref>
            <content> and pray for those who persecute you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>that you may be sons of your Father in heaven. He causes his sun to rise on the evil and the good, and sends rain on the righteous and the unrighteous.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>If you love those who love you, what reward will you get? Are not even the tax collectors doing that?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>And if you greet only your brothers, what are you doing more than others? Do not even pagans do that?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>Be perfect, therefore, as your heavenly Father is perfect.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Exodus 20:13</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">brother without cause</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> An Aramaic term of contempt</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">26</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">kodrantes</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">27</content>
            <content> Exodus 20:14</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">31</content>
            <content> Deut. 24:1</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">38</content>
            <content> Exodus 21:24; Lev. 24:20; Deut. 19:21</content>
        </note>
        <note num="8">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">43</content>
            <content> Lev. 19:18</content>
        </note>
        <note num="9">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">44</content>
            <content> Some late manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">enemies, bless those who curse you, do good to those who hate you</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Be careful not to do your `acts of righteousness' before men, to be seen by them. If you do, you will have no reward from your Father in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"So when you give to the needy, do not announce it with trumpets, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and on the streets, to be honored by men. I tell you the truth, they have received their reward in full.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>But when you give to the needy, do not let your left hand know what your right hand is doing,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>so that your giving may be in secret. Then your Father, who sees what is done in secret, will reward you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"And when you pray, do not be like the hypocrites, for they love to pray standing in the synagogues and on the street corners to be seen by men. I tell you the truth, they have received their reward in full.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>But when you pray, go into your room, close the door and pray to your Father, who is unseen. Then your Father, who sees what is done in secret, will reward you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And when you pray, do not keep on babbling like pagans, for they think they will be heard because of their many words.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Do not be like them, for your Father knows what you need before you ask him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"This, then, is how you should pray: "`Our Father in heaven, hallowed be your name,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Give us today our daily bread.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> '</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For if you forgive men when they sin against you, your heavenly Father will also forgive you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>But if you do not forgive men their sins, your Father will not forgive your sins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"When you fast, do not look somber as the hypocrites do, for they disfigure their faces to show men they are fasting. I tell you the truth, they have received their reward in full.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But when you fast, put oil on your head and wash your face,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>so that it will not be obvious to men that you are fasting, but only to your Father, who is unseen; and your Father, who sees what is done in secret, will reward you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"Do not store up for yourselves treasures on earth, where moth and rust destroy, and where thieves break in and steal.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>But store up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where moth and rust do not destroy, and where thieves do not break in and steal.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"The eye is the lamp of the body. If your eyes are good, your whole body will be full of light.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>But if your eyes are bad, your whole body will be full of darkness. If then the light within you is darkness, how great is that darkness!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"No one can serve two masters. Either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will be devoted to the one and despise the other. You cannot serve both God and Money.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>"Therefore I tell you, do not worry about your life, what you will eat or drink; or about your body, what you will wear. Is not life more important than food, and the body more important than clothes?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Look at the birds of the air; they do not sow or reap or store away in barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not much more valuable than they?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Who of you by worrying can add a single hour to his life </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"And why do you worry about clothes? See how the lilies of the field grow. They do not labor or spin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Yet I tell you that not even Solomon in all his splendor was dressed like one of these.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>If that is how God clothes the grass of the field, which is here today and tomorrow is thrown into the fire, will he not much more clothe you, O you of little faith?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>So do not worry, saying, `What shall we eat?' or `What shall we drink?' or `What shall we wear?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>For the pagans run after all these things, and your heavenly Father knows that you need them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>But seek first his kingdom and his righteousness, and all these things will be given to you as well.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Therefore do not worry about tomorrow, for tomorrow will worry about itself. Each day has enough trouble of its own.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">from evil</content>
            <content>; some late manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">one, for yours is the kingdom and the power and the glory forever. Amen.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">27</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">single cubit to his height</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Do not judge, or you too will be judged.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>For in the same way you judge others, you will be judged, and with the measure you use, it will be measured to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>"Why do you look at the speck of sawdust in your brother's eye and pay no attention to the plank in your own eye?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>How can you say to your brother, `Let me take the speck out of your eye,' when all the time there is a plank in your own eye?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>You hypocrite, first take the plank out of your own eye, and then you will see clearly to remove the speck from your brother's eye.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"Do not give dogs what is sacred; do not throw your pearls to pigs. If you do, they may trample them under their feet, and then turn and tear you to pieces.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Ask and it will be given to you; seek and you will find; knock and the door will be opened to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For everyone who asks receives; he who seeks finds; and to him who knocks, the door will be opened.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"Which of you, if his son asks for bread, will give him a stone?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Or if he asks for a fish, will give him a snake?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>If you, then, though you are evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father in heaven give good gifts to those who ask him!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>So in everything, do to others what you would have them do to you, for this sums up the Law and the Prophets.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"Enter through the narrow gate. For wide is the gate and broad is the road that leads to destruction, and many enter through it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But small is the gate and narrow the road that leads to life, and only a few find it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"Watch out for false prophets. They come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly they are ferocious wolves.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>By their fruit you will recognize them. Do people pick grapes from thornbushes, or figs from thistles?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Likewise every good tree bears good fruit, but a bad tree bears bad fruit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>A good tree cannot bear bad fruit, and a bad tree cannot bear good fruit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Every tree that does not bear good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Thus, by their fruit you will recognize them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Not everyone who says to me, `Lord, Lord,' will enter the kingdom of heaven, but only he who does the will of my Father who is in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Many will say to me on that day, `Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy in your name, and in your name drive out demons and perform many miracles?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Then I will tell them plainly, `I never knew you. Away from me, you evildoers!'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"Therefore everyone who hears these words of mine and puts them into practice is like a wise man who built his house on the rock.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The rain came down, the streams rose, and the winds blew and beat against that house; yet it did not fall, because it had its foundation on the rock.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>But everyone who hears these words of mine and does not put them into practice is like a foolish man who built his house on sand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The rain came down, the streams rose, and the winds blew and beat against that house, and it fell with a great crash." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>When Jesus had finished saying these things, the crowds were amazed at his teaching,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>because he taught as one who had authority, and not as their teachers of the law.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>When he came down from the mountainside, large crowds followed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>A man with leprosy </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> came and knelt before him and said, "Lord, if you are willing, you can make me clean."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Jesus reached out his hand and touched the man. "I am willing," he said. "Be clean!" Immediately he was cured </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> of his leprosy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Then Jesus said to him, "See that you don't tell anyone. But go, show yourself to the priest and offer the gift Moses commanded, as a testimony to them."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>When Jesus had entered Capernaum, a centurion came to him, asking for help.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"Lord," he said, "my servant lies at home paralyzed and in terrible suffering."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Jesus said to him, "I will go and heal him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The centurion replied, "Lord, I do not deserve to have you come under my roof. But just say the word, and my servant will be healed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For I myself am a man under authority, with soldiers under me. I tell this one, `Go,' and he goes; and that one, `Come,' and he comes. I say to my servant, `Do this,' and he does it."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>When Jesus heard this, he was astonished and said to those following him, "I tell you the truth, I have not found anyone in Israel with such great faith.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>I say to you that many will come from the east and the west, and will take their places at the feast with Abraham, Isaac and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But the subjects of the kingdom will be thrown outside, into the darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then Jesus said to the centurion, "Go! It will be done just as you believed it would." And his servant was healed at that very hour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>When Jesus came into Peter's house, he saw Peter's mother-in-law lying in bed with a fever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>He touched her hand and the fever left her, and she got up and began to wait on him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>When evening came, many who were demon-possessed were brought to him, and he drove out the spirits with a word and healed all the sick.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>This was to fulfill what was spoken through the prophet Isaiah: "He took up our infirmities and carried our diseases." </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>When Jesus saw the crowd around him, he gave orders to cross to the other side of the lake.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Then a teacher of the law came to him and said, "Teacher, I will follow you wherever you go."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Jesus replied, "Foxes have holes and birds of the air have nests, but the Son of Man has no place to lay his head."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Another disciple said to him, "Lord, first let me go and bury my father."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But Jesus told him, "Follow me, and let the dead bury their own dead."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Then he got into the boat and his disciples followed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Without warning, a furious storm came up on the lake, so that the waves swept over the boat. But Jesus was sleeping.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The disciples went and woke him, saying, "Lord, save us! We're going to drown!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>He replied, "You of little faith, why are you so afraid?" Then he got up and rebuked the winds and the waves, and it was completely calm.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The men were amazed and asked, "What kind of man is this? Even the winds and the waves obey him!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>When he arrived at the other side in the region of the Gadarenes, </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> two demon-possessed men coming from the tombs met him. They were so violent that no one could pass that way.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"What do you want with us, Son of God?" they shouted. "Have you come here to torture us before the appointed time?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Some distance from them a large herd of pigs was feeding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>The demons begged Jesus, "If you drive us out, send us into the herd of pigs."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>He said to them, "Go!" So they came out and went into the pigs, and the whole herd rushed down the steep bank into the lake and died in the water.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Those tending the pigs ran off, went into the town and reported all this, including what had happened to the demon-possessed men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Then the whole town went out to meet Jesus. And when they saw him, they pleaded with him to leave their region.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> The Greek word was used for various diseases affecting the skin--not necessarily leprosy.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">3</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">made clean</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Isaiah 53:4</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">28</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">Gergesenes</content>
            <content>; others </content>
            <content kind="EM">Gerasenes</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Jesus stepped into a boat, crossed over and came to his own town.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Some men brought to him a paralytic, lying on a mat. When Jesus saw their faith, he said to the paralytic, "Take heart, son; your sins are forgiven."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>At this, some of the teachers of the law said to themselves, "This fellow is blaspheming!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Knowing their thoughts, Jesus said, "Why do you entertain evil thoughts in your hearts?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Which is easier: to say, `Your sins are forgiven,' or to say, `Get up and walk'?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>But so that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins...." Then he said to the paralytic, "Get up, take your mat and go home."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>And the man got up and went home.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>When the crowd saw this, they were filled with awe; and they praised God, who had given such authority to men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>As Jesus went on from there, he saw a man named Matthew sitting at the tax collector's booth. "Follow me," he told him, and Matthew got up and followed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>While Jesus was having dinner at Matthew's house, many tax collectors and "sinners" came and ate with him and his disciples.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>When the Pharisees saw this, they asked his disciples, "Why does your teacher eat with tax collectors and `sinners'?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>On hearing this, Jesus said, "It is not the healthy who need a doctor, but the sick.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>But go and learn what this means: `I desire mercy, not sacrifice.' </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> For I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Then John's disciples came and asked him, "How is it that we and the Pharisees fast, but your disciples do not fast?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Jesus answered, "How can the guests of the bridegroom mourn while he is with them? The time will come when the bridegroom will be taken from them; then they will fast.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"No one sews a patch of unshrunk cloth on an old garment, for the patch will pull away from the garment, making the tear worse.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Neither do men pour new wine into old wineskins. If they do, the skins will burst, the wine will run out and the wineskins will be ruined. No, they pour new wine into new wineskins, and both are preserved."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>While he was saying this, a ruler came and knelt before him and said, "My daughter has just died. But come and put your hand on her, and she will live."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Jesus got up and went with him, and so did his disciples.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Just then a woman who had been subject to bleeding for twelve years came up behind him and touched the edge of his cloak.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>She said to herself, "If I only touch his cloak, I will be healed."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Jesus turned and saw her. "Take heart, daughter," he said, "your faith has healed you." And the woman was healed from that moment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>When Jesus entered the ruler's house and saw the flute players and the noisy crowd,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>he said, "Go away. The girl is not dead but asleep." But they laughed at him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>After the crowd had been put outside, he went in and took the girl by the hand, and she got up.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>News of this spread through all that region.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>As Jesus went on from there, two blind men followed him, calling out, "Have mercy on us, Son of David!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>When he had gone indoors, the blind men came to him, and he asked them, "Do you believe that I am able to do this?" "Yes, Lord," they replied.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Then he touched their eyes and said, "According to your faith will it be done to you";</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>and their sight was restored. Jesus warned them sternly, "See that no one knows about this."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>But they went out and spread the news about him all over that region.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>While they were going out, a man who was demon-possessed and could not talk was brought to Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>And when the demon was driven out, the man who had been mute spoke. The crowd was amazed and said, "Nothing like this has ever been seen in Israel."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>But the Pharisees said, "It is by the prince of demons that he drives out demons."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>Jesus went through all the towns and villages, teaching in their synagogues, preaching the good news of the kingdom and healing every disease and sickness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>When he saw the crowds, he had compassion on them, because they were harassed and helpless, like sheep without a shepherd.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Then he said to his disciples, "The harvest is plentiful but the workers are few.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Ask the Lord of the harvest, therefore, to send out workers into his harvest field."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Hosea 6:6</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>He called his twelve disciples to him and gave them authority to drive out evil </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> spirits and to heal every disease and sickness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>These are the names of the twelve apostles: first, Simon (who is called Peter) and his brother Andrew; James son of Zebedee, and his brother John;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Philip and Bartholomew; Thomas and Matthew the tax collector; James son of Alphaeus, and Thaddaeus;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Simon the Zealot and Judas Iscariot, who betrayed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>These twelve Jesus sent out with the following instructions: "Do not go among the Gentiles or enter any town of the Samaritans.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Go rather to the lost sheep of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>As you go, preach this message: `The kingdom of heaven is near.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Heal the sick, raise the dead, cleanse those who have leprosy, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> drive out demons. Freely you have received, freely give.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Do not take along any gold or silver or copper in your belts;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>take no bag for the journey, or extra tunic, or sandals or a staff; for the worker is worth his keep.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"Whatever town or village you enter, search for some worthy person there and stay at his house until you leave.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>As you enter the home, give it your greeting.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>If the home is deserving, let your peace rest on it; if it is not, let your peace return to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>If anyone will not welcome you or listen to your words, shake the dust off your feet when you leave that home or town.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>I tell you the truth, it will be more bearable for Sodom and Gomorrah on the day of judgment than for that town.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I am sending you out like sheep among wolves. Therefore be as shrewd as snakes and as innocent as doves.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Be on your guard against men; they will hand you over to the local councils and flog you in their synagogues.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>On my account you will be brought before governors and kings as witnesses to them and to the Gentiles.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>But when they arrest you, do not worry about what to say or how to say it. At that time you will be given what to say,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>for it will not be you speaking, but the Spirit of your Father speaking through you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Brother will betray brother to death, and a father his child; children will rebel against their parents and have them put to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>All men will hate you because of me, but he who stands firm to the end will be saved.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>When you are persecuted in one place, flee to another. I tell you the truth, you will not finish going through the cities of Israel before the Son of Man comes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"A student is not above his teacher, nor a servant above his master.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>It is enough for the student to be like his teacher, and the servant like his master. If the head of the house has been called Beelzebub, </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> how much more the members of his household!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>"So do not be afraid of them. There is nothing concealed that will not be disclosed, or hidden that will not be made known.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>What I tell you in the dark, speak in the daylight; what is whispered in your ear, proclaim from the roofs.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Do not be afraid of those who kill the body but cannot kill the soul. Rather, be afraid of the One who can destroy both soul and body in hell.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Are not two sparrows sold for a penny </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> ? Yet not one of them will fall to the ground apart from the will of your Father.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And even the very hairs of your head are all numbered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>So don't be afraid; you are worth more than many sparrows.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>"Whoever acknowledges me before men, I will also acknowledge him before my Father in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>But whoever disowns me before men, I will disown him before my Father in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>"Do not suppose that I have come to bring peace to the earth. I did not come to bring peace, but a sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>For I have come to turn "`a man against his father, a daughter against her mother, a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>a man's enemies will be the members of his own household.' </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>"Anyone who loves his father or mother more than me is not worthy of me; anyone who loves his son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>and anyone who does not take his cross and follow me is not worthy of me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>Whoever finds his life will lose it, and whoever loses his life for my sake will find it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>"He who receives you receives me, and he who receives me receives the one who sent me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>Anyone who receives a prophet because he is a prophet will receive a prophet's reward, and anyone who receives a righteous man because he is a righteous man will receive a righteous man's reward.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>And if anyone gives even a cup of cold water to one of these little ones because he is my disciple, I tell you the truth, he will certainly not lose his reward."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">unclean</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">8</content>
            <content> The Greek word was used for various diseases affecting the skin--not necessarily leprosy.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">25</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">Beezeboul</content>
            <content> or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Beelzeboul</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">29</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">an assarion</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">36</content>
            <content> Micah 7:6</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>After Jesus had finished instructing his twelve disciples, he went on from there to teach and preach in the towns of Galilee. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>When John heard in prison what Christ was doing, he sent his disciples</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>to ask him, "Are you the one who was to come, or should we expect someone else?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Jesus replied, "Go back and report to John what you hear and see:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The blind receive sight, the lame walk, those who have leprosy </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> are cured, the deaf hear, the dead are raised, and the good news is preached to the poor.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Blessed is the man who does not fall away on account of me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>As John's disciples were leaving, Jesus began to speak to the crowd about John: "What did you go out into the desert to see? A reed swayed by the wind?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>If not, what did you go out to see? A man dressed in fine clothes? No, those who wear fine clothes are in kings' palaces.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Then what did you go out to see? A prophet? Yes, I tell you, and more than a prophet.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>This is the one about whom it is written: "`I will send my messenger ahead of you, who will prepare your way before you.' </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>I tell you the truth: Among those born of women there has not risen anyone greater than John the Baptist; yet he who is least in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>From the days of John the Baptist until now, the kingdom of heaven has been forcefully advancing, and forceful men lay hold of it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For all the Prophets and the Law prophesied until John.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And if you are willing to accept it, he is the Elijah who was to come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>He who has ears, let him hear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"To what can I compare this generation? They are like children sitting in the marketplaces and calling out to others:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"`We played the flute for you, and you did not dance; we sang a dirge, and you did not mourn.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, `He has a demon.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>The Son of Man came eating and drinking, and they say, `Here is a glutton and a drunkard, a friend of tax collectors and "sinners."' But wisdom is proved right by her actions."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Then Jesus began to denounce the cities in which most of his miracles had been performed, because they did not repent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Woe to you, Korazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! If the miracles that were performed in you had been performed in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But I tell you, it will be more bearable for Tyre and Sidon on the day of judgment than for you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>And you, Capernaum, will you be lifted up to the skies? No, you will go down to the depths. </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> If the miracles that were performed in you had been performed in Sodom, it would have remained to this day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>But I tell you that it will be more bearable for Sodom on the day of judgment than for you."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>At that time Jesus said, "I praise you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have hidden these things from the wise and learned, and revealed them to little children.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Yes, Father, for this was your good pleasure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"All things have been committed to me by my Father. No one knows the Son except the Father, and no one knows the Father except the Son and those to whom the Son chooses to reveal him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"Come to me, all you who are weary and burdened, and I will give you rest.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Take my yoke upon you and learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart, and you will find rest for your souls.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>For my yoke is easy and my burden is light."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">in their towns</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> The Greek word was used for various diseases affecting the skin--not necessarily leprosy.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> Mal. 3:1</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">23</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">Hades</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>At that time Jesus went through the grainfields on the Sabbath. His disciples were hungry and began to pick some heads of grain and eat them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>When the Pharisees saw this, they said to him, "Look! Your disciples are doing what is unlawful on the Sabbath."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>He answered, "Haven't you read what David did when he and his companions were hungry?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>He entered the house of God, and he and his companions ate the consecrated bread--which was not lawful for them to do, but only for the priests.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Or haven't you read in the Law that on the Sabbath the priests in the temple desecrate the day and yet are innocent?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>I tell you that one </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> greater than the temple is here.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>If you had known what these words mean, `I desire mercy, not sacrifice,' </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> you would not have condemned the innocent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Going on from that place, he went into their synagogue,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>and a man with a shriveled hand was there. Looking for a reason to accuse Jesus, they asked him, "Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He said to them, "If any of you has a sheep and it falls into a pit on the Sabbath, will you not take hold of it and lift it out?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>How much more valuable is a man than a sheep! Therefore it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then he said to the man, "Stretch out your hand." So he stretched it out and it was completely restored, just as sound as the other.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But the Pharisees went out and plotted how they might kill Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Aware of this, Jesus withdrew from that place. Many followed him, and he healed all their sick,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>warning them not to tell who he was.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>This was to fulfill what was spoken through the prophet Isaiah:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"Here is my servant whom I have chosen, the one I love, in whom I delight; I will put my Spirit on him, and he will proclaim justice to the nations.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He will not quarrel or cry out; no one will hear his voice in the streets.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>A bruised reed he will not break, and a smoldering wick he will not snuff out, till he leads justice to victory.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>In his name the nations will put their hope." </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Then they brought him a demon-possessed man who was blind and mute, and Jesus healed him, so that he could both talk and see.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>All the people were astonished and said, "Could this be the Son of David?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>But when the Pharisees heard this, they said, "It is only by Beelzebub, </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> the prince of demons, that this fellow drives out demons."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Jesus knew their thoughts and said to them, "Every kingdom divided against itself will be ruined, and every city or household divided against itself will not stand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>If Satan drives out Satan, he is divided against himself. How then can his kingdom stand?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>And if I drive out demons by Beelzebub, by whom do your people drive them out? So then, they will be your judges.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>But if I drive out demons by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God has come upon you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"Or again, how can anyone enter a strong man's house and carry off his possessions unless he first ties up the strong man? Then he can rob his house.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>"He who is not with me is against me, and he who does not gather with me scatters.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And so I tell you, every sin and blasphemy will be forgiven men, but the blasphemy against the Spirit will not be forgiven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Anyone who speaks a word against the Son of Man will be forgiven, but anyone who speaks against the Holy Spirit will not be forgiven, either in this age or in the age to come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>"Make a tree good and its fruit will be good, or make a tree bad and its fruit will be bad, for a tree is recognized by its fruit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>You brood of vipers, how can you who are evil say anything good? For out of the overflow of the heart the mouth speaks.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>The good man brings good things out of the good stored up in him, and the evil man brings evil things out of the evil stored up in him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>But I tell you that men will have to give account on the day of judgment for every careless word they have spoken.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>For by your words you will be acquitted, and by your words you will be condemned."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Then some of the Pharisees and teachers of the law said to him, "Teacher, we want to see a miraculous sign from you."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>He answered, "A wicked and adulterous generation asks for a miraculous sign! But none will be given it except the sign of the prophet Jonah.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>For as Jonah was three days and three nights in the belly of a huge fish, so the Son of Man will be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>The men of Nineveh will stand up at the judgment with this generation and condemn it; for they repented at the preaching of Jonah, and now one </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> greater than Jonah is here.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>The Queen of the South will rise at the judgment with this generation and condemn it; for she came from the ends of the earth to listen to Solomon's wisdom, and now one greater than Solomon is here.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>"When an evil </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> spirit comes out of a man, it goes through arid places seeking rest and does not find it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>Then it says, `I will return to the house I left.' When it arrives, it finds the house unoccupied, swept clean and put in order.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>Then it goes and takes with it seven other spirits more wicked than itself, and they go in and live there. And the final condition of that man is worse than the first. That is how it will be with this wicked generation."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>While Jesus was still talking to the crowd, his mother and brothers stood outside, wanting to speak to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>Someone told him, "Your mother and brothers are standing outside, wanting to speak to you." </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>He replied to him, "Who is my mother, and who are my brothers?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>Pointing to his disciples, he said, "Here are my mother and my brothers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>For whoever does the will of my Father in heaven is my brother and sister and mother."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">something</content>
            <content>; also in verses 41 and 42</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> Hosea 6:6</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Isaiah 42:1-4</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">Beezeboul</content>
            <content> or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Beelzeboul</content>
            <content>; also in verse 27</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">41</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">something</content>
            <content>; also in verse 42</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">43</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">unclean</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">47</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts do not have verse 47.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>That same day Jesus went out of the house and sat by the lake.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Such large crowds gathered around him that he got into a boat and sat in it, while all the people stood on the shore.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Then he told them many things in parables, saying: "A farmer went out to sow his seed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>As he was scattering the seed, some fell along the path, and the birds came and ate it up.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Some fell on rocky places, where it did not have much soil. It sprang up quickly, because the soil was shallow.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>But when the sun came up, the plants were scorched, and they withered because they had no root.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Other seed fell among thorns, which grew up and choked the plants.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Still other seed fell on good soil, where it produced a crop--a hundred, sixty or thirty times what was sown.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>He who has ears, let him hear."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The disciples came to him and asked, "Why do you speak to the people in parables?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He replied, "The knowledge of the secrets of the kingdom of heaven has been given to you, but not to them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Whoever has will be given more, and he will have an abundance. Whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken from him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>This is why I speak to them in parables: "Though seeing, they do not see; though hearing, they do not hear or understand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>In them is fulfilled the prophecy of Isaiah: "`You will be ever hearing but never understanding; you will be ever seeing but never perceiving.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>For this people's heart has become calloused; they hardly hear with their ears, and they have closed their eyes. Otherwise they might see with their eyes, hear with their ears, understand with their hearts and turn, and I would heal them.' </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But blessed are your eyes because they see, and your ears because they hear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>For I tell you the truth, many prophets and righteous men longed to see what you see but did not see it, and to hear what you hear but did not hear it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"Listen then to what the parable of the sower means:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>When anyone hears the message about the kingdom and does not understand it, the evil one comes and snatches away what was sown in his heart. This is the seed sown along the path.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>The one who received the seed that fell on rocky places is the man who hears the word and at once receives it with joy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>But since he has no root, he lasts only a short time. When trouble or persecution comes because of the word, he quickly falls away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>The one who received the seed that fell among the thorns is the man who hears the word, but the worries of this life and the deceitfulness of wealth choke it, making it unfruitful.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>But the one who received the seed that fell on good soil is the man who hears the word and understands it. He produces a crop, yielding a hundred, sixty or thirty times what was sown."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Jesus told them another parable: "The kingdom of heaven is like a man who sowed good seed in his field.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>But while everyone was sleeping, his enemy came and sowed weeds among the wheat, and went away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>When the wheat sprouted and formed heads, then the weeds also appeared.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"The owner's servants came to him and said, `Sir, didn't you sow good seed in your field? Where then did the weeds come from?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"`An enemy did this,' he replied. "The servants asked him, `Do you want us to go and pull them up?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"`No,' he answered, `because while you are pulling the weeds, you may root up the wheat with them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Let both grow together until the harvest. At that time I will tell the harvesters: First collect the weeds and tie them in bundles to be burned; then gather the wheat and bring it into my barn.'"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>He told them another parable: "The kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed, which a man took and planted in his field.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Though it is the smallest of all your seeds, yet when it grows, it is the largest of garden plants and becomes a tree, so that the birds of the air come and perch in its branches."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>He told them still another parable: "The kingdom of heaven is like yeast that a woman took and mixed into a large amount </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> of flour until it worked all through the dough."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Jesus spoke all these things to the crowd in parables; he did not say anything to them without using a parable.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>So was fulfilled what was spoken through the prophet: "I will open my mouth in parables, I will utter things hidden since the creation of the world." </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Then he left the crowd and went into the house. His disciples came to him and said, "Explain to us the parable of the weeds in the field."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>He answered, "The one who sowed the good seed is the Son of Man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>The field is the world, and the good seed stands for the sons of the kingdom. The weeds are the sons of the evil one,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>and the enemy who sows them is the devil. The harvest is the end of the age, and the harvesters are angels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>"As the weeds are pulled up and burned in the fire, so it will be at the end of the age.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>The Son of Man will send out his angels, and they will weed out of his kingdom everything that causes sin and all who do evil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>They will throw them into the fiery furnace, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father. He who has ears, let him hear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>"The kingdom of heaven is like treasure hidden in a field. When a man found it, he hid it again, and then in his joy went and sold all he had and bought that field.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>"Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a merchant looking for fine pearls.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>When he found one of great value, he went away and sold everything he had and bought it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>"Once again, the kingdom of heaven is like a net that was let down into the lake and caught all kinds of fish.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>When it was full, the fishermen pulled it up on the shore. Then they sat down and collected the good fish in baskets, but threw the bad away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>This is how it will be at the end of the age. The angels will come and separate the wicked from the righteous</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>and throw them into the fiery furnace, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
            <content>"Have you understood all these things?" Jesus asked. "Yes," they replied.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
            <content>He said to them, "Therefore every teacher of the law who has been instructed about the kingdom of heaven is like the owner of a house who brings out of his storeroom new treasures as well as old."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
            <content>When Jesus had finished these parables, he moved on from there.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
            <content>Coming to his hometown, he began teaching the people in their synagogue, and they were amazed. "Where did this man get this wisdom and these miraculous powers?" they asked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
            <content>"Isn't this the carpenter's son? Isn't his mother's name Mary, and aren't his brothers James, Joseph, Simon and Judas?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
            <content>Aren't all his sisters with us? Where then did this man get all these things?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
            <content>And they took offense at him. But Jesus said to them, "Only in his hometown and in his own house is a prophet without honor."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="58">
            <content>And he did not do many miracles there because of their lack of faith.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Isaiah 6:9,10</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">three satas</content>
            <content> (probably about 1/2 bushel or 22 liters)</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">35</content>
            <content> Psalm 78:2</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>At that time Herod the tetrarch heard the reports about Jesus,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>and he said to his attendants, "This is John the Baptist; he has risen from the dead! That is why miraculous powers are at work in him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Now Herod had arrested John and bound him and put him in prison because of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>for John had been saying to him: "It is not lawful for you to have her."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Herod wanted to kill John, but he was afraid of the people, because they considered him a prophet.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>On Herod's birthday the daughter of Herodias danced for them and pleased Herod so much</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>that he promised with an oath to give her whatever she asked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Prompted by her mother, she said, "Give me here on a platter the head of John the Baptist."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The king was distressed, but because of his oaths and his dinner guests, he ordered that her request be granted</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>and had John beheaded in the prison.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>His head was brought in on a platter and given to the girl, who carried it to her mother.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>John's disciples came and took his body and buried it. Then they went and told Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>When Jesus heard what had happened, he withdrew by boat privately to a solitary place. Hearing of this, the crowds followed him on foot from the towns.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>When Jesus landed and saw a large crowd, he had compassion on them and healed their sick.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>As evening approached, the disciples came to him and said, "This is a remote place, and it's already getting late. Send the crowds away, so they can go to the villages and buy themselves some food."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Jesus replied, "They do not need to go away. You give them something to eat."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"We have here only five loaves of bread and two fish," they answered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"Bring them here to me," he said.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>And he directed the people to sit down on the grass. Taking the five loaves and the two fish and looking up to heaven, he gave thanks and broke the loaves. Then he gave them to the disciples, and the disciples gave them to the people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>They all ate and were satisfied, and the disciples picked up twelve basketfuls of broken pieces that were left over.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>The number of those who ate was about five thousand men, besides women and children.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Immediately Jesus made the disciples get into the boat and go on ahead of him to the other side, while he dismissed the crowd.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>After he had dismissed them, he went up on a mountainside by himself to pray. When evening came, he was there alone,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>but the boat was already a considerable distance </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> from land, buffeted by the waves because the wind was against it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>During the fourth watch of the night Jesus went out to them, walking on the lake.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>When the disciples saw him walking on the lake, they were terrified. "It's a ghost," they said, and cried out in fear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>But Jesus immediately said to them: "Take courage! It is I. Don't be afraid."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"Lord, if it's you," Peter replied, "tell me to come to you on the water."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"Come," he said. Then Peter got down out of the boat, walked on the water and came toward Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>But when he saw the wind, he was afraid and, beginning to sink, cried out, "Lord, save me!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Immediately Jesus reached out his hand and caught him. "You of little faith," he said, "why did you doubt?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>And when they climbed into the boat, the wind died down.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Then those who were in the boat worshiped him, saying, "Truly you are the Son of God."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>When they had crossed over, they landed at Gennesaret.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>And when the men of that place recognized Jesus, they sent word to all the surrounding country. People brought all their sick to him</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>and begged him to let the sick just touch the edge of his cloak, and all who touched him were healed.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">many stadia</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="15">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then some Pharisees and teachers of the law came to Jesus from Jerusalem and asked,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Why do your disciples break the tradition of the elders? They don't wash their hands before they eat!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Jesus replied, "And why do you break the command of God for the sake of your tradition?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>For God said, `Honor your father and mother' </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and `Anyone who curses his father or mother must be put to death.' </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But you say that if a man says to his father or mother, `Whatever help you might otherwise have received from me is a gift devoted to God,'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>he is not to `honor his father </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> ' with it. Thus you nullify the word of God for the sake of your tradition.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>You hypocrites! Isaiah was right when he prophesied about you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"`These people honor me with their lips, but their hearts are far from me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>They worship me in vain; their teachings are but rules taught by men.' </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Jesus called the crowd to him and said, "Listen and understand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>What goes into a man's mouth does not make him `unclean,' but what comes out of his mouth, that is what makes him `unclean.'"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Then the disciples came to him and asked, "Do you know that the Pharisees were offended when they heard this?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>He replied, "Every plant that my heavenly Father has not planted will be pulled up by the roots.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Leave them; they are blind guides. </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> If a blind man leads a blind man, both will fall into a pit."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Peter said, "Explain the parable to us."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"Are you still so dull?" Jesus asked them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Don't you see that whatever enters the mouth goes into the stomach and then out of the body?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But the things that come out of the mouth come from the heart, and these make a man `unclean.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>For out of the heart come evil thoughts, murder, adultery, sexual immorality, theft, false testimony, slander.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>These are what make a man `unclean'; but eating with unwashed hands does not make him `unclean.'"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Leaving that place, Jesus withdrew to the region of Tyre and Sidon.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>A Canaanite woman from that vicinity came to him, crying out, "Lord, Son of David, have mercy on me! My daughter is suffering terribly from demon-possession."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Jesus did not answer a word. So his disciples came to him and urged him, "Send her away, for she keeps crying out after us."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>He answered, "I was sent only to the lost sheep of Israel."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The woman came and knelt before him. "Lord, help me!" she said.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>He replied, "It is not right to take the children's bread and toss it to their dogs."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"Yes, Lord," she said, "but even the dogs eat the crumbs that fall from their masters' table."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Then Jesus answered, "Woman, you have great faith! Your request is granted." And her daughter was healed from that very hour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Jesus left there and went along the Sea of Galilee. Then he went up on a mountainside and sat down.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Great crowds came to him, bringing the lame, the blind, the crippled, the mute and many others, and laid them at his feet; and he healed them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>The people were amazed when they saw the mute speaking, the crippled made well, the lame walking and the blind seeing. And they praised the God of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Jesus called his disciples to him and said, "I have compassion for these people; they have already been with me three days and have nothing to eat. I do not want to send them away hungry, or they may collapse on the way."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>His disciples answered, "Where could we get enough bread in this remote place to feed such a crowd?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>"How many loaves do you have?" Jesus asked. "Seven," they replied, "and a few small fish."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>He told the crowd to sit down on the ground.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Then he took the seven loaves and the fish, and when he had given thanks, he broke them and gave them to the disciples, and they in turn to the people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>They all ate and were satisfied. Afterward the disciples picked up seven basketfuls of broken pieces that were left over.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>The number of those who ate was four thousand, besides women and children.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>After Jesus had sent the crowd away, he got into the boat and went to the vicinity of Magadan.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Exodus 20:12; Deut. 5:16</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Exodus 21:17; Lev. 20:9</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">father or his mother</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">9</content>
            <content> Isaiah 29:13</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">14</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">guides of the blind</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="16">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The Pharisees and Sadducees came to Jesus and tested him by asking him to show them a sign from heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He replied,</content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> "When evening comes, you say, `It will be fair weather, for the sky is red,'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>and in the morning, `Today it will be stormy, for the sky is red and overcast.' You know how to interpret the appearance of the sky, but you cannot interpret the signs of the times.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>A wicked and adulterous generation looks for a miraculous sign, but none will be given it except the sign of Jonah." Jesus then left them and went away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>When they went across the lake, the disciples forgot to take bread.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"Be careful," Jesus said to them. "Be on your guard against the yeast of the Pharisees and Sadducees."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>They discussed this among themselves and said, "It is because we didn't bring any bread."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Aware of their discussion, Jesus asked, "You of little faith, why are you talking among yourselves about having no bread?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Do you still not understand? Don't you remember the five loaves for the five thousand, and how many basketfuls you gathered?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Or the seven loaves for the four thousand, and how many basketfuls you gathered?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>How is it you don't understand that I was not talking to you about bread? But be on your guard against the yeast of the Pharisees and Sadducees."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Then they understood that he was not telling them to guard against the yeast used in bread, but against the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>When Jesus came to the region of Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, "Who do people say the Son of Man is?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>They replied, "Some say John the Baptist; others say Elijah; and still others, Jeremiah or one of the prophets."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"But what about you?" he asked. "Who do you say I am?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Simon Peter answered, "You are the Christ,</content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> the Son of the living God."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Jesus replied, "Blessed are you, Simon son of Jonah, for this was not revealed to you by man, but by my Father in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>And I tell you that you are Peter,</content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of Hades</content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> will not overcome it.</content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven; whatever you bind on earth will be</content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be</content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> loosed in heaven."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Then he warned his disciples not to tell anyone that he was the Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>From that time on Jesus began to explain to his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many things at the hands of the elders, chief priests and teachers of the law, and that he must be killed and on the third day be raised to life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Peter took him aside and began to rebuke him. "Never, Lord!" he said. "This shall never happen to you!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Jesus turned and said to Peter, "Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me; you do not have in mind the things of God, but the things of men."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Then Jesus said to his disciples, "If anyone would come after me, he must deny himself and take up his cross and follow me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>For whoever wants to save his life</content>
            <note_ref>8</note_ref>
            <content> will lose it, but whoever loses his life for me will find it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>What good will it be for a man if he gains the whole world, yet forfeits his soul? Or what can a man give in exchange for his soul?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>For the Son of Man is going to come in his Father's glory with his angels, and then he will reward each person according to what he has done.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>I tell you the truth, some who are standing here will not taste death before they see the Son of Man coming in his kingdom."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> Some early manuscripts do not have the rest of verse 2 and all of verse 3.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">16</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Messiah</content>
            <content>; also in verse 20</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> </content>
            <content kind="EM">Peter</content>
            <content> means </content>
            <content kind="EM">rock.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">hell</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">not prove stronger than it</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">have been</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">have been</content>
        </note>
        <note num="8">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">25</content>
            <content> The Greek word means either </content>
            <content kind="EM">life</content>
            <content> or </content>
            <content kind="EM">soul</content>
            <content>; also in verse 26.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="17">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>After six days Jesus took with him Peter, James and John the brother of James, and led them up a high mountain by themselves.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>There he was transfigured before them. His face shone like the sun, and his clothes became as white as the light.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Just then there appeared before them Moses and Elijah, talking with Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Peter said to Jesus, "Lord, it is good for us to be here. If you wish, I will put up three shelters--one for you, one for Moses and one for Elijah."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>While he was still speaking, a bright cloud enveloped them, and a voice from the cloud said, "This is my Son, whom I love; with him I am well pleased. Listen to him!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>When the disciples heard this, they fell facedown to the ground, terrified.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>But Jesus came and touched them. "Get up," he said. "Don't be afraid."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>When they looked up, they saw no one except Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>As they were coming down the mountain, Jesus instructed them, "Don't tell anyone what you have seen, until the Son of Man has been raised from the dead."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The disciples asked him, "Why then do the teachers of the law say that Elijah must come first?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Jesus replied, "To be sure, Elijah comes and will restore all things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But I tell you, Elijah has already come, and they did not recognize him, but have done to him everything they wished. In the same way the Son of Man is going to suffer at their hands."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then the disciples understood that he was talking to them about John the Baptist.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>When they came to the crowd, a man approached Jesus and knelt before him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"Lord, have mercy on my son," he said. "He has seizures and is suffering greatly. He often falls into the fire or into the water.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I brought him to your disciples, but they could not heal him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"O unbelieving and perverse generation," Jesus replied, "how long shall I stay with you? How long shall I put up with you? Bring the boy here to me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Jesus rebuked the demon, and it came out of the boy, and he was healed from that moment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Then the disciples came to Jesus in private and asked, "Why couldn't we drive it out?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>He replied, "Because you have so little faith. I tell you the truth, if you have faith as small as a mustard seed, you can say to this mountain, `Move from here to there' and it will move. Nothing will be impossible for you. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content/>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>When they came together in Galilee, he said to them, "The Son of Man is going to be betrayed into the hands of men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>They will kill him, and on the third day he will be raised to life." And the disciples were filled with grief.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>After Jesus and his disciples arrived in Capernaum, the collectors of the two-drachma tax came to Peter and asked, "Doesn't your teacher pay the temple tax </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> ?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>"Yes, he does," he replied. When Peter came into the house, Jesus was the first to speak. "What do you think, Simon?" he asked. "From whom do the kings of the earth collect duty and taxes--from their own sons or from others?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>"From others," Peter answered. "Then the sons are exempt," Jesus said to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"But so that we may not offend them, go to the lake and throw out your line. Take the first fish you catch; open its mouth and you will find a four-drachma coin. Take it and give it to them for my tax and yours."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">20</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">you. </content>
            <content kind="REF_VERSE">21</content>
            <content kind="EM"> But this kind does not go out except by prayer and fasting.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Greek </content>
            <content kind="EM">the two drachmas</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="18">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>At that time the disciples came to Jesus and asked, "Who is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He called a little child and had him stand among them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>And he said: "I tell you the truth, unless you change and become like little children, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Therefore, whoever humbles himself like this child is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"And whoever welcomes a little child like this in my name welcomes me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>But if anyone causes one of these little ones who believe in me to sin, it would be better for him to have a large millstone hung around his neck and to be drowned in the depths of the sea.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Woe to the world because of the things that cause people to sin! Such things must come, but woe to the man through whom they come!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>If your hand or your foot causes you to sin cut it off and throw it away. It is better for you to enter life maimed or crippled than to have two hands or two feet and be thrown into eternal fire.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And if your eye causes you to sin, gouge it out and throw it away. It is better for you to enter life with one eye than to have two eyes and be thrown into the fire of hell.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"See that you do not look down on one of these little ones. For I tell you that their angels in heaven always see the face of my Father in heaven. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content/>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"What do you think? If a man owns a hundred sheep, and one of them wanders away, will he not leave the ninety-nine on the hills and go to look for the one that wandered off?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And if he finds it, I tell you the truth, he is happier about that one sheep than about the ninety-nine that did not wander off.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>In the same way your Father in heaven is not willing that any of these little ones should be lost.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"If your brother sins against you, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> go and show him his fault, just between the two of you. If he listens to you, you have won your brother over.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But if he will not listen, take one or two others along, so that `every matter may be established by the testimony of two or three witnesses.' </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the church; and if he refuses to listen even to the church, treat him as you would a pagan or a tax collector.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"I tell you the truth, whatever you bind on earth will be </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> loosed in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"Again, I tell you that if two of you on earth agree about anything you ask for, it will be done for you by my Father in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>For where two or three come together in my name, there am I with them."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Then Peter came to Jesus and asked, "Lord, how many times shall I forgive my brother when he sins against me? Up to seven times?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Jesus answered, "I tell you, not seven times, but seventy-seven times. </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"Therefore, the kingdom of heaven is like a king who wanted to settle accounts with his servants.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>As he began the settlement, a man who owed him ten thousand talents </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> was brought to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Since he was not able to pay, the master ordered that he and his wife and his children and all that he had be sold to repay the debt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>"The servant fell on his knees before him. `Be patient with me,' he begged, `and I will pay back everything.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The servant's master took pity on him, canceled the debt and let him go.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"But when that servant went out, he found one of his fellow servants who owed him a hundred denarii. </content>
            <note_ref>8</note_ref>
            <content> He grabbed him and began to choke him. `Pay back what you owe me!' he demanded.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"His fellow servant fell to his knees and begged him, `Be patient with me, and I will pay you back.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>"But he refused. Instead, he went off and had the man thrown into prison until he could pay the debt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>When the other servants saw what had happened, they were greatly distressed and went and told their master everything that had happened.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>"Then the master called the servant in. `You wicked servant,' he said, `I canceled all that debt of yours because you begged me to.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Shouldn't you have had mercy on your fellow servant just as I had on you?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>In anger his master turned him over to the jailers to be tortured, until he should pay back all he owed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>"This is how my heavenly Father will treat each of you unless you forgive your brother from your heart."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">heaven. </content>
            <content kind="REF_VERSE">11</content>
            <content kind="EM"> The Son of Man came to save what was lost.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts do not have </content>
            <content kind="EM">against you.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">16</content>
            <content> Deut. 19:15</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">have been</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">have been</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">seventy times seven</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> That is, millions of dollars</content>
        </note>
        <note num="8">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">28</content>
            <content> That is, a few dollars</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="19">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>When Jesus had finished saying these things, he left Galilee and went into the region of Judea to the other side of the Jordan.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Large crowds followed him, and he healed them there.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Some Pharisees came to him to test him. They asked, "Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife for any and every reason?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Haven't you read," he replied, "that at the beginning the Creator `made them male and female,' </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>and said, `For this reason a man will leave his father and mother and be united to his wife, and the two will become one flesh' </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>So they are no longer two, but one. Therefore what God has joined together, let man not separate."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Why then," they asked, "did Moses command that a man give his wife a certificate of divorce and send her away?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Jesus replied, "Moses permitted you to divorce your wives because your hearts were hard. But it was not this way from the beginning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>I tell you that anyone who divorces his wife, except for marital unfaithfulness, and marries another woman commits adultery."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The disciples said to him, "If this is the situation between a husband and wife, it is better not to marry."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Jesus replied, "Not everyone can accept this word, but only those to whom it has been given.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For some are eunuchs because they were born that way; others were made that way by men; and others have renounced marriage </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> because of the kingdom of heaven. The one who can accept this should accept it."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then little children were brought to Jesus for him to place his hands on them and pray for them. But the disciples rebuked those who brought them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Jesus said, "Let the little children come to me, and do not hinder them, for the kingdom of heaven belongs to such as these."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>When he had placed his hands on them, he went on from there.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Now a man came up to Jesus and asked, "Teacher, what good thing must I do to get eternal life?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Why do you ask me about what is good?" Jesus replied. "There is only One who is good. If you want to enter life, obey the commandments."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"Which ones?" the man inquired. Jesus replied, "`Do not murder, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not give false testimony,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>honor your father and mother,' </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> and `love your neighbor as yourself.' </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"All these I have kept," the young man said. "What do I still lack?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Jesus answered, "If you want to be perfect, go, sell your possessions and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven. Then come, follow me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>When the young man heard this, he went away sad, because he had great wealth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Then Jesus said to his disciples, "I tell you the truth, it is hard for a rich man to enter the kingdom of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Again I tell you, it is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of God."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>When the disciples heard this, they were greatly astonished and asked, "Who then can be saved?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Jesus looked at them and said, "With man this is impossible, but with God all things are possible."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Peter answered him, "We have left everything to follow you! What then will there be for us?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Jesus said to them, "I tell you the truth, at the renewal of all things, when the Son of Man sits on his glorious throne, you who have followed me will also sit on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>And everyone who has left houses or brothers or sisters or father or mother </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> or children or fields for my sake will receive a hundred times as much and will inherit eternal life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>But many who are first will be last, and many who are last will be first.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Gen. 1:27</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> Gen. 2:24</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">have made themselves eunuchs</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Exodus 20:12-16; Deut. 5:16-20</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Lev. 19:18</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">29</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">mother or wife</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="20">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"For the kingdom of heaven is like a landowner who went out early in the morning to hire men to work in his vineyard.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He agreed to pay them a denarius for the day and sent them into his vineyard.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>"About the third hour he went out and saw others standing in the marketplace doing nothing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>He told them, `You also go and work in my vineyard, and I will pay you whatever is right.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>So they went. "He went out again about the sixth hour and the ninth hour and did the same thing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>About the eleventh hour he went out and found still others standing around. He asked them, `Why have you been standing here all day long doing nothing?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"`Because no one has hired us,' they answered. "He said to them, `You also go and work in my vineyard.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"When evening came, the owner of the vineyard said to his foreman, `Call the workers and pay them their wages, beginning with the last ones hired and going on to the first.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"The workers who were hired about the eleventh hour came and each received a denarius.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>So when those came who were hired first, they expected to receive more. But each one of them also received a denarius.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>When they received it, they began to grumble against the landowner.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>`These men who were hired last worked only one hour,' they said, `and you have made them equal to us who have borne the burden of the work and the heat of the day.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"But he answered one of them, `Friend, I am not being unfair to you. Didn't you agree to work for a denarius?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Take your pay and go. I want to give the man who was hired last the same as I gave you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Don't I have the right to do what I want with my own money? Or are you envious because I am generous?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"So the last will be first, and the first will be last."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Now as Jesus was going up to Jerusalem, he took the twelve disciples aside and said to them,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"We are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be betrayed to the chief priests and the teachers of the law. They will condemn him to death</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>and will turn him over to the Gentiles to be mocked and flogged and crucified. On the third day he will be raised to life!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Then the mother of Zebedee's sons came to Jesus with her sons and, kneeling down, asked a favor of him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"What is it you want?" he asked. She said, "Grant that one of these two sons of mine may sit at your right and the other at your left in your kingdom."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"You don't know what you are asking," Jesus said to them. "Can you drink the cup I am going to drink?" "We can," they answered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Jesus said to them, "You will indeed drink from my cup, but to sit at my right or left is not for me to grant. These places belong to those for whom they have been prepared by my Father."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>When the ten heard about this, they were indignant with the two brothers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Jesus called them together and said, "You know that the rulers of the Gentiles lord it over them, and their high officials exercise authority over them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Not so with you. Instead, whoever wants to become great among you must be your servant,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>and whoever wants to be first must be your slave--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>just as the Son of Man did not come to be served, but to serve, and to give his life as a ransom for many."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>As Jesus and his disciples were leaving Jericho, a large crowd followed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Two blind men were sitting by the roadside, and when they heard that Jesus was going by, they shouted, "Lord, Son of David, have mercy on us!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>The crowd rebuked them and told them to be quiet, but they shouted all the louder, "Lord, Son of David, have mercy on us!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Jesus stopped and called them. "What do you want me to do for you?" he asked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>"Lord," they answered, "we want our sight."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Jesus had compassion on them and touched their eyes. Immediately they received their sight and followed him.</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="21">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>As they approached Jerusalem and came to Bethphage on the Mount of Olives, Jesus sent two disciples,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>saying to them, "Go to the village ahead of you, and at once you will find a donkey tied there, with her colt by her. Untie them and bring them to me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If anyone says anything to you, tell him that the Lord needs them, and he will send them right away."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>This took place to fulfill what was spoken through the prophet:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"Say to the Daughter of Zion, `See, your king comes to you, gentle and riding on a donkey, on a colt, the foal of a donkey.'" </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The disciples went and did as Jesus had instructed them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>They brought the donkey and the colt, placed their cloaks on them, and Jesus sat on them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>A very large crowd spread their cloaks on the road, while others cut branches from the trees and spread them on the road.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The crowds that went ahead of him and those that followed shouted, "Hosanna </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> to the Son of David!" "Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord!" </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> "Hosanna </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> in the highest!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>When Jesus entered Jerusalem, the whole city was stirred and asked, "Who is this?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The crowds answered, "This is Jesus, the prophet from Nazareth in Galilee."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Jesus entered the temple area and drove out all who were buying and selling there. He overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches of those selling doves.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"It is written," he said to them, "`My house will be called a house of prayer,' </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> but you are making it a `den of robbers.' </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The blind and the lame came to him at the temple, and he healed them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>But when the chief priests and the teachers of the law saw the wonderful things he did and the children shouting in the temple area, "Hosanna to the Son of David," they were indignant.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"Do you hear what these children are saying?" they asked him. "Yes," replied Jesus, "have you never read, "`From the lips of children and infants you have ordained praise' </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> ?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And he left them and went out of the city to Bethany, where he spent the night.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Early in the morning, as he was on his way back to the city, he was hungry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Seeing a fig tree by the road, he went up to it but found nothing on it except leaves. Then he said to it, "May you never bear fruit again!" Immediately the tree withered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>When the disciples saw this, they were amazed. "How did the fig tree wither so quickly?" they asked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Jesus replied, "I tell you the truth, if you have faith and do not doubt, not only can you do what was done to the fig tree, but also you can say to this mountain, `Go, throw yourself into the sea,' and it will be done.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>If you believe, you will receive whatever you ask for in prayer."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Jesus entered the temple courts, and, while he was teaching, the chief priests and the elders of the people came to him. "By what authority are you doing these things?" they asked. "And who gave you this authority?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Jesus replied, "I will also ask you one question. If you answer me, I will tell you by what authority I am doing these things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>John's baptism--where did it come from? Was it from heaven, or from men?" They discussed it among themselves and said, "If we say, `From heaven,' he will ask, `Then why didn't you believe him?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>But if we say, `From men'--we are afraid of the people, for they all hold that John was a prophet."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>So they answered Jesus, "We don't know." Then he said, "Neither will I tell you by what authority I am doing these things.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"What do you think? There was a man who had two sons. He went to the first and said, `Son, go and work today in the vineyard.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"`I will not,' he answered, but later he changed his mind and went.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>"Then the father went to the other son and said the same thing. He answered, `I will, sir,' but he did not go.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>"Which of the two did what his father wanted?" "The first," they answered. Jesus said to them, "I tell you the truth, the tax collectors and the prostitutes are entering the kingdom of God ahead of you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>For John came to you to show you the way of righteousness, and you did not believe him, but the tax collectors and the prostitutes did. And even after you saw this, you did not repent and believe him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>"Listen to another parable: There was a landowner who planted a vineyard. He put a wall around it, dug a winepress in it and built a watchtower. Then he rented the vineyard to some farmers and went away on a journey.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>When the harvest time approached, he sent his servants to the tenants to collect his fruit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>"The tenants seized his servants; they beat one, killed another, and stoned a third.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Then he sent other servants to them, more than the first time, and the tenants treated them the same way.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Last of all, he sent his son to them. `They will respect my son,' he said.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>"But when the tenants saw the son, they said to each other, `This is the heir. Come, let's kill him and take his inheritance.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>So they took him and threw him out of the vineyard and killed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>"Therefore, when the owner of the vineyard comes, what will he do to those tenants?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>"He will bring those wretches to a wretched end," they replied, "and he will rent the vineyard to other tenants, who will give him his share of the crop at harvest time."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>Jesus said to them, "Have you never read in the Scriptures: "`The stone the builders rejected has become the capstone </content>
            <note_ref>8</note_ref>
            <content> ; the Lord has done this, and it is marvelous in our eyes' </content>
            <note_ref>9</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>"Therefore I tell you that the kingdom of God will be taken away from you and given to a people who will produce its fruit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>He who falls on this stone will be broken to pieces, but he on whom it falls will be crushed." </content>
            <note_ref>10</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>When the chief priests and the Pharisees heard Jesus' parables, they knew he was talking about them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>They looked for a way to arrest him, but they were afraid of the crowd because the people held that he was a prophet.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> Zech. 9:9</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">9</content>
            <content> A Hebrew expression meaning "Save!" which became an exclamation of praise; also in verse 15</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">9</content>
            <content> Psalm 118:26</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">9</content>
            <content> A Hebrew expression meaning "Save!" which became an exclamation of praise; also in verse 15</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Isaiah 56:7</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Jer. 7:11</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">16</content>
            <content> Psalm 8:2</content>
        </note>
        <note num="8">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">42</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">cornerstone</content>
        </note>
        <note num="9">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">42</content>
            <content> Psalm 118:22,23</content>
        </note>
        <note num="10">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">44</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts do not have verse 44.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="22">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Jesus spoke to them again in parables, saying:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"The kingdom of heaven is like a king who prepared a wedding banquet for his son.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>He sent his servants to those who had been invited to the banquet to tell them to come, but they refused to come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Then he sent some more servants and said, `Tell those who have been invited that I have prepared my dinner: My oxen and fattened cattle have been butchered, and everything is ready. Come to the wedding banquet.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"But they paid no attention and went off--one to his field, another to his business.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The rest seized his servants, mistreated them and killed them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The king was enraged. He sent his army and destroyed those murderers and burned their city.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Then he said to his servants, `The wedding banquet is ready, but those I invited did not deserve to come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Go to the street corners and invite to the banquet anyone you find.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>So the servants went out into the streets and gathered all the people they could find, both good and bad, and the wedding hall was filled with guests.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"But when the king came in to see the guests, he noticed a man there who was not wearing wedding clothes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>`Friend,' he asked, `how did you get in here without wedding clothes?' The man was speechless.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"Then the king told the attendants, `Tie him hand and foot, and throw him outside, into the darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"For many are invited, but few are chosen."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Then the Pharisees went out and laid plans to trap him in his words.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>They sent their disciples to him along with the Herodians. "Teacher," they said, "we know you are a man of integrity and that you teach the way of God in accordance with the truth. You aren't swayed by men, because you pay no attention to who they are.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Tell us then, what is your opinion? Is it right to pay taxes to Caesar or not?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But Jesus, knowing their evil intent, said, "You hypocrites, why are you trying to trap me?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Show me the coin used for paying the tax." They brought him a denarius,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>and he asked them, "Whose portrait is this? And whose inscription?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Caesar's," they replied. Then he said to them, "Give to Caesar what is Caesar's, and to God what is God's."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>When they heard this, they were amazed. So they left him and went away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>That same day the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, came to him with a question.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"Teacher," they said, "Moses told us that if a man dies without having children, his brother must marry the widow and have children for him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Now there were seven brothers among us. The first one married and died, and since he had no children, he left his wife to his brother.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>The same thing happened to the second and third brother, right on down to the seventh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Finally, the woman died.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Now then, at the resurrection, whose wife will she be of the seven, since all of them were married to her?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Jesus replied, "You are in error because you do not know the Scriptures or the power of God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>At the resurrection people will neither marry nor be given in marriage; they will be like the angels in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>But about the resurrection of the dead--have you not read what God said to you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>`I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob' </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ? He is not the God of the dead but of the living."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>When the crowds heard this, they were astonished at his teaching.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Hearing that Jesus had silenced the Sadducees, the Pharisees got together.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>One of them, an expert in the law, tested him with this question:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>"Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Jesus replied: "`Love the Lord your God with all your heart and with all your soul and with all your mind.' </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>This is the first and greatest commandment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>And the second is like it: `Love your neighbor as yourself.' </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>All the Law and the Prophets hang on these two commandments."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>While the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus asked them,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>"What do you think about the Christ </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> ? Whose son is he?" "The son of David," they replied.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>He said to them, "How is it then that David, speaking by the Spirit, calls him `Lord'? For he says,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>"`The Lord said to my Lord: "Sit at my right hand until I put your enemies under your feet."' </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>If then David calls him `Lord,' how can he be his son?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>No one could say a word in reply, and from that day on no one dared to ask him any more questions.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">32</content>
            <content> Exodus 3:6</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">37</content>
            <content> Deut. 6:5</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">39</content>
            <content> Lev. 19:18</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">42</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Messiah</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">44</content>
            <content> Psalm 110:1</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="23">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Jesus said to the crowds and to his disciples:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"The teachers of the law and the Pharisees sit in Moses' seat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>So you must obey them and do everything they tell you. But do not do what they do, for they do not practice what they preach.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>They tie up heavy loads and put them on men's shoulders, but they themselves are not willing to lift a finger to move them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"Everything they do is done for men to see: They make their phylacteries </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> wide and the tassels on their garments long;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>they love the place of honor at banquets and the most important seats in the synagogues;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>they love to be greeted in the marketplaces and to have men call them `Rabbi.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"But you are not to be called `Rabbi,' for you have only one Master and you are all brothers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And do not call anyone on earth `father,' for you have one Father, and he is in heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Nor are you to be called `teacher,' for you have one Teacher, the Christ. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The greatest among you will be your servant.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>For whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You shut the kingdom of heaven in men's faces. You yourselves do not enter, nor will you let those enter who are trying to. </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content/>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You travel over land and sea to win a single convert, and when he becomes one, you make him twice as much a son of hell as you are.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"Woe to you, blind guides! You say, `If anyone swears by the temple, it means nothing; but if anyone swears by the gold of the temple, he is bound by his oath.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>You blind fools! Which is greater: the gold, or the temple that makes the gold sacred?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>You also say, `If anyone swears by the altar, it means nothing; but if anyone swears by the gift on it, he is bound by his oath.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>You blind men! Which is greater: the gift, or the altar that makes the gift sacred?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Therefore, he who swears by the altar swears by it and by everything on it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And he who swears by the temple swears by it and by the one who dwells in it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And he who swears by heaven swears by God's throne and by the one who sits on it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You give a tenth of your spices--mint, dill and cummin. But you have neglected the more important matters of the law--justice, mercy and faithfulness. You should have practiced the latter, without neglecting the former.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>You blind guides! You strain out a gnat but swallow a camel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You clean the outside of the cup and dish, but inside they are full of greed and self-indulgence.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Blind Pharisee! First clean the inside of the cup and dish, and then the outside also will be clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You are like whitewashed tombs, which look beautiful on the outside but on the inside are full of dead men's bones and everything unclean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>In the same way, on the outside you appear to people as righteous but on the inside you are full of hypocrisy and wickedness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You build tombs for the prophets and decorate the graves of the righteous.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And you say, `If we had lived in the days of our forefathers, we would not have taken part with them in shedding the blood of the prophets.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>So you testify against yourselves that you are the descendants of those who murdered the prophets.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Fill up, then, the measure of the sin of your forefathers!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>"You snakes! You brood of vipers! How will you escape being condemned to hell?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>Therefore I am sending you prophets and wise men and teachers. Some of them you will kill and crucify; others you will flog in your synagogues and pursue from town to town.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>And so upon you will come all the righteous blood that has been shed on earth, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zechariah son of Berekiah, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>I tell you the truth, all this will come upon this generation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>"O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, you who kill the prophets and stone those sent to you, how often I have longed to gather your children together, as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, but you were not willing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Look, your house is left to you desolate.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>For I tell you, you will not see me again until you say, `Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord.' </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> That is, boxes containing Scripture verses, worn on forehead and arm</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Messiah</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">to. </content>
            <content kind="REF_VERSE">14</content>
            <content kind="EM"> Woe to you, teachers of the law and Pharisees, you hypocrites! You devour widows' houses and for a show make lengthy prayers. Therefore you will be punished more severely.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">39</content>
            <content> Psalm 118:26</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="24">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Jesus left the temple and was walking away when his disciples came up to him to call his attention to its buildings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Do you see all these things?" he asked. "I tell you the truth, not one stone here will be left on another; every one will be thrown down."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>As Jesus was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples came to him privately. "Tell us," they said, "when will this happen, and what will be the sign of your coming and of the end of the age?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Jesus answered: "Watch out that no one deceives you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>For many will come in my name, claiming, `I am the Christ, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ' and will deceive many.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>You will hear of wars and rumors of wars, but see to it that you are not alarmed. Such things must happen, but the end is still to come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will be famines and earthquakes in various places.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>All these are the beginning of birth pains.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"Then you will be handed over to be persecuted and put to death, and you will be hated by all nations because of me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>At that time many will turn away from the faith and will betray and hate each other,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>and many false prophets will appear and deceive many people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Because of the increase of wickedness, the love of most will grow cold,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>but he who stands firm to the end will be saved.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And this gospel of the kingdom will be preached in the whole world as a testimony to all nations, and then the end will come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"So when you see standing in the holy place `the abomination that causes desolation,' </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> spoken of through the prophet Daniel--let the reader understand--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Let no one on the roof of his house go down to take anything out of the house.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Let no one in the field go back to get his cloak.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>How dreadful it will be in those days for pregnant women and nursing mothers!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Pray that your flight will not take place in winter or on the Sabbath.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For then there will be great distress, unequaled from the beginning of the world until now--and never to be equaled again.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>If those days had not been cut short, no one would survive, but for the sake of the elect those days will be shortened.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>At that time if anyone says to you, `Look, here is the Christ!' or, `There he is!' do not believe it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>For false Christs and false prophets will appear and perform great signs and miracles to deceive even the elect--if that were possible.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>See, I have told you ahead of time.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>"So if anyone tells you, `There he is, out in the desert,' do not go out; or, `Here he is, in the inner rooms,' do not believe it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>For as lightning that comes from the east is visible even in the west, so will be the coming of the Son of Man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Wherever there is a carcass, there the vultures will gather.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"Immediately after the distress of those days "`the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light; the stars will fall from the sky, and the heavenly bodies will be shaken.' </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>"At that time the sign of the Son of Man will appear in the sky, and all the nations of the earth will mourn. They will see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of the sky, with power and great glory.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>And he will send his angels with a loud trumpet call, and they will gather his elect from the four winds, from one end of the heavens to the other.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>"Now learn this lesson from the fig tree: As soon as its twigs get tender and its leaves come out, you know that summer is near.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Even so, when you see all these things, you know that it </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> is near, right at the door.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>I tell you the truth, this generation </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> will certainly not pass away until all these things have happened.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will never pass away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>"No one knows about that day or hour, not even the angels in heaven, nor the Son, </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> but only the Father.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>As it was in the days of Noah, so it will be at the coming of the Son of Man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>For in the days before the flood, people were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, up to the day Noah entered the ark;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>and they knew nothing about what would happen until the flood came and took them all away. That is how it will be at the coming of the Son of Man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>Two men will be in the field; one will be taken and the other left.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>Two women will be grinding with a hand mill; one will be taken and the other left.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>"Therefore keep watch, because you do not know on what day your Lord will come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>But understand this: If the owner of the house had known at what time of night the thief was coming, he would have kept watch and would not have let his house be broken into.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>So you also must be ready, because the Son of Man will come at an hour when you do not expect him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>"Who then is the faithful and wise servant, whom the master has put in charge of the servants in his household to give them their food at the proper time?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>It will be good for that servant whose master finds him doing so when he returns.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>I tell you the truth, he will put him in charge of all his possessions.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>But suppose that servant is wicked and says to himself, `My master is staying away a long time,'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>and he then begins to beat his fellow servants and to eat and drink with drunkards.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>The master of that servant will come on a day when he does not expect him and at an hour he is not aware of.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
            <content>He will cut him to pieces and assign him a place with the hypocrites, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Messiah</content>
            <content>; also in verse 23</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Daniel 9:27; 11:31; 12:11</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">29</content>
            <content> Isaiah 13:10; 34:4</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">he</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">34</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">race</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">36</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts do not have </content>
            <content kind="EM">nor the Son.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="25">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"At that time the kingdom of heaven will be like ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Five of them were foolish and five were wise.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>The foolish ones took their lamps but did not take any oil with them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The wise, however, took oil in jars along with their lamps.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The bridegroom was a long time in coming, and they all became drowsy and fell asleep.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"At midnight the cry rang out: `Here's the bridegroom! Come out to meet him!'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Then all the virgins woke up and trimmed their lamps.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The foolish ones said to the wise, `Give us some of your oil; our lamps are going out.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"`No,' they replied, `there may not be enough for both us and you. Instead, go to those who sell oil and buy some for yourselves.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"But while they were on their way to buy the oil, the bridegroom arrived. The virgins who were ready went in with him to the wedding banquet. And the door was shut.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"Later the others also came. `Sir! Sir!' they said. `Open the door for us!'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"But he replied, `I tell you the truth, I don't know you.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"Therefore keep watch, because you do not know the day or the hour.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"Again, it will be like a man going on a journey, who called his servants and entrusted his property to them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>To one he gave five talents </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> of money, to another two talents, and to another one talent, each according to his ability. Then he went on his journey.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>The man who had received the five talents went at once and put his money to work and gained five more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>So also, the one with the two talents gained two more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But the man who had received the one talent went off, dug a hole in the ground and hid his master's money.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"After a long time the master of those servants returned and settled accounts with them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>The man who had received the five talents brought the other five. `Master,' he said, `you entrusted me with five talents. See, I have gained five more.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"His master replied, `Well done, good and faithful servant! You have been faithful with a few things; I will put you in charge of many things. Come and share your master's happiness!'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"The man with the two talents also came. `Master,' he said, `you entrusted me with two talents; see, I have gained two more.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"His master replied, `Well done, good and faithful servant! You have been faithful with a few things; I will put you in charge of many things. Come and share your master's happiness!'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"Then the man who had received the one talent came. `Master,' he said, `I knew that you are a hard man, harvesting where you have not sown and gathering where you have not scattered seed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>So I was afraid and went out and hid your talent in the ground. See, here is what belongs to you.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>"His master replied, `You wicked, lazy servant! So you knew that I harvest where I have not sown and gather where I have not scattered seed?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Well then, you should have put my money on deposit with the bankers, so that when I returned I would have received it back with interest.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"`Take the talent from him and give it to the one who has the ten talents.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>For everyone who has will be given more, and he will have an abundance. Whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken from him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>And throw that worthless servant outside, into the darkness, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>"When the Son of Man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, he will sit on his throne in heavenly glory.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate the people one from another as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>He will put the sheep on his right and the goats on his left.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>"Then the King will say to those on his right, `Come, you who are blessed by my Father; take your inheritance, the kingdom prepared for you since the creation of the world.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>For I was hungry and you gave me something to eat, I was thirsty and you gave me something to drink, I was a stranger and you invited me in,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>I needed clothes and you clothed me, I was sick and you looked after me, I was in prison and you came to visit me.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>"Then the righteous will answer him, `Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty and give you something to drink?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>When did we see you a stranger and invite you in, or needing clothes and clothe you?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>When did we see you sick or in prison and go to visit you?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>"The King will reply, `I tell you the truth, whatever you did for one of the least of these brothers of mine, you did for me.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>"Then he will say to those on his left, `Depart from me, you who are cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>For I was hungry and you gave me nothing to eat, I was thirsty and you gave me nothing to drink,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>I was a stranger and you did not invite me in, I needed clothes and you did not clothe me, I was sick and in prison and you did not look after me.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>"They also will answer, `Lord, when did we see you hungry or thirsty or a stranger or needing clothes or sick or in prison, and did not help you?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>"He will reply, `I tell you the truth, whatever you did not do for one of the least of these, you did not do for me.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>"Then they will go away to eternal punishment, but the righteous to eternal life."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> A talent was worth more than a thousand dollars.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="26">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>When Jesus had finished saying all these things, he said to his disciples,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"As you know, the Passover is two days away--and the Son of Man will be handed over to be crucified."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Then the chief priests and the elders of the people assembled in the palace of the high priest, whose name was Caiaphas,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>and they plotted to arrest Jesus in some sly way and kill him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"But not during the Feast," they said, "or there may be a riot among the people."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>While Jesus was in Bethany in the home of a man known as Simon the Leper,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>a woman came to him with an alabaster jar of very expensive perfume, which she poured on his head as he was reclining at the table.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>When the disciples saw this, they were indignant. "Why this waste?" they asked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"This perfume could have been sold at a high price and the money given to the poor."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Aware of this, Jesus said to them, "Why are you bothering this woman? She has done a beautiful thing to me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The poor you will always have with you, but you will not always have me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>When she poured this perfume on my body, she did it to prepare me for burial.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>I tell you the truth, wherever this gospel is preached throughout the world, what she has done will also be told, in memory of her."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Then one of the Twelve--the one called Judas Iscariot--went to the chief priests</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>and asked, "What are you willing to give me if I hand him over to you?" So they counted out for him thirty silver coins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>From then on Judas watched for an opportunity to hand him over.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>On the first day of the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the disciples came to Jesus and asked, "Where do you want us to make preparations for you to eat the Passover?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He replied, "Go into the city to a certain man and tell him, `The Teacher says: My appointed time is near. I am going to celebrate the Passover with my disciples at your house.'"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>So the disciples did as Jesus had directed them and prepared the Passover.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>When evening came, Jesus was reclining at the table with the Twelve.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>And while they were eating, he said, "I tell you the truth, one of you will betray me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>They were very sad and began to say to him one after the other, "Surely not I, Lord?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Jesus replied, "The one who has dipped his hand into the bowl with me will betray me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>The Son of Man will go just as it is written about him. But woe to that man who betrays the Son of Man! It would be better for him if he had not been born."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Then Judas, the one who would betray him, said, "Surely not I, Rabbi?" Jesus answered, "Yes, it is you." </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>While they were eating, Jesus took bread, gave thanks and broke it, and gave it to his disciples, saying, "Take and eat; this is my body."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Then he took the cup, gave thanks and offered it to them, saying, "Drink from it, all of you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>This is my blood of the </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>I tell you, I will not drink of this fruit of the vine from now on until that day when I drink it anew with you in my Father's kingdom."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>When they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Then Jesus told them, "This very night you will all fall away on account of me, for it is written: "`I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered.' </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>But after I have risen, I will go ahead of you into Galilee."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Peter replied, "Even if all fall away on account of you, I never will."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>"I tell you the truth," Jesus answered, "this very night, before the rooster crows, you will disown me three times."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>But Peter declared, "Even if I have to die with you, I will never disown you." And all the other disciples said the same.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Then Jesus went with his disciples to a place called Gethsemane, and he said to them, "Sit here while I go over there and pray."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>He took Peter and the two sons of Zebedee along with him, and he began to be sorrowful and troubled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Then he said to them, "My soul is overwhelmed with sorrow to the point of death. Stay here and keep watch with me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>Going a little farther, he fell with his face to the ground and prayed, "My Father, if it is possible, may this cup be taken from me. Yet not as I will, but as you will."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>Then he returned to his disciples and found them sleeping. "Could you men not keep watch with me for one hour?" he asked Peter.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>"Watch and pray so that you will not fall into temptation. The spirit is willing, but the body is weak."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>He went away a second time and prayed, "My Father, if it is not possible for this cup to be taken away unless I drink it, may your will be done."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>When he came back, he again found them sleeping, because their eyes were heavy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>So he left them and went away once more and prayed the third time, saying the same thing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>Then he returned to the disciples and said to them, "Are you still sleeping and resting? Look, the hour is near, and the Son of Man is betrayed into the hands of sinners.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>Rise, let us go! Here comes my betrayer!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>While he was still speaking, Judas, one of the Twelve, arrived. With him was a large crowd armed with swords and clubs, sent from the chief priests and the elders of the people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>Now the betrayer had arranged a signal with them: "The one I kiss is the man; arrest him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>Going at once to Jesus, Judas said, "Greetings, Rabbi!" and kissed him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>Jesus replied, "Friend, do what you came for." </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> Then the men stepped forward, seized Jesus and arrested him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
            <content>With that, one of Jesus' companions reached for his sword, drew it out and struck the servant of the high priest, cutting off his ear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
            <content>"Put your sword back in its place," Jesus said to him, "for all who draw the sword will die by the sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
            <content>Do you think I cannot call on my Father, and he will at once put at my disposal more than twelve legions of angels?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
            <content>But how then would the Scriptures be fulfilled that say it must happen in this way?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
            <content>At that time Jesus said to the crowd, "Am I leading a rebellion, that you have come out with swords and clubs to capture me? Every day I sat in the temple courts teaching, and you did not arrest me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
            <content>But this has all taken place that the writings of the prophets might be fulfilled." Then all the disciples deserted him and fled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
            <content>Those who had arrested Jesus took him to Caiaphas, the high priest, where the teachers of the law and the elders had assembled.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="58">
            <content>But Peter followed him at a distance, right up to the courtyard of the high priest. He entered and sat down with the guards to see the outcome.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="59">
            <content>The chief priests and the whole Sanhedrin were looking for false evidence against Jesus so that they could put him to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="60">
            <content>But they did not find any, though many false witnesses came forward. Finally two came forward</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="61">
            <content>and declared, "This fellow said, `I am able to destroy the temple of God and rebuild it in three days.'"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="62">
            <content>Then the high priest stood up and said to Jesus, "Are you not going to answer? What is this testimony that these men are bringing against you?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="63">
            <content>But Jesus remained silent. The high priest said to him, "I charge you under oath by the living God: Tell us if you are the Christ, </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> the Son of God."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="64">
            <content>"Yes, it is as you say," Jesus replied. "But I say to all of you: In the future you will see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of the Mighty One and coming on the clouds of heaven."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="65">
            <content>Then the high priest tore his clothes and said, "He has spoken blasphemy! Why do we need any more witnesses? Look, now you have heard the blasphemy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="66">
            <content>What do you think?" "He is worthy of death," they answered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="67">
            <content>Then they spit in his face and struck him with their fists. Others slapped him</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="68">
            <content>and said, "Prophesy to us, Christ. Who hit you?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="69">
            <content>Now Peter was sitting out in the courtyard, and a servant girl came to him. "You also were with Jesus of Galilee," she said.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="70">
            <content>But he denied it before them all. "I don't know what you're talking about," he said.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="71">
            <content>Then he went out to the gateway, where another girl saw him and said to the people there, "This fellow was with Jesus of Nazareth."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="72">
            <content>He denied it again, with an oath: "I don't know the man!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="73">
            <content>After a little while, those standing there went up to Peter and said, "Surely you are one of them, for your accent gives you away."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="74">
            <content>Then he began to call down curses on himself and he swore to them, "I don't know the man!" Immediately a rooster crowed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="75">
            <content>Then Peter remembered the word Jesus had spoken: "Before the rooster crows, you will disown me three times." And he went outside and wept bitterly.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">25</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">"You yourself have said it"</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">28</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">the new</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">31</content>
            <content> Zech. 13:7</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">50</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">"Friend, why have you come?"</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">63</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Messiah</content>
            <content>; also in verse 68</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="27">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Early in the morning, all the chief priests and the elders of the people came to the decision to put Jesus to death.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>They bound him, led him away and handed him over to Pilate, the governor.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>When Judas, who had betrayed him, saw that Jesus was condemned, he was seized with remorse and returned the thirty silver coins to the chief priests and the elders.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"I have sinned," he said, "for I have betrayed innocent blood." "What is that to us?" they replied. "That's your responsibility."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>So Judas threw the money into the temple and left. Then he went away and hanged himself.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The chief priests picked up the coins and said, "It is against the law to put this into the treasury, since it is blood money."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>So they decided to use the money to buy the potter's field as a burial place for foreigners.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>That is why it has been called the Field of Blood to this day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Then what was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled: "They took the thirty silver coins, the price set on him by the people of Israel,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>and they used them to buy the potter's field, as the Lord commanded me." </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Meanwhile Jesus stood before the governor, and the governor asked him, "Are you the king of the Jews?" "Yes, it is as you say," Jesus replied.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>When he was accused by the chief priests and the elders, he gave no answer.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then Pilate asked him, "Don't you hear the testimony they are bringing against you?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But Jesus made no reply, not even to a single charge--to the great amazement of the governor.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Now it was the governor's custom at the Feast to release a prisoner chosen by the crowd.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>At that time they had a notorious prisoner, called Barabbas.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>So when the crowd had gathered, Pilate asked them, "Which one do you want me to release to you: Barabbas, or Jesus who is called Christ?"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For he knew it was out of envy that they had handed Jesus over to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>While Pilate was sitting on the judge's seat, his wife sent him this message: "Don't have anything to do with that innocent man, for I have suffered a great deal today in a dream because of him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>But the chief priests and the elders persuaded the crowd to ask for Barabbas and to have Jesus executed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Which of the two do you want me to release to you?" asked the governor. "Barabbas," they answered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"What shall I do, then, with Jesus who is called Christ?" Pilate asked. They all answered, "Crucify him!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"Why? What crime has he committed?" asked Pilate. But they shouted all the louder, "Crucify him!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>When Pilate saw that he was getting nowhere, but that instead an uproar was starting, he took water and washed his hands in front of the crowd. "I am innocent of this man's blood," he said. "It is your responsibility!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>All the people answered, "Let his blood be on us and on our children!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Then he released Barabbas to them. But he had Jesus flogged, and handed him over to be crucified.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Then the governor's soldiers took Jesus into the Praetorium and gathered the whole company of soldiers around him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>They stripped him and put a scarlet robe on him,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>and then twisted together a crown of thorns and set it on his head. They put a staff in his right hand and knelt in front of him and mocked him. "Hail, king of the Jews!" they said.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>They spit on him, and took the staff and struck him on the head again and again.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>After they had mocked him, they took off the robe and put his own clothes on him. Then they led him away to crucify him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>As they were going out, they met a man from Cyrene, named Simon, and they forced him to carry the cross.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>They came to a place called Golgotha (which means The Place of the Skull).</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>There they offered Jesus wine to drink, mixed with gall; but after tasting it, he refused to drink it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>When they had crucified him, they divided up his clothes by casting lots. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>And sitting down, they kept watch over him there.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Above his head they placed the written charge against him: THIS IS JESUS, THE KING OF THE JEWS.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>Two robbers were crucified with him, one on his right and one on his left.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>Those who passed by hurled insults at him, shaking their heads</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>and saying, "You who are going to destroy the temple and build it in three days, save yourself! Come down from the cross, if you are the Son of God!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>In the same way the chief priests, the teachers of the law and the elders mocked him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="42">
            <content>"He saved others," they said, "but he can't save himself! He's the King of Israel! Let him come down now from the cross, and we will believe in him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="43">
            <content>He trusts in God. Let God rescue him now if he wants him, for he said, `I am the Son of God.'"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="44">
            <content>In the same way the robbers who were crucified with him also heaped insults on him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="45">
            <content>From the sixth hour until the ninth hour darkness came over all the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="46">
            <content>About the ninth hour Jesus cried out in a loud voice, "Eloi, Eloi, </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> lama sabachthani?"--which means, "My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?" </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="47">
            <content>When some of those standing there heard this, they said, "He's calling Elijah."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="48">
            <content>Immediately one of them ran and got a sponge. He filled it with wine vinegar, put it on a stick, and offered it to Jesus to drink.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="49">
            <content>The rest said, "Now leave him alone. Let's see if Elijah comes to save him."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="50">
            <content>And when Jesus had cried out again in a loud voice, he gave up his spirit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="51">
            <content>At that moment the curtain of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom. The earth shook and the rocks split.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="52">
            <content>The tombs broke open and the bodies of many holy people who had died were raised to life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="53">
            <content>They came out of the tombs, and after Jesus' resurrection they went into the holy city and appeared to many people.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="54">
            <content>When the centurion and those with him who were guarding Jesus saw the earthquake and all that had happened, they were terrified, and exclaimed, "Surely he was the Son </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> of God!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="55">
            <content>Many women were there, watching from a distance. They had followed Jesus from Galilee to care for his needs.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="56">
            <content>Among them were Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of Zebedee's sons.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="57">
            <content>As evening approached, there came a rich man from Arimathea, named Joseph, who had himself become a disciple of Jesus.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="58">
            <content>Going to Pilate, he asked for Jesus' body, and Pilate ordered that it be given to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="59">
            <content>Joseph took the body, wrapped it in a clean linen cloth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="60">
            <content>and placed it in his own new tomb that he had cut out of the rock. He rolled a big stone in front of the entrance to the tomb and went away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="61">
            <content>Mary Magdalene and the other Mary were sitting there opposite the tomb.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="62">
            <content>The next day, the one after Preparation Day, the chief priests and the Pharisees went to Pilate.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="63">
            <content>"Sir," they said, "we remember that while he was still alive that deceiver said, `After three days I will rise again.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="64">
            <content>So give the order for the tomb to be made secure until the third day. Otherwise, his disciples may come and steal the body and tell the people that he has been raised from the dead. This last deception will be worse than the first."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="65">
            <content>"Take a guard," Pilate answered. "Go, make the tomb as secure as you know how."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="66">
            <content>So they went and made the tomb secure by putting a seal on the stone and posting the guard.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> See Zech. 11:12,13; Jer. 19:1-13; 32:6-9.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">35</content>
            <content> A few late manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">lots that the word spoken by the prophet might be fulfilled: "They divided my garments among themselves and cast lots for my clothing"</content>
            <content> (Psalm 22:18)</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">46</content>
            <content> Some manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">Eli, Eli</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">46</content>
            <content> Psalm 22:1</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">54</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">a son</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="28">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>After the Sabbath, at dawn on the first day of the week, Mary Magdalene and the other Mary went to look at the tomb.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>There was a violent earthquake, for an angel of the Lord came down from heaven and, going to the tomb, rolled back the stone and sat on it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>His appearance was like lightning, and his clothes were white as snow.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The guards were so afraid of him that they shook and became like dead men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The angel said to the women, "Do not be afraid, for I know that you are looking for Jesus, who was crucified.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>He is not here; he has risen, just as he said. Come and see the place where he lay.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Then go quickly and tell his disciples: `He has risen from the dead and is going ahead of you into Galilee. There you will see him.' Now I have told you."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>So the women hurried away from the tomb, afraid yet filled with joy, and ran to tell his disciples.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Suddenly Jesus met them. "Greetings," he said. They came to him, clasped his feet and worshiped him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Then Jesus said to them, "Do not be afraid. Go and tell my brothers to go to Galilee; there they will see me."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>While the women were on their way, some of the guards went into the city and reported to the chief priests everything that had happened.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>When the chief priests had met with the elders and devised a plan, they gave the soldiers a large sum of money,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>telling them, "You are to say, `His disciples came during the night and stole him away while we were asleep.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>If this report gets to the governor, we will satisfy him and keep you out of trouble."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>So the soldiers took the money and did as they were instructed. And this story has been widely circulated among the Jews to this very day.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Then the eleven disciples went to Galilee, to the mountain where Jesus had told them to go.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>When they saw him, they worshiped him; but some doubted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Then Jesus came to them and said, "All authority in heaven and on earth has been given to me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Therefore go and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>and teaching them to obey everything I have commanded you. And surely I am with you always, to the very end of the age." </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">into</content>
            <content>; see Acts 8:16; 19:5; Romans 6:3; 1 Cor. 1:13; 10:2 and Gal. 3:27.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
</book>
