<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Daniel 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and besieged it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the Lord delivered into his hand Jehoiakim the king of Judah and a portion of the vessels of the house of God. And he carried them away into the land of Shinar, to the house of his god, and he brought the vessels into the treasure chamber of his god.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the king told Ashpenaz, the chief of the eunuchs, that he should bring in some of the sons of Israel, and some of the offspring of the king and of the sovereigns:</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>young men, in whom there was no blemish, noble in appearance, and accomplished in all wisdom, cautious in knowledge, and well-educated, and who could stand in the palace of the king, so that he might teach them the letters and the language of the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the king appointed for them provisions for each day, from his own food and from the wine which he himself drank, so that, after being nourished for three years, they would stand in the sight of the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now, among those of the sons of Judah, there were Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the chief of the eunuchs assigned names to them: to Daniel, Belteshazzar; to Hananiah, Shadrach; to Mishael, Meshach; and to Azariah, Abednego.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But Daniel resolved in his heart that he would not be polluted with the king&#8217;s meal, nor with the wine he drank, and he requested of the chief of the eunuchs that he might not be contaminated.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And so God gave Daniel grace and mercy in the sight of the leader of the eunuchs.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the leader of the eunuchs said to Daniel, &#8220;I am afraid of my lord the king, who has appointed food and drink for you, who, if he should see that your faces are leaner than those of the other youths your age, you would condemn my head to the king.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Daniel said to Malasar, whom the leader of the eunuchs had appointed over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>&#8220;I beg you to test us, your servants, for ten days, and let roots be given to us to eat and water to drink,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and then observe our faces, and the faces of the children who eat the king&#8217;s food, and then deal with your servants according to what you see.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When he had heard these words, he tested them for ten days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But, after ten days, their faces appeared better and fatter than all the children who had eaten from the king&#8217;s food.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thereafter, Malasar took away their portions and their wine for drinking, and he gave them roots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Yet, to these children, God gave knowledge and instruction in every book, and wisdom, but to Daniel, also the understanding of all visions and dreams.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when the time was completed, after which the king had said that they would be brought in, the chief of the eunuchs brought them in before the sight of Nebuchadnezzar.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And, when the king conversed with them, there had not been found any so great in all the world as Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah; and so they stood in the sight of the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And in every concept of wisdom and understanding, about which the king consulted with them, he found them to be ten times better than all the seers and astrologers put together, who were in his entire kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And so Daniel remained, even until the first year of king Cyrus.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word tyrannorum could also be translated as tyrants, but in this context it does not seem to refer to tyrannical leaders. The word tyrannorum probably refers to various rulers conquered and subjugated by the king, as opposed to leaders who are part of this king&#8217;s own administration. It is interesting that the term &#8220;sons&#8221; is used to refer to those of Israel, whereas &#8220;offspring&#8221; is used, perhaps in a somewhat derogatory manner, to refer to the others.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Notice that the chief of the eunuchs &#8220;pr&#230;positus eunuchorum&#8221; is different from the leader of the eunuchs &#8220;principis eunuchorum.&#8221; The leader of the eunuchs seems to be a step down from the chief of the eunuchs.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> Malasar is sometimes replaced in translations with &#8220;steward&#8221;. He seems to be two steps down in rank, that is, one step down from the leader, and another step down from the chief eunuch. Daniel begins with one of the lowest ranks in this society, as one of the captive sons of Israel. He then moves up to a position akin to that of a student, but he still cannot approach the chief of the eunuchs directly. He must plead his case through intermediaries.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content>The word legumina resembles the English word legume, but is often translated more generally as vegetables. In this case, roots was chosen for the translation of legumina out of deference to the Douay-Rheims translation &#8220;let pulse be given us to eat.&#8221; Pulse refers to vegetable roots, (somewhat different from our potatoes) which must be beaten as part of their preparation. It is unlikely that these young men in training, captives from a war, having rejected the king&#8217;s own food and wine, would be given food as desirable as a variety of fresh vegetables. Rather, they received easily stored vegetables, such as roots.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> The chief of the eunuchs brings them in, not the leader of the eunuchs, and not Malasar.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The word magos is the same word often translated in the Gospel of Matthew as Magi. In this case, it probably refers not merely to wise men or learned men, but those specializing in interpreting the stars, i.e., astrologers.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="Daniel 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar saw a dream, and his spirit was terrified, and his dream fled from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Yet the king commanded that the seers, and the astrologers, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans be gathered together to reveal to the king his dreams. When they arrived, they stood in front of the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the king said to them, &#8220;I saw a dream, and, being confused in mind, I do not know what I saw.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the Chaldeans answered the king in Syriac, &#8220;O king, live forever. Tell the dream to your servants, and we will reveal its interpretation.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And in answer, the king said to the Chaldeans, &#8220;The memory of it has slipped away from me. Unless you reveal the dream to me, and its meaning, you will be put to death, and your houses will be confiscated.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But if you explain the dream and its meaning, you will receive from me rewards, and gifts, and great honor. Therefore, reveal to me the dream and its interpretation.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They answered again and said, &#8220;Let the king tell the dream to his servants, and we will reveal its interpretation.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The king answered and said, &#8220;I am certain that you are stalling for time because you know that the memory of it has slipped away from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Therefore, if you do not reveal to me the dream, there is only one conclusion to be reached about you, that the interpretation is likewise false, and packed full of deception, so as to speak before me until the time passes away. And so, tell me the dream, so that I will also know that the interpretation that you tell me is likewise true.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then the Chaldeans answered before the king, and they said, &#8220;There is no man on earth who can accomplish your word, O king. For neither has any king, however great and mighty, asked for an answer of this kind from every seer, and astrologer, and Chaldean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the answer that you seek, O king, is very difficult. Neither can anyone be found who can reveal it in the sight of the king, except the gods, whose conversation is not with men.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When he heard this, the king commanded, in fury and in great wrath, that all the wise men of Babylon should be destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when the decree had gone forth, the wise men were put to death; and Daniel and his companions were sought, to be destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then Daniel inquired, about the law and the sentence, of Arioch, the general of the king&#8217;s army, who had gone forth to execute the wise men of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And he asked him, who had received the orders of the king, for what reason such a cruel sentence had gone forth from the face of the king. And so, when Arioch had revealed the matter to Daniel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Daniel went in and asked of the king that he would grant him time to reveal the solution to the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he went into his house and explained the task to Hananiah, and Mishael, and Azariah, his companions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>so that they would seek mercy before the face of the God of heaven, about this mystery, and so that Daniel and his companions might not perish with the other wise men of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then the secret was revealed to Daniel by a vision in the night. And Daniel blessed the God of heaven,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and speaking aloud, he said, &#8220;May the name of the Lord be blessed by the present generation and forever; for wisdom and fortitude are his.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And he alters the times and the ages. He takes away kingdoms and he establishes them. He gives wisdom to those who are wise and teaching skills to those who understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He reveals deep and hidden things, and he knows what has been established in darkness. And the light is with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>To you, God of our fathers, I confess, and you, I praise. For you have given wisdom and fortitude to me, and now you have revealed to me what we asked of you, for you have uncovered for us the king&#8217;s thoughts.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>After this, Daniel went in to Arioch, whom the king had appointed to destroy the wise men of Babylon, and he spoke to him in this way, &#8220;Do not destroy the wise men of Babylon. Bring me in before the king, and I will explain the solution to the king.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then Arioch quickly brought Daniel to the king, and he said to him, &#8220;I have found a man of the sons of the transmigration of Judah, who would announce the solution to the king.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, &#8220;Do you really think that you can reveal to me the dream that I saw and its interpretation?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And Daniel, facing the king, answered and said, &#8220;The secret that the king seeks, the wise men, the seers, and the soothsayers are unable to reveal to the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But there is a God in heaven who reveals mysteries, who has revealed to you, king Nebuchadnezzar, what will happen in the latter times. Your dream and the visions of your head upon your bed, are such as these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>You, O king, began to think, while in your blanket, about what will be hereafter. And he who reveals secrets showed you what will happen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>To me, likewise, this mystery is revealed, not according to the wisdom that is in me more than in other living things, but so that the interpretation might be made manifest to the king, and so that you may know the thoughts of your mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>You, O king, saw, and behold, something like a great statue. This statue, which was great and high, stood exalted above you, and you considered how terrible it was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The head of this statue was of the finest gold, but the breast and the arms were of silver, and further on, the belly and the thighs were of brass;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>but the shins were of iron, a certain part of the feet were of iron and another part were of clay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And so you looked until a stone was broken off without hands from a mountain, and it struck the statue on its feet, which were of iron and clay, and it shattered them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold were crushed together and diminished like the ashes of a summer courtyard, and they were quickly taken away by the wind, and no place was found for them; but the stone that struck the statue became a great mountain and filled the whole earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>This is the dream; we will also tell its interpretation before you, O king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>You are a king among kings, and the God of heaven has given to you a kingdom, and fortitude, and power, and glory,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and all the places wherein the sons of men and the beasts of the field dwell. He has likewise given the flying creatures of the air into your hand, and he has placed all things under your realm. Therefore, you are the head of gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And after you, another kingdom will rise up, inferior to you, of silver, and another third kingdom of brass, which will rule over the whole world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And the fourth kingdom will be like iron. Just as iron shatters and conquers all things, so will it shatter and crush all these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Furthermore, because you saw the feet and the toes to be part of potter&#8217;s clay and part of iron, the kingdom will be divided, but still, from the slip of iron it will take its origin, since you saw the iron mingled with the earthenware from clay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And as the toes of the feet were partly of iron and partly of clay, part of the kingdom will be strong and part will be crushed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Yet, because you saw the iron mingled with pottery from the earth, they will indeed be combined together with the offspring of man, but they will not adhere to one another, just as iron cannot be mixed with earthenware.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>But in the days of those kingdoms, the God of heaven will inspire a kingdom that will never be destroyed, and his kingdom will not be handed over to another people, and it will crush and will consume all these kingdoms, and this kingdom itself will stand in eternity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>In accordance with what you saw, because the stone was torn away from the mountain without hands, and it crushed the earthenware, and the iron, and the brass, and the silver, and the gold, the great God has shown the king what will happen after this. And the dream is true, and its interpretation is faithful.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Then king Nebuchadnezzar fell on his face and adored Daniel, and he commanded that they should offer in sacrifice to him victims and incense.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And so the king spoke with Daniel and said, &#8220;Truly, your God is the God of gods, and Lord of kings, and also a revealer of secrets, since you could uncover this mystery.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Then the king raised Daniel to a high rank and gave him many great gifts, and he appointed him as leader over all the provinces of Babylon and as chief of the magistrates over all the other wise men of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>However, Daniel required of the king that he appoint Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego over the works of the province of Babylon. But Daniel himself was at the king&#8217;s door.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Notice that this is the second year of Nebuchadnezzar, yet Daniel spent three years preparing to be chosen by Nebuchadnezzar. This is the second year counting from a different point in time, probably from the time that Daniel was chosen as one of the wise men of the kingdom, i.e., &#8220;In (Daniel&#8217;s) second year, during the reign of Nebuchadnezzar....&#8221;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The word malefici, in this context, refers to those who practiced black magic. The word Chaldeans generally refers to an ancient Semitic people from Mesopotamia (particularly Babylonia). But the word can also refer to pagan priests who practice the occult. In this context, it probably refers to the most learned among the Chaldean people, many of whom may have had some knowledge of Chaldean occult practices.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The king has forgotten his dream. The word sermo means &#8220;word,&#8221; but can also refer to a concept or an idea or a plan or, as in this case, a memory.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> Literally &#8220;tempus redimitis&#8221; means buying back time or recovering time, but the modern expression &#8220;stalling for time&#8221; is a fitting, slightly less literal, translation.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> The verb &#8220;interficiebantur&#8221; does not merely mean to kill someone. It implies that the killing has been officially ordered or sanctioned, as in an execution, where a criminal is put to death. This word is not generally used to refer to murder.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The words &#8220;scientiam disciplinam&#8221; means the skill or knowledge used in teaching; whereas &#8220;intelligentibus&#8221; means &#8220;the understanding&#8221; or &#8220;those who understand.&#8221; The phrase &#8220;tempora et &#230;tates&#8221; more literally means &#8220;shorter periods of time and longer periods of time.&#8221;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> Man is made from the earth, that is why Daniel&#8217;s interpretation of earthenware and pottery from the earth speaks of the offspring of man. Iron mixed with earthenware symbolizes an unwise, and ultimately unworkable, mingling of some type of technology (iron) with human nature (earthenware).</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="Daniel 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>King Nebuchadnezzar made a statue of gold, sixty cubits high and six cubits wide, and he set it up in the plain of Dura in the province of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then king Nebuchadnezzar sent to gather together the governors, magistrates and judges, generals and sovereigns and commanders, and all the leaders of the regions, to come together for the dedication of the statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar had raised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the governors, magistrates and judges, generals and sovereigns and nobles, who were appointed to power, and all the leaders of the regions were brought together so as to convene for the dedication of the statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar had raised. And so they stood before the statue that king Nebuchadnezzar had set up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And a herald proclaimed loudly, &#8220;To you it is said, to you peoples, tribes, and languages,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>that in the hour when you will hear the sound of the trumpet and the pipe and the lute, the harp and the psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, you must fall down and adore the gold statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar has set up.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But if anyone will not bow down and adore, in the same hour he will be cast into a furnace of burning fire.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>After this, therefore, as soon as all the people heard the sound of the trumpet, the pipe and the lute, the harp and the psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, all the peoples, tribes, and languages fell down and adored the gold statue, which king Nebuchadnezzar had set up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And soon, about the same time, some influential Chaldeans came and accused the Jews,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and they said to king Nebuchadnezzar, &#8220;O king, live forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>You, O king, have established a decree, so that every man who might hear the sound of the trumpet, the pipe and the lute, the harp and the psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, will prostrate himself and adore the gold statue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But if any man will not fall down and adore, he would be cast into a furnace of burning fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Yet there are influential Jews, whom you have appointed over the works of the region of Babylon, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. These men, O king, have scorned your decree. They do not worship your gods, and they do not adore the gold statue which you have raised up.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Nebuchadnezzar, in fury and in wrath, commanded that Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego should be brought, and so, without delay, they were brought before the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And king Nebuchadnezzar addressed them and said, &#8220;Is it true, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, that you do not worship my gods, nor adore the gold statue, which I have set up?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Therefore, if you are prepared now, whenever you hear the sound of the trumpet, pipe, lute, harp and psaltery, and of the symphony and every kind of music, prostrate yourselves and adore the statue which I have made. But if you will not adore, in the same hour you will be cast into the furnace of burning fire. And who is the God that will rescue you from my hand?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego answered and said to king Nebuchadnezzar, &#8220;It is not right for us to obey you in this matter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For behold our God, whom we worship, is able to rescue us from the oven of burning fire and to free us from your hands, O king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But even if he will not, let it be known to you, O king, that we will not worship your gods, nor adore the gold statue, which you have raised up.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then Nebuchadnezzar was filled with fury and the appearance of his face was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and he commanded that the furnace should be heated to seven times its usual fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And he ordered the strongest men of his army to bind the feet of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and to cast them into the furnace of burning fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And immediately these men were bound, and along with their coats, and their hats, and their shoes, and their garments, were cast into the middle of the furnace of burning fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But the king&#8217;s order was so urgent that the furnace was heated excessively. As a result, those men who had cast in Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, were killed by the flame of the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But these three men, that is, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, having been bound, fell down in the middle of the oven of burning fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they were walking in the midst of the flame, praising God and blessing the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then Azariah, while standing, prayed in this manner, and opening his mouth in the midst of the fire, he said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>&#8220;Blessed are you, O Lord, the God of our fathers, and your name is praiseworthy and glorious for all ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For you are just in all the things that you have accomplished for us, and all your works are true, and your ways are right, and all your judgments are true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For you have made equally true judgments in all the things that you have brought upon us and upon Jerusalem, the holy city of our fathers. For in truth and in judgment, you have brought down all these things because of our sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For we have sinned, and we have committed iniquity in withdrawing from you, and we have offended in all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And we have not listened to your precepts, nor have we observed or done as you have ordered us, so that it might go well with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore, everything that you have brought upon us, and all that you have done for us, you have done in true judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And you have delivered us into the hands of our enemies: traitors, unjust and most wicked, and to a king, unjust and most wicked, even more so than all others on earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And now we are not able to open our mouths. We have become a shame and a disgrace to your servants and to those who worship you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Do not hand us over forever, we ask you, because of your name, and do not abolish your covenant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And do not withdraw your mercy from us, because of Abraham, your beloved, and Isaac, your servant, and Israel, your holy one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>You have spoken with them, promising that you would multiply their offspring like the stars of heaven and like the sand on the seashore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For we, O Lord, are diminished more than all other peoples, and we are brought low throughout all the earth, this day, because of our sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Neither is there, at this time, a leader, or a ruler, or a prophet, nor any holocaust, or sacrifice, or oblation, or incense, or place of first fruits, in your eyes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>so that we may be able to find your mercy. Nevertheless, with a contrite soul and humble spirit, let us be accepted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Just as in the holocausts of rams and bullocks, and as in thousands of fat lambs, so let our sacrifice be in your sight this day, in order to please you. For there is no shame for those who trust in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And now we follow you wholeheartedly, and we fear you, and we seek your face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Do not put us to shame, but deal with us in agreement with your clemency and according to the multitude of your mercies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And rescue us by your wonders and give glory to your name, O Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And let all those be confounded who lead your servants towards evil. May they be confounded by all your power and may their strength be crushed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And may they know that you are the Lord, the only God, and glorious above the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And they did not cease, those attendants of the king who had cast them in, to heat the furnace with oil, and flax, and pitch, and brush.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And the flame streamed forth above the furnace for forty-nine cubits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And the fire erupted and burnt those of the Chaldeans within its reach near the furnace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>But the angel of the Lord descended with Azariah and his companions into the furnace; and he cast the flame of the fire out of the furnace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>And he made the middle of the furnace like the blowing of a damp wind, and the fire did not touch them, nor afflict them, nor bother them at all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Then these three, as if with one voice, praised and glorified and blessed God, in the furnace, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>&#8220;Blessed are you, Lord, God of our fathers: praiseworthy, and glorious, and exalted above all forever. And blessed is the holy name of your glory: praiseworthy, and exalted above all, for all ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Blessed are you in the holy temple of your glory: praiseworthy above all and exalted above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Blessed are you on the throne of your kingdom: praiseworthy above all and exalted above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Blessed are you who beholds the abyss and sits upon the cherubim: praiseworthy and exalted above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Blessed are you in the firmament of heaven: praiseworthy and glorious forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>All works of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Angels of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>Heaven, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>All waters that are above the heavens, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>All powers of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>Sun and moon, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>Stars of heaven, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>Every rain and dew, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>Every breath of God, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>Fire and steam, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>Cold and heat, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>Dews and frost, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>Sleet and winter, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>8</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>Ice and snow, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>Nights and days, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>Light and darkness, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="73">
      <content>Lightning and clouds, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="74">
      <content>May the land bless the Lord: and praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="75">
      <content>Mountains and hills, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="76">
      <content>All things that grow in the land, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="77">
      <content>Fountains, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="78">
      <content>Seas and rivers, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="79">
      <content>Whales and all things that move in the waters, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="80">
      <content>All things that fly in the heavens, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="81">
      <content>All beasts and cattle, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="82">
      <content>Sons of men, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="83">
      <content>May Israel bless the Lord: and praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="84">
      <content>Priests of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="85">
      <content>Servants of the Lord, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="86">
      <content>Spirits and souls of the just, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>9</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>10</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="87">
      <content>Those who are holy and humble in heart, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="88">
      <content>Hananiah, Azariah, Mishael, bless the Lord: praise and exalt him above all forever. For he has delivered us from the underworld, and saved us from the hand of death, and freed us from the midst of the burning flame, and rescued us from the midst of the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="89">
      <content>Give thanks to the Lord because he is good: because his mercy is forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="90">
      <content>All those who are pious, bless the Lord, the God of gods: praise him and acknowledge him because his mercy is for all generations.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="91">
      <content>Then king Nebuchadnezzar was astonished, and he quickly got up and said to his nobles: &#8220;Did we not cast three men shackled into the midst of the fire?&#8221; Answering the king, they said, &#8220;True, O king.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>11</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="92">
      <content>He answered and said, &#8220;Behold, I see four men unbound and walking in the midst of the fire, and no harm is in them, and the appearance of the fourth is like a son of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="93">
      <content>Then Nebuchadnezzar approached the entrance of the furnace of burning fire, and he said, &#8220;Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, servants of the supreme God, come out and approach.&#8221; And immediately Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego went out from the midst of the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="94">
      <content>And when the governors, and the magistrates, and the judges, and the powerful of the king had gathered together, they considered these men because the fire had no power against their bodies, and not a hair of their head had been scorched, and their pants had not been affected, and the smell of the fire had not passed onto them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="95">
      <content>Then Nebuchadnezzar, bursting out, said, &#8220;Blessed is their God, the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who sent his angel and rescued his servants who believed in him. And they altered the verdict of the king, and they delivered up their bodies, so that they would not serve or adore any god except their God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="96">
      <content>Therefore, this decree is established by me: that every people, tribe, and language, whenever they have spoken blasphemy against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, will perish and their homes will be destroyed. For there is no other God who is able to save in this way.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="97">
      <content>Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego in the province of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="98">
      <content>NEBUCHADNEZZAR, the king, to all peoples, nations, and languages, who dwell in the whole world, may peace be increased with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>12</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="99">
      <content>The supreme God has accomplished signs and wonders with me. Therefore, it has pleased me to proclaim</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>13</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="100">
      <content>his signs, which are great, and his wonders, which are mighty. For his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his power continues from generation to generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The list of the names of the musical instruments is somewhat modernized. In ancient times, the assortment of musical instruments would have been quite different from those of today.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> These were not merely &#8220;homines,&#8221; men, but &#8220;viri,&#8221; that is, men of some influence.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The word braccis is translated by the Douay-Rheims as coats; however, the word could be bracis, meaning pants, especially in view of the subsequent verse (3:94), where pants are mentioned as being unaffected by the fire. On the other hand, braccis could refer to the arms, that is, to a covering for the arms, in which case &#8220;coats&#8221; would be an apt translation. Since a different word is used for pants in verse 94, and since the word &#8220;vestibus&#8221; would already include pants, coats seems to fit the context better.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> The word praevaricatorum is difficult to translate succinctly. It refers to one who is supposed to be an advocate or helper, but who colludes with ones enemies (perhaps secretly) instead; in other words, one who betrays trust. Traitor is a fairly close translation; prevaricator in English is too different in meaning from praevaricatorum.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> Naphtha refers to any type of oil which comes from the ground, such as mineral oil or &#8220;rock oil;&#8221; stuppa refers to tow (coarse flax which is used for spinning) or, more generally, to the chaff leftover when the grain is removed from flax; pice is pitch or tar; malleolis is brush or, more generally, any kind of light kindling used for burning.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> Or, who beholds the abyss even while sitting on the cherubims.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> Spiritus can mean the breath of life within living things (but not the soul), or it can refer to wind or the air or breath from one&#8217;s mouth. In this case, a translation is used which permits multiple interpretations.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="8">
      <content> Gelu can mean frost, ice, snow, icy or snowy weather, cold, or cold weather. In this case, since other types of cold are mentioned in other places (cold, frost, ice, snow), the translation &#8220;sleet&#8221; nicely combines &#8220;ice&#8221; and &#8220;snowy or icy weather&#8221; and &#8220;cold weather&#8221; in one word.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="9">
      <content> In the ancient view, the human person is body, soul, and the breath of life (spiritus). At death, the body is buried in a grave, the soul (hopefully) goes to heaven, and the breath of life merely ceases to exist. Thus, spiritus is not another way of referring to the soul, nor is it a separated second soul-like substance, but merely the condition of a body which is alive and which obviously ceases at death. In the modern view, the human person is body and soul. We take for granted the understanding that during life the body has life and at death that bodily life ceases.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="10">
      <content>Some have claimed that the human person is tripartite (consisting of three parts) based on a misunderstanding of passages in Scripture that refer to spirit as well as soul. Some passages have been misunderstood because they say that man&#8217;s spirit ceases to exist when he dies. Such passages are correctly stating that the breath of life (spiritus) ceases to exist upon death; but these passages are not denying the immortality of the soul (animae).</content>
    </note>
    <note num="11">
      <content> The word optimatibus means aristocrats or nobles. Taken more literally, it refers to the king&#8217;s &#8220;best.&#8221;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="12">
      <content> In the Latin vulgate text, a word in all capital letters is used to begin a quotation from a letter.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="13">
      <content> Excelsus is repeatedly used to refer to God in the book of Daniel. Some texts translate this the same as the word Altissimus (Most High). But a better translation uses a different wording, Supreme God or the Supreme One, when translating excelsus Deus or the word Excelsus by itself.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="Daniel 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I, Nebuchadnezzar, was content in my house and prospering in my palace.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I saw a dream that terrified me, and my thoughts on my bed and the visions in my head disturbed me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And so a decree was established by me, that all of the wise men of Babylon should be brought in before me, and that they should reveal to me the answer to the dream.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then the seers, the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers entered, and I explained about the dream in their presence, but they did not reveal its answer to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And then their colleague came in before me, Daniel, (whose name is Belteshazzar according to the name of my god,) who has the spirit of the holy gods within his very self, and I told the dream directly to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Belteshazzar, leader of the seers, since I know that you have in you the spirit of the holy gods, and that no mystery is unreachable to you, explain to me the visions of my dreams, which I saw, and the solution to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>This was the vision of my head on my bed. I looked, and behold, a tree in the middle of the earth, and its height was exceedingly great.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The tree was great and strong, and its height reached up to heaven. It could be seen all the way to the ends of the entire earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Its leaves were very beautiful, and its fruit was very abundant, and in it was food for the whole world. Under it, animals and beasts were dwelling, and in its branches, the birds of the sky were sheltered, and from it, all flesh was fed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I saw in the vision of my head upon my blanket, and behold, a watcher and a holy one descended from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He cried out loudly, and he said this: &#8220;Cut down the tree and prune its branches; shake off its leaves and scatter its fruits; let flee the beasts, which are under it, and the birds from its branches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Nevertheless, leave the stump of its roots in the earth, and let it be bound with a band of iron and brass among the plants, which are close by, and let it be touched by the dew of heaven, and let its place be with the wild animals among the plants of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Let his heart be changed from being human, and let the heart of a wild animal be given to him, and let seven periods of time pass over him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>This is the decree from the judgment of the watchers, and the decision and proclamation of the holy ones, until the living shall know that the Supreme One is ruler in the kingdom of men, and that he will give it to whomever he wills, and he will appoint the lowest man over it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I, king Nebuchadnezzar, saw this dream. And so you, Belteshazzar, must quickly explain to me the interpretation because all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to declare the meaning of it to me. But you are able because the spirit of the holy gods is in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, began silently to think within himself for about one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. But the king responded, saying, &#8220;Belteshazzar, do not let the dream and its interpretation disturb you.&#8221; Belteshazzar answered and said, &#8220;My lord, the dream is for those who hate you, and its interpretation may be for your enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The tree that you saw was lofty and strong; its height reached toward heaven, and it could be seen throughout the whole world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And its branches were very beautiful, and its fruit very abundant, and in it was food for all. Under it, dwelt the beasts of the field, and in its branches, the birds of the air stayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>It is you, O king, who has been greatly esteemed, and you have grown strong. And you have increased your power, and it reaches towards heaven, and your rule is to the ends of the whole earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Yet the king also saw a watcher and a holy one descend from heaven and say: &#8216;Cut down the tree and scatter it; however, leave the stump of its roots in the earth, and let it be bound with iron and brass, among the surrounding plants, and let it be sprinkled with the dew of heaven, and let his feeding be with the wild beasts, until seven periods of time pass over him.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>This is the interpretation of the judgment of the Most High, which has reached my lord, the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>They will expel you from among men, and your dwelling will be with the beasts and the wild animals, and you will eat hay like an ox, and you will be drenched with the dew of heaven. Likewise, seven periods of time will pass over you, until you know that the Supreme One rules over the kingdom of men, and he gives it to whomever he wills.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But, since he commanded that the stump of its roots, that is, of the tree, should be left behind, your kingdom will be left for you, after you have realized that power is from divinity.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Because of this, O king, let my counsel be acceptable to you. And redeem your sins with alms, and your iniquities with mercy towards the poor. Perhaps he will forgive your offenses.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>All these things came upon king Nebuchadnezzar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>After the end of twelve months, he was taking a walk in the palace of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the king spoke out loud, saying, &#8220;Isn&#8217;t this the great Babylon, which I have built, as the home of the kingdom, by the strength of my power and in the glory of my excellence?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And while the words were still in the king&#8217;s mouth, a voice rushed down from heaven, &#8220;To you, O king Nebuchadnezzar, it is said: &#8216;Your kingdom will be taken away from you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and they will expel you from among men, and your dwelling will be with the beasts and the wild animals. You will eat hay like an ox, and seven times will pass over you, until you know that the Supreme One rules in the kingdom of men, and he gives it to whomever he wills.&#8217;&#160;&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The same hour, the sentence was fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar, and he was driven away from among men, and he ate hay like an ox, and his body was drenched with the dew of heaven, until his hair increased like the feathers of eagles, and his nails like those of birds.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore, at the end of these days, I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted up my eyes to heaven, and my mind was restored to me. And I blessed the Most High, and I praised and glorified him who lives forever. For his power is an everlasting power, and his kingdom is from generation to generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing before him. For he acts according to his own will, with the inhabitants of the earth just as with the holy inhabitants of heaven. And there is no one who can resist his hand, or say to him, &#8220;Why have you done this?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>At the same time, my mind returned to me, and I arrived at the honor and glory of my kingdom. And my appearance was given back to me. And my nobles and my magistrates needed me. And I was restored to my kingdom, and even greater majesty was added to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Therefore I, Nebuchadnezzar, now praise, and magnify, and glorify the King of heaven, because all his works and the judgments of his way are true, and those who go forth in arrogance, he is able to bring low.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Quietus is typically translated as &#8220;resting.&#8221; But the rest of the sentence refers to the king&#8217;s general state of well-being, not to one particular day. Therefore, quietus is also referring to the king&#8217;s general condition, i.e., that he was content in his house, not that he was continually taking rest.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Or, that power is heavenly, i.e., power is from God in heaven, not from kings on earth.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The word deambulabat does not merely refer to the act of walking; it means that someone was walking around, as one would do when talking a walk for recreation or exercise or meditation.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> Infectum can mean infected or imbued or corrupted or stained or dyed or even poisoned, but in this context it means that one is covered by the dew or thoroughly wet with dew, that is, drenched.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> Or, &#8220;What have you done?&#8221; Note the similarity between this verse and the Our Father prayer as taught by Our Lord.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5" preferred_title="Daniel 5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Belshazzar, the king, made a great feast for a thousand of his nobles, and each one of them drank according to his age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And so, when they were drunk, he instructed that the vessels of gold and silver should be brought, which Nebuchadnezzar, his father, had carried away from the temple, which was in Jerusalem, so that the king, and his nobles, and his wives, and the concubines, might drink from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the gold and silver vessels were presented, which he had carried away from the temple and which had been in Jerusalem, and the king, and his nobles, wives, and concubines, drank from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They drank wine, and they praised their gods of gold, and silver, brass, iron, and wood and stone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>In the same hour, there appeared fingers, as of the hand of a man, writing on the surface of the wall, opposite the candlestick, in the king&#8217;s palace. And the king observed the part of the hand that wrote.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then the king&#8217;s countenance was changed, and his thoughts disturbed him, and he lost his self-control, and his knees knocked against one other.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the king cried out loudly for them to bring in the astrologers, Chaldeans, and soothsayers. And the king proclaimed to the wise men of Babylon, saying, &#8220;Whoever will read this writing and make known to me its interpretation will be clothed with purple, and will have a golden chain on his neck, and will be third in my kingdom.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then, in came all the wise men of the king, but they could neither read the writing, nor reveal the interpretation to the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Therefore, king Belshazzar was quite confused, and his face was altered, and even his nobles were disturbed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But the queen, because of what had happened to the king and his nobles, entered the banquet house. And she spoke out, saying, &#8220;O king, live forever. Do not let your thoughts confuse you, neither should your face be altered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>There is a man in your kingdom, who has the spirit of the holy gods within himself, and in the days of your father, knowledge and wisdom were found in him. For king Nebuchadnezzar, your father, appointed him leader of the astrologers, enchanters, Chaldeans, and soothsayers, even your father, I say to you, O king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For a greater spirit, and foresight, and understanding, and interpretation of dreams, and the revealing of secrets, and the solution to difficulties were found in him, that is, in Daniel, to whom the king gave the name Belteshazzar. Now, therefore, let Daniel be summoned, and he will explain the interpretation.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Daniel was brought in before the king. And the king spoke to him, saying, &#8220;Are you Daniel, of the sons of the captivity of Judah, whom my father the king led out of Judea?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have heard of you, that you have the spirit of the gods, and that greater knowledge, as well as understanding and wisdom, have been found in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And now the wise astrologers have entered into my presence, so as to read this writing and to reveal to me its interpretation. And they were not able to tell me the meaning of this writing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Furthermore, I have heard about you that you can interpret obscure things and solve difficulties. So then, if you succeed in reading the writing, and in revealing its interpretation, you will be clothed with purple, and you will have a chain of gold around your neck, and you will be the third leader in my kingdom.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>To this Daniel responded by saying directly to the king, &#8220;Your rewards should be for yourself, and the gifts of your house you may give to another, but I will read to you the writing, O king, and I will reveal to you its interpretation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>O king, the Most High God gave to Nebuchadnezzar, your father, a kingdom and greatness, glory and honor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And because of the greatness that he gave to him, all peoples, tribes, and languages trembled and were afraid of him. Whomever he wished, he put to death; and whomever he wished, he destroyed; and whomever he wished, he exalted; and whomever he wished, he lowered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But when his heart was lifted up and his spirit was hardened in arrogance, he was deposed from the throne of his kingdom and his glory was taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And he was expelled from the sons of men, and so his heart was placed with the beasts, and his dwelling was with the wild donkeys, and he ate hay like an ox, and his body was drenched with the dew of heaven, until he realized that the Most High holds power over the kingdom of men, and that whoever he wishes, he will set over it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Likewise, you, his son Belshazzar, have not humbled your heart, though you knew all these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But you have lifted yourself up against the Lord of heaven. And the vessels of his house have been presented before you. And you, and your nobles, and your wives, and your concubines, have drunk wine from them. Likewise, you have praised the gods of silver, and gold, and brass, iron, and wood and stone, who neither see, nor hear, nor feel, yet you have not glorified the God who holds your breath and all your ways in his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore, he has sent the part of the hand which has written this, which has been inscribed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But this is the writing that has been decreed: MANE, THECEL, PHARES.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And this is the interpretation of the words. MANE: God has numbered your kingdom and has finished it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>THECEL: you have been weighed on the scales and found lacking.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>PHARES: your kingdom has been divided and has been given to the Medes and the Persians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then, by the king&#8217;s command, Daniel was dressed with purple, and a chain of gold was placed around his neck, and it was proclaimed of him that he held power as the third in the kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>That same night, king Belshazzar the Chaldean was killed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And Darius the Mede succeeded to the kingdom, at the age of sixty-two years.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Articulos manus can also mean the joints of the hand.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;compages renum eius solvebantur&#8221; literally means that the binding of his kidneys was loosened. But renum (kidney) was often used figuratively in ancient times (see Wisdom, chapter 1, for another example). It was used to refer to the concepts of temperament, self-control, composure, and patience.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The color purple is repeatedly mentioned in the Book of Daniel as being associated with wealth and royal power. This is because the purple color of ancient times was obtained, in a time-consuming and laborious process, from a certain gland in certain types of shellfish. Thousands of these shellfish were required to produce a small amount of the dye, and so the dye was expensive and rare, and usually only found with the very wealthy or the powerful. This color is often called Royal purple, because of its use by kings, or Tyrian purple, after the city which was a center of production and commerce for the dye.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6" preferred_title="Daniel 6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>It pleased Darius, and so he appointed over the kingdom one hundred twenty governors, to be placed throughout his whole kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And over these, three leaders, of whom Daniel was one, so that the governors would be accountable to them and the king would have no trouble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And so Daniel excelled above all the leaders and governors, because a greater spirit of God was in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Furthermore, the king considered setting him over the entire kingdom; whereupon the leaders and the governors sought to find a complaint against Daniel and in favor of the king. And they could find no case, or even suspicion, because he was faithful, and no fault or suspicion was found in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Therefore, these men said, &#8220;We will not find any complaint against this Daniel, unless it is against the law of his God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then the leaders and governors took the king aside privately and spoke to him in this way: &#8220;King Darius, live forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>All the leaders of your kingdom, the magistrates and governors, the senators and judges, have taken counsel that an imperial decree and edict should be published, so that all who ask any petition of any god or man for thirty days, except of you, O king, will be cast into the den of lions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now, therefore, O king, confirm this judgment and write the decree, so that what is established by the Medes and Persians may not be altered, nor will any man be allowed to transgress it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And so king Darius set forth the decree and established it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now when Daniel learned of this, namely, that the law had been established, he entered his house, and, opening the windows in his upper room towards Jerusalem, he knelt down three times a day, and he adored and gave thanks before his God, as he had been accustomed to do previously.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore, these men, inquiring diligently, discovered that Daniel was praying and making supplication to his God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they approached and spoke to the king about the edict. &#8220;O king, did you not decree that every man who makes a request to any of the gods or men for thirty days, except to yourself, O king, would be cast into the den of lions?&#8221; To which the king replied, saying, &#8220;The sentence is true, and according to the decree of the Medes and Persians, it is not lawful to violate it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then they answered and said before the king, &#8220;Daniel, of the sons of the captivity of Judah, is not concerned about your law, nor about the decree that you have established, but three times a day he prays his supplication.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now when the king had heard these words, he was greatly grieved, and, on behalf of Daniel, he set his heart to free him, and he labored even until sunset to rescue him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But these men, knowing the king, said to him, &#8220;You know, O king, that the law of the Medes and Persians is that every decree which the king has established may not be altered.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel and cast him into the den of lions. And the king said to Daniel, &#8220;Your God, whom you always serve, he himself will free you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And a stone was brought, and it was placed over the mouth of the den, which the king sealed with his own ring, and with the ring of his nobles, so that no one would act against Daniel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the king departed into his house, and he went to bed without eating, and food was not set before him, moreover, even sleep fled from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then the king, getting himself up at first light, went quickly to the den of lions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And coming near to the den, he cried out with a tearful voice to Daniel and spoke to him. &#8220;Daniel, servant of the living God, your God, whom you serve always, do you believe he has prevailed to free you from the lions?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And Daniel, answering the king, said, &#8220;O king, live forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>My God has sent his angel, and he has closed the mouths of the lions, and they have not harmed me, because before him justice has been found in me, and, even before you, O king, I have committed no offense.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then was the king exceedingly glad for him, and he commanded that Daniel should be taken out of the den. And Daniel was taken out of the den, and no wound was found in him, because he believed in his God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Moreover, by order of the king, those men were brought who had accused Daniel, and they were cast into the lions&#8217; den, they, and their sons, and their wives, and they did not reach the bottom of the den before the lions seized them and crushed all their bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then king Darius wrote to all peoples, tribes, and languages dwelling in all the land. &#8220;May peace be increased with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>It is hereby established by my decree that, in all my empire and my kingdom, they shall begin to tremble and fear the God of Daniel. For he is the living and eternal God forever, and his kingdom will not be destroyed, and his power will last forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He is the liberator and the savior, performing signs and wonders in heaven and on earth, who has freed Daniel from the lions&#8217; den.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thereafter, Daniel continued through the reign of Darius until the reign of Cyrus, the Persian.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;ex latere regis&#8221; means on the side of the king, or, more loosely, in favor of the king. They wanted to find, not merely a complaint against Daniel, but one which would pit the king against Daniel.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Mirabilia could also be translated as miracles.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7" preferred_title="Daniel 7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the first year of Belshazzar, king of Babylon, Daniel saw a dream and a vision in his head on his bed. And, writing down the dream, he understood it in a concise manner, and so, summarizing it tersely, he said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I saw in my vision at night, and behold, the four winds of the heavens fought upon the great sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And four great beasts, different from one another, ascended from the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The first was like a lioness and had the wings of an eagle. I watched as its wings were plucked off, and it was raised from the earth and stood on its feet like a man, and the heart of a man was given to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And behold, another beast, like a bear, stood to one side, and there were three rows in its mouth and in its teeth, and they spoke to it in this way: &#8220;Arise, devour much flesh.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>After this, I watched, and behold, another like a leopard, and it had wings like a bird, four upon it, and four heads were on the beast, and power was given to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>After this, I watched in the vision of the night, and behold, a fourth beast, terrible yet wondrous, and exceedingly strong; it had great iron teeth, eating yet crushing, and trampling down the remainder with his feet, but it was unlike the other beasts, which I had seen before it, and it had ten horns.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I considered the horns, and behold, another little horn rose out of the midst of them. And three of the first horns were rooted out by its presence. And behold, eyes like the eyes of a man were in this horn, and a mouth speaking unnatural things.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I watched until thrones were set up, and the Ancient of days sat down. His garment was radiant like snow, and the hair of his head like clean wool; his throne was flames of fire, its wheels had been set on fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>A river of fire rushed forth from his presence. Thousands upon thousands ministered to him, and ten thousand times hundreds of thousands attended before him. The trial began, and the books were opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I watched because of the voice of the great words which that horn was speaking, and I saw that the beast had been destroyed, and its body was ruined and had been handed over to be burnt with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Likewise, the power of the other beasts was taken away, and a limited time of life was appointed to them, until one time and another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I watched, therefore, in the vision of the night, and behold, with the clouds of heaven, one like a son of man arrived, and he approached all the way to the Ancient of days, and they presented him before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he gave him power, and honor, and the kingdom, and all peoples, tribes, and languages will serve him. His power is an eternal power, which will not be taken away, and his kingdom, one which will not be corrupted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>My spirit was terrified. I, Daniel, was fearful at these things, and the visions of my head disturbed me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I approached one of the attendants and asked the truth from him about all these things. He told me the interpretation of the words, and he instructed me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>&#8220;These four great beasts are four kingdoms, which will rise from the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Yet it is the saints of the Most High God who will receive the kingdom, and they will hold the kingdom from this generation, and forever and ever.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>After this, I wanted to learn diligently about the fourth beast, which was very different from all, and exceedingly terrible; his teeth and claws were of iron; he devoured and crushed, and the remainder he trampled with his feet;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and about the ten horns, which he had on his head, and about the other, which had sprung up, before which three horns fell, and about that horn which had eyes and a mouth speaking great things, and which was more powerful than the rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I watched, and behold, that horn made war against the holy ones and prevailed over them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>until the Ancient of days came and gave judgment to the holy ones of the Supreme One, and the time arrived, and the holy ones obtained the kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And thus he said, &#8220;The fourth beast will be the fourth kingdom on earth, which will be greater than all the kingdoms, and will devour the whole earth, and will trample and crush it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Moreover, the ten horns of the same kingdom will be ten kings, and another will rise up after them, and he will be mightier than the ones before him, and he will bring down three kings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And he will speak words against the Supreme One, and will exhaust the holy ones of the Most High, and he will think about what it would take to change the times and the laws, and they will be given into his hand until a time, and times, and half a time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And a trial will begin, so that his power may be taken away, and be crushed, and be undone all the way to the end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Yet the kingdom, and the power, and the greatness of that kingdom, which is under all of heaven, shall be given to the people of the holy ones of the Most High, whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all kings will serve and obey him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And here is the end of the message. I, Daniel, was greatly disturbed by my thoughts, and my mood was changed in me, but I preserved the message in my heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word leaena is clearly and deliberately the feminine word for lion. This word choice indicates that the group of nations represented by the lioness will have at least one prominent nation that will be led by a woman at this point in time. The wings of an eagle represent the United States and its military air power.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The three rows in its mouth and in its teeth represent three branches of government and three branches of the military, all of which are saying to the country to go to war and to conquer and annex other nations (growing fatter as when one devours much food).</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> Pardus can mean leopard or panther.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> The word ingentia can mean unnatural or monstrous or enormous. In this case, since this kingdom and its leader are unlike any other, it cannot mean merely great or enormous things, because many arrogant leaders have spoken as if they were greater than they were. The false prophetess is the one who speaks unnatural things, things contrary to nature and God, monstrous things against all good order and reason. The eyes of a man in this horn refers to the Antichrist, and the mouth is the false prophetess who speaks on his behalf.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> Or &#8220;millions ministered to him and billions attended before him.&#8221; Iudicium sedit literally means the judgment sat or the trial sat, i.e., the trial began. This refers to the Day of Judgment.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The translation here avoids saying that the beast (the Antichrist) was killed, because the Book of Revelation clearly states, about the beast and the false prophet: &#8220;These two were thrown alive into the lake of fire that burns with brimstone.&#8221; (Rev 19:20).</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8" preferred_title="Daniel 8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the third year of the reign of Belshazzar the king, a vision appeared to me. After that which I had seen in the beginning, I, Daniel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>saw in my vision, that I was in the capital city of Susa, which is in the region of Elam, yet I saw in the vision that I was over the gate of Ulai.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I lifted up my eyes and saw, and behold, a single ram stood before the marsh, having two high horns, and one was higher than the other and growing higher still.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>After this, I saw the ram brandishing his horns against the West, and against the North, and against the Meridian, and all the beasts could not withstand him, nor be freed from his hand, and he did according to his own will, and he became great.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I understood, and behold, a he-goat among she-goats came from the West above the face of the entire earth, and he did not touch the ground. Furthermore, the he-goat had a preeminent horn between his eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And he went all the way to the ram that had the horns, which I had seen standing before the gate, and he ran towards him in the force of his strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when he approached near to the ram, he was enraged against him, and he struck the ram, and broke his two horns, and the ram could not withstand him, and when he had cast him down on the ground, he trampled him, and no one was able to free the ram from his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But the he-goat among she-goats became exceedingly great, and when he had prospered, the great horn was shattered, and four horns were rising up beneath it by means of the four winds of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But from one of them came forth one little horn, and it became great against the Meridian, and against the East, and against the strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And it was magnified even towards the strength of heaven, and it threw down those of the strength and of the stars, and it trampled them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And it was magnified, even to the leader of the strength, and it took away from him the continual sacrifice, and cast down the place of his sanctuary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the advantage was given to him against the continual sacrifice, because of the sins, and truth will be struck down to the ground, and he will act, and he will prosper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And I heard one of the holy ones speaking, and one saint said to another, (I know not to whom he was speaking,) &#8220;What is the extent of the vision, and the continual sacrifice, and the sin of the desolation, which has happened, and of the sanctuary and the strength, which will be trampled?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he said to him, &#8220;From evening until morning, two thousand three hundred days, and so the sanctuary will be cleansed.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But it came to pass, when I, Daniel, saw the vision and sought understanding that, behold, there stood in my sight something like the appearance of a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And I heard the voice of a man within Ulai, and he called out and said, &#8220;Gabriel, make this one understand the vision.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he came and stood next to where I was standing, and when he approached, I fell on my face, trembling, and he said to me, &#8220;Understand, son of man, for in the time of the end the vision will be fulfilled.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when he spoke to me, I fell forward onto the ground, and so he touched me and stood me upright.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And he said to me, &#8220;I will reveal to you what the future things are in the earlier tribulation, for the time has its end.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The ram, which you saw to have horns, is the king of the Medes and Persians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Furthermore, the he-goat among she-goats is the king of the Greeks, and the great horn, which was between his eyes, is the same one, the first king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And since, having been shattered, there grew four in its place, four kings will rise up from his people, but not in his strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And after their reign, when iniquities will be increased, there will arise a king of shameless face and understanding negotiations.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And his advantage will be strengthened, but not by his kind of force, and other than what he will be able to trust, everything will be eradicated, and he will prosper, and he will act. And he will execute the successful and the people of the saints,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>8</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>according to his will, and treachery will be guided by his hand. And his heart will be inflated, and by the abundance of everything he will kill many, and he will rise up against the Lord of lords, and he will be knocked down without a hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>9</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the vision of the evening and the morning, which was told, is true. Therefore, you must seal the vision, because, after many days, it will occur.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>10</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And I, Daniel, languished and was sick for some days, and when I had lifted myself up, I performed the king&#8217;s works, and I was astonished at the vision, and there was none who could interpret it.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word Meridiem is sometimes incorrectly translated as South. Later in the book of Daniel, the Latin word for South is used, Austri. But here, a different area of the world is indicated. The Meridian, in my interpretation, refers to central Africa, where the meridians of latitude and longitude cross (just off the coast of central Africa). South is used to refer, instead, to the area of the world formerly the southern part of the great monarch&#8217;s (the he-goat&#8217;s) kingdom.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;hircus caprarum&#8221; literally means a he-goat of she-goats. Caprarum is in the genitive case, which often, but not always, implies possession. However, this phrase can be more loosely, and yet more accurately, translated as &#8220;a he-goat among she-goats.&#8221; The implication is that the leader symbolized by the he-goat is a leader among a group of other leaders, many of whom are women. This would be very unusual in past centuries, but fits the modern political situation, which is nevertheless unfortunate and offensive to God, wherein women take roles of leadership in society. Traveling across the whole earth without touching the ground was not possible when this book was written, nor for many centuries afterwards; it has only become possible relatively recently.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> These are the three kings the Antichrist (the little horn) will put down: the king of the meridian (near the equator), the king of the East, and the king of the strength (the Middle East, where the holy land is and which will be the last bastion of Christianity). The king of the strength is also called the king of the South, because this kingdom used to be the southern part of the great monarch&#8217;s kingdom.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> The text is not counting 1150 days as 1150 evenings plus 1150 mornings (1150 x 2 = 2300); nor is the text telling us what we already know, that a day includes daytime and nighttime. Here the translation, &#8220;From evening until morning,&#8221; refers metaphorically to this space of time, i.e., from a time of darkness (evening) until a new day dawns (morning). The time of the Antichrist is a time of darkness, which lasts 2300 days, that is, until the end of his reign. After that end, and a brief time for repentance and the punishment of the unrepentant, Christ returns.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> In the phrase &#8220;novissimo maledictionis,&#8221; novissimo does not mean newest, nor does it mean last, but rather refers, in this context, to something which occurs both at a later time (than the time of Daniel) and earlier than a similar event. The word maledictionis, which often means curse (evil-speaking), refers to an accursed time, that is, to the time often called the tribulation. The tribulation is divided into two parts, occurring in two different time periods; this text refers to the earlier of the two.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The word fortitudine, or strength, is used here and elsewhere to refer to the strength of the Christian faith and to those areas or persons who are strong in the Faith.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> Or, understanding strategies, or understanding (intellectual) arguments.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="8">
      <content> Again, fortitudo is used to refer to the strength of the Christian faith. Literally, it says &#8220;his strength will be strengthened.&#8221; However, in this case, fortitudo is combined with roborabitur to indicate that the Antichrist&#8217;s kind of strength will be reinforced by a strength from out of the midst of the Christian faith. This text refers to false Christians. The Antichrist will increase his advantage by making an alliance with the dishonorable, deceitful, unfaithful, false Christians. It is these false Christians who devise the abomination of desolation as a way to try to destroy the Church from within. The abomination of desolation is a false Eucharist, a perverse imitation of the Blessed Sacrament and the Holy Mass.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="9">
      <content> Principem is often translated as Prince, but it usually refers not to the king&#8217;s son, but to the more general concept of a leader of some kind. The Principem principum is clearly Christ, the King of kings and Lord of lords. The phrase &#8220;sine manu&#8221; can mean &#8220;without hand&#8221; or &#8220;by no human hand,&#8221; i.e., that God&#8217;s angel strikes him down, or it can mean &#8220;without effort,&#8221; in that he is struck down by God very easily, without need of great force or a legion of angels.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="10">
      <content> The word signa can refer to sealing something or to signing something. In this case, the context indicates sealing.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9" preferred_title="Daniel 9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the first year of Darius, the son of Ahasuerus, of the offspring of the Medes, who ruled over the kingdom of the Chaldeans,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>in year one of his reign, I, Daniel, understood in the books the number of the years, concerning the word of the Lord which came to Jeremiah, the prophet, that the desolation of Jerusalem would be completed in seventy years.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I set my face to the Lord, my God, to ask and make supplication with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And I prayed to the Lord, my God, and I confessed, and I said, &#8220;I beg you, O Lord God, great and terrible, preserving the covenant and mercy for those who love you and keep your commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>We have sinned, we have committed iniquity, we acted impiously and have withdrawn, and we have turned aside from your commandments as well as your judgments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>We have not obeyed your servants, the prophets, who have spoken in your name to our kings, our leaders, our fathers, and all the people of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>To you, O Lord, is justice, but to us is confusion of face, just as it is on this day for the men of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and all Israel, for those who are near and those who are far off, in all the lands to which you have driven them, because of their iniquities by which they have sinned against you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>O Lord, to us belongs confusion of face: to our kings, our leaders, and our fathers, who have sinned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But to you, the Lord our God, is mercy and atonement, for we have withdrawn from you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and we have not listened to the voice of the Lord, our God, so as to walk in his law, which he established for us by his servants, the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And all Israel has transgressed your law and has turned away, not listening to your voice, and so the condemnation and the curse, which is written in the book of Moses, servant of God, has rained down upon us, because we have sinned against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And he has fulfilled his words, which he has spoken over us and over our leaders who judged us, that he would lead over us a great evil, such as has never before existed under all of heaven, according to what has been done in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Just as it has been written in the law of Moses, all this evil has come upon us, and we did not entreat your face, O Lord our God, so that we might turn back from our iniquities and consider your truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the Lord kept watch over the evil and has led it over us; the Lord, our God, is just in all his works, which he has accomplished, for we have not listened to his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And now, O Lord, our God, who has led your people out of the land of Egypt with a strong hand and has made yourself a name in accordance with this day: we have sinned, we have done wrong.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>O Lord, for all your righteousness, turn away, I beg you, your anger and your fury from your city, Jerusalem, and from your holy mountain. For, because of our sins and the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and your people are a reproach to all who surround us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now, therefore, heed, O God, the prayer of your servant and his requests, and reveal your face over your sanctuary, which is desolate, for your own sake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Incline your ear, O my God, and hear, open your eyes and see our desolation and the city over which your name is invoked. For it is not through our justifications that we offer requests before your face, but through the fullness of your compassion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Heed, O Lord. Be pleased, O Lord. Turn and act. Do not delay, for your own sake, O my God, because your name is invoked over your city and over your people.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And while I was still speaking and praying and confessing my sins, and the sins of my people, Israel, and offering my prayers in the sight of my God, on behalf of the holy mountain of my God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>as I was still speaking in prayer, behold, the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, flying swiftly, touched me at the time of the evening sacrifice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And he instructed me, and he spoke to me and said, &#8220;Now, Daniel, I have come forth to teach you and to help you understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>At the beginning of your prayers, the message came forth, yet I have come to explain it to you because you are a man who is seeking. Therefore, you must pay close attention to the message and understand the vision.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Seventy weeks of years are concentrated on your people and on your holy city, so that transgression shall be finished, and sin shall reach an end, and iniquity shall be wiped away, and so that everlasting justice shall be brought in, and vision and prophecy shall be fulfilled, and the Saint of saints shall be anointed.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Therefore, know and take heed: from the going forth of the word to build up Jerusalem again, until the Christ leader, there will be seven weeks of years, and sixty-two weeks of years; and the wide path will be built again, and the walls, in a time of anguish.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And after sixty-two weeks of years, the Christ leader will be slain. And the people who have denied him will not be his. And the people, when their leader arrives, will destroy the city and the sanctuary. And its end will be devastation, and, after the end of the war, the desolation will be set up.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>8</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But he will confirm a covenant with many for one week of years; and for half of the week of years, victim and sacrifice will nearly cease; but there will be in the temple the abomination of desolation. And the desolation will continue even to the consummation and the end.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>9</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Daniel initially thinks he has understood the number of the years as seventy, but later he is told that it is seventy times seven years, or seventy weeks of years.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The word confessus is more literally translated as confessed, but is sometimes also translated as &#8220;gave thanks.&#8221; Even in English, the word confess can have a range of meanings which includes admitting ones errors and acknowledging God&#8217;s greatness (and thus thanking Him).</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> Stillavit super nos means to fall in drops over us, in other words, to rain down upon us.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> Sermonem can mean word, but it often refers instead to something more general, to a concept or a message, of some kind.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> Literally, &#8220;Septuaginta hebdomades&#8221; means seventy groups of seven. Here the revelation to Daniel is correcting his misunderstanding; he thought it was seventy years, but the angel informs him it is actually seventy groups of seven (years). The translation uses &#8220;weeks of years&#8221; because years is clearly implied and because &#8220;weeks&#8221; is a concise way to say &#8220;groups of seven.&#8221;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The &#8220;Christum ducem&#8221; is quite a striking expression in the Latin; clearly, to a Christian mind, the translation of Christum as Christ is justified. But, in the case of the leader who arrives after only seven weeks of years, this is not Christ himself, but a Christ-like leader (the great monarch). In the case of the leader who arrives after the additional sixty-two weeks of years, again this cannot be Christ himself (since there is still one more week of years to be completed), but again a Christ-like leader (this time it refers to the king of the South, as well as the Pope). Some translations give the weaker and more ambiguous translation of &#8220;Anointed one.&#8221;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> Interestingly, some Christians have misinterpreted the Christum ducem who arrives seven weeks of years after the rebuilding of Jerusalem (that is, after the founding of the State of Israel,) to mean that Christ himself would arrive at this early date (in the late 1990&#8217;s A.D.). Such an interpretation is not called for by the text itself.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="8">
      <content> Again, the Christus who is killed is not Christ himself. Rather, this text refers to the king of the South, a Christian, a Christ-leader, the king of the last bastion of Christianity, the only one of the ten kingdoms that still tolerates Christianity. He is defeated in battle, because of betrayal or denial by some persons, but not by any people who are Christians. Some non-Christians betray him. Then the Antichrist and his people arrive in the Holy Land of Israel and destroy the city and the sanctuary. They also kill the Pope of that time, another Christ-leader. The desolation is the abomination of desolation, which begins at this time, but does not reach its full power until the last half of the Antichrist's reign.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="9">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;hostia et sacrificium&#8221; could also be translated as &#8220;sacrifice and offering.&#8221; The phrase &#8220;abominatio desolationis&#8221; could also be rendered as &#8220;the detestable thing of abandonment.&#8221; From a Catholic perspective, the first phrase clearly refers to the Eucharist and the sacrifice of the Mass. Thus, the abomination of desolation is a perverse imitation of the Eucharist and the Mass, a false Eucharist, which continues for about three and one half years, even until the end of the Passion and Crucifixion of the Church and the end of the reign of sin on earth.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10" preferred_title="Daniel 10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the third year of Cyrus, king of the Persians, a message was revealed to Daniel, called Belteshazzar, and a true word, and great strength. And he understood the message, for understanding is needed in a vision.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>In those days, I, Daniel, mourned for three weeks of days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I ate no desirable bread, and neither meat, nor wine, entered my mouth, neither was I anointed with ointment, until the three weeks of days were completed.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But on the twenty-fourth day of the first month, I was next to the great river, which is the Tigris.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I lifted up my eyes, and I saw, and behold, one man clothed in linen, and his waist was wrapped with the finest gold,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and his body was like the golden stone, and his face had the appearance of lightning, and his eyes that of a burning lamp, and his arms and all that is downward all the way to the feet had the appearance of glowing brass, and his speaking voice was like the voice of a multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But I, Daniel, alone saw the vision, for the men who were with me did not see it, but an exceedingly great terror rushed over them, and they fled into hiding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And I, having been left alone, saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me, moreover, my appearance was altered, and I languished, not having any strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And I heard the voice of his words, and when I heard, I lay down in confusion on my face, and my face was close to the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And behold, a hand touched me, and raised me onto my knees and the knuckles of my hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And he said to me, &#8220;Daniel, man of longing, understand the words that I speak to you, and stand yourself upright, for I am now sent to you.&#8221; And when he had said these words to me, I stood trembling.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And he said to me, &#8220;Do not be afraid, Daniel, because from the first day that you set your heart to understand, by afflicting yourself in the sight of your God, your words have been heeded, and I have arrived because of your words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But the leader of the kingdom of the Persians resisted me for twenty-one days, and behold, Michael, one of the primary leaders, came to help me, and I remained there next to the king of the Persians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But I have come to teach you what will happen to your people in the latter days, because the vision is for a long time from now.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And while he was speaking words to me in this way, I cast my face down to the ground and was silent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And behold, something in the likeness of a son of man touched my lips. Then, opening my mouth, I spoke and said to him who stood before me, &#8220;My lord, at the sight of you, my limbs became weak and no strength has remained in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And so, how can the servant of my lord speak with my lord? For no strength remains in me; and even my breathing is hindered.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore, he who looked like a man, touched me again and strengthened me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And he said, &#8220;Fear not, O man of longing. May peace be with you. Take courage and be strong.&#8221; And when he spoke to me, I recovered, and I said, &#8220;Speak, my lord, for you have strengthened me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And he said, &#8220;Do you not know why I have come to you? And next I will return, to fight against the leader of the Persians. When I was leaving, there appeared the leader of the Greeks arriving.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But, in truth, I announce to you what is expressed in the scripture of truth. And no one is my helper in all these things, except Michael your leader.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Or, for understanding is the work of a vision.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> He ate no desirable bread, but he did eat bread of some kind. He fasted on bread and water.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The first month is Nisan, when Passover is celebrated. But Daniel could not celebrate the feast in captivity, so he fasted instead.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> Here renes, kidneys, is used to refer to the waistline, not specifically to refer to the kidneys. This is often, somewhat inaccurately translated as loins. The waistline, in current modern fashions, tends to be at the hips. But the waistline in ancient times was considerably higher, encircling the torso at the level of the kidneys.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> The word chrysolithus takes its origins from Greek, in which language it literally means &#8220;golden stone.&#8221; Which mineral or gemstone the word refers to is largely irrelevant. The body of the angel is being described by the text as similar to a gemstone, and lightening, and a burning lamp, and glowing brass &#8211; all of which have a golden bright appearance.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;vir desideriorum&#8221; is sometimes translated as &#8220;man of desire.&#8221; But the word vir is usually used in a complementary sense, and the word desire, in this context, is more like a longing for truth and justice, as seen by Daniel&#8217;s decisions and his search for the truth of the visions.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;scriptura veritatis&#8221; refers to the Bible. The word &#8220;leader&#8221; is a better translation of &#8220;princeps&#8221; than the word &#8220;prince&#8221; would be.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11" preferred_title="Daniel 11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>&#8220;And so, from the first year of Darius the Mede, I stood firm, so that he might be reinforced and strengthened.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And now I will announce to you the truth. Behold, up to a certain point, three kings will stand in Persia, and the fourth will be exceedingly enriched in power above them all. And when he has grown strong by his resources, he will stir up all against the kingdom of Greece.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But there will rise up a strong king, and he will rule with great power, and he will do what he pleases.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when he has been firmly established, his kingdom will be shattered and will be divided towards the four winds of the heaven, but not to his posterity, nor according to his power with which he ruled. For his kingdom will be torn to pieces, even for the outsiders who have been expelled from these.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the king of the South will be reinforced, yet one of his leaders will prevail over him, and he will rule with riches, for great is his domain.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And after the end of years, they will form a federation, and the daughter of the king of the South will come to the king of the North to make friendship, but she will not obtain the strength of arms, neither will her offspring stand firm, and she will be handed over, along with those who brought her, her young men, and those who comforted her in these times.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And a transplant from the germination of her roots will stand up, and he will come with an army, and will enter into the province of the king of the North, and he will abuse them, and will hold it fast.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And, in addition, he will carry away captive into Egypt their gods, and their graven images, and likewise their precious vessels of gold and silver. He will prevail against the king of the North.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the king of the South will enter into the kingdom, and will return to his own land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But his sons will be challenged, and they will assemble a multitude of very many forces. And he will arrive rushing and overflowing. And he will be turned back, and he will be enraged, and he will join the battle in his redness.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the king of the South, having being challenged, will go forth and will fight against the king of the North, and he will prepare an exceedingly great multitude, and a multitude will be given into his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And he will seize a multitude, and his heart will be exalted, and he will cast down many thousands, but he will not prevail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For the king of the North will change strategy and will prepare a multitude much greater than before, and at the end of times and years, he will rush forward with a great army and exceedingly great resources.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>8</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And in those times, many will rise up against the king of the South. And likewise the sons of the deceivers among your people will extol themselves, so as to fulfill the vision, and they will collapse.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>9</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the king of the North will arrive and will transport siege works, and he will seize the most fortified cities. And the arms of the South will not withstand him, and his elect will rise up to resist, but the strength will not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when he arrives, he will do just as he pleases, and there will be none who stand against his face. And he will stand in the illustrious land, and it will be consumed by his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>10</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he will set his face to strive to hold his entire kingdom, and he will make fair conditions with him. And he will give him a daughter among women, so as to overthrow it. But she will not stand, neither will she be for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>11</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And he will turn his face towards the islands, and he will seize many. And he will cause the leader of his reproach to cease, and his reproach will be turned around for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And he will turn his face to the empire of his own land, and he will strike, and will overthrow, but he will not succeed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And there will stand up in his place one who is most worthless and unworthy of kingly honor. And in a short time, he will be worn out, but not in fury, nor in battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And there will stand up in his place the despicable one, and he will not be assigned the honor of a king. And he will arrive in secret, and he will obtain the kingdom by deceitfulness.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>12</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And the arms of the fighting will be assaulted before his face and will be shattered, and, in addition, the leader of the federation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And, after making friends, he will trick him, and he will go up and will overcome with a small people.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>13</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And he will enter into rich and resourceful cities, and he will do what his fathers never did, nor his fathers&#8217; fathers. He will scatter their spoils, and their prey, and their riches, and will form a plan against the most steadfast, and this until a time.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>14</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And his strength and his heart will be enraged against the king of the South with a great army. And the king of the South will be provoked into going to war by having many allies and exceedingly good circumstances, and yet these will not stand, for they will form plans against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>15</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And those who eat bread with him will crush him, and his army will be suppressed, and very many will die, having been executed.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>16</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the heart of two kings will be similar, to do harm, and they will speak lies at one table, but they will not succeed, because as yet the end is for another time.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>17</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And he will return to his land with many resources. And his heart will be against the holy testament, and he will act, and he will return to his own land.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>18</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>At the appointed time, he will return, and he will approach the South, but the latter time will not be like the former.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the Greek warships and the Romans will come upon him, and he will be pierced, and will retreat, and will have scorn against the testament of the sanctuary, and he will act. And he will return and will consult their adversaries, who have forsaken the covenant of the sanctuary.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>19</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>20</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>21</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And arms will take his side, and they will pollute the sanctuary of the strength, and they will take away the continual sacrifice and will replace it with the abomination of desolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>22</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the impious within the testament will imitate deceitfully, but the people, knowing their God, will persevere and will act.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the teachers among the people will teach many, but they will be ruined by the sword, and by fire, and by captivity, and by assaults for many days.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>23</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And when they have fallen, they will be supported with a little help, but many will apply to them deceitfully.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And some of the learned will be ruined, that they may be kindled and chosen and purified, up to the predetermined time, because there will be still another time.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>24</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And the king will act according to his will, and he will be lifted up and will be extolled against every god. And he will speak great things against the God of gods, and he will control, until the passion is completed. Once accomplished, the limit is reached with certainty.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>25</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And he will give no thought to the God of his fathers, and he will be in the desire of women, and he will not attend to any gods, because he will rise up against all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>26</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But he will do homage to the god Maozim in his place, and, a god whom his fathers did not know, he will worship with gold, and silver, and precious stones, and costly things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And he will act to reinforce Maozim with an alien god, of whom he has become aware, and he will increase their glory, and will give them power over many, and he will distribute land for free.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And, at the predetermined time, the king of the South will fight against him, and the king of the North will come against him like a tempest, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with a great fleet, and he will enter into the lands, and will crush and pass through.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And he will enter into the glorious land, and many will fall. But only these will be saved from his hand: Edom, and Moab, and the first part of the sons of Ammon.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>27</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And he will cast his hand upon the lands, and the land of Egypt will not escape.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And he will rule over the treasure chests of gold, and silver, and all the precious things of Egypt, and likewise he will pass through Libya and Ethiopia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And rumors from the East and from the North will trouble him. And he will arrive with a great multitude to destroy and to execute many.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>28</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And he will fasten his tabernacle, Apadno, between the seas, upon an illustrious and holy mountain, and he will come even to its summit, and no one will help him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>29</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word fortis is used in Daniel to refer to the strength of the Christian faith. But here the word roboraretur is used instead. Thus, Darius the Mede is not a faithful Christian or Jew. The angel strengthens him for some purpose, but he is not a holy leader whose strength is from God.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> This king is the long-awaited great monarch, a holy devout Catholic king. Here the word fortis is again used to refer to the strength of the Christian faith. This king is not merely strong in body or in worldly power, he has a strong in faith in God.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The word &#8220;lacerabitur&#8221; has a meaning like: mangled, or wounded, or lacerated, but also (esp. in this context) means torn into pieces. Not a happy day for this kingdom. The externos or outsiders are those outside the Catholic faith or who have been &#8220;exceptis his&#8221; that is, who have been expelled from the Church.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> Notice that now we are told about the South, Austri, whereas before we were told about the Meridian, the area near the equator.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> A federation, or a league, or an alliance.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;germine radicum eius plantation&#8221; is an unusual expression, which probably refers to some type of unusual medical technology used (in the distant future) in procreation. In modern terms, this sounds like something having to do with unnatural conception and birth, something similar to in vitro fertilization, or surrogate mothering, or human cloning.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> Even though the translation is the literal &#8220;sons&#8221; the meaning might be metaphorical. The reference to the king&#8217;s redness, robere eius, means that the king will be either angry or embarrassed. The word provocabuntur can also be translated as provoked.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="8">
      <content> Usually, opibus is translated as power or wealth, but in this context it means something like resources, though with a distinct military connotation.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="9">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;filii pr&#230;varicatorum populi tui&#8221; literally means the sons of the deceivers (or traitors) of your people. But the word &#8220;sons&#8221; is often used metaphorically in Jewish literature. The sons of the deceivers are not the biological offspring of deceivers, but those who act as if they were the offspring of deception personified.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="10">
      <content> The illustrious land might seem to be the holy land of Israel, but the expression in Latin used here is somewhat different from other expressions referring to the land of Israel, so perhaps a different interpretation is indicated.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="11">
      <content> A woman among women is an exemplary woman (cf. song of songs). But the phrase a daughter among women is an unusual twist on the more common expression of a woman among women. From the context and from the expression, this phrase would still seem somewhat complementary. She is an exemplary woman &#8211; but so young as to be called a daughter rather than a woman. An exemplary young woman, and perhaps the meaning is also that she is too young for the task she has been given. In any case, she fails at her unenviable task and she does not remain with him.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="12">
      <content> The despectus is the despicable one, the Antichrist.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="13">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;modico populo&#8221; can mean a small people (not influential), or people who are short of stature, or people who are moderate and restrained, or people who are a short distance away. The phrase is quite ambiguous, in and of itself.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="14">
      <content> The word rapinas resembles the English word rape, and can mean rape in some contexts. But it tends to have a more general meaning, something like assault (including robbery) and/or the loot obtained from such a robbery. The most steadfast would seem to be the Christians.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="15">
      <content> The king of the South is not foolish or rash, he knows it is very dangerous to go to war against the North &#8211; the only kingdom which can and has repeatedly defeated the South in war. But he will have so many things in his favor, including allies and good fortune, that he enters into a war that he ultimately will lose.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="16">
      <content> &#8220;Et comedentes panem cum eo,&#8221; (those who eat bread with him,) could well be a reference to the Eucharist. The king of the South and his kingdom may be the last refuge of Christianity, but it is a sinful kingdom, not a holy one. Here the Antichrist uses unfaithful Christians to help him overcome the kingdom where Christianity has the most influence. Later, he uses a similar tactic (in promoting the abomination of desolation).</content>
    </note>
    <note num="17">
      <content> These two other kings are the kings of the East and of the Meridian (Africa). They realize the danger of the Antichrist and try to outmaneuver and out-deceive him. The word &#8220;malefaciant&#8221; can mean to do evil, but in this context (of trying to defeat the Antichrist), it tends more towards the meaning of doing harm.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="18">
      <content> The holy testament is the Christian faith. He acts against Christianity in the conquered land of the South, where Christianity is strongest, and in the two conquered lands of the two kings.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="19">
      <content> This text is translated quite differently in other English texts. RSV: &#8220;ships of Kittim,&#8221; NIV: &#8220;Ships of the western coastlands,&#8221; NKJV: &#8220;ships from Cyprus,&#8221; NIRV: &#8220;Roman ships,&#8221; NLT: &#8220;warships from western coastlands.&#8221; The Bible has been translated into Latin since the earliest days of the Church, so this Latin text (Trieres, et Romani) may be based on some ancient manuscripts, in Hebrew or Greek, which are not now extant.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="20">
      <content> The Trieres is a type of warship used by the ancient Greeks. But in Daniel, Greece symbolizes democracy, since that is where democracy first began. So, giving the text a modern interpretation, these warships are from an area which still, at that time in the future, practices some form of democracy. But, though the ships are Greek ships, the crew is Roman, which in the modern context would refer to Roman Catholics (or to Christians in general during a future time when all Christians are united in one Church). This interpretation explains why the Antichrist is indignant against Christianity after his defeat and why he sets out to destroy the Faith about halfway through his reign. Daniel 9:27 refers to this time of half a week of years.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="21">
      <content> The Antichrist then consults the adversaries of the Christians, those who have abandoned the Christian faith.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="22">
      <content> Here again the word strength is used to refer to Christianity, as in the sanctuary of the strength, which will be polluted by the abomination of desolation (a false Eucharist). The continual sacrifice is the Eucharist.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="23">
      <content> The word rapina can mean sexual assault. In other contexts, rapina tends more towards robbery or even the loot obtained by robbery, but in this context rapina refers to physical assaults of various kinds.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="24">
      <content> The learned are not pure and on fire with the love of God; but some will be brought to this by suffering. Not many, just some. The very learned tend not to be very faithful nor very holy.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="25">
      <content> The word &#8220;iracundia&#8221; can refer to anger and is sometimes translated in this context as wrath, that is, until the wrath of God is completed. But such a translation does not fit the context well. The verse is about the Antichrist exalting himself, and acting according to his ill will, and controlling the world, and blaspheming God. This is not yet the Wrath of God on the unrepentant wicked. In this context, the phrase refers to the Passion of the Church, that is, to the great sufferings of the faithful during the reign of the Antichrist.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="26">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;erit in concupiscentiis feminarum&#8221; does not mean that he will lust after women, but that women will lust for him.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="27">
      <content> The illustrious land, terra inclyta, (Dan 11:16) is probably a different land than the glorious land, terram gloriosam. The glorious land appears to be Israel, the holy land.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="28">
      <content> Fama is rumors, or news, or reports. The word interficiat implies that the killing is an execution, from governmental authority (whether legitimate or not), and not a killing in battle.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="29">
      <content> Again, illustrious would seem to indicate a different land than the glorious land of Israel.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12" preferred_title="Daniel 12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>&#8220;But at that time Michael will rise up, the great leader, who stands up for the sons of your people. And a time will come, such as has not been from the time that nations began, even until that time. And, at that time, your people will be saved, all who will be found written in the book.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth will awaken: some to everlasting life, and others to a reproach that they will always see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But those who have taught will shine like the brightness of the firmament, and those who instruct many towards justice, like the stars for unending eternity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But you, Daniel, close the message and seal the book, until the established time. Many will pass through, and knowledge will be increased.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I, Daniel, looked, and behold, similarly two others stood up, one over here, on the bank of the river, and the other over there, on the other bank of the river.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I said to the man, who was clothed in linen, who stood over the waters of the river, &#8220;How long will it be until the end of these wonders?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And I heard the man, who was clothed in linen, who stood over the waters of the river, when he had lifted his right hand and his left hand up to heaven, and had sworn by He who lives forever, that it would be for a time, and times, and half a time. And when the dispersion of the hand of the holy people is completed, all these things will be completed.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And I heard and did not understand. And I said, &#8220;My lord, what will be after these things?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he said, &#8220;Go, Daniel, for the words are closed and sealed until the predetermined time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Many will be chosen and purified, and, as if by fire, they will be tested, and the impious will act impiously, and none of the impious will understand, yet the teachers will understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And from the time when the continual sacrifice will be taken away and the abomination of desolation will be set up, there will be one thousand two hundred ninety days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Blessed is he who waits and reaches until one thousand three hundred thirty-five days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But you, go, until the predetermined time, and you will rest and will stand in your allotted place at the end of days.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The phrase &#8220;plurimi pertransibunt&#8221; refers to the passage of time. Many generations will pass through between the time of Daniel and the events of his visions.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The word manus, usually translated as hand, can also mean a band or small group of people, especially soldiers.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13" preferred_title="Daniel 13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And there was a man living in Babylon, and his name was Joakim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And he received a wife named Susanna, the daughter of Hilkiah, who was very beautiful and God-fearing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For her parents, because they were righteous, had educated their daughter according to the law of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But Joakim was very wealthy, and he had an orchard near his house, and the Jews flocked to him, because he was the most honorable of them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And two elder judges had been appointed among the people that year, about whom the Lord has said, &#8220;Iniquity has come out of Babylon, from the elder judges, who seemed to govern the people.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>These frequented the house of Joakim, and all came to them, who had need of judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But when the people departed at noontime, Susanna went in and walked around in her husband&#8217;s orchard.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the elders saw her entering and walking around every day, and they were inflamed with desire towards her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And they perverted their reason and turned away their eyes, so that they would not look to heaven, nor call to mind just judgments.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And so they were both wounded by the love of her, yet they did not reveal their grief to one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For they were ashamed to reveal to each other their desire, wanting to lie with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And so they watched carefully every day to see her. And one said to the other,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>&#8220;Let us go home, for it is lunch time.&#8221; And going out, they departed one from another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And returning again, they came to the same place, and, each asking the other the reason, they admitted their desire. And then they agreed to set a time when they would be able to find her alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But it happened, while they watched for an opportune day, that she entered at a particular time, just as yesterday and the day before, with only two maids, and she wanted to wash in the orchard, because it was so hot.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And there was no one there, except the two elders in hiding, and they were studying her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And so she said to the maids, &#8220;Bring me oil and ointments, and shut the doors of the orchard, so that I may wash.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And they did as she ordered them. And they shut the doors of the orchard and left through a back door to fetch what she required, and they did not know that the elders were hiding within.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But when the maids had departed, the two elders arose and hurried to her, and they said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>&#8220;Behold, the doors of the orchard are closed, and no one can see us, and we are in desire for you. Because of these things, consent to us and lie with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But if you will not, we will bear witness against you that a young man was with you and, for this reason, you sent your maids away from you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Susanna sighed and said, &#8220;I am closed in on every side. For if I do this thing, it is death to me; yet if I do not do it, I will not escape your hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But it is better for me to fall unavoidably into your hands, than to sin in the sight of the Lord.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Susanna cried out with a loud voice, but the elders also cried out against her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And one of them hurried to the door of the orchard and opened it.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>8</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And so, when the servants of the house heard the outcry in the orchard, they rushed in by the back door to see what was happening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But after the old men had spoken, the servants were greatly ashamed, for there had never been anything of this kind said about Susanna. And it happened on the next day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>when the people came to Joakim her husband, that the two appointed elders also came, full of wicked plans against Susanna, in order to put her to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>9</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And they said before the people, &#8220;Send for Susanna, daughter of Hilkiah, the wife of Joakim.&#8221; And immediately they sent for her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And she arrived with her parents, and sons, and all her relatives.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>10</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Moreover, Susanna was exceedingly delicate and beautiful in appearance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But those wicked ones commanded that her face should be uncovered, (for she was covered,) so that at least they might be satisfied with her beauty.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>11</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Therefore, her own and all who knew her wept.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Yet the two appointed elders, rising up in the midst of the people, set their hands upon her head.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>12</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And weeping, she gazed up to heaven, for her heart had faith in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And the appointed elders said, &#8220;While we were taking a walk in the orchard alone, this one came in with two maids, and she shut the doors of the orchard, and she sent the maids away from her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And a young man came to her, who was in hiding, and he lay down with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>13</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Furthermore, since we were in a corner of the orchard, seeing this wickedness, we ran up to them, and we saw them consorting together.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>14</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And, indeed, we were unable to catch him, because he was stronger than us, and opening the doors, he leaped out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>But, since we had apprehended this one, we demanded to know who the young man was, but she was unwilling to tell us. On this matter, we are witnesses.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The multitude believed them, just as if they were elders and the judges of the people, and they condemned her to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>But Susanna cried out with a loud voice and said, &#8220;Eternal God, who knows what is hidden, who knows all things before they happen,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>you know that they have borne false witness against me, and behold, I must die, though I have done none of these things, which these men have maliciously invented against me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>15</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>But the Lord heeded her voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And when she was led away to death, the Lord raised up the holy spirit of a young boy, whose name was Daniel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And he cried out with a loud voice, &#8220;I am clean of the blood of this one.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And all the people, turning back towards him, said, &#8220;What is this word that you are saying?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>But he, while standing in the midst of them, said, &#8220;Are you so foolish, sons of Israel, that without judging and without knowing what the truth is, you have condemned a daughter of Israel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Return to judgment, because they have spoken false witness against her.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Therefore, the people returned with haste, and the old men said to him, &#8220;Come and sit down in our midst and show us, since God has given you the honor of old age.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And Daniel said to them, &#8220;Separate these at a distance from one another, and I will judge between them.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>And so, when they were divided, one from the other, he called one of them, and he said to him, &#8220;You deep-rooted ancient evil, now your sins have come out, which you have committed before,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>16</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>judging unjust judgments, oppressing the innocent, and setting free the guilty, though the Lord declares, &#8216;The innocent and the just you must not put to death.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Now then, if you saw her, declare under which tree you saw them conversing together.&#8221; He said, &#8220;Under an evergreen mastic tree.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>17</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>But Daniel said, &#8220;Truly, you have lied against your own head. For behold, the angel of God, having received the sentence from him, will split you down the middle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>And, having put him aside, he commanded the other to approach, and he said to him, &#8220;You offspring of Canaan, and not of Judah, beauty has deceived you, and desire has perverted your heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>Thus did you do to the daughters of Israel, and they, out of fear, consorted with you, but a daughter of Judah would not tolerate your iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>18</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Now then, declare to me, under which tree you caught them conversing together.&#8221; He said, &#8220;Under an evergreen oak tree.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>And Daniel said to him, &#8220;Truly, you also have lied against your own head. For the angel of the Lord waits, holding a sword, to cut you down the middle and put you to death.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>19</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>And then the entire assembly cried out in a loud voice, and they blessed God, who saves those who hope in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>And they rose up against the two appointed elders, (for Daniel had convicted them, by their own mouth, of bearing false witness,) and they did to them just as they had wickedly done against their neighbor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>so as to act according to the law of Moses. And they put them to death, and innocent blood was saved on that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>But Hilkiah and his wife praised God for their daughter, Susanna, with Joakim, her husband, and all her relatives, because there had been found in her no disgrace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>And so Daniel became great in the sight of the people from that day, and thereafter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>And king Astyages was laid to rest with his fathers. And Cyrus the Persian received his kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> One of the terms used to describe these two judges is &#8220;senes iudices,&#8221; elder judges.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Deambulabat means to walk around or to take a walk, it does not merely mean walking.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> Sensum can also mean mind or understanding.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> Here is one way to refer to sexual relations: concumbere, to lie with (someone).</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> The word quippe means &#8220;of course&#8221; or &#8220;naturally&#8221; or &#8220;as you see.&#8221; Literally, the phrase says &#8220;it was, of course, very hot.&#8221;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The word smegmata is obscure, translated as &#8220;washing balls&#8221; by the Douay-Rheims and, alternately, as &#8220;ointments.&#8221; It refers to whatever type of soap or other substance the persons of that time and place used to wash themselves.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> Here is another way to refer to sexual relations: commiscere, to intermingle or to unite.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="8">
      <content> So the door was closed, which would not be the case if a young man had just been chased out of it.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="9">
      <content> Here the elders are referred to as &#8220;presbyteri,&#8221; a word which could be translated as elders, but which indicates that these were elders who were appointed to a position of leadership, appointed elders.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="10">
      <content> The word cognatis means relatives, but resembles the word for knowing, and so, it is those who knew her well.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="11">
      <content> Now the elders are referred to as iniqui, wicked ones.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="12">
      <content> They not only uncovered her face, they dared to touch her, thus showing their lack of chastity and self-restraint by their actions.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="13">
      <content> Again, sexual relations is referred to with the word concubuit, to lie with someone.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="14">
      <content> Now the word commisceri, to intermingle is used to refer to sexual relations. Both of these expressions are somewhat euphemistic: to lie together or to intermingle. But both expressions are also fairly blunt and show, in the social and religious context of this story, that the elders are unchaste and unrestrained with their words.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="15">
      <content> Susanna shows her chastity and self-restraint by not even repeating explicitly the charge against herself.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="16">
      <content> &#8220;Inveterate dierum malorum&#8221; translates somewhat loosely as &#8220;deep-rooted ancient evil.&#8221; More literally, dierum means a long time, malorum means evil or harmful, and inveterate means to become old or to become rooted or to become hardened by age.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="17">
      <content> This tree is a short evergreen tree found in the Middle East. Notice that Daniel shows more discretion than the elders in the language he uses to describe sexual relations. He uses the more euphemistic and more discrete term &#8220;colloquentes sibi.&#8221; The term conversation was used by Flavius Josephus to denote sexual relations. It is an ancient euphemistic expression.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="18">
      <content> Again, Daniel uses a term referring to conversation, loquebantur, to refer to sexual relations. He does the same in the next verse also.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="19">
      <content> Note that &#8220;interficiat&#8221; refers to execution by authority and that &#8220;vos&#8221; is plural. Daniel is saying that God will execute both of these elders for their false testimony against Susanna.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14" preferred_title="Daniel 14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And so Daniel was living with the king, and he was honored above all his friends.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now there was an idol with the Babylonians named Bel. And each day there was expended on him twelve great measures of fine flour, and forty sheep, and six vessels of wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The king likewise worshipped him and went each day to adore him, but Daniel adored his God. And the king said to him, &#8220;Why do you not adore Bel?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And answering, he said to him, &#8220;Because I do not worship idols made with hands, but the living God, who created heaven and earth, and who holds power over all flesh.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the king said to him, &#8220;Does not Bel seem to you to be a living god? Do you not see how much he eats and drinks every day?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then Daniel said, smiling, &#8220;O king, do not make a mistake, for this one is clay on the inside and brass on the outside, and he has never eaten.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the king, being angry, called for his priests and said to them, &#8220;If you do not tell me who it is that has eaten these expenses, you will die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But if you can show that Bel has eaten these, Daniel will die, because he has blasphemed against Bel.&#8221; And Daniel said to the king, &#8220;Let it be according to your word.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now the priests of Bel were seventy, besides their wives, and little ones, and sons. And the king went with Daniel into the temple of Bel.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the priests of Bel said, &#8220;Behold, we are going out, and you, O king, set out the meats, and mix the wine, and close the door, and seal it with your ring.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when you have entered in the morning, if you have not found that Bel has consumed all, we will suffer death, or else Daniel will, who has lied against us.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But they had no concern because they had made a secret entrance under the table, and they always went in through it and devoured those things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And so it happened, after they had departed, that the king set the foods before Bel, and Daniel commanded his servants, and they brought ashes, and he sifted them throughout the temple in the sight of the king, and, as they left, they shut the door, and after sealing it with the king&#8217;s ring, they departed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But the priests entered by night, according to their custom, with their wives, and their sons, and they ate and drank everything.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But the king arose at first light, and Daniel with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the king said, &#8220;Are the seals unbroken, Daniel?&#8221; And he answered, &#8220;They are unbroken, O king.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And as soon as he had opened the door, the king stared at the table, and cried out with a loud voice, &#8220;Great are you, O Bel, and there is not any deceit with you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And Daniel laughed, and he held back the king, so that he would not enter, and he said, &#8220;Look at the pavement, notice whose footsteps these are.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the king said, &#8220;I see the footsteps of men, and women, and children.&#8221; And the king was angry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then he apprehended the priests, and their wives, and their sons, and they showed him the secret doors through which they entered and consumed the things that were on the table.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, the king slaughtered them and delivered Bel into the power of Daniel, who overturned him and his temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And there was a great dragon in that place, and the Babylonians worshipped him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the king said to Daniel, &#8220;Behold, now you cannot say that this is not a living god; therefore, adore him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Daniel said, &#8220;I adore the Lord, my God, for he is the living God. But that one is not a living god.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Therefore, you give me the power, O king, and I will execute this dragon without sword or club.&#8221; And the king said, &#8220;I give it to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And so Daniel took pitch, and fat, and hair, and cooked them together. And he made lumps and put them into the dragon&#8217;s mouth, and the dragon burst open. And he said, &#8220;Behold, this is what you worship.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>When the Babylonians had heard this, they were greatly indignant. And gathering together against the king, they said, &#8220;The king has become a Jew. He has destroyed Bel, he has executed the dragon, and he has slaughtered the priests.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when they came to the king, they said, &#8220;Deliver Daniel to us, otherwise we will execute you and your house.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>8</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Thus the king saw that they pressured him vehemently, and so, being compelled by necessity, he delivered Daniel to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And they cast him into the den of lions, and he was there for six days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Furthermore, in the den there were seven lions, and they had given to them two carcasses every day, and two sheep, but then they were not given to them, so that they would devour Daniel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now there was in Judea a prophet called Habakkuk, and he had cooked a small meal and had broken bread in a bowl, and he was going into the field, to bring it to the harvesters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the angel of the Lord said to Habakkuk, &#8220;Carry the meal that you have into Babylon, to Daniel, who is in the lions&#8217; den.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And Habakkuk said, &#8220;Lord, I have not seen Babylon, and I do not know the den.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the angel of the Lord seized him by the top of his head, and carried him by the hair of his head, and set him in Babylon, over the den, by the force of his spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And Habakkuk shouted, saying, &#8220;Daniel, servant of God, take the dinner that God has sent you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Daniel said, &#8220;You have remembered me, O God, and you have not abandoned those who love you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And Daniel arose and ate. And then the angel of the Lord immediately returned Habakkuk to his place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And so, on the seventh day, the king came to mourn Daniel. And he came to the den, and gazed in, and behold, Daniel was sitting in the midst of the lions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And the king cried out with a loud voice, saying, &#8220;Great are you, O Lord, the God of Daniel.&#8221; And he pulled him out of the lions&#8217; den.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Furthermore, those who had been the cause of his downfall, he hurled into the den, and they were devoured in a moment before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Then the king said, &#8220;Let all the inhabitants of the whole earth fear the God of Daniel. For he is the Savior, working signs and miracles on earth, who has freed Daniel from the lions&#8217; den.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>9</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Artabae is an Egyptian unit of measure equivalent to 3.5 Roman measures or about 7 gallons.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Fiat means &#8220;let it be&#8221; or &#8220;let it be done&#8221; or &#8220;may it be done.&#8221; The form of the word is subjunctive, present tense.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The word filiis literally means sons, but is sometimes used to refer to a group of children, including both boys and girls. The male term is used to denote both males and female, as in mankind (or man), or brethren, because men are intended by God to be leaders in the Church, the family, and society.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> The wine is most likely mixed with water. The use of the term &#8220;mix the wine&#8221; might seem strange, but in ancient times they mixed wine with water. The alcohol purified the water and the water prevented the wine from too easily causing drunkenness.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> The king &#8220;occidit,&#8221; that is, slaughtered them. He did not interfecit, put them to death by execution. In other words, the king did not give them a trial, nor send them to prison to await formal execution. He merely ordered their immediate deaths by his soldiers.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> The word draco, dragon, can also mean snake. It most likely refers to some unusual type of animal kept by the Babylonians. This was not so unusual. The Roman leaders used to obtain and keep unusual animals from far off lands, including lions and other animals brought to Rome from Africa.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> The dragon&#8217;s death was an execution by authority (interfecit), whereas the priests where killed where they stood.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="8">
      <content> An insurrection is threatened whereby the other leaders in the kingdom would rise up and take power, then put the king to death by a formal execution. They were not threatening merely to kill the king.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="9">
      <content> The word mirabilia means wonders or miracles.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
</book>