<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="John 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and God was the Word.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He was with God in the beginning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>All things were made through Him, and nothing that was made was made without Him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Life was in Him, and Life was the light of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the light shines in the darkness, and the darkness did not comprehend it.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>There was a man sent by God, whose name was John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He arrived as a witness to offer testimony about the Light, so that all would believe through him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He was not the Light, but he was to offer testimony about the Light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The true Light, which illuminates every man, was coming into this world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He was in the world, and the world was made through him, and the world did not recognize him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He went to his own, and his own did not accept him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Yet whoever did accept him, those who believed in his name, he gave them the power to become the sons of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>These are born, not of blood, nor of the will of flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the Word became flesh, and he lived among us, and we saw his glory, glory like that of an only-begotten Son from the Father, full of grace and truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>John offers testimony about him, and he cries out, saying: &#8220;This is the one about whom I said: &#8216;He who is to come after me, has been placed ahead of me, because he existed before me.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And from his fullness, we all have received, even grace for grace.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For the law was given through Moses, but grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>No one ever saw God; the only-begotten Son, who is in the bosom of the Father, he himself has described him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And this is the testimony of John, when the Jews sent priests and Levites from Jerusalem to him, so that they might ask him, &#8220;Who are you?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And he confessed it and did not deny it; and what he confessed was: &#8220;I am not the Christ.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they questioned him: &#8220;Then what are you? Are you Elijah?&#8221; And he said, &#8220;I am not.&#8221; &#8220;Are you the Prophet?&#8221; And he answered, &#8220;No.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Therefore, they said to him: &#8220;Who are you, so that we may give an answer to those who sent us? What do you say about yourself?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He said, &#8220;I am a voice crying out in the desert, &#8216;Make straight the way of the Lord,&#8217; just as the prophet Isaiah said.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And some of those who had been sent were from among the Pharisees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And they questioned him and said to him, &#8220;Then why do you baptize, if you are not the Christ, and not Elijah, and not the Prophet?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>John answered them by saying: &#8220;I baptize with water. But in your midst stands one, whom you do not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The same is he who is to come after me, who has been placed ahead of me, the laces of whose shoes I am not worthy to loosen.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>These things happened in Bethania, across the Jordan, where John was baptizing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>On the next day, John saw Jesus coming toward him, and so he said: &#8220;Behold, the Lamb of God. Behold, he who takes away the sin of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>This is the one about whom I said, &#8216;After me arrives a man, who has been placed ahead of me, because he existed before me.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And I did not know him. Yet it is for this reason that I come baptizing with water: so that he may be made manifest in Israel.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And John offered testimony, saying: &#8220;For I saw the Spirit descending from heaven like a dove; and he remained upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And I did not know him. But he who sent me to baptize with water said to me: &#8216;He over whom you will see the Spirit descending and remaining upon him, this is the one who baptizes with the Holy Spirit.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And I saw, and I gave testimony: that this one is the Son of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The next day again, John was standing with two of his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And catching sight of Jesus walking, he said, &#8220;Behold, the Lamb of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And two disciples were listening to him speaking. And they followed Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then Jesus, turning around and seeing them following him, said to them, &#8220;What are you seeking?&#8221; And they said to him, &#8220;Rabbi (which means in translation, Teacher), where do you live?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>He said to them, &#8220;Come and see.&#8221; They went and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day. Now it was about the tenth hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who had heard about him from John and had followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>First, he found his brother Simon, and he said to him, &#8220;We have found the Messiah,&#8221; (which is translated as the Christ).</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And he led him to Jesus. And Jesus, gazing at him, said: &#8220;You are Simon, son of Jonah. You shall be called Cephas,&#8221; (which is translated as Peter).</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>On the next day, he wanted to go into Galilee, and he found Philip. And Jesus said to him, &#8220;Follow me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Now Philip was from Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Philip found Nathanael, and he said to him, &#8220;We have found the one about whom Moses wrote in the Law and the Prophets: Jesus, the son of Joseph, from Nazareth.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And Nathanael said to him, &#8220;Can anything good be from Nazareth?&#8221; Philip said to him, &#8220;Come and see.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Jesus saw Nathanael coming toward him, and he said about him, &#8220;Behold, an Israelite in whom truly there is no deceit.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Nathanael said to him, &#8220;From where do you know me?&#8221; Jesus responded and said to him, &#8220;Before Philip called you, when you were under the fig tree, I saw you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Nathanael answered him and said: &#8220;Rabbi, you are the Son of God. You are the King of Israel.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>7</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to him: &#8220;Because I told you that I saw you under the fig tree, you believe. Greater things than these, you will see.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And he said to him, &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, you will see heaven opened, and the Angels of God ascending and descending over the Son of man.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The words 'Deus' and 'Verbum' are both in the nominative case, so the text could be read as 'God was the Word,' or as 'the Word was God.'
&lt;br&gt;
However, word order in Latin is not entirely irrelevant, therefore this translation prefers &#8216;God was the Word,&#8217; over &#8216;the Word was God.&#8217; The same translation choice is made in the original Rheims New Testament of 1582.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Deus, Verbum, Vita represents Father, Son, Spirit.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The darkness represents the fallen angels and all evil in the world, which cannot understand the light of goodness. Notice that the light shines in the present tense, which is the closest tense to the timelessness of the Eternity of God, but the darkness is spoken of using the past tense, because fallen angels are trapped in Time.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> On one level of meaning, &#8216;ante me factus est&#8217; means &#8216;ranks ahead of me.&#8217; But there are other levels of meaning which that translation obscures. This is a frequent translation dilemma: one translation makes one level of meaning clearer, and other levels of meaning more obscure.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> This verse (particularly the last phrase) has several levels of meaning, and is somewhat obscure. This translation does not try to clear up every obscurity in Scripture, nor does it try to decide between various levels of meaning. On one level, it means that we have received grace upon grace; on another level, it means that we need grace from Christ for everything we do, even our cooperation with grace is a grace. And it seems to me that there are other levels of meaning also.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> I believe that John originally wrote his Gospel in Aramaic, the same language that Jesus most often used to teach, and that later John&#8217;s disciples translated it into Greek and added to it. That is why there are repeated references in the text saying &#8216;which is translated as.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="7">
      <content> He was able to perceive the truth so readily because there was no deceit in him.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="John 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And on the third day, a wedding was held in Cana of Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now Jesus was also invited to the wedding, with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when the wine was failing, the mother of Jesus said to him, &#8220;They have no wine.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Jesus said to her: &#8220;What is that to me and to you, woman? My hour has not yet arrived.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>His mother said to the servants, &#8220;Do whatever he tells you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now in that place, there were six stone water jars, for the purification ritual of the Jews, containing two or three measures each.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Jesus said to them, &#8220;Fill the water jars with water.&#8221; And they filled them to the very top.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And Jesus said to them, &#8220;Now draw from it, and carry it to the chief steward of the feast.&#8221; And they took it to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then, when the chief steward had tasted the water made into wine, since he did not know where it was from, for only the servants who had drawn the water knew, the chief steward called the groom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and he said to him: &#8220;Every man offers the good wine first, and then, when they have become inebriated, he offers what is worse. But you have kept the good wine until now.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This was the beginning of the signs that Jesus accomplished in Cana of Galilee, and it manifested his glory, and his disciples believed in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>After this, he descended to Capernaum, with his mother and his brothers and his disciples, but they did not remain there for many days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the Passover of the Jews was near, and so Jesus ascended to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he found, sitting in the temple, sellers of oxen and sheep and doves, and the moneychangers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when he had made something like a whip out of little cords, he drove them all out of the temple, including the sheep and the oxen. And he poured out the brass coins of the moneychangers, and he overturned their tables.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And to those who were selling doves, he said: &#8220;Take these things out of here, and do not make my Father&#8217;s house into a house of commerce.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And truly, his disciples were reminded that it is written: &#8220;Zeal for your house consumes me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then the Jews responded and said to him, &#8220;What sign can you show to us, that you may do these things?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to them, &#8220;Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then the Jews said, &#8220;This temple has been built up over forty-six years, and you will raise it up in three days?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>6</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Yet he was speaking about the Temple of his body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Therefore, when he had resurrected from the dead, his disciples were reminded that he had said this, and they believed in the Scriptures and in the word that Jesus had spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now while he was at Jerusalem during the Passover, on the day of the feast, many trusted in his name, seeing his signs that he was accomplishing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But Jesus did not trust himself to them, because he himself had knowledge of all persons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and because he had no need of anyone to offer testimony about a man. For he knew what was within a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Mary is saying that they lack the wine of a true Sacrament of marriage, for all they have is the water of an Old Testament (natural) marriage.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Jesus replies that He has not yet died on the Cross, which is the source of all the Sacraments. But she knows that time is no obstacle to God.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> Jesus turned the water of the Old Testament marriage into the wine of the New Testament marriage.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> The word &#8216;Solvite&#8217; is not so much &#8216;destroy&#8217; as it is to loosen or release or set free. Jesus is referring primarily to his own death, which is not his destruction, but the separation of his soul from his body, a kind of loosening or release.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> The length of time, 46 years, is divided into 40 plus 6 providentially. The 46 years is counted as the 46th Passover since the completion of the rebuilding of the Temple Sanctuary, which took 1.5 years. Josephus tell us that the Temple more generally, not merely the Sanctuary alone, took 8 years. Subtracting 1.5 years gives us 6.5 years: the length of time from the completion of the Sanctuary (at which time the rebuilt Temple was consecrated to God and the count of the years began) to the completion of the other buildings related to the Sanctuary. Then 40 more years are counted until Christ cleansed the temple by driving out the buyers and sellers.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="6">
      <content> Since Jesus was referring to his body as a temple, of which the temple building is merely a symbol, this passage also refers symbolically to the length of time since the Immaculate Conception. This was now the 46th Passover since the Immaculate Conception, when God began to build the temple of Christ&#8217;s body by first building the temple of Mary&#8217;s body, in which God dwelt for 9 months (in the womb).</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="John 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now there was a man among the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a leader of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He went to Jesus at night, and he said to him: &#8220;Rabbi, we know that you have arrived as a teacher from God. For no one would be able to accomplish these signs, which you accomplish, unless God were with him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to him, &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, unless one has been reborn anew, he is not able to see the kingdom of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Nicodemus said to him: &#8220;How could a man be born when he is old? Surely, he cannot enter a second time into his mother&#8217;s womb to be reborn?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Jesus responded: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, unless one has been reborn by water and the Holy Spirit, he is not able to enter into the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>What is born of the flesh is flesh, and what is born of the Spirit is spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>You should not be amazed that I said to you: You must be born anew.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The Spirit inspires where he wills. And you hear his voice, but you do not know where he comes from, or where he is going. So it is with all who are born of the Spirit.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Nicodemus responded and said to him, &#8220;How are these things able to be accomplished?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to him: &#8220;You are a teacher in Israel, and you are ignorant of these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, that we speak about what we know, and we testify about what we have seen. But you do not accept our testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If I have spoken to you about earthly things, and you have not believed, then how will you believe, if I will speak to you about heavenly things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And no one has ascended to heaven, except the one who descended from heaven: the Son of man who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the desert, so also must the Son of man be lifted up,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>so that whoever believes in him may not perish, but may have eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For God so loved the world that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that all who believe in him may not perish, but may have eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For God did not send his Son into the world, in order to judge the world, but in order that the world may be saved through him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whoever believes in him is not judged. But whoever does not believe is already judged, because he does not believe in the name of the only-begotten Son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And this is the judgment: that the Light has come into the world, and men loved darkness more than light. For their works were evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For everyone who does evil hates the Light and does not go toward the Light, so that his works may not be corrected.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But whoever acts in truth goes toward the Light, so that his works may be manifested, because they have been accomplished in God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>After these things, Jesus and his disciples went into the land of Judea. And he was living there with them and baptizing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now John was also baptizing, at Aenon near Salim, because there was much water in that place. And they were arriving and being baptized.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For John had not yet been cast into prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then a dispute occurred between the disciples of John and the Jews, about purification.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And they went to John and said to him: &#8220;Rabbi, the one who was with you across the Jordan, about whom you offered testimony: behold, he is baptizing and everyone is going to him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>John responded and said: &#8220;A man is not able to receive anything, unless it has been given to him from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>You yourselves offer testimony for me that I said, &#8216;I am not the Christ,&#8217; but that I have been sent before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He who holds the bride is the groom. But the friend of the groom, who stands and listens to Him, rejoices joyfully at the voice of the groom. And so, this, my joy, has been fulfilled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He must increase, while I must decrease.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>He who comes from above, is above everything. He who is from below, is of the earth, and he speaks about the earth. He who comes from heaven is above everything.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And what he has seen and heard, about this he testifies. And no one accepts his testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Whoever has accepted his testimony has certified that God is truthful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For he whom God has sent speaks the words of God. For God does not give the Spirit by measure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The Father loves the Son, and he has given everything into his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Whoever believes in the Son has eternal life. But whoever is unbelieving toward the Son shall not see life; instead the wrath of God remains upon him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> I realize that this verse is translated using a dangling preposition, but it sounds more natural in conversation to leave it this way, whereas the grammatically correct alternative is awkward.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Jesus uses the first person plural here because He is referring to the work done by Himself and the Holy Spirit together.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="John 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And so, when Jesus realized that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus made more disciples and baptized more than John,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>(though Jesus himself was not baptizing, but only his disciples)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>he left behind Judea, and he traveled again to Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now he needed to cross through Samaria.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Therefore, he went into a city of Samaria which is called Sychar, near the estate which Jacob gave to his son Joseph.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And Jacob&#8217;s well was there. And so Jesus, being tired from the journey, was sitting in a certain way on the well. It was about the sixth hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>A woman of Samaria arrived to draw water. Jesus said to her, &#8220;Give me to drink.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For his disciples had gone into the city in order to buy food.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And so, that Samaritan woman said to him, &#8220;How is it that you, being a Jew, are requesting a drink from me, though I am a Samaritan woman?&#8221; For the Jews do not associate with the Samaritans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to her: &#8220;If you knew the gift of God, and who it is who is saying to you, &#8216;Give me to drink,&#8217; perhaps you would have made a request of him, and he would have given you living water.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The woman said to him: &#8220;Lord, you do not have anything with which to draw water, and the well is deep. From where, then, do you have living water?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Surely, you are not greater than our father Jacob, who gave us the well and who drank from it, with his sons and his cattle?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to her: &#8220;All who drink from this water will thirst again. But whoever shall drink from the water that I will give to him will not thirst for eternity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Instead, the water that I will give to him will become in him a fountain of water, springing up into eternal life.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The woman said to him, &#8220;Lord, give me this water, so that I may not thirst and may not come here to draw water.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesus said to her, &#8220;Go, call your husband, and return here.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The woman responded and said, &#8220;I have no husband.&#8221; Jesus said to her: &#8220;You have spoken well, in saying, &#8216;I have no husband.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For you have had five husbands, but he whom you have now is not your husband. You have spoken this in truth.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The woman said to him: &#8220;Lord, I see that you are a Prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Our fathers worshipped on this mountain, but you say that Jerusalem is the place where one ought to worship.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Jesus said to her: &#8220;Woman, believe me, the hour is coming when you shall worship the Father, neither on this mountain, nor in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>You worship what you do not know; we worship what we do know. For salvation is from the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But the hour is coming, and it is now, when true worshippers shall worship the Father in spirit and in truth. For the Father also seeks such persons who may worship him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>God is Spirit. And so, those who worship him must worship in spirit and in truth.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The woman said to him: &#8220;I know that the Messiah is coming (who is called the Christ). And then, when he will have arrived, he will announce everything to us.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus said to her: &#8220;I am he, the one who is speaking with you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And then his disciples arrived. And they wondered that he was speaking with the woman. Yet no one said: &#8220;What are you seeking?&#8221; or, &#8220;Why are you talking with her?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And so the woman left behind her water jar and went into the city. And she said to the men there:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>&#8220;Come and see a man who has told me all the things that I have done. Is he not the Christ?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Therefore, they went out of the city and came to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Meanwhile, the disciples petitioned him, saying, &#8220;Rabbi, eat.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But he said to them, &#8220;I have food to eat which you do not know.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Therefore, the disciples said to one another, &#8220;Could someone have brought him something to eat?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus said to them: &#8220;My food is to do the will of the One who sent me, so that I may perfect his work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Do you not say, &#8216;There are still four months, and then the harvest arrives?&#8217; Behold, I say to you: Lift up your eyes and look at the countryside; for it is already ripe for the harvest.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For he who reaps, receives wages and gathers fruit unto eternal life, so that both he who sows and he who reaps may rejoice together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For in this the word is true: that it is one who sows, and it is another who reaps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>I have sent you to reap that for which you did not labor. Others have labored, and you have entered into their labors.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now many of the Samaritans from that city believed in him, because of the word of the woman who was offering testimony: &#8220;For he told me all the things that I have done.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Therefore, when the Samaritans had come to him, they petitioned him to lodge there. And he lodged there for two days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And many more believed in him, because of his own word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And they said to the woman: &#8220;Now we believe, not because of your speech, but because we ourselves have heard him, and so we know that he is truly the Savior of the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then, after two days, he departed from there, and he traveled into Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>For Jesus himself offered testimony that a Prophet has no honor in his own country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And so, when he had arrived in Galilee, the Galileans received him, because they had seen all that he had done at Jerusalem, in the day of the feast. For they also went to the feast day.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Then he went again into Cana of Galilee, where he made water into wine. And there was a certain ruler, whose son was sick at Capernaum.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Since he had heard that Jesus came to Galilee from Judea, he sent to him and begged him to come down and heal his son. For he was beginning to die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to him, &#8220;Unless you have seen signs and wonders, you do not believe.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>The ruler said to him, &#8220;Lord, come down before my son dies.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Jesus said to him, &#8220;Go, your son lives.&#8221; The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him, and so he went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Then, as he was going down, his servants met him. And they reported to him, saying that his son was alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Therefore, he asked them at which hour he had become better. And they said to him, &#8220;Yesterday, at the seventh hour, the fever left him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Then the father realized that it was at the same hour that Jesus said to him, &#8220;Your son lives.&#8221; And both he and his entire household believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>This next sign was the second that Jesus accomplished, after he had arrived in Galilee from Judea.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The verse literally says &#8216;white&#8217; rather than &#8216;ripe,&#8217; with whiteness indicating that the harvest is ready. And this is probably not a literal whiteness to the grain, but rather a lighter color to the ripe grain fields.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> They welcomed him in Galilee, having seen signs in Judea, therefore, as a prophet, He was accepted for signs he did in another region, not for what he had done in Galilee.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5" preferred_title="John 5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After these things, there was a feast day of the Jews, and so Jesus ascended to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now at Jerusalem is the Pool of Evidence, which in Hebrew is known as the Place of Mercy; it has five porticos.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Along these lay a great multitude of the sick, the blind, the lame, and the withered, waiting for the movement of the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now at times an Angel of the Lord would descend into the pool, and so the water was moved. And whoever descended first into the pool, after the motion of the water, he was healed of whatever infirmity held him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And there was a certain man in that place, having been in his infirmity for thirty-eight years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then, when Jesus had seen him reclining, and when he realized that he had been afflicted for a long time, he said to him, &#8220;Do you want to be healed?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The invalid answered him: &#8220;Lord, I do not have any man to put me in the pool, when the water has been stirred. For as I am going, another descends ahead of me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Jesus said to him, &#8220;Rise, take up your stretcher, and walk.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And immediately the man was healed. And he took up his stretcher and walked. Now this day was the Sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews said to the one who had been healed: &#8220;It is the Sabbath. It is not lawful for you to take up your stretcher.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He answered them, &#8220;The one who healed me, he said to me, &#8216;Take up your stretcher and walk.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore, they questioned him, &#8220;Who is that man, who said to you, &#8216;Take up your bed and walk?&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But the one who had been given health did not know who it was. For Jesus had turned aside from the crowd gathered in that place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Afterwards, Jesus found him in the temple, and he said to him: &#8220;Behold, you have been healed. Do not choose to sin further, otherwise something worse may happen to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>This man went away, and he reported to the Jews that it was Jesus who had given him health.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Because of this, the Jews were persecuting Jesus, for he was doing these things on the Sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But Jesus answered them, &#8220;Even now, my Father is working, and I am working.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And so, because of this, the Jews were seeking to kill him even more so. For not only did he break the Sabbath, but he even said that God was his Father, making himself equal to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then Jesus responded and said to them: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, the Son is not able to do anything of himself, but only what he has seen the Father doing. For whatever he does, even this does the Son do, similarly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For the Father loves the Son, and he shows him all that he himself does. And greater works than these will he show him, so much so that you shall wonder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For just as the Father raises the dead and gives life, so also does the Son give life to whomever he wills.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For the Father does not judge anyone. But he has given all judgment to the Son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>so that all may honor the Son, just as they honor the Father. Whoever does not honor the Son, does not honor the Father who sent him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, that whoever hears my word, and believes in him who sent me, has eternal life, and he does not go into judgment, but instead he crosses from death into life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, that the hour is coming, and it is now, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God; and those who hear it shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For just as the Father has life in himself, so also has he granted to the Son to have life in himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And he has given him the authority to accomplish judgment. For he is the Son of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Do not be amazed at this. For the hour is coming in which all who are in the grave shall hear the voice of the Son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And those who have done good shall go forth to the resurrection of life. Yet truly, those who have done evil shall go to the resurrection of judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I am not able to do anything of myself. As I hear, so do I judge. And my judgment is just. For I do not seek my own will, but the will of him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>If I offer testimony about myself, my testimony is not true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>There is another who offers testimony about me, and I know that the testimony which he offers about me is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>You sent to John, and he offered testimony to the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But I do not accept testimony from man. Instead, I say these things, so that you may be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>He was a burning and shining light. So you were willing, at the time, to exult in his light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But I hold a greater testimony than that of John. For the works which the Father has given to me, so that I may complete them, these works themselves that I do, offer testimony about me: that the Father has sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And the Father who has sent me has himself offered testimony about me. And you have never heard his voice, nor have you beheld his appearance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And you do not have his word abiding in you. For the one whom he sent, the same you would not believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Study the Scriptures. For you think that in them you have eternal life. And yet they also offer testimony about me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And you are not willing to come to me, so that you may have life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>I do not accept glory from men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>But I know you, that you do not have the love of God within you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>I have come in the name of my Father, and you do not accept me. If another will arrive in his own name, him you will accept.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>How are you able to believe, you who accept glory from one another and yet do not seek the glory that is from God alone?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Do not consider that I might accuse you with the Father. There is one who accuses you, Moses, in whom you hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>For if you were believing in Moses, perhaps you would believe in me also. For he wrote about me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>But if you do not believe by his writings, how will you believe by my words?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word Probatica in Latin certainly refers to evidence or proof of something. This pool was proof of the existence of Angels. In Hebrew, the term is most likely 'Bethesda' (Place of Mercy). The five porticos are symbolic of the Five Wounds of Christ, which have the power to heal us in body and soul.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> This last part refers to the Antichrist. Those who reject Christ, who comes in the name of the Father, will accept the Antichrist, who exalts himself and who comes in his own name.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6" preferred_title="John 6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After these things, Jesus traveled across the sea of Galilee, which is the Sea of Tiberias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And a great multitude was following him, for they saw the signs that he was accomplishing toward those who were infirm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus went onto a mountain, and he sat down there with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now the Passover, the feast day of the Jews, was near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And so, when Jesus had lifted up his eyes and had seen that a very great multitude came to him, he said to Philip, &#8220;From where should we buy bread, so that these may eat?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But he said this to test him. For he himself knew what he would do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Philip answered him, &#8220;Two hundred denarii of bread would not be sufficient for each of them to receive even a little.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>One of his disciples, Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, said to him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>&#8220;There is a certain boy here, who has five barley loaves and two fish. But what are these among so many?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Jesus said, &#8220;Have the men sit down to eat.&#8221; Now, there was much grass in that place. And so the men, in number about five thousand, sat down to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus took the bread, and when he had given thanks, he distributed it to those who were sitting down to eat; similarly also, from the fish, as much as they wanted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then, when they were filled, he said to his disciples, &#8220;Gather the fragments that are left over, lest they be lost.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And so they gathered, and they filled twelve baskets with the fragments of the five barley loaves, which were left over from those who had eaten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore, those men, when they had seen that Jesus had accomplished a sign, they said, &#8220;Truly, this one is the Prophet who is to come into the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And so, when he realized that they were going to come and take him away and make him king, Jesus fled back to the mountain, by himself alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then, when evening arrived, his disciples descended to the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when they had climbed into a boat, they went across the sea to Capernaum. And darkness had now arrived, and Jesus had not returned to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then the sea was stirred up by a great wind that was blowing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And so, when they had rowed about twenty-five or thirty stadia, they saw Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing near to the boat, and they were afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But he said to them: &#8220;It is I. Do not be afraid.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, they were willing to receive him into the boat. But immediately the boat was at the land to which they were going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>On the next day, the crowd which was standing across the sea saw that there were no other small boats in that place, except one, and that Jesus had not entered into the boat with his disciples, but that his disciples had departed alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Yet truly, other boats came over from Tiberias, next to the place where they had eaten the bread after the Lord gave thanks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore, when the crowd had seen that Jesus was not there, nor his disciples, they climbed into the small boats, and they went to Capernaum, seeking Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And when they had found him across the sea, they said to him, &#8220;Rabbi, when did you come here?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus answered them and said: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, you seek me, not because you have seen signs, but because you have eaten from the bread and were satisfied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Do not work for food that perishes, but for that which endures to eternal life, which the Son of man will give to you. For God the Father has sealed him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Therefore, they said to him, &#8220;What should we do, so that we may labor in the works of God?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to them, &#8220;This is the work of God, that you believe in him whom he sent.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And so they said to him: &#8220;Then what sign will you do, so that we may see it and believe in you? What will you work?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Our fathers ate manna in the desert, just as it has been written, &#8216;He gave them bread from heaven to eat.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to them: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, Moses did not give you bread from heaven, but my Father gives you the true bread from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>For the bread of God is he who descends from heaven and gives life to the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And so they said to him, &#8220;Lord, give us this bread always.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them: &#8220;I am the bread of life. Whoever comes to me shall not hunger, and whoever believes in me shall never thirst.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But I say to you, that even though you have seen me, you do not believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>All that the Father gives to me shall come to me. And whoever comes to me, I will not cast out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For I descended from heaven, not to do my own will, but the will of him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Yet this is the will of the Father who sent me: that I should lose nothing out of all that he has given to me, but that I should raise them up on the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>So then, this is the will of my Father who sent me: that everyone who sees the Son and believes in him may have eternal life, and I will raise him up on the last day.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews murmured about him, because he had said: &#8220;I am the living bread, who descended from heaven.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And they said: &#8220;Is this not Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? Then how can he say: &#8216;For I descended from heaven?&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And so Jesus responded and said to them: &#8220;Do not choose to murmur among yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>No one is able to come to me, unless the Father, who has sent me, has drawn him. And I will raise him up on the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>It has been written in the Prophets: &#8216;And they shall all be taught by God.&#8217; Everyone who has listened and learned from the Father comes to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Not that anyone has seen the Father, except he who is from God; this one has seen the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, whoever believes in me has eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>I am the bread of life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Your fathers ate manna in the desert, and they died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>This is the bread which descends from heaven, so that if anyone will eat from it, he may not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>I am the living bread, who descended from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>If anyone eats from this bread, he shall live in eternity. And the bread that I will give is my flesh, for the life of the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews debated among themselves, saying, &#8220;How can this man give us his flesh to eat?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>And so, Jesus said to them: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, unless you eat the flesh of the Son of man and drink his blood, you will not have life in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Whoever eats my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life, and I will raise him up on the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>For my flesh is true food, and my blood is true drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>Whoever eats my flesh and drinks my blood abides in me, and I in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Just as the living Father has sent me and I live because of the Father, so also whoever eats me, the same shall live because of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>This is the bread that descends from heaven. It is not like the manna that your fathers ate, for they died. Whoever eats this bread shall live forever.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>He said these things when he was teaching in the synagogue at Capernaum.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>Therefore, many of his disciples, upon hearing this, said: &#8220;This saying is difficult,&#8221; and, &#8220;Who is able to listen to it?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>But Jesus, knowing within himself that his disciples were murmuring about this, said to them: &#8220;Does this offend you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>Then what if you were to see the Son of man ascending to where he was before?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>It is the Spirit who gives life. The flesh does not offer anything of benefit. The words that I have spoken to you are spirit and life.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>But there are some among you who do not believe.&#8221; For Jesus knew from the beginning who were unbelieving and which one would betray him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>And so he said, &#8220;For this reason, I said to you that no one is able to come to me, unless it has been given to him by my Father.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>After this, many of his disciples went back, and they no longer walked with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to the twelve, &#8220;Do you also want to go away?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>Then Simon Peter answered him: &#8220;Lord, to whom would we go? You have the words of eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>And we have believed, and we recognize that you are the Christ, the Son of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>Jesus answered them: &#8220;Have I not chosen you twelve? And yet one among you is a devil.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>Now he was speaking about Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon. For this one, even though he was one of the twelve, was about to betray him.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Notice that coming to Jesus is not as effective as believing in him. The one who comes to him shall not hunger, but those who believe shall not thirst ever. The world umquam is added because coming to him is not enough to be satisfied forever in eternity; one must also believe.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The verb &#8216;descendi&#8217; is here first person singular perfect active indicative, not infinitive, because the phrase &#8216;Ego sum&#8217; (I am) in effect makes the word &#8216;qui&#8217; (who) first person singular.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The use of the word &#8216;docibiles&#8217; here is unusual. It could also be translated as &#8216;And they shall all be students of God.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> Without the grace and cooperation of the Holy Spirit, the Eucharist will not benefit those who receive it. The graces that come from receiving the Eucharist are received by a response to the graces of the Spirit, who gives life through the Eucharist.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7" preferred_title="John 7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then, after these things, Jesus was walking in Galilee. For he was not willing to walk in Judea, because the Jews were seeking to kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now the feast day of the Jews, the Feast of Tabernacles, was near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And his brothers said to him: &#8220;Move away from here and go into Judea, so that your disciples there may also see your works that you do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Of course, no one does anything in secret, but he himself seeks to be in the public view. Since you do these things, manifest yourself to the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For neither did his brothers believe in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to them: &#8220;My time has not yet come; but your time is always at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The world cannot hate you. But it hates me, because I offer testimony about it, that its works are evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>You may go up to this feast day. But I am not going up to this feast day, because my time has not yet been fulfilled.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When he had said these things, he himself remained in Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But after his brothers went up, then he also went up to the feast day, not openly, but as if in secret.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews were seeking him on the feast day, and they were saying, &#8220;Where is he?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And there was much murmuring in the crowd concerning him. For certain ones were saying, &#8220;He is good.&#8221; But others were saying, &#8220;No, for he seduces the crowds.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Yet no one was speaking openly about him, out of fear of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then, about the middle of the feast, Jesus ascended into the temple, and he was teaching.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Jews wondered, saying: &#8220;How does this one know letters, though he has not been taught?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesus responded to them and said: &#8220;My doctrine is not of me, but of him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If anyone has chosen to do his will, then he will realize, about the doctrine, whether it is from God, or whether I am speaking from myself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whoever speaks from himself seeks his own glory. But whoever seeks the glory of him who sent him, this one is true, and injustice is not in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Did not Moses give you the law? And yet not one among you keeps the law!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Why are you seeking to kill me?&#8221; The crowd responded and said: &#8220;You must have a demon. Who is seeking to kill you?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to them: &#8220;One work have I done, and you all wonder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For Moses gave you circumcision, (not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers) and on the Sabbath you circumcise a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If a man can receive circumcision on the Sabbath, so that the law of Moses may not be broken, why are you indignant toward me, because I have made a man whole on the Sabbath?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Do not judge according to appearances, but instead judge a just judgment.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Therefore, some of those from Jerusalem said: &#8220;Is he not the one whom they are seeking to kill?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And behold, he is speaking openly, and they say nothing to him. Could the leaders have decided that it is true this one is the Christ?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But we know him and where he is from. And when the Christ has arrived, no one will know where he is from.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus cried out in the temple, teaching and saying: &#8220;You know me, and you also know where I am from. And I have not arrived of myself, but he who sent me is true, and him you do not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>I know him. For I am from him, and he has sent me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Therefore, they were seeking to apprehend him, and yet no one laid hands on him, because his hour had not yet come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But many among the crowd believed in him, and they were saying, &#8220;When the Christ arrives, will he perform more signs than this man does?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The Pharisees heard the crowd murmuring these things about him. And the leaders and the Pharisees sent attendants to apprehend him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to them: &#8220;For a brief time, I am still with you, and then I am going to him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>You shall seek me, and you will not find me. And where I am, you are not able to go.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And so the Jews said among themselves: &#8220;Where is this place to which he will go, such that we will not find him? Will he go to those dispersed among the Gentiles and teach the Gentiles?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>What is this word that he spoke, &#8216;You will seek me and you will not find me; and where I am, you are not able to go?&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then, on the last great day of the feast, Jesus was standing and crying out, saying: &#8220;If anyone thirsts, let him come to me and drink:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>whoever believes in me, just as Scripture says, &#8216;From his chest shall flow rivers of living water.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now he said this about the Spirit, which those who believe in him would soon be receiving. For the Spirit had not yet been given, because Jesus had not yet been glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Therefore, some from that crowd, when they had heard these words of his, were saying, &#8220;This one truly is the Prophet.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Others were saying, &#8220;He is the Christ.&#8221; Yet certain ones were saying: &#8220;Does the Christ come from Galilee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Does Scripture not say that the Christ comes from the offspring of David and from Bethlehem, the town where David was?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And so there arose a dissension among the multitude because of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Now certain ones among them wanted to apprehend him, but no one laid hands upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Therefore, the attendants went to the high priests and the Pharisees. And they said to them, &#8220;Why have you not brought him?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>The attendants responded, &#8220;Never has a man spoken like this man.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And so the Pharisees answered them: &#8220;Have you also been seduced?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Have any of the leaders believed in him, or any of the Pharisees?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>But this crowd, which does not know the law, they are accursed.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Nicodemus, the one who came to him by night and who was one of them, said to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>&#8220;Does our law judge a man, unless it has first heard him and has known what he has done?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>They responded and said to him: &#8220;Are you also a Galilean? Study the Scriptures, and see that a prophet does not arise from Galilee.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>And each one returned to his own house.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;ventre&#8217; is a general term in Latin used to refer to the inner organs, or the inner parts of the body. It is used metaphorically in many instances. It can be properly translated as &#8216;belly&#8217; or &#8216;heart&#8217; or &#8216;inner self&#8217; or &#8216;chest.&#8217; In this case, the living waters that flow from Christ&#8217;s chest, flow from the wound in his side. This event is a living symbol of the graces that flow from the Sacraments.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The word &#8216;Pontifices&#8217; is the plural of &#8216;Pontifex,&#8217; which means high priest. The word is used in the plural because there was one high priest, plus a former high priest who had been deposed by the Romans. But both wielded authority over the Jews, because the position of high priest was supposed to be for life.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8" preferred_title="John 8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But Jesus continued on to the Mount of Olives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And early in the morning, he went again to the temple; and all the people came to him. And sitting down, he taught them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now the scribes and Pharisees brought forward a woman caught in adultery, and they stood her in front of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And they said to him: &#8220;Teacher, this woman was just now caught in adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And in the law, Moses commanded us to stone such a one. Therefore, what do you say?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But they were saying this to test him, so that they might be able to accuse him. Then Jesus bent down and wrote with his finger on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And then, when they persevered in questioning him, he stood upright and said to them, &#8220;Let whoever is without sin among you be the first to cast a stone at her.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And bending down again, he wrote on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But upon hearing this, they went away, one by one, beginning with the eldest. And Jesus alone remained, with the woman standing in front of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Jesus, raising himself up, said to her: &#8220;Woman, where are those who accused you? Has no one condemned you?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And she said, &#8220;No one, Lord.&#8221; Then Jesus said: &#8220;Neither will I condemn you. Go, and now do not choose to sin anymore.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Jesus spoke to them again, saying: &#8220;I am the light of the world. Whoever follows me does not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And so the Pharisees said to him, &#8220;You offer testimony about yourself; your testimony is not true.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to them: &#8220;Even though I offer testimony about myself, my testimony is true, for I know where I came from and where I am going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>You judge according to the flesh. I do not judge anyone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when I do judge, my judgment is true. For I am not alone, but it is I and he who sent me: the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And it is written in your law that the testimony of two men is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I am one who offers testimony about myself, and the Father who sent me offers testimony about me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore, they said to him, &#8220;Where is your Father?&#8221; Jesus answered: &#8220;You know neither me, nor my Father. If you did know me, perhaps you would know my Father also.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Jesus spoke these words at the treasury, while teaching in the temple. And no one apprehended him, because his hour had not yet come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus again spoke to them: &#8220;I am going, and you shall seek me. And you will die in your sin. Where I am going, you are not able to go.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And so the Jews said, &#8220;Is he going to kill himself, for he said: &#8216;Where I am going, you are not able to go?&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And he said to them: &#8220;You are from below. I am from above. You are of this world. I am not of this world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore, I said to you, that you will die in your sins. For if you will not believe that I am, you will die in your sin.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And so they said to him, &#8220;Who are you?&#8221; Jesus said to them: &#8220;The Beginning, who is also speaking to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I have much to say about you and to judge. But he who sent me is true. And what I have heard from him, this I speak within the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And they did not realize that he was calling God his Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And so Jesus said to them: &#8220;When you will have lifted up the Son of man, then you shall realize that I am, and that I do nothing of myself, but just as the Father has taught me, so do I speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And he who sent me is with me, and he has not abandoned me alone. For I always do what is pleasing to him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>As he was speaking these things, many believed in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to those Jews who believed in him: &#8220;If you will abide in my word, you will truly be my disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And you shall know the truth, and the truth shall set you free.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>They answered him: &#8220;We are the offspring of Abraham, and we have never been a slave to anyone. How can you say, &#8216;You shall be set free?&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus answered them: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, that everyone who commits sin is a slave of sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now the slave does not abide in the house for eternity. Yet the Son does abide in eternity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Therefore, if the Son has set you free, then you will truly be free.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>I know that you are sons of Abraham. But you are seeking to kill me, because my word has not taken hold in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>I speak what I have seen with my Father. And you do what you have seen with your father.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>They responded and said to him, &#8220;Abraham is our father.&#8221; Jesus said to them: &#8220;If you are the sons of Abraham, then do the works of Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>But now you are seeking to kill me, a man who has spoken the truth to you, which I have heard from God. This is not what Abraham did.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>You do the works of your father.&#8221; Therefore, they said to him: &#8220;We were not born out of fornication. We have one father: God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them: &#8220;If God were your father, certainly you would love me. For I proceeded and came from God. For I did not come from myself, but he sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Why do you not recognize my speech? It is because you are not able to hear my word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>You are of your father, the devil. And you will carry out the desires of your father. He was a murderer from the beginning. And he did not stand in the truth, because the truth is not in him. When he speaks a lie, he speaks it from his own self. For he is a liar, and the father of lies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>But if I speak the truth, you do not believe me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Which of you can convict me of sin? If I speak the truth to you, why do you not believe me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Whoever is of God, hears the words of God. For this reason, you do not hear them: because you are not of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews responded and said to him, &#8220;Are we not correct in saying that you are a Samaritan, and that you have a demon?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Jesus responded: &#8220;I do not have a demon. But I honor my Father, and you have dishonored me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>But I am not seeking my own glory. There is One who seeks and judges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, if anyone will have kept my word, he will not see death for eternity.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews said: &#8220;Now we know that you have a demon. Abraham is dead, and the Prophets; and yet you say, &#8216;If anyone will have kept my word, he shall not taste death for eternity.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Are you greater than our father Abraham, who is dead? And the prophets are dead. So who do you make yourself to be?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Jesus responded: &#8220;If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing. It is my Father who glorifies me. And you say about him that he is your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>And yet you have not known him. But I know him. And if I were to say that I do not know him, then I would be like you, a liar. But I know him, and I keep his word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Abraham, your father, rejoiced that he might see my day; he saw it and was glad.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>And so the Jews said to him, &#8220;You have not yet reached fifty years, and you have seen Abraham?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Jesus said to them, &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, before Abraham was made, I am.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>Therefore, they took up stones to cast at him. But Jesus hid himself, and he departed from the temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Jesus wrote on the earth with his finger because the ten commandments were written on tablets of stone from the earth with the finger of God. This woman broke one of the ten commandments. Jesus wrote twice on the ground symbolizing the two new commandments, to love God and love neighbor.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9" preferred_title="John 9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And Jesus, while passing by, saw a man blind from birth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And his disciples asked him, &#8220;Rabbi, who sinned, this man or his parents, that he would be born blind?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Jesus responded: &#8220;Neither this man nor his parents sinned, but it was so that the works of God would be made manifest in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I must work the works of him who sent me, while it is day: the night is coming, when no one is able to work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>When he had said these things, he spat on the ground, and he made clay from the spittle, and he smeared the clay over his eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And he said to him: &#8220;Go, wash in the pool of Siloam&#8221; (which is translated as: one who has been sent). Therefore, he went away and washed, and he returned, seeing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And so the bystanders and those who had seen him before, when he was a beggar, said, &#8220;Is this not the one who was sitting and begging?&#8221; Some said, &#8220;This is he.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But others said, &#8220;Certainly not, but he is similar to him.&#8221; Yet truly, he himself said, &#8220;I am he.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore, they said to him, &#8220;How were your eyes opened?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He responded: &#8220;That man who is called Jesus made clay, and he anointed my eyes and said to me, &#8216;Go to the pool of Siloam and wash.&#8217; And I went, and I washed, and I see.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they said to him, &#8220;Where is he?&#8221; He said, &#8220;I do not know.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They brought the one who had been blind to the Pharisees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now it was the Sabbath, when Jesus made the clay and opened his eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Therefore, again the Pharisees questioned him as to how he had seen. And he said to them, &#8220;He placed clay over my eyes, and I washed, and I see.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And so certain Pharisees said: &#8220;This man, who does not keep the Sabbath, is not from God.&#8221; But others said, &#8220;How could a sinful man accomplish these signs?&#8221; And there was a schism among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore, they spoke again to the blind man, &#8220;What do you say about him who opened your eyes?&#8221; Then he said, &#8220;He is a Prophet.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews did not believe, about him, that he had been blind and had seen, until they called the parents of him who had seen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And they questioned them, saying: &#8220;Is this your son, whom you say was born blind? Then how is it that he now sees?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>His parents responded to them and said: &#8220;We know that this is our son and that he was born blind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But how it is that he now sees, we do not know. And who opened his eyes, we do not know. Ask him. He is old enough. Let him speak for himself.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>His parents said these things because they were afraid of the Jews. For the Jews had already conspired, so that if anyone were to confess him to be the Christ, he would be expelled from the synagogue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>It was for this reason that his parents said: &#8220;He is old enough. Ask him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore, they again called the man who had been blind, and they said to him: &#8220;Give glory to God. We know that this man is a sinner.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And so he said to them: &#8220;If he is a sinner, I do not know it. One thing I do know, that although I was blind, now I see.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then they said to him: &#8220;What did he do to you? How did he open your eyes?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He answered them: &#8220;I have already told you, and you heard it. Why do you want to hear it again? Do you also want to become his disciples?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Therefore, they cursed him and said: &#8220;You be his disciple. But we are disciples of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>We know that God spoke to Moses. But this man, we do not know where he is from.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The man responded and said to them: &#8220;Now in this is a wonder: that you do not know where he is from, and yet he has opened my eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And we know that God does not hear sinners. But if anyone is a worshipper of God and does his will, then he heeds him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>From ancient times, it has not been heard that anyone has opened the eyes of someone born blind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Unless this man were of God, he would not be able to do any such thing.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>They responded and said to him, &#8220;You were born entirely in sins, and you would teach us?&#8221; And they cast him out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Jesus heard that they had cast him out. And when he had found him, he said to him, &#8220;Do you believe in the Son of God?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>He responded and said, &#8220;Who is he, Lord, so that I may believe in him?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Jesus said to him, &#8220;You have both seen him, and he is the one who is speaking with you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And he said, &#8220;I believe, Lord.&#8221; And falling prostrate, he worshipped him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And Jesus said, &#8220;I came into this world in judgment, so that those who do not see, may see; and so that those who see, may become blind.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And certain Pharisees, who were with him, heard this, and they said to him, &#8220;Are we also blind?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Jesus said to them: &#8220;If you were blind, you would not have sin. Yet now you say, &#8216;We see.&#8217; So your sin persists.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> In this context, &#8216;vicini&#8217; is not &#8216;neighbors&#8217; but &#8216;those standing near,&#8217; or &#8216;bystanders.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The phrasing of this last part, &#8216;Et abii, et lavi, et video,&#8217; sounds as if it might have been originally spoken in Latin. Perhaps this man spoke Latin, rather than the more common Aramaic. As a blind man, he would have been considered to be blind as a punishment for sin, and would therefore be excluded from being taught by the Jewish priests. So he would not have learned much Hebrew. Being excluded, to some extent, from Jewish society, he may have favored Latin as his spoken language. His other quoted words also sound very natural in Latin.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10" preferred_title="John 10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>&#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, he who does not enter through the door into the fold of the sheep, but climbs up by another way, he is a thief and a robber.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But he who enters through the door is the shepherd of the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>To him the doorkeeper opens, and the sheep hear his voice, and he calls his own sheep by name, and he leads them out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when he has sent out his sheep, he goes before them, and the sheep follow him, because they know his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But they do not follow a stranger; instead they flee from him, because they do not know the voice of strangers.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Jesus spoke this proverb to them. But they did not understand what he was saying to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus spoke to them again: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, that I am the door of the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>All others, as many as have come, are thieves and robbers, and the sheep did not listen to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I am the door. If anyone has entered through me, he will be saved. And he shall go in and go out, and he shall find pastures.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The thief does not come, except so that he may steal and slaughter and destroy. I have come so that they may have life, and have it more abundantly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I am the good Shepherd. The good Shepherd gives his life for his sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But the hired hand, and whoever is not a shepherd, to whom the sheep do not belong, he sees the wolf approaching, and he departs from the sheep and flees. And the wolf ravages and scatters the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the hired hand flees, because he is a hired hand and there is no concern for the sheep within him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I am the good Shepherd, and I know my own, and my own know me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>just as the Father knows me, and I know the Father. And I lay down my life for my sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And I have other sheep that are not of this fold, and I must lead them. They shall hear my voice, and there shall be one sheepfold and one shepherd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For this reason, the Father loves me: because I lay down my life, so that I may take it up again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>No one takes it away from me. Instead, I lay it down of my own accord. And I have the power to lay it down. And I have the power to take it up again. This is the commandment that I have received from my Father.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>A dissension occurred again among the Jews because of these words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then many of them were saying: &#8220;He has a demon or he is insane. Why do you listen him?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Others were saying: &#8220;These are not the words of someone who has a demon. How would a demon be able to open the eyes of the blind?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now it was the Feast of the Dedication at Jerusalem, and it was winter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And Jesus was walking in the temple, in the portico of Solomon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And so the Jews surrounded him and said to him: &#8220;How long will you hold our souls in suspense? If you are the Christ, tell us plainly.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Jesus answered them: &#8220;I speak to you, and you do not believe. The works that I do in the name of my Father, these offer testimony about me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But you do not believe, because you are not of my sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>My sheep hear my voice. And I know them, and they follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And I give them eternal life, and they shall not perish, for eternity. And no one shall seize them from my hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>What my Father gave to me is greater than all, and no one is able to seize from the hand of my Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I and the Father are one.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews took up stones, in order to stone him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Jesus answered them: &#8220;I have shown you many good works from my Father. For which of those works do you stone me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>The Jews answered him: &#8220;We do not stone you for a good work, but for blasphemy and because, though you are a man, you make yourself God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus responded to them: &#8220;Is it not written in your law, &#8216;I said: you are gods?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>If he called those to whom the word of God was given gods, and Scripture cannot be broken,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>why do you say, about him whom the Father has sanctified and sent into the world, &#8216;You have blasphemed,&#8217; because I said, &#8216;I am the Son of God?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>If I do not do the works of my Father, do not believe in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But if I do them, even if you are not willing to believe in me, believe the works, so that you may know and believe that the Father is in me, and I am in the Father.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Therefore, they sought to apprehend him, but he escaped from their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And he went again across the Jordan, to that place where John first was baptizing. And he lodged there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And many went out to him. And they were saying: &#8220;Indeed, John accomplished no signs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>But all things whatsoever that John said about this man were true.&#8221; And many believed in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> On one level of meaning, this verse refers to the Antichrist.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The verb in Latin is different here: the Father &#8216;novit&#8217; the Christ, but the Christ &#8216;agnosco&#8217; the Father, because the relationship between the Father, Son, and Spirit is asymmetrical. Also the verb used to say that Christ knows his sheep and his sheep know him is different from that used to refer to the Father-Son relationship, because the God-man relationship is fundamentally different from relationships within the Trinity.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11" preferred_title="John 11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now there was a certain sick man, Lazarus of Bethania, from the town of Mary and her sister Martha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Mary was the one who anointed the Lord with ointment and wiped his feet with her hair; her brother Lazarus was sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore, his sisters sent to him, saying: &#8220;Lord, behold, he whom you love is sick.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then, upon hearing this, Jesus said to them: &#8220;This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, so that the Son of God may be glorified by it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister Mary, and Lazarus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Even so, after he heard that he was sick, he then still remained in the same place for two days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then, after these things, he said to his disciples, &#8220;Let us go into Judea again.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The disciples said to him: &#8220;Rabbi, the Jews are even now seeking to stone you. And would you go there again?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Jesus responded: &#8220;Are there not twelve hours in the day? If anyone walks in the daylight, he does not stumble, because he sees the light of this world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But if he walks in the nighttime, he stumbles, because the light is not in him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He said these things, and after this, he said to them: &#8220;Lazarus our friend is sleeping. But I am going, so that I may awaken him from sleep.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And so his disciples said, &#8220;Lord, if he is sleeping, he shall be healthy.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But Jesus had spoken about his death. Yet they thought that he spoke about the repose of sleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus then said to them plainly, &#8220;Lazarus has died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And I am glad for your sake that I was not there, so that you may believe. But let us go to him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And then Thomas, who is called the Twin, said to his fellow disciples, &#8220;Let us go, too, so that we may die with him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And so Jesus went. And he found that he had already been in the tomb for four days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>(Now Bethania was near Jerusalem, about fifteen stadia.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary, so as to console them over their brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Therefore, Martha, when she heard that Jesus was arriving, went out to meet him. But Mary was sitting at home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And then Martha said to Jesus: &#8220;Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But even now, I know that whatever you will request from God, God will give to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus said to her, &#8220;Your brother shall rise again.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Martha said to him, &#8220;I know that he shall rise again, at the resurrection on the last day.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Jesus said to her: &#8220;I am the Resurrection and the Life. Whoever believes in me, even though he has died, he shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And everyone who lives and believes in me shall not die for eternity. Do you believe this?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>She said to him: &#8220;Certainly, Lord. I have believed that you are the Christ, the Son of the living God, who has come into this world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when she had said these things, she went and called her sister Mary quietly, saying, &#8220;The Teacher is here, and he is calling you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>When she heard this, she rose up quickly and went to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For Jesus had not yet arrived in the town. But he was still at that place where Martha had met him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews who were with her in the house and who were consoling her, when they had seen that Mary rose up quickly and went out, they followed her, saying, &#8220;She is going to the tomb, so that she may weep there.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Therefore, when Mary had arrived to where Jesus was, seeing him, she fell down at his feet, and she said to him. &#8220;Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And then, when Jesus saw her weeping, and the Jews who had arrived with her weeping, he groaned in spirit and became troubled.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And he said, &#8220;Where have you laid him?&#8221; They said to him, &#8220;Lord, come and see.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And Jesus wept.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Therefore, the Jews said, &#8220;See how much he loved him!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>But some of them said, &#8220;Would not he who opened the eyes of one born blind have been able to cause this man not to die?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus, again groaning from within himself, went to the tomb. Now it was a cave, and a stone had been placed over it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Jesus said, &#8220;Take away the stone.&#8221; Martha, the sister of him who had died, said to him, &#8220;Lord, by now it will smell, for this is the fourth day.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Jesus said to her, &#8220;Did I not say to you that if you believe, you shall see the glory of God?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Therefore, they took away the stone. Then, lifting up his eyes, Jesus said: &#8220;Father, I give thanks to you because you have heard me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And I know that you always hear me, but I have said this for the sake of the people who are standing nearby, so that they may believe that you have sent me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>When he had said these things, he cried in a loud voice, &#8220;Lazarus, come out.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And immediately, he who had been dead went forth, bound at the feet and hands with winding bands. And his face was bound with a separate cloth. Jesus said to them, &#8220;Release him and let him go.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Therefore, many of the Jews, who had come to Mary and Martha, and who had seen the things that Jesus did, believed in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>But certain ones among them went to the Pharisees and told them the things that Jesus had done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And so, the high priests and the Pharisees gathered a council, and they were saying: &#8220;What can we do? For this man accomplishes many signs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>If we leave him alone, in this way all will believe in him. And then the Romans will come and take away our place and our nation.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Then one of them, named Caiaphas, since he was the high priest that year, said to them: &#8220;You do not understand anything.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Nor do you realize that it is expedient for you that one man should die for the people, and that the entire nation should not perish.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Yet he did not say this from himself, but since he was the high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus would die for the nation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>And not only for the nation, but in order to gather together as one the children of God who have been dispersed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Therefore, from that day, they planned to put him to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>And so, Jesus no longer walked in public with the Jews. But he went into a region near the desert, to a city which is called Ephraim. And he lodged there with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Now the Passover of the Jews was near. And many from the countryside ascended to Jerusalem before the Passover, so that they might sanctify themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Therefore, they were seeking Jesus. And they conferred with one another, while standing in the temple: &#8220;What do you think? Will he come to the feast day?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>And the high priests and Pharisees had given an order, so that if anyone would know where he may be, he should reveal it, so that they might apprehend him.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Here the phrase &#8216;turbavit seipsum,&#8217; literally &#8216;he troubled himself,&#8217; which is an active tense paired with a reflective pronoun, is translated with the passive tense, &#8216;he because troubled&#8217;.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12" preferred_title="John 12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then six days before the Passover, Jesus went to Bethania, where Lazarus had died, whom Jesus raised up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And they made a dinner for him there. And Martha was ministering. And truly, Lazarus was one of those who were sitting at table with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And then Mary took twelve ounces of pure spikenard ointment, very precious, and she anointed the feet of Jesus, and she wiped his feet with her hair. And the house was filled with the fragrance of the ointment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then one of his disciples, Judas Iscariot, who was soon to betray him, said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>&#8220;Why was this ointment not sold for three hundred denarii and given to the needy?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now he said this, not out of concern for the needy, but because he was a thief and, since he held the purse, he used to carry what was put into it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But Jesus said: &#8220;Permit her, so that she may keep it against the day of my burial.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For the poor, you have with you always. But me, you do always not have.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now a great multitude of the Jews knew that he was in that place, and so they came, not so much because of Jesus, but so that they might see Lazarus, whom he had raised from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the leaders of the priests planned to put Lazarus to death also.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For many of the Jews, because of him, were going away and were believing in Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then, on the next day, the great crowd that had come to the feast day, when they had heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>took branches of palm trees, and they went ahead to meet him. And they were crying out: &#8220;Hosanna! Blessed is he who arrives in the name of the Lord, the king of Israel!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And Jesus found a small donkey, and he sat upon it, just as it is written:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>&#8220;Do not be afraid, daughter of Zion. Behold, your king arrives, sitting on the colt of a donkey.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>At first, his disciples did not realize these things. But when Jesus was glorified, then they remembered that these things were written about him, and that these things happened to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And so the crowd that had been with him, when he called Lazarus from the tomb and raised him from the dead, offered testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Because of this, too, the crowd went out to meet him. For they heard that he had accomplished this sign.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore, the Pharisees said among themselves: &#8220;Do you see that we are accomplishing nothing? Behold, the entire world has gone after him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now there were certain Gentiles among those who went up so that they might worship on the feast day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, these approached Philip, who was from Bethsaida of Galilee, and they petitioned him, saying: &#8220;Sir, we want to see Jesus.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Philip went and told Andrew. Next, Andrew and Philip told Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But Jesus answered them by saying: &#8220;The hour arrives when the Son of man shall be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, unless the grain of wheat falls to the ground and dies,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>it remains alone. But if it dies, it yields much fruit. Whoever loves his life, will lose it. And whoever hates his life in this world, preserves it unto eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>If anyone serves me, let him follow me. And where I am, there too my minister shall be. If anyone has served me, my Father will honor him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now my soul is troubled. And what should I say? Father, save me from this hour? But it is for this reason that I came to this hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Father, glorify your name!&#8221; And then a voice came from heaven, &#8220;I have glorified it, and I will glorify it again.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Therefore, the crowd, which was standing near and had heard it, said that it was like thunder. Others were saying, &#8220;An Angel was speaking with him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Jesus responded and said: &#8220;This voice came, not for my sake, but for your sakes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Now is the judgment of the world. Now will the prince of this world be cast out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And when I have been lifted up from the earth, I will draw all things to myself.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>(Now he said this, signifying what kind of death he would die.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>The crowd answered him: &#8220;We have heard, from the law, that the Christ remains forever. And so how can you say, &#8216;The Son of man must be lifted up?&#8217; Who is this Son of man?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to them: &#8220;For a brief time, the Light is among you. Walk while you have the Light, so that the darkness may not overtake you. But whoever walks in darkness does not know where is he going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>While you have the Light, believe in the Light, so that you may be sons of the Light.&#8221; Jesus spoke these things, and then he went away and hid himself from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And although he had done such great signs in their presence, they did not believe in him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>so that the word of the prophet Isaiah might be fulfilled, which says: &#8220;Lord, who has believed in our hearing? And to whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Because of this, they were not able to believe, for Isaiah said again:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>&#8220;He has blinded their eyes, and hardened their heart, so that they may not see with their eyes, and understand with their heart, and be converted: and then I would heal them.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>These things Isaiah said, when he saw his glory and was speaking about him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Yet truly, many of the leaders also believed in him. But because of the Pharisees, they did not confess him, so that they would not be cast out of the synagogue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>For they loved the glory of men more than the glory of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>But Jesus cried out and said: &#8220;Whoever believes in me, does not believe in me, but in him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And whoever sees me, sees him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>I have arrived as a light to the world, so that all who believe in me might not remain in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And if anyone has heard my words and not kept them, I do not judge him. For I did not come so that I may judge the world, but so that I may save the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Whoever despises me and does not accept my words has one who judges him. The word that I have spoken, the same shall judge him on the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>For I am not speaking from myself, but from the Father who sent me. He gave a commandment to me as to what I should say and how I should speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>And I know that his commandment is eternal life. Therefore, the things that I speak, just as the Father has said to me, so also do I speak.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The phrase &#8216;principes sacerdotum&#8217; means &#8216;chief priests&#8217; or &#8216;leaders of the priests.&#8217; Whereas, the word &#8216;Pontifices&#8217; refers to the high priests.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13" preferred_title="John 13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Before the feast day of the Passover, Jesus knew that the hour was approaching when he would pass from this world to the Father. And since he had always loved his own who were in the world, he loved them unto the end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when the meal had taken place, when the devil had now put it into the heart of Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon, to betray him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands and that he came from God and was going to God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>he rose up from the meal, and he set aside his vestments, and when he had received a towel, he wrapped it around himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Next he put water into a shallow bowl, and he began to wash the feet of the disciples and to wipe them with the towel with which he was wrapped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And then he came to Simon Peter. And Peter said to him, &#8220;Lord, would you wash my feet?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to him: &#8220;What I am doing, you do not now understand. But you shall understand it afterward.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Peter said to him, &#8220;You shall never wash my feet!&#8221; Jesus answered him, &#8220;If I do not wash you, you will have no place with me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Simon Peter said to him, &#8220;Then Lord, not only my feet, but also my hands and my head!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus said to him: &#8220;He who is washed need only wash his feet, and then he will be entirely clean. And you are clean, but not all.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For he knew which one would betray him. For this reason, he said, &#8220;You are not all clean.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And so, after he washed their feet and received his vestments, when he had sat down at table again, he said to them: &#8220;Do you know what I have done for you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>You call me Teacher and Lord, and you speak well: for so I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore, if I, your Lord and Teacher, have washed your feet, you also ought to wash the feet of one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For I have given you an example, so that just as I have done for you, so also should you do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, the servant is not greater than his Lord, and the apostle is not greater than he who sent him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If you understand this, you shall be blessed if you will do it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I am not speaking about all of you. I know those whom I have chosen. But this is so that the Scripture may be fulfilled, &#8216;He who eats bread with me shall lift up his heel against me.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I tell you this now, before it happens, so that when it has happened, you may believe that I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, whoever receives anyone whom I send, receives me. And whoever receives me, receives him who sent me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>When Jesus had said these things, he was troubled in spirit. And he bore witness by saying: &#8220;Amen, amen, I say to you, that one among you shall betray me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Therefore, the disciples looked around at one another, uncertain about whom he spoke.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And leaning against the bosom of Jesus was one of his disciples, the one whom Jesus loved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore, Simon Peter motioned to this one and said to him, &#8220;Who is it that he is speaking about?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And so, leaning against the chest of Jesus, he said to him, &#8220;Lord, who is it?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus responded, &#8220;It is he to whom I shall extend the dipped bread.&#8221; And when he had dipped the bread, he gave it to Judas Iscariot, son of Simon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And after the morsel, Satan entered into him. And Jesus said to him, &#8220;What you are going to do, do quickly.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now none of those sitting at table knew why he had said this to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For some were thinking that, because Judas held the purse, that Jesus had told him, &#8220;Buy those things which are needed by us for the feast day,&#8221; or that he might give something to the needy.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Therefore, having accepted the morsel, he went out immediately. And it was night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then, when he had gone out, Jesus said: &#8220;Now the Son of man has been glorified, and God has been glorified in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>If God has been glorified in him, then God will also glorify him in himself, and he will glorify him without delay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Little sons, for a brief while, I am with you. You shall seek me, and just as I said to the Jews, &#8216;Where I am going, you are not able to go,&#8217; so also I say to you now.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>I give you a new commandment: Love one another. Just as I have loved you, so also must you love one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>By this, all shall recognize that you are my disciples: if you will have love for one another.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Simon Peter said to him, &#8220;Lord, where are you going?&#8221; Jesus responded: &#8220;Where I am going, you are not able to follow me now. But you shall follow afterward.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Peter said to him: &#8220;Why am I unable to follow you now? I will lay down my life for you!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Jesus answered him: &#8220;You will lay down your life for me? Amen, amen, I say to you, the rooster will not crow, until you deny me three times.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> When Peter is washed at his head, his whole body is clean. Therefore, when a man become the Roman Pontiff, i.e. the successor of Peter, he cannot possibly fall into heresy. For he is necessarily prevented from this failing: his head has been washed by taking the office of Pope, so his whole self is clean from heresy and schism.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> But they could not have bought anything if this was the regular time for the Passover meal, after sunset on Friday, Nisan 14, because then the Sabbath would begin. Therefore, this Passover meal was held on Thursday, Nisan 13, a day before most Jews would celebrate the Passover. This was permitted to the Jews from Galilee, as Blessed A. C. Emmerich explains.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14" preferred_title="John 14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>&#8220;Do not let your heart be troubled. You believe in God. Believe in me also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>In my Father&#8217;s house, there are many dwelling places. If there were not, I would have told you. For I go to prepare a place for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will return again, and then I will take you to myself, so that where I am, you also may be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And you know where I am going. And you know the way.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thomas said to him, &#8220;Lord, we do not know where you are going, so how can we know the way?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Jesus said to him: &#8220;I am the Way, and the Truth, and the Life. No one comes to the Father, except through me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If you had known me, certainly you would also have known my Father. And from now on, you shall know him, and you have seen him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Philip said to him, &#8220;Lord, reveal the Father to us, and it is enough for us.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Jesus said to him: &#8220;Have I been with you for so long, and you have not known me? Philip, whoever sees me, also sees the Father. How can you say, &#8216;Reveal the Father to us?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Do you not believe that I am in the Father and the Father is in me? The words that I am speaking to you, I do not speak from myself. But the Father abiding in me, he does these works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Do you not believe that I am in the Father and the Father is in me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Or else, believe because of these same works. Amen, amen, I say to you, whoever believes in me shall also do the works that I do. And greater things than these shall he do, for I go to the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And whatever you shall ask the Father in my name, that I will do, so that the Father may be glorified in the Son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If you shall ask anything of me in my name, that I will do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If you love me, keep my commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And I will ask the Father, and he will give another Advocate to you, so that he may abide with you for eternity:</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the Spirit of Truth, whom the world is not able to accept, because it neither perceives him nor knows him. But you shall know him. For he will remain with you, and he will be in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I will not leave you orphans. I will return to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Yet a little while and the world will not see me any longer. But you will see me. For I live, and you shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In that day, you shall know that I am in my Father, and you are in me, and I am in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whoever holds to my commandments and keeps them: it is he who loves me. And whoever loves me shall be loved by my Father. And I will love him, and I will manifest myself to him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Judas, not the Iscariot, said to him: &#8220;Lord, how does it happen that you will manifest yourself to us and not to the world?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus responded and said to him: &#8220;If anyone loves me, he shall keep my word. And my Father will love him, and we will come to him, and we will make our dwelling place with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Whoever does not love me, does not keep not my words. And the word that you have heard is not of me, but it is of the Father who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you, while abiding with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But the Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, will teach you all things and will suggest to you everything whatsoever that I have said to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Peace I leave for you; my Peace I give to you. Not in the way that the world gives, do I give to you. Do not let your heart be troubled, and let it not fear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>You have heard that I said to you: I am going away, and I am returning to you. If you loved me, certainly you would be gladdened, because I am going to the Father. For the Father is greater than I.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And now I have told you this, before it happens, so that, when it will happen, you may believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I will not now speak at length with you. For the prince of this world is coming, but he does not have anything in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Yet this is so that the world may know that I love the Father, and that I am acting according to the commandment that the Father has given to me. Rise up, let us go from here.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Some translations render &#8216;mansiones&#8217; as &#8216;mansions.&#8217; But a translator should not always use the English word that most closely resembles the Latin word. In this case, &#8216;mansions&#8217; is not accurate and &#8216;rooms&#8217; can be used only metaphorically, so &#8216;dwelling places&#8217; is a better fit, being more general and a more accurate rendering of &#8216;mansiones.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The word Paraclete is translated as Advocate, rather than leaving it as &#8216;Paraclete&#8217; which then would need to be explained to many people. Generally, I think that words should be translated, even if they are place names or titles, wherever it would otherwise be unclear.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15" preferred_title="John 15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>&#8220;I am the true vine, and my Father is the vinedresser.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Every branch in me that does not bear fruit, he will take away. And each one that does bear fruit, he will cleanse, so that it may bring forth more fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>You are clean now, because of the word that I have spoken to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Abide in me, and I in you. Just as the branch is not able to bear fruit of itself, unless it abides in the vine, so also are you unable, unless you abide in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I am the vine; you are the branches. Whoever abides in me, and I in him, bears much fruit. For without me, you are able to do nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If anyone does not abide in me, he will be cast away, like a branch, and he will wither, and they will gather him and cast him into the fire, and he burns.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If you abide in me, and my words abide in you, then you may ask for whatever you will, and it shall be done for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>In this, my Father is glorified: that you should bring forth very much fruit and become my disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As the Father has loved me, so I have loved you. Abide in my love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If you keep my precepts, you shall abide in my love, just as I also have kept my Father&#8217;s precepts and I abide in his love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you, so that my joy may be in you, and your joy may be fulfilled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>This is my precept: that you love one another, just as I have loved you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>No one has a greater love than this: that he lay down his life for his friends.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>You are my friends, if you do what I instruct you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I will no longer call you servants, for the servant does not know what his Lord is doing. But I have called you friends, because everything whatsoever that I have heard from my Father, I have made known to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>You have not chosen me, but I have chosen you. And I have appointed you, so that you may go forth and bear fruit, and so that your fruit may last. Then whatever you have asked of the Father in my name, he shall give to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This I command you: that you love one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If the world hates you, know that it has hated me before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>If you had been of the world, the world would love what is its own. Yet truly, you are not of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world; because of this, the world hates you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Remember my saying that I told you: The servant is not greater than his Lord. If they have persecuted me, they will persecute you also. If they have kept my word, they will keep yours also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But all these things they will do to you because of my name, for they do not know him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>If I had not come and had not spoken to them, they would not have sin. But now they have no excuse for their sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Whoever hates me, hates my Father also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If I had not accomplished among them works that no other person has accomplished, they would not have sin. But now they have both seen me, and they have hated me and my Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But this is so that the word may be fulfilled which was written in their law: &#8216;For they hated me without cause.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But when the Advocate has arrived, whom I will send to you from the Father, the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, he will offer testimony about me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And you shall offer testimony, because you are with me from the beginning.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;agricola&#8217; really does not mean &#8216;vinedresser.&#8217; It has more of a general meaning, like &#8216;farmer&#8217; or &#8216;gardener.&#8217; But context is very important to an accurate translation, and in this context of &#8216;vines,&#8217; the person caring for the vines is called a &#8216;vinedresser.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16" preferred_title="John 16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>&#8220;These things I have spoken to you, so that you would not stumble.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>They will put you out of the synagogues. But the hour is coming when everyone who puts you to death will consider that he is offering an excellent service to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And they will do these things to you because they have not known the Father, nor me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But these things I have spoken to you, so that, when the hour for these things will have arrived, you may remember that I told you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But I did not tell you these things from the beginning, because I was with you. And now I am going to him who sent me. And no one among you has asked me, &#8216;Where are you going?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But because I have spoken these things to you, sorrow has filled your heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But I tell you the truth: it is expedient for you that I am going. For if I do not go, the Advocate will not come to you. But when I will have gone away, I will send him to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when he has arrived, he will argue against the world, about sin and about justice and about judgment:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>about sin, indeed, because they have not believed in me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>about justice, truly, because I am going to the Father, and you will not see me any longer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>about judgment, then, because the prince of this world has already been judged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I still have many things to say to you, but you are not able to bear them now.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But when the Spirit of truth has arrived, he will teach the whole truth to you. For he will not be speaking from himself. Instead, whatever he will hear, he will speak. And he will announce to you the things that are to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He shall glorify me. For he will receive from what is mine, and he will announce it to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>All things whatsoever that the Father has are mine. For this reason, I said that he will receive from what is mine and that he will announce it to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>A little while, and then you will not see me. And again a little while, and you will see me. For I am going to the Father.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then some of his disciples said to one another: &#8220;What is this, that he is saying to us: &#8216;A little while, and you will not see me,&#8217; and &#8216;Again a little while, and you will see me,&#8217; and, &#8216;For I am going to the Father?&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And they said: &#8220;What is this, that he is saying, &#8216;A little while?&#8217; We do not understand what he is saying.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But Jesus realized that they wanted to question him, and so he said to them: &#8220;Are you inquiring among yourselves about this, that I said: &#8216;A little while, and you will not see me, and again a little while, and you will see me?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, that you shall mourn and weep, but the world will rejoice. And you shall be greatly saddened, yet your sorrow shall be turned into joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>A woman, when she is giving birth, has sorrow, because her hour has arrived. But when she has given birth to the child, then she no longer remembers the difficulties, because of the joy: for a man has been born into the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Therefore, you also, indeed, have sorrow now. But I will see you again, and your heart shall rejoice. And no one will take away your joy from you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And, in that day, you will not petition me for anything. Amen, amen, I say to you, if you ask the Father for anything in my name, he will give it to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Until now, you have not requested anything in my name. Ask, and you shall receive, so that your joy may be full.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I have spoken these things to you in proverbs. The hour is coming when I will no longer speak to you in proverbs; instead, I will announce to you plainly from the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>In that day, you shall ask in my name, and I do not say to you that I will ask the Father for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For the Father himself loves you, because you have loved me, and because you have believed that I went forth from God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>I went forth from the Father, and I have come into the world. Next I am leaving the world, and I am going to the Father.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>His disciples said to him: &#8220;Behold, now you are speaking plainly and not reciting a proverb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now we know that you know all things, and that you have no need for anyone to question you. By this, we believe that you went forth from God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Jesus answered them: &#8220;Do you believe now?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Behold, the hour is coming, and it has now arrived, when you will be scattered, each one on his own, and you will leave me behind, alone. And yet I am not alone, for the Father is with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you, so that you may have peace in me. In the world, you will have difficulties. But have confidence: I have overcome the world.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Or, &#8216;would not be scandalized.&#8217; The word &#8216;scandalized&#8217; is becoming fairly obscure in English, and the word &#8216;scandal&#8217; has a different meaning in secular usage than it does in religious usage, so stumble is perhaps a better choice.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17" preferred_title="John 17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Jesus said these things, and then, lifting up his eyes toward heaven, he said: &#8220;Father, the hour has arrived: glorify your Son, so that your Son may glorify you,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>just as you have given authority over all flesh to him, so that he may give eternal life to all those whom you have given to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And this is eternal life: that they may know you, the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom you have sent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I have glorified you on earth. I have completed the work that you gave me to accomplish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And now Father, glorify me within yourself, with the glory that I had with you before the world ever was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I have manifested your name to the men whom you have given to me from the world. They were yours, and you gave them to me. And they have kept your word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now they realize that all the things that you have given me are from you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For I have given them the words that you gave to me. And they have accepted these words, and they have truly understood that I went forth from you, and they have believed that you sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I pray for them. I do not pray for the world, but for those whom you have given to me. For they are yours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And all that is mine is yours, and all that is yours is mine, and I am glorified in this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And though I am not in the world, these are in the world, and I am coming to you. Father most holy, preserve them in your name, those whom you have given to me, so that they may be one, even as we are one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>While I was with them, I preserved them in your name. I have guarded those whom you have given to me, and not one of them is lost, except the son of perdition, so that the Scripture may be fulfilled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And now I am coming to you. But I am speaking these things in the world, so that they may have the fullness of my joy within themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have given them your word, and the world has hated them. For they are not of the world, just as I, too, am not of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I am not praying that you would take them out of the world, but that you would preserve them from evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They are not of the world, just as I also am not of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Sanctify them in truth. Your word is truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Just as you have sent me into the world, I also have sent them into the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And it is for them that I sanctify myself, so that they, too, may be sanctified in truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But I am not praying for them only, but also for those who through their word shall believe in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So may they all be one. Just as you, Father, are in me, and I am in you, so also may they be one in us: so that the world may believe that you have sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And the glory that you have given to me, I have given to them, so that they may be one, just as we also are one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I am in them, and you are in me. So may they be perfected as one. And may the world know that you have sent me and that you have loved them, just as you have also loved me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Father, I will that where I am, those whom you have given to me may also be with me, so that they may see my glory which you have given to me. For you loved me before the founding of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Father most just, the world has not known you. But I have known you. And these have known that you sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And I have made known your name to them, and I will make it known, so that the love in which you have loved me may be in them, and so that I may be in them.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Here and in subsequent verses, the word &#8216;clarificet&#8217; is translated as &#8216;glorify.&#8217; There is perhaps no better word in his context, but the word in Latin is a bit different than glorify. It has more of a sense of making something well-known, and is somewhat less abstract than glorify.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18" preferred_title="John 18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus had said these things, he departed with his disciples across the Torrent of Kidron, where there was a garden, into which he entered with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But Judas, who betrayed him, also knew the place, for Jesus had frequently met with his disciples there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then Judas, when he had received a cohort from both the high priests and the attendants of the Pharisees, approached the place with lanterns and torches and weapons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And so Jesus, knowing all that was about to happen to him, advanced and said to them, &#8220;Who are you seeking?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They answered him, &#8220;Jesus the Nazarene.&#8221; Jesus said to them, &#8220;I am he.&#8221; Now Judas, who betrayed him, was also standing with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then, when he said to them, &#8220;I am he,&#8221; they moved back and fell to the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then again he questioned them: &#8220;Who are you seeking?&#8221; And they said, &#8220;Jesus the Nazarene.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Jesus responded: &#8220;I told you that I am he. Therefore, if you are seeking me, permit these others to go away.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>This was so that the word might be fulfilled, which he said, &#8220;Of those whom you have given to me, I have not lost any of them.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Simon Peter, having a sword, drew it, and he struck the servant of the high priest, and he cut off his right ear. Now the name of the servant was Malchus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore, Jesus said to Peter: &#8220;Set your sword into the scabbard. Should I not drink the chalice which my Father has given to me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the cohort, and the tribune, and the attendants of the Jews apprehended Jesus and bound him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they led him away, first to Annas, for he was the father-in-law of Caiaphas, who was the high priest that year.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now Caiaphas was the one who had given counsel to the Jews that it was expedient for one man to die for the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Simon Peter was following Jesus with another disciple. And that disciple was known to the high priest, and so he entered with Jesus into the court of the high priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But Peter was standing outside at the entrance. Therefore, the other disciple, who was known to the high priest, went out and spoke to the woman who was the doorkeeper, and he led in Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore, the woman servant keeping the door said to Peter, &#8220;Are you not also among the disciples of this man?&#8221; He said, &#8220;I am not.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now the servants and attendants were standing before burning coals, for it was cold, and they were warming themselves. And Peter was standing with them also, warming himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then the high priest questioned Jesus about his disciples and about his doctrine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Jesus responded to him: &#8220;I have spoken openly to the world. I have always taught in the synagogue and in the temple, where all the Jews meet. And I have said nothing in secret.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Why do you question me? Question those who heard what I said to them. Behold, they know these things that I have said.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then, when he had said this, one of the attendants standing nearby struck Jesus, saying: &#8220;Is this the way you answer the high priest?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus answered him: &#8220;If I have spoken wrongly, offer testimony about the wrong. But if I have spoken correctly, then why do you strike me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Annas sent him bound to Caiaphas, the high priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now Simon Peter was standing and warming himself. Then they said to him, &#8220;Are you not also one of his disciples?&#8221; He denied it and said, &#8220;I am not.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>One of the servants of the high priest (a relative of him whose ear Peter had cut off) said to him, &#8220;Did I not see you in the garden with him?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Therefore, again, Peter denied it. And immediately the rooster crowed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then they led Jesus from Caiaphas into the praetorium. Now it was morning, and so they did not enter into the praetorium, so that they would not be defiled, but might eat the Passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Therefore, Pilate went outside to them, and he said, &#8220;What accusation are you bringing against this man?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>They responded and said to him, &#8220;If he were not an evil-doer, we would not have handed him over to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore, Pilate said to them, &#8220;Take him yourselves and judge him according to your own law.&#8221; Then the Jews said to him, &#8220;It is not lawful for us to execute anyone.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>This was so that the word of Jesus would be fulfilled, which he spoke signifying what kind of death he would die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then Pilate entered the praetorium again, and he called Jesus and said to him, &#8220;You are the king of the Jews?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus responded, &#8220;Are you saying this of yourself, or have others spoken to you about me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Pilate responded: &#8220;Am I a Jew? Your own nation and the high priests have handed you over to me. What have you done?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Jesus responded: &#8220;My kingdom is not of this world. If my kingdom were of this world, my ministers would certainly strive so that I would not be handed over to the Jews. But my kingdom is not now from here.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And so Pilate said to him, &#8220;You are a king, then?&#8221; Jesus answered, &#8220;You are saying that I am a king. For this I was born, and for this I came into the world: so that I may offer testimony to the truth. Everyone who is of the truth hears my voice.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Pilate said to him, &#8220;What is truth?&#8221; And when he had said this, he went out again to the Jews, and he said to them, &#8220;I find no case against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But you have a custom, that I should release someone to you at the Passover. Therefore, do you want me to release to you the king of the Jews?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Then they all cried out repeatedly, saying: &#8220;Not this one, but Barabbas.&#8221; Now Barabbas was a robber.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> I realize that using Who instead of Whom is grammatically incorrect, but using Whom is awkward sounding and it is not the way that people speak in conversation.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The Last Supper occurred a day earlier than most Jews celebrated the Passover supper, so that Jesus could both celebrate the Passover and be the Passover Lamb on the Cross. This was arranged by the Providence of God and permitted by a tradition of the Jews for those from Galilee.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19" preferred_title="John 19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore, Pilate then took Jesus into custody and scourged him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the soldiers, plaiting a crown of thorns, imposed it on his head. And they put a purple garment around him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And they were approaching him and saying, &#8220;Hail, king of the Jews!&#8221; And they struck him repeatedly.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Pilate went outside again, and he said to them: &#8220;Behold, I am bringing him out to you, so that you may realize that I find no case against him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>(Then Jesus went out, bearing the crown of thorns and the purple garment.) And he said to them, &#8220;Behold the man.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore, when the high priests and the attendants had seen him, they cried out, saying: &#8220;Crucify him! Crucify him!&#8221; Pilate said to them: &#8220;Take him yourselves and crucify him. For I find no case against him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The Jews answered him, &#8220;We have a law, and according to the law, he ought to die, for he has made himself the Son of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore, when Pilate had heard this word, he was more fearful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he entered into the praetorium again. And he said to Jesus. &#8220;Where are you from?&#8221; But Jesus gave him no response.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore, Pilate said to him: &#8220;Will you not speak to me? Do you not know that I have authority to crucify you, and I have authority to release you?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Jesus responded, &#8220;You would not have any authority over me, unless it were given to you from above. For this reason, he who has handed me over to you has the greater sin.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And from then on, Pilate was seeking to release him. But the Jews were crying out, saying: &#8220;If you release this man, you are no friend of Caesar. For anyone who makes himself a king contradicts Caesar.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now when Pilate had heard these words, he brought Jesus outside, and he sat down in the seat of judgment, in a place which is called the Pavement, but in Hebrew, it is called the Elevation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now it was the preparation day of the Passover, about the sixth hour. And he said to the Jews, &#8220;Behold your king.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But they were crying out: &#8220;Take him away! Take him away! Crucify him!&#8221; Pilate said to them, &#8220;Shall I crucify your king?&#8221; The high priests responded, &#8220;We have no king except Caesar.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore, he then handed him over to them to be crucified. And they took Jesus and led him away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And carrying his own cross, he went forth to the place which is called Calvary, but in Hebrew it is called the Place of the Skull.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>There they crucified him, and with him two others, one on each side, with Jesus in the middle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then Pilate also wrote a title, and he set it above the cross. And it was written: JESUS THE NAZARENE, KING OF THE JEWS.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Therefore, many of the Jews read this title, for the place where Jesus was crucified was close to the city. And it was written in Hebrew, in Greek, and in Latin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then the high priests of the Jews said to Pilate: Do not write, &#8216;King of the Jews,&#8217; but that he said, &#8216;I am King of the Jews.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Pilate responded, &#8220;What I have written, I have written.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then the soldiers, when they had crucified him, took his garments, and they made four parts, one part to each soldier, and the tunic. But the tunic was seamless, woven from above throughout the whole.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then they said to one another, &#8220;Let us not cut it, but instead let us cast lots over it, to see whose it will be.&#8221; This was so that the Scripture would be fulfilled, saying: &#8220;They have distributed my garments among themselves, and for my vesture they have cast lots.&#8221; And indeed, the soldiers did these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And standing beside the cross of Jesus were his mother, and his mother&#8217;s sister, and Mary of Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Therefore, when Jesus had seen his mother and the disciple whom he loved standing near, he said to his mother, &#8220;Woman, behold your son.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Next, he said to the disciple, &#8220;Behold your mother.&#8221; And from that hour, the disciple accepted her as his own.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>After this, Jesus knew that all had been accomplished, so in order that the Scripture might be completed, he said, &#8220;I thirst.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And there was a container placed there, full of vinegar. Then, placing a sponge full of vinegar around hyssop, they brought it to his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then Jesus, when he had received the vinegar, said: &#8220;It is consummated.&#8221; And bowing down his head, he surrendered his spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then the Jews, because it was the preparation day, so that the bodies would not remain upon the cross on the Sabbath (for that Sabbath was a great day), they petitioned Pilate in order that their legs might be broken, and they might be taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Therefore, the soldiers approached, and, indeed, they broke the legs of the first one, and of the other who was crucified with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But after they had approached Jesus, when they saw that he was already dead, they did not break his legs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Instead, one of the soldiers opened his side with a lance, and immediately there went out blood and water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And he who saw this has offered testimony, and his testimony is true. And he knows that he speaks the truth, so that you also may believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For these things happened so that the Scripture would be fulfilled: &#8220;You shall not break a bone of him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And again, another Scripture says: &#8220;They shall look upon him, whom they have pierced.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then, after these things, Joseph from Arimathea, (because he was a disciple of Jesus, but a secret one for fear of the Jews) petitioned Pilate so that he might take away the body of Jesus. And Pilate gave permission. Therefore, he went and took away the body of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now Nicodemus also arrived, (who had gone to Jesus at first by night) bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloe, weighing about seventy pounds.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Therefore, they took the body of Jesus, and they bound it with linen cloths and the aromatic spices, just as it is the manner of the Jews to bury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden, and in the garden there was a new tomb, in which no one had yet been laid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Therefore, because of the preparation day of the Jews, since the tomb was nearby, they placed Jesus there.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The expression &#8216;dabant alapas&#8217; has the verb in the imperative tense, so the translation of &#8216;repeatedly&#8217; is justified. More literally (and more awkwardly) it says &#8216;they were giving him blows.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Pilate was most likely speaking in Latin when he said these words. These words show a manner of thought and expression found in ancient Roman culture and society. It is also a very natural expression in Latin.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> According to Blessed Anne Catherine Emmerich, Mary Cleophas was the daughter of Cleophas and Maria Heli (the Virgin Mary&#8217;s older sister). So the sister of Christ&#8217;s mother, and the woman named Mary Cleophas are two different persons.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> The libra was a weight of one Roman pound, but this is substantially less than what is called a pound today. Thus 100 libras is not 100 modern pounds, but about 71.2 pounds or about 32.3 kilograms.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20" preferred_title="John 20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then on the first Sabbath, Mary Magdalene went to the tomb early, while it was still dark, and she saw that the stone had been rolled away from the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Therefore, she ran and went to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple, whom Jesus loved, and she said to them, &#8220;They have taken the Lord away from the tomb, and we do not know where they have laid him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore, Peter departed with the other disciple, and they went to the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now they both ran together, but the other disciple ran more quickly, ahead of Peter, and so he arrived at the tomb first.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when he bowed down, he saw the linen cloths lying there, but he did not yet enter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then Simon Peter arrived, following him, and he entered the tomb, and he saw the linen cloths lying there,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the separate cloth which had been over his head, not placed with the linen cloths, but in a separate place, wrapped up by itself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the other disciple, who had arrived first at the tomb, also entered. And he saw and believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For as yet they did not understand the Scripture, that it was necessary for him to rise again from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then the disciples went away again, each by himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But Mary was standing outside the tomb, weeping. Then, while she was weeping, she bowed down and gazed into the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And she saw two Angels in white, sitting where the body of Jesus had been placed, one at the head, and one at the feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They said to her, &#8220;Woman, why are you weeping?&#8221; She said to them, &#8220;Because they have taken away my Lord, and I do not know where they have placed him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When she had said this, she turned around and saw Jesus standing there, but she did not know that it was Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Jesus said to her: &#8220;Woman, why are you weeping? Who are you seeking?&#8221; Considering that it was the gardener, she said to him, &#8220;Sir, if you have moved him, tell me where you have placed him, and I will take him away.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesus said to her, &#8220;Mary!&#8221; And turning, she said to him, &#8220;Rabboni!&#8221; (which means, Teacher).</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Jesus said to her: &#8220;Do not touch me. For I have not yet ascended to my Father. But go to my brothers and tell them: &#8216;I am ascending to my Father and to your Father, to my God and to your God.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Mary Magdalene went, announcing to the disciples, &#8220;I have seen the Lord, and these are the things that he said to me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then, when it was late on the same day, on the first of the Sabbaths, and the doors were closed where the disciples were gathered, for fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in their midst, and he said to them: &#8220;Peace to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when he had said this, he showed them his hands and side. And the disciples were gladdened when they saw the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, he said to them again: &#8220;Peace to you. As the Father has sent me, so I send you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When he had said this, he breathed on them. And he said to them: &#8220;Receive the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Those whose sins you shall forgive, they are forgiven them, and those whose sins you shall retain, they are retained.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now Thomas, one of the twelve, who is called the Twin, was not with them when Jesus arrived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Therefore, the other disciples said to him, &#8220;We have seen the Lord.&#8221; But he said to them, &#8220;Unless I will see in his hands the mark of the nails and place my finger into the place of the nails, and place my hand into his side, I will not believe.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And after eight days, again his disciples were within, and Thomas was with them. Jesus arrived, though the doors had been closed, and he stood in their midst and said, &#8220;Peace to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Next, he said to Thomas: &#8220;Look at my hands, and place your finger here; and bring your hand close, and place it at my side. And do not choose to be unbelieving, but faithful.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thomas responded and said to him, &#8220;My Lord and my God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Jesus said to him: &#8220;You have seen me, Thomas, so you have believed. Blessed are those who have not seen and yet have believed.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Jesus also accomplished many other signs in the sight of his disciples. These have not been written in this book.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But these things have been written, so that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and so that, in believing, you may have life in his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> As with the other Gospels, John points out that this Sunday was the first Christian Sabbath. The phrase &#8216;una sabbati&#8217; does not mean the first day of the week, but the first Sabbath.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21" preferred_title="John 21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this, Jesus manifested himself again to the disciples at the Sea of Tiberias. And he manifested himself in this way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>These were together: Simon Peter and Thomas, who is called the Twin, and Nathanael, who was from Cana of Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two others of his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Simon Peter said to them, &#8220;I am going fishing.&#8221; They said to him, &#8220;And we are going with you.&#8221; And they went and climbed into the ship. And in that night, they caught nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But when morning arrived, Jesus stood on the shore. Yet the disciples did not realize that it was Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them, &#8220;Children, do you have any food?&#8221; They answered him, &#8220;No.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He said to them, &#8220;Cast the net to the right side of the ship, and you will find some.&#8221; Therefore, they cast it out, and then they were not able to draw it in, because of the multitude of fish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Therefore, the disciple whom Jesus loved said to Peter, &#8220;It is the Lord.&#8221; Simon Peter, when he had heard that it was the Lord, wrapped his tunic around himself, (for he was naked) and he cast himself into the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the other disciples arrived in a boat, (for they were not far from the land, only about two hundred cubits) dragging the net with the fish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then, when they climbed down to the land they saw burning coals prepared, and fish already placed above them, and bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus said to them, &#8220;Bring some of the fish that you have just now caught.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Simon Peter climbed up and drew in the net to land: full of large fish, one hundred and fifty-three of them. And although there were so many, the net was not torn.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Jesus said to them, &#8220;Approach and dine.&#8221; And not one of them sitting down to eat dared to ask him, &#8220;Who are you?&#8221; For they knew that it was the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And Jesus approached, and he took bread, and he gave it to them, and similarly with the fish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>This was now the third time that Jesus was manifested to his disciples, after he had resurrected from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then, when they had dined, Jesus said to Simon Peter, &#8220;Simon, son of John, do you love me more than these?&#8221; He said to him, &#8220;Yes, Lord, you know that I love you.&#8221; He said to him, &#8220;Feed my lambs.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He said to him again: &#8220;Simon, son of John, do you love me?&#8221; He said to him, &#8220;Yes, Lord, you know that I love you.&#8221; He said to him, &#8220;Feed my lambs.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He said to him a third time, &#8220;Simon, son of John, do you love me?&#8221; Peter was very grieved that he had asked him a third time, &#8220;Do you love me?&#8221; And so he said to him: &#8220;Lord, you know all things. You know that I love you.&#8221; He said to him, &#8220;Feed my sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Amen, amen, I say to you, when you were younger, you girded yourself and walked wherever you wanted. But when you are older, you will extend your hands, and another shall gird you and lead you where you do not want to go.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now he said this to signify by what kind of death he would glorify God. And when he had said this, he said to him, &#8220;Follow me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Peter, turning around, saw the disciple whom Jesus loved following, the one who also had leaned on his chest at supper and said, &#8220;Lord, who is it who shall betray you?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, when Peter had seen him, he said to Jesus, &#8220;Lord, but what about this one?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Jesus said to him: &#8220;If I want him to remain until I return, what is that to you? You follow me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Therefore, the saying went out among the brothers that this disciple would not die. But Jesus did not say to him that he would not die, but only, &#8220;If I want him to remain until I return, what is that to you?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>This is the same disciple who offers testimony about these things, and who has written these things. And we know that his testimony is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now there are also many other things that Jesus did, which, if each of these were written down, the world itself, I suppose, would not be able to contain the books that would be written.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The catch of fish represents souls saved by the Church in the end times. The size of the fish represents the number of souls saved: a large number. The number of the fish represents the way that they are saved: through the holy Rosary, represented figuratively by the 153 Hail Mary&#8217;s found in the traditional form of the prayer.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Notice that the verb tense is active not passive. Jesus has the power, as the Son of God, to raise himself up from the dead. At the general resurrection, we shall all be resurrected from the dead (passive tense) by Christ. But at His own resurrection, Christ resurrected himself from the dead (active tense).</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> All the Apostles were martyred except John. This is a foreshadowing of the last days before the Return of Christ, when almost the whole Church will suffer severe persecution, but one part will be spared, so that the Church will not pass away prior to Christ&#8217;s return.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
</book>