<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Certainly, O Theophilus, I composed the first discourse about everything that Jesus began to do and to teach,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>instructing the Apostles, whom he had chosen through the Holy Spirit, even until the day on which he was taken up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He also presented himself alive to them, after his Passion, appearing to them throughout forty days and speaking about the kingdom of God with many elucidations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And dining with them, he instructed them that they should not depart from Jerusalem, but that they should wait for the Promise of the Father, &#8220;about which you have heard,&#8221; he said, &#8220;from my own mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For John, indeed, baptized with water, but you shall be baptized with the Holy Spirit, not many days from now.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore, those who had assembled together questioned him, saying, &#8220;Lord, is this the time when you will restore the kingdom of Israel?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But he said to them: &#8220;It is not yours to know the times or the moments, which the Father has set by his own authority.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But you shall receive the power of the Holy Spirit, passing over you, and you shall be witnesses for me in Jerusalem, and in all Judea and Samaria, and even to the ends of the earth.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when he had said these things, while they were watching, he was lifted up, and a cloud took him from their sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And while they were watching him going up to heaven, behold, two men stood near them in white vestments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And they said: &#8220;Men of Galilee, why do you stand here looking up toward heaven? This Jesus, who has been taken up from you into heaven, shall return in just the same way that you have seen him going up to heaven.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then they returned to Jerusalem from the mountain, which is called Olivet, which is next to Jerusalem, within a Sabbath day&#8217;s journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when they had entered into the cenacle, they ascended to the place where Peter and John, James and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bartholomew and Matthew, James of Alphaeus and Simon the Zealot, and Jude of James, were staying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>All these were persevering with one accord in prayer with the women, and with Mary, the mother of Jesus, and with his brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In those days, Peter, rising up in the midst of the brothers, said (now the crowd of men altogether was about one hundred and twenty):</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>&#8220;Noble brothers, the Scripture must be fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit predicted by the mouth of David about Judas, who was the leader of those who apprehended Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He had been numbered among us, and he was chosen by lot for this ministry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And this man certainly possessed an estate from the wages of iniquity, and so, having been hanged, he burst open in the middle and all his internal organs poured out.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And this became known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that this field was called in their language, Akeldama, that is, &#8216;Field of Blood.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For it has been written in the book of Psalms: &#8216;Let their dwelling place be desolate and may there be no one who dwells within it,&#8217; and &#8216;Let another take his episcopate.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore, it is necessary that, out of these men who have been assembling with us throughout the entire time that the Lord Jesus went in and out among us,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>beginning from the baptism of John, until the day when he was taken up from us, one of these be made a witness with us of his Resurrection.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And they appointed two: Joseph, who was called Barsabbas, who was surnamed Justus, and Matthias.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And praying, they said: &#8220;May you, O Lord, who knows the heart of everyone, reveal which one of these two you have chosen,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>to take a place in this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas prevaricated, so that he might go to his own place.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And they cast lots concerning them, and the lot fell upon Matthias. And he was numbered with the eleven Apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;viri&#8217; does not simply mean men; it is derived from a Latin word meaning power or virtue, so it can also mean &#8216;good men&#8217; or &#8216;noble men.&#8217; When combined with &#8216;fratres,&#8217; the meaning is that these brothers are also good or noble.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> No one was willing to take down the dead body of someone who had committed suicide, because it was the Feast of Passover, and so his body most probably hung there from Friday, Nisan 14, until at least Saturday, Nisan 22, after sunset. The length of time that he hung there, and the decay of his body, caused his skin to burst open and all his internal organs to pour out.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> Barsabbas was clearly the more well-known of the two, since he had two nicknames. He was also held, in the opinion of many to be the holier of the two, for he was called Barsabbas (son of the Sabbath) and Justus (the just one). Yet God chose Matthias over Barsabbas, for God knows the hidden secrets of the soul.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when the days of Pentecost were completed, they were all together in the same place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And suddenly, there came a sound from heaven, like that of a wind approaching violently, and it filled the entire house where they were sitting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And there appeared to them separate tongues, as if of fire, which settled upon each one of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit. And they began to speak in various languages, just as the Holy Spirit bestowed eloquence to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now there were Jews staying in Jerusalem, pious men from every nation that is under heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when this sound occurred, the multitude came together and was confused in mind, because each one was listening to them speaking in his own language.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then all were astonished, and they wondered, saying: &#8220;Behold, are not all of these who are speaking Galileans?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And how is it that we have each heard them in our own language, into which we were born?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Parthians and Medes and Elamites, and those who inhabit Mesopotamia, Judea and Cappadocia, Pontus and Asia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Phrygia and Pamphylia, Egypt and the parts of Libya which are around Cyrene, and new arrivals of the Romans,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>likewise Jews and new converts, Cretans and Arabs: we have heard them speaking in our own languages the mighty deeds of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they were all astonished, and they wondered, saying to one another: &#8220;But what does this mean?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But others mockingly said, &#8220;These men are full of new wine.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But Peter, standing up with the eleven, lifted up his voice, and he spoke to them: &#8220;Men of Judea, and all those who are staying in Jerusalem, let this be known to you, and incline your ears to my words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For these men are not inebriated, as you suppose, for it is the third hour of the day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But this is what was spoken of by the prophet Joel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>&#8216;And this shall be: in the last days, says the Lord, I will pour out, from my Spirit, upon all flesh. And your sons and your daughters shall prophesy. And your youths shall see visions, and your elders shall dream dreams.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And certainly, upon my men and women servants in those days, I will pour out from my Spirit, and they shall prophesy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I will bestow wonders in heaven above, and signs on earth below: blood and fire and the vapor of smoke.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The sun shall be turned into darkness and the moon into blood, before the great and manifest day of the Lord arrives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And this shall be: whoever shall invoke the name of the Lord will be saved.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Men of Israel, hear these words: Jesus the Nazarene is a man confirmed by God among you through the miracles and wonders and signs that God accomplished through him in your midst, just as you also know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>This man, under the definitive plan and foreknowledge of God, was delivered by the hands of the unjust, afflicted, and put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And he whom God has raised up has broken the sorrows of Hell, for certainly it was impossible for him to be held by it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For David said about him: &#8216;I foresaw the Lord always in my sight, for he is at my right hand, so that I may not be moved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Because of this, my heart has rejoiced, and my tongue has exulted. Moreover, my flesh shall also rest in hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For you will not abandon my soul to Hell, nor will you allow your Holy One to see corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>You have made known to me the ways of life. You will completely fill me with happiness by your presence.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Noble brothers, permit me to speak freely to you about the Patriarch David: for he passed away and was buried, and his sepulcher is with us, even to this very day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Therefore, he was a prophet, for he knew that God had sworn an oath to him about the fruit of his loins, about the One who would sit upon his throne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Foreseeing this, he was speaking about the Resurrection of the Christ. For he was neither left behind in Hell, nor did his flesh see corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>This Jesus, God raised up again, and of this we are all witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Therefore, being exalted to the right hand of God, and having received from the Father the Promise of the Holy Spirit, he poured this out, just as you now see and hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For David did not ascend into heaven. But he himself said: &#8216;The Lord said to my Lord: Sit at my right hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>until I make your enemies your footstool.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Therefore, may the entire house of Israel know most certainly that God has made this same Jesus, whom you crucified, both Lord and Christ.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Now when they had heard these things, they were contrite in heart, and they said to Peter and to the other Apostles: &#8220;What should we do, noble brothers?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Yet truly, Peter said to them: &#8220;Do penance; and be baptized, each one of you, in the name of Jesus Christ, for the remission of your sins. And you shall receive the gift of the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>For the Promise is for you and for your sons, and for all who are far away: for whomever the Lord our God will have called.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And then, with very many other words, he testified and he exhorted them, saying, &#8220;Save yourselves from this depraved generation.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Therefore, those who accepted his discourse were baptized. And about three thousand souls were added on that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Now they were persevering in the doctrine of the Apostles, and in the communion of the breaking of the bread, and in the prayers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And fear developed in every soul. Also, many miracles and signs were accomplished by the Apostles in Jerusalem. And there was a great awe in everyone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And then all who believed were together, and they held all things in common.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>They were selling their possessions and belongings, and dividing them to all, just as any of them had need.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Also, they continued, daily, to be of one accord in the temple and to break bread among the houses; and they took their meals with exultation and simplicity of heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>praising God greatly, and holding favor with all the people. And every day, the Lord increased those who were being saved among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;replebis&#8217; is not merely to fill, but to complete or to fill completely. The word &#8216;iucunditate&#8217; can have the mild meaning of something that is pleasing or agreeable, but in this context of complete fulfillment in the presence of God, it can only mean happiness.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now Peter and John went up to the temple at the ninth hour of prayer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And a certain man, who was lame from his mother&#8217;s womb, was being carried in. They would lay him every day at the gate of the temple, which is called the Beautiful, so that he might request alms from those entering into the temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And this man, when he had seen Peter and John beginning to enter the temple, was begging, so that he might receive alms.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Peter and John, gazing at him, said, &#8220;Look at us.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And he looked intently at them, hoping that he might receive something from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But Peter said: &#8220;Silver and gold is not mine. But what I have, I give to you. In the name of Jesus Christ the Nazarene, rise up and walk.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And taking him by the right hand, he lifted him up. And immediately his legs and feet were strengthened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And leaping up, he stood and walked around. And he entered with them into the temple, walking and leaping and praising God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And all the people saw him walking and praising God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And they recognized him, that he was the same one who was sitting for alms at the Beautiful Gate of the temple. And they were filled with awe and amazement at what had happened to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then, as he held on to Peter and John, all the people ran to them at the portico, which is called Solomon&#8217;s, in astonishment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But Peter, seeing this, responded to the people: &#8220;Men of Israel, why do you wonder at this? Or why do you stare at us, as if it were by our own strength or power that we caused this man to walk?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob, the God of our fathers, has glorified his Son Jesus, whom you, indeed, handed over and denied before the face of Pilate, when he was giving judgment to release him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then you denied the Holy and Just One, and petitioned for a murderous man to be given to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Truly, it was the Author of Life whom you put to death, whom God raised from the dead, to whom we are witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And by faith in his name, this man, whom you have seen and known, has confirmed his name. And faith through him has given this man complete health in the sight of you all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And now, brothers, I know that you did this through ignorance, just as your leaders also did.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But in this way God has fulfilled the things that he announced beforehand through the mouth of all the Prophets: that his Christ would suffer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore, repent and be converted, so that your sins may be wiped away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And then, when the time of consolation will have arrived from the presence of the Lord, he will send the One who was foretold to you, Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>whom heaven certainly must take up, until the time of the restoration of all things, which God has spoken of by the mouth of his holy prophets, from ages past.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Indeed, Moses said: &#8216;For the Lord your God shall raise up a Prophet for you from your brothers, one like me; the same shall you listen to according to everything whatsoever that he shall speak to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And this shall be: every soul who will not listen to that Prophet shall be exterminated from the people.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And all the prophets who have spoken, from Samuel and thereafter, have announced these days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>You are sons of the prophets and of the testament which God has appointed for our fathers, saying to Abraham: &#8216;And by your offspring all the families of the earth shall be blessed.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>God raised up his Son and sent him first to you, to bless you, so that each one may turn himself away from his wickedness.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The time of consolation is the time of the Return of Jesus Christ, after the end of the Antichrist&#8217;s reign.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> But then, after Christ&#8217;s return, Heaven must certainly take him up again (Second Ascension), until yet another time, the time of the restoration of all things, Judgment Day, after which God makes a new heaven and a new earth. This passage supports the teaching that Christ returns twice: once at the end of the Antichrist&#8217;s reign, to establish his kingdom on earth, and again, well over a thousand years later, at the end of the Millennium of peace and holiness, for Judgment and the restoration of all things.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But while they were speaking to the people, the priests and the magistrate of the temple and the Sadducees overwhelmed them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>being grieved that they were teaching the people and announcing in Jesus the resurrection from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And they laid hands on them, and they placed them under guard until the next day. For it was now evening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But many of those who had heard the word believed. And the number of men became five thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And it happened on the next day that their leaders and elders and scribes gathered together in Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>including Annas, the high priest, and Caiaphas, and John and Alexander, and as many as were of the priestly family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And stationing them in the middle, they questioned them: &#8220;By what power, or in whose name, have you done this?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, said to them: &#8220;Leaders of the people and elders, listen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If we today are judged by a good deed done to an infirm man, by which he has been made whole,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>let it be known to all of you and to all of the people of Israel, that in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ the Nazarene, whom you crucified, whom God has raised from the dead, by him, this man stands before you, healthy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He is the stone, which was rejected by you, the builders, which has become the head of the corner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And there is no salvation in any other. For there is no other name under heaven given to men, by which it is necessary for us to be saved.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then, seeing the constancy of Peter and John, having verified that they were men without letters or learning, they wondered. And they recognized that they had been with Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Also, seeing the man who had been cured standing with them, they were unable to say anything to contradict them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But they ordered them to withdraw outside, away from the council, and they conferred among themselves,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>saying: &#8220;What shall we do to these men? For certainly a public sign has been done through them, before all the inhabitants of Jerusalem. It is manifest, and we cannot deny it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But lest it spread further among the people, let us threaten them not to speak anymore in this name to any man.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And calling them in, they warned them not to speak or teach at all in the name of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Yet truly, Peter and John said in response to them: &#8220;Judge whether it is just in the sight of God to listen to you, rather than to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For we are unable to refrain from speaking the things that we have seen and heard.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But they, threatening them, sent them away, having not found a way that they might punish them because of the people. For all were glorifying the things that had been done in these events.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For the man in whom this sign of a cure had been accomplished was more than forty years old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then, having been released, they went to their own, and they reported in full what the leaders of the priests and the elders had said to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when they had heard it, with one accord, they lifted up their voice to God, and they said: &#8220;Lord, you are the One who made heaven and earth, the sea and all that is in them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>who, by the Holy Spirit, through the mouth of our father David, your servant, said: &#8216;Why have the Gentiles been seething, and why have the people been pondering nonsense?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The kings of the earth have stood up, and the leaders have joined together as one, against the Lord and against his Christ.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For truly Herod and Pontius Pilate, with the Gentiles and the people of Israel, joined together in this city against your holy servant Jesus, whom you anointed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>to do what your hand and your counsel had decreed would be done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And now, O Lord, look upon their threats, and grant to your servants that they may speak your word with all confidence,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>by extending your hand in cures and signs and miracles, to be done through the name of your holy Son, Jesus.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when they had prayed, the place in which they were gathered was moved. And they were all filled with the Holy Spirit. And they were speaking the Word of God with confidence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then the multitude of believers were of one heart and one soul. Neither did anyone say that any of the things that he possessed were his own, but all things were common to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And with great power, the Apostles were rendering testimony to the Resurrection of Jesus Christ our Lord. And great grace was in them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And neither was anyone among them in need. For as many as were owners of fields or houses, selling these, were bringing the proceeds of the things that they were selling,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and were placing it before the feet of the Apostles. Then it was divided to each one, just as he had need.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Now Joseph, who the Apostles surnamed Barnabas (which is translated as &#8216;son of consolation&#8217;), who was a Levite of Cyprian descent,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>since he had land, he sold it, and he brought the proceeds and placed these at the feet of the Apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> This double negative in the Latin translates awkwardly if it is translated too literally.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But a certain man named Ananias, with his wife Sapphira, sold a field,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he was deceitful about the price of the field, with his wife&#8217;s consent. And bringing only part of it, he placed it at the feet of the Apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But Peter said: &#8220;Ananias, why has Satan tempted your heart, so that you would lie to the Holy Spirit and be deceitful about the price of the land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Did it not belong to you while you retained it? And having sold it, was it not in your power? Why have you set this thing in your heart? You have not lied to men, but to God!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Ananias, upon hearing these words, fell down and expired. And a great fear overwhelmed all who heard of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the young men rose up and removed him; and carrying him out, they buried him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then about the space of three hours passed, and his wife entered, not knowing what had happened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And Peter said to her, &#8220;Tell me, woman, if you sold the field for this amount?&#8221; And she said, &#8220;Yes, for that amount.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And Peter said to her: &#8220;Why have you agreed together to test the Spirit of the Lord? Behold, the feet of those who have buried your husband are at the door, and they shall carry you out!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Immediately, she fell down before his feet and expired. Then the young men entered and found her dead. And they carried her out and buried her next to her husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And a great fear came over the entire Church and over all who heard these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And through the hands of the Apostles many signs and wonders were accomplished among the people. And they all met with one accord at Solomon&#8217;s portico.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And among the others, no one dared to join himself to them. But the people magnified them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now the multitude of men and women who believed in the Lord was ever increasing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>so much so that they laid the infirm in the streets, placing them on beds and stretchers, so that, as Peter arrived, at least his shadow might fall upon any one of them, and they would be freed from their infirmities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But a multitude also hurried to Jerusalem from the neighboring cities, carrying the sick and those troubled by unclean spirits, who were all healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then the high priest and all those who were with him, that is, the heretical sect of the Sadducees, rose up and were filled with jealousy.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And they laid hands on the Apostles, and they placed them in the common prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But in the night, an Angel of the Lord opened the doors of the prison and led them out, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>&#8220;Go and stand in the temple, speaking to the people all these words of life.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And when they had heard this, they entered the temple at first light, and they were teaching. Then the high priest, and those who were with him, approached, and they called together the council and all the elders of the sons of Israel. And they sent to the prison to have them brought.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But when the attendants had arrived, and, upon opening the prison, had not found them, they returned and reported to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>saying: &#8220;We found the prison certainly locked up with all diligence, and the guards standing before the door. But upon opening it, we found no one within.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then, when the magistrate of the temple and the chief priests heard these words, they were uncertain about them, as to what should happen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But someone arrived and reported to them, &#8220;Behold, the men whom you placed in prison are in the temple, standing and teaching the people.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then the magistrate, with the attendants, went and brought them without force. For they were afraid of the people, lest they be stoned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when they had brought them, they stood them before the council. And the high priest questioned them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and said: &#8220;We strongly order you not to teach in this name. For behold, you have filled Jerusalem with your doctrine, and you wish to bring the blood of this man upon us.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>But Peter and the Apostles responded by saying: &#8220;It is necessary to obey God, more so than men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The God of our fathers has raised up Jesus, whom you put to death by hanging him on a tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>It is he whom God has exalted at his right hand as Ruler and Savior, so as to offer repentance and the remission of sins to Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And we are witnesses of these things, with the Holy Spirit, whom God has given to all who are obedient to him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>When they had heard these things, they were deeply wounded, and they were planning to put them to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But someone in the council, a Pharisee named Gamaliel, a teacher of the law honored by all the people, rose up and ordered the men to be put outside briefly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And he said to them: &#8220;Men of Israel, you should be careful in your intentions about these men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For before these days, Theudas stepped forward, asserting himself to be someone, and a number of men, about four hundred, joined with him. But he was killed, and all who believed in him were scattered, and they were reduced to nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>After this one, Judas the Galilean stepped forward, in the days of the enrollment, and he turned the people toward himself. But he also perished, and all of them, as many as had joined with him, were dispersed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And now therefore, I say to you, withdraw from these men and leave them alone. For if this counsel or work is of men, it will be broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Yet truly, if it is of God, you will not be able to break it, and perhaps you might be found to have fought against God.&#8221; And they agreed with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And calling in the Apostles, having beaten them, they warned them not to speak at all in the name of Jesus. And they dismissed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And indeed, they went forth from the presence of the council, rejoicing that they were considered worthy to suffer insult on behalf of the name of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And every day, in the temple and among the houses, they did not cease to teach and to evangelize Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Notice that the Pharisees have now lost power, and the Sadducees are the ones who are associated with the high priest and are influential with him. The Sadducees were heretical because they did not believe in Angels, nor in fallen angels, nor in the Resurrection. The Pharisees probably lost power due to their actions against Jesus, whereby they pressured Pilate to allow him to be put to death, even though he was innocent.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The repetition of the verb intensifies its meaning.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The Holy Spirit and sanctifying grace are not given only to those who are formally baptized, but those who are obedient to the will of God can also receive sanctifying grace in a non-formal baptism.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In those days, as the number of disciples was increasing, there occurred a murmuring of the Greeks against the Hebrews, because their widows were treated with disdain in the daily ministration.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And so the twelve, calling together the multitude of the disciples, said: &#8220;It is not fair for us to leave behind the Word of God to serve at tables also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore, brothers, search among yourselves for seven men of good testimony, filled with the Holy Spirit and with wisdom, whom we may appoint over this work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Yet truly, we will be continually in prayer and in the ministry of the Word.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the plan pleased the entire multitude. And they chose Stephen, a man filled with faith and with the Holy Spirit, and Philip and Prochorus and Nicanor and Timon and Parmenas and Nicolas, a new arrival from Antioch.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>These they set before the sight of the Apostles, and while praying, they imposed hands on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the Word of the Lord was increasing, and the number of disciples in Jerusalem was multiplied exceedingly. And even a large group of the priests were obedient to the faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then Stephen, filled with grace and fortitude, wrought great signs and miracles among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But certain ones, from the synagogue of the so-called Libertines, and of the Cyrenians, and of the Alexandrians, and of those who were from Cilicia and Asia rose up and were disputing with Stephen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But they were not able to resist the wisdom and the Spirit with which he was speaking.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then they suborned men who were to claim that they had heard him speaking words of blasphemy against Moses and against God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And thus did they stir up the people and the elders and the scribes. And hurrying together, they seized him and brought him to the council.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they set up false witnesses, who said: &#8220;This man does not cease to speak words against the holy place and the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For we have heard him saying that this Jesus the Nazarene will destroy this place and will change the traditions, which Moses handed down to us.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And all those who were sitting in the council, gazing at him, saw his face, as if it had become the face of an Angel.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> It is this Nicolas whom the Nicolaitans claim was the inspiration for their heretical group, but he himself was never a member, nor the founder, of the group, nor did he teach their heresies.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the high priest said, &#8220;Are these things so?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Stephen said: &#8220;Noble brothers and fathers, listen. The God of glory appeared to our father Abraham, when he was in Mesopotamia, before he stayed in Haran.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And God said to him, &#8216;Depart from your country and from your kindred, and go into the land that I will show to you.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then he went away from the land of the Chaldeans, and he lived at Haran. And later, after his father was dead, God brought him into this land, in which you now dwell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And he gave him no inheritance in it, not even the space of one step. But he promised to give it to him as a possession, and to his offspring after him, though he did not have a son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then God told him that his offspring would be a settler in a foreign land, and that they would subjugate them, and treat them badly, for four hundred years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>&#8216;And the nation whom they will serve, I will judge,&#8217; said the Lord. &#8216;And after these things, they shall depart and shall serve me in this place.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And he gave him the covenant of circumcision. And so he conceived Isaac and circumcised him on the eighth day. And Isaac conceived Jacob, and Jacob, the twelve Patriarchs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the Patriarchs, being jealous, sold Joseph into Egypt. But God was with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And he rescued him from all his tribulations. And he gave him grace and wisdom in the sight of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. And he appointed him as governor over Egypt and over all his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then a famine occurred in all of Egypt and Canaan, and a great tribulation. And our fathers did not find food.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But when Jacob had heard that there was grain in Egypt, he sent our fathers first.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And on the second occasion, Joseph was recognized by his brothers, and his ancestry was made manifest to Pharaoh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then Joseph sent for and brought his father Jacob, with all his kindred, seventy-five souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Jacob descended into Egypt, and he passed away, and so did our fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And they crossed over into Shechem, and they were placed in the sepulcher which Abraham bought for a sum of money from the sons of Hamor, the son of Shechem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when the time of the Promise that God had revealed to Abraham drew near, the people increased and were multiplied in Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>even until another king, who did not know Joseph, rose up in Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>This one, encompassing our kindred, afflicted our fathers, so that they would expose their infants, lest they be kept alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In the same time, Moses was born. And he was in the grace of God, and he was nourished for three months in the house of his father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then, having been abandoned, the daughter of Pharaoh took him in, and she raised him as her own son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians. And he was mighty in his words and in his deeds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But when forty years of age were completed in him, it rose up in his heart that he should visit his brothers, the sons of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when he had seen a certain one suffering injury, he defended him. And striking the Egyptian, he wrought a retribution for him who was enduring the injury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now he supposed that his brothers would understand that God would grant them salvation through his hand. But they did not understand it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So truly, on the following day, he appeared before those who were arguing, and he would have reconciled them in peace, saying, &#8216;Men, you are brothers. So why would you harm one another?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But he who was causing the injury to his neighbor rejected him, saying: &#8216;Who has appointed you as leader and judge over us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Could it be that you want to kill me, in the same way that you killed the Egyptian yesterday?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then, at this word, Moses fled. And he became a foreigner in the land of Midian, where he produced two sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And when forty years were completed, there appeared to him, in the desert of Mount Sinai, an Angel, in a flame of fire in a bush.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And upon seeing this, Moses was amazed at the sight. And as he drew near in order to gaze at it, the voice of the Lord came to him, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>&#8216;I am the God of your fathers: the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.&#8217; And Moses, being made to tremble, did not dare to look.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But the Lord said to him: &#8216;Loosen the shoes from your feet. For the place in which you stand is holy ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Certainly, I have seen the affliction of my people who are in Egypt, and I have heard their groaning. And so, I am coming down to free them. And now, go forth and I will send you into Egypt.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>This Moses, whom they rejected by saying, &#8216;Who has appointed you as leader and judge?&#8217; is the one God sent to be leader and redeemer, by the hand of the Angel who appeared to him in the bush.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>This man led them out, accomplishing signs and wonders in the land of Egypt, and at the Red Sea, and in the desert, for forty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>This is Moses, who said to the sons of Israel: &#8216;God will raise up for you a prophet like me from your own brothers. You shall listen to him.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>This is he who was in the Church in the wilderness, with the Angel who was speaking to him on Mount Sinai, and with our fathers. It is he who received the words of life to give to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>It is he whom our fathers were not willing to obey. Instead, they rejected him, and in their hearts they turned away toward Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>saying to Aaron: &#8216;Make gods for us, which may go before us. For this Moses, who led us away from the land of Egypt, we do not know what has happened to him.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And so they fashioned a calf in those days, and they offered sacrifices to an idol, and they rejoiced in the works of their own hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Then God turned, and he handed them over, to subservience to the armies of heaven, just as it was written in the Book of the Prophets: &#8216;Did you not offer victims and sacrifices to me for forty years in the desert, O house of Israel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And yet you took up for yourselves the tabernacle of Moloch and the star of your god Rephan, figures which you yourselves formed in order to adore them. And so I will carry you away, beyond Babylon.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>The tabernacle of the testimony was with our fathers in the desert, just as God ordained for them, speaking to Moses, so that he would make it according to the form that he had seen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>But our fathers, receiving it, also brought it, with Joshua, into the land of the Gentiles, whom God expelled before the face of our fathers, even until the days of David,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>who found grace before God and who asked that he might obtain a tabernacle for the God of Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>But it was Solomon who built a house for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Yet the Most High does not live in houses built by hands, just as he said through the prophet:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>&#8216;Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool. What kind of house would you build for me? says the Lord. And which is my resting place?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Has not my hand made all these things?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Stiff-necked and uncircumcised in heart and ears, you ever resist the Holy Spirit. Just as your fathers did, so also do you do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Which of the Prophets have your fathers not persecuted? And they killed those who foretold the advent of the Just One. And you have now become the betrayers and murderers of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>You received the law by the actions of Angels, and yet you have not kept it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Then, upon hearing these things, they were deeply wounded in their hearts, and they gnashed their teeth at him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>But he, being filled with the Holy Spirit, and gazing intently toward heaven, saw the glory of God and Jesus standing at the right hand of God. And he said, &#8220;Behold, I see the heavens opened, and the Son of man standing at the right hand of God.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Then they, crying out with a loud voice, blocked their ears and, with one accord, rushed violently toward him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>And driving him out, beyond the city, they stoned him. And witnesses placed their garments beside the feet of a youth, who was called Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>And as they were stoning Stephen, he called out and said, &#8220;Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>Then, having been brought to his knees, he cried out with a loud voice, saying, &#8220;Lord, do not hold this sin against them.&#8221; And when he had said this, he fell asleep in the Lord. And Saul was consenting to his murder.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Famines are associated with both the first and second parts of the tribulation.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Good Angels often have a role in miraculous signs and wonders, therefore, the assertion that a true miracle is something that is done by God alone is not correct. God often chooses to give true miracles through both the use of His power and through the use of His holy Angels.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> The repetition of the verb intensified the meaning; it is not necessary to repeat the verb in the translation, but rather this intensification can be expressed in other ways.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> The assembly of the Israelites in the desert was a foreshadowing of the Catholic Christian Church, and was itself a kind of Church.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now in those days, there occurred a great persecution against the Church at Jerusalem. And they were all dispersed throughout the regions of Judea and Samaria, except the Apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But God-fearing men arranged for Stephen&#8217;s funeral, and they made a great mourning over him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then Saul was laying waste to the Church by entering throughout the houses, and dragging away men and women, and committing them to prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Therefore, those who had been dispersed were traveling around, evangelizing the Word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now Philip, descending to a city of Samaria, was preaching Christ to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the crowd was listening intently and with one accord to those things which were being said by Philip, and they were watching the signs which he was accomplishing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For many of them had unclean spirits, and, crying out with a loud voice, these departed from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And many of the paralytics and the lame were cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Therefore, there was great gladness in that city. Now there was a certain man named Simon, who formerly had been a magician in that city, seducing the people of Samaria, claiming himself to be someone great.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And to all those who would listen, from the least even to the greatest, he was saying: &#8220;Here is the power of God, which is called great.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And they were attentive to him because, for a long time, he had deluded them with his magic.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Yet truly, once they had believed Philip, who was evangelizing the kingdom of God, both men and women were baptized in the name of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Simon himself also believed and, when he had been baptized, he adhered to Philip. And now, seeing also the greatest signs and miracles being wrought, he was amazed and stupefied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now when the Apostles who were in Jerusalem had heard that Samaria had received the Word of God, they sent Peter and John to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when they had arrived, they prayed for them, so that they might receive the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For he had not yet come to any among them, since they were only baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then they laid their hands on them, and they received the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But when Simon had seen that, by the imposition of the hands of the Apostles, the Holy Spirit was given, he offered them money,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>saying, &#8220;Give this power to me also, so that on whomever I will lay my hands, he may receive the Holy Spirit.&#8221; But Peter said to him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>&#8220;Let your money be with you in perdition, for you have supposed that a gift of God might be possessed by money.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>There is no part or place for you in this matter. For your heart is not upright in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And so, repent from this, your wickedness, and beg God, so that perhaps this plan of your heart might be forgiven you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For I perceive you to be in the gall of bitterness and in the bond of iniquity.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then Simon responded by saying, &#8220;Pray for me to the Lord, so that nothing of what you have said may happen to me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And indeed, after testifying and speaking the Word of the Lord, they returned to Jerusalem, and they evangelized the many regions of the Samaritans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now an Angel of the Lord spoke to Philip, saying, &#8220;Rise up and go toward the south, to the way which descends from Jerusalem into Gaza, where there is a desert.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And rising up, he went. And behold, an Ethiopian man, a eunuch, powerful under Candace, the queen of the Ethiopians, who was over all her treasures, had arrived in Jerusalem to worship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And while returning, he was sitting upon his chariot and reading from the prophet Isaiah.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then the Spirit said to Philip, &#8220;Draw near and join yourself to this chariot.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And Philip, hurrying, heard him reading from the prophet Isaiah, and he said, &#8220;Do you think that you understand what you are reading?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And he said, &#8220;But how can I, unless someone will have revealed it to me?&#8221; And he asked Philip to climb up and sit with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now the place in Scripture that he was reading was this: &#8220;Like a sheep he was led to the slaughter. And like a lamb silent before his shearer, so he opened not his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He endured his judgment with humility. Who of his generation shall describe how his life was taken away from the earth?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then the eunuch responded to Philip, saying: &#8220;I beg you, about whom is the prophet saying this? About himself, or about someone else?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then Philip, opening his mouth and beginning from this Scripture, evangelized Jesus to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And while they were going along the way, they arrived at a certain water source. And the eunuch said: &#8220;There is water. What would prevent me from being baptized?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then Philip said, &#8220;If you believe from your whole heart, it is permitted.&#8221; And he responded by saying, &#8220;I believe the Son of God to be Jesus the Christ.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And he ordered the chariot to stand still. And both Philip and the eunuch descended into the water. And he baptized him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And when they had ascended from the water, the Spirit of the Lord took Philip away, and the eunuch did not see him anymore. Then he went on his way, rejoicing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Now Philip was found in Azotus. And continuing on, he evangelized all the cities, until he arrived in Caesarea.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> It seems from this passage that some early valid Baptisms used only the name of Jesus, and that receiving the Holy Spirit was a separate Sacrament, that of Confirmation. This is clear because the receiving of the Holy Spirit was through the laying on of hands, without the use of water.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now Saul, still breathing threats and beatings against the disciples of the Lord, went to the high priest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he petitioned him for letters to the synagogues in Damascus, so that, if he found any men or women belonging to this Way, he could lead them as prisoners to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And as he made the journey, it happened that he was approaching Damascus. And suddenly, a light from heaven shone around him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And falling to the ground, he heard a voice saying to him, &#8220;Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And he said, &#8220;Who are you, Lord?&#8221; And he: &#8220;I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting. It is hard for you to kick against the goad.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And he, trembling and astonished, said, &#8220;Lord, what do you want me to do?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the Lord said to him, &#8220;Rise up and go into the city, and there you will be told what you ought to do.&#8221; Now the men who were accompanying him were standing stupefied, hearing indeed a voice, but seeing no one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then Saul rose up from the ground. And upon opening his eyes, he saw nothing. So leading him by the hand, they brought him into Damascus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And in that place, he was without sight for three days, and he neither ate nor drank.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now there was a certain disciple at Damascus, named Ananias. And the Lord said to him in a vision, &#8220;Ananias!&#8221; And he said, &#8220;Here I am, Lord.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the Lord said to him: &#8220;Rise up and go into the street that is called Straight, and seek, in the house of Judas, the one named Saul of Tarsus. For behold, he is praying.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>(And Paul saw a man named Ananias entering and imposing hands upon him, so that he might receive his sight.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But Ananias responded: &#8220;Lord, I have heard from many about this man, how much harm he has done to your saints in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he has authority here from the leaders of the priests to bind all who invoke your name.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then the Lord said to him: &#8220;Go, for this one is an instrument chosen by me to convey my name before nations and kings and the sons of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For I will reveal to him how much he must suffer on behalf of my name.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Ananias departed. And he entered the house. And laying his hands upon him, he said: &#8220;Brother Saul, the Lord Jesus, he who appeared to you on the way by which you arrived, sent me so that you would receive your sight and be filled with the Holy Spirit.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And immediately, it was as if scales had fallen from his eyes, and he received his sight. And rising up, he was baptized.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when he had taken a meal, he was strengthened. Now he was with the disciples who were at Damascus for some days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And he was continuously preaching Jesus in the synagogues: that he is the Son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And all who heard him were astonished, and they said, &#8220;Is this not the one who, in Jerusalem, was fighting against those invoking this name, and who came here for this: so that he might lead them away to the leaders of the priests?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But Saul was increasing to a greater extent in ability, and so he was confounding the Jews who lived at Damascus, by affirming that he is the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when many days were completed, the Jews took counsel as one, so that they might put him to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But their treachery became known to Saul. Now they were also watching the gates, day and night, so that they might put him to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But the disciples, taking him away by night, sent him over the wall by letting him down in a basket.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when he had arrived in Jerusalem, he attempted to join himself to the disciples. And they were all afraid of him, not believing that he was a disciple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But Barnabas took him aside and led him to the Apostles. And he explained to them how he had seen the Lord, and that he had spoken to him, and how, in Damascus, he had acted faithfully in the name of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And he was with them, entering and departing Jerusalem, and acting faithfully in the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He also was speaking with the Gentiles and disputing with the Greeks. But they were seeking to kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And when the brothers had realized this, they brought him to Caesarea and sent him away to Tarsus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Certainly, the Church had peace throughout all of Judea and Galilee and Samaria, and it was being built up, while walking in the fear of the Lord, and it was being filled with the consolation of the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then it happened that Peter, as he traveled around everywhere, came to the saints who were living at Lydda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But he found there a certain man, named Aeneas, who was a paralytic, who had lain in bed for eight years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And Peter said to him: &#8220;Aeneas, the Lord Jesus Christ heals you. Rise up and arrange your bed.&#8221; And immediately he rose up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And all who were living in Lydda and Sharon saw him, and they were converted to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Now in Joppa there was a certain disciple named Tabitha, which in translation is called Dorcas. She was filled with the good works and almsgiving that she was accomplishing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And it happened that, in those days, she became ill and died. And when they had washed her, they laid her in an upper room.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Now since Lydda was close to Joppa, the disciples, upon hearing that Peter was there, sent two men to him, asking him: &#8220;Do not be slow in coming to us.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Then Peter, rising up, went with them. And when he had arrived, they led him to an upper room. And all the widows were standing around him, weeping and showing him the tunics and garments that Dorcas had made for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And when they had all been sent outside, Peter, kneeling down, prayed. And turning to the body, he said: &#8220;Tabitha, arise.&#8221; And she opened her eyes and, upon seeing Peter, sat up again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And offering her his hand, he lifted her up. And when he had called in the saints and the widows, he presented her alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Now this became known throughout all of Joppa. And many believed in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And it happened that he resided for many days in Joppa, with a certain Simon, a tanner.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The text literally says &#8216;kick against the goad,&#8217; but this is an idiomatic expression meaning: &#8216;It is hard for you to resist the will of God,&#8217; in other words: it is hard to act against Divine Providence and grace. This phrase occurs twice in Acts and in this translation is given in two different wordings, each of which reveals the meaning of the idiomatic expression, rather than translating that expression literally and obscurely.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now there was a certain man in Caesarea, named Cornelius, a centurion of the cohort which is called Italian,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>a devout man, fearing God with all his house, giving many alms to the people, and praying to God continually.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>This man saw in a vision clearly, at about the ninth hour of the day, the Angel of God entering to him and saying to him: &#8220;Cornelius!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And he, gazing at him, was seized by fear, and he said, &#8220;What is it, lord?&#8221; And he said to him: &#8220;Your prayers and your almsgiving have ascended as a memorial in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And now, send men to Joppa and summon a certain Simon, who is surnamed Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This man is a guest with a certain Simon, a tanner, whose house is beside the sea. He will tell you what you must do.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when the Angel who was speaking to him had departed, he called, out of those who were subject to him, two of his household servants and a soldier who feared the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when he had explained everything to them, he sent them to Joppa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then, on the following day, while they were making the journey and approaching the city, Peter ascended to the upper rooms, so that he might pray, at about the sixth hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And since he was hungry, he wanted to enjoy some food. Then, as they were preparing it, an ecstasy of mind fell over him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And he saw heaven opened, and a certain container descending, as if a great linen sheet were let down, by its four corners, from heaven to earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>on which were all four-footed beasts, and the crawling things of the earth and the flying things of the air.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And a voice came to him: &#8220;Rise up, Peter! Kill and eat.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But Peter said: &#8220;Far be it from me, lord. For I have never eaten anything common or unclean.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the voice, again a second time to him: &#8220;What God has purified, you shall not call common.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now this was done three times. And immediately the container was taken up to heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now while Peter was still hesitant within himself as to what the vision, which he had seen, might mean, behold, the men who had been sent from Cornelius stood at the gate, inquiring about Simon&#8217;s house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when they had called out, they asked if Simon, who is surnamed Peter, was a guest in that place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then, as Peter was thinking about the vision, the Spirit said to him, &#8220;Behold, three men seek you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And so, rise up, descend, and go with them, doubting nothing. For I have sent them.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Peter, descending to the men, said: &#8220;Behold, I am the one whom you seek. What is the reason for which you have arrived?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And they said: &#8220;Cornelius, a centurion, a just and God-fearing man, who has good testimony from the entire nation of the Jews, received a message from a holy Angel to summon you to his house and to listen to words from you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Therefore, leading them in, he received them as guests. Then, on following the day, rising up, he set out with them. And some of the brothers from Joppa accompanied him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And on the next day, he entered Caesarea. And truly, Cornelius was waiting for them, having called together his family and closest friends.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And it happened that, when Peter had entered, Cornelius went to meet him. And falling before his feet, he reverenced.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Yet truly, Peter, lifting him up, said: &#8220;Rise up, for I also am only a man.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And speaking with him, he entered, and he found many who had gathered together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And he said to them: &#8220;You know how abominable it would be for a Jewish man to be joined with, or to be added to, a foreign people. But God has revealed to me to call no man common or unclean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Because of this and without doubt, I came when summoned. Therefore, I ask you, for what reason have you summoned me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And Cornelius said: &#8220;It is now the fourth day, to this very hour, since I was praying in my house at the ninth hour, and behold, a man stood before me in a white vestment, and he said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>&#8216;Cornelius, your prayer has been heard and your almsgiving has been remembered in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Therefore, send to Joppa and summon Simon, who is surnamed Peter. This man is a guest in the house of Simon, a tanner, near the sea.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And so, I promptly sent for you. And you have done well in coming here. Therefore, all of us are now present in your sight to hear all the things that were taught to you by the Lord.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then, Peter, opening his mouth, said: &#8220;I have concluded in truth that God is not a respecter of persons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>But within every nation, whoever fears him and works justice is acceptable to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>God sent the Word to the sons of Israel, announcing the peace through Jesus Christ, for he is the Lord of all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>You know that the Word has been made known throughout all Judea. For beginning from Galilee, after the baptism which John preached,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Jesus of Nazareth, whom God anointed with the Holy Spirit and with power, traveled around doing good and healing all those oppressed by the devil. For God was with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And we are witnesses of all that he did in the region of Judea and in Jerusalem, he whom they killed by hanging him on a tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>God raised him up on the third day and permitted him to be made manifest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>not to all the people, but to the witnesses preordained by God, to those of us who ate and drank with him after he rose again from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And he instructed us to preach to the people, and to testify that he is the One who was appointed by God to be the judge of the living and of the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>To him all the Prophets offer testimony that through his name all who believe in him receive the remission of sins.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>While Peter was still speaking these words, the Holy Spirit fell over all of those who were listening to the Word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And the faithful of the circumcision, who had arrived with Peter, were astonished that the grace of the Holy Spirit was also poured out upon the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>For they heard them speaking in tongues and magnifying God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Then Peter responded, &#8220;How could anyone prohibit water, so that those who have received the Holy Spirit would not be baptized, just as we also have been?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And he ordered them to be baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Then they begged him to remain with them for some days.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The earliest valid Sacrament of Baptism was in the name of Jesus, probably without the Trinitarian formula. But the Church has authority over the Sacraments, even concerning certain conditions for validity, so that today, the Trinitarian formula is generally required for a valid Baptism.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the Apostles and brothers who were in Judea heard that the Gentiles had also received the Word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then, when Peter had gone up to Jerusalem, those who were of the circumcision argued against him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>saying, &#8220;Why did you enter to uncircumcised men, and why did you eat with them?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Peter began to explain to them, in an orderly manner, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>&#8220;I was in the city of Joppa praying, and I saw, in an ecstasy of mind, a vision: a certain container descending, like a great linen sheet being let down from heaven by its four corners. And it drew near to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And looking into it, I considered and saw the four-footed beasts of the earth, and the wild beasts, and the reptiles, and the flying things of the air.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then I also heard a voice saying to me: &#8216;Rise up, Peter. Kill and eat.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But I said: &#8216;Never, lord! For what is common or unclean has never entered into my mouth.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then the voice responded a second time from heaven, &#8216;What God has cleansed, you shall not call common.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now this was done three times. And then everything was taken up again into heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And behold, immediately there were three men standing near the house where I was, having been sent to me from Caesarea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the Spirit told me that I should go with them, doubting nothing. And these six brothers went with me also. And we entered into the house of the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And he described for us how he had seen an Angel in his house, standing and saying to him: &#8216;Send to Joppa and summon Simon, who is surnamed Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he shall speak to you words, by which you shall be saved with your whole house.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when I had begun to speak, the Holy Spirit fell upon them, just as upon us also, in the beginning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then I remembered the words of the Lord, just as he himself said: &#8216;John, indeed, baptized with water, but you shall be baptized with the Holy Spirit.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore, if God gave them the same grace, as also to us, who have believed in the Lord Jesus Christ, who was I, that I would be able to prohibit God?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Having heard these things, they were silent. And they glorified God, saying: &#8220;So has God also given to the Gentiles repentance unto life.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And some of them, having been dispersed by the persecution that had occurred under Stephen, traveled around, even to Phoenicia and Cyprus and Antioch, speaking the Word to no one, except to Jews only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But some of these men from Cyprus and Cyrene, when they had entered into Antioch, were speaking also to the Greeks, announcing the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the hand of the Lord was with them. And a great number believed and were converted to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now the news came to the ears of the Church at Jerusalem about these things, and they sent Barnabas as far as Antioch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when he had arrived there and had seen the grace of God, he was gladdened. And he exhorted them all to continue in the Lord with a resolute heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For he was a good man, and he was filled with the Holy Spirit and with faith. And a great multitude was added to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then Barnabas set out for Tarsus, so that he might seek Saul. And when he had found him, he brought him to Antioch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And they were conversing there in the Church for an entire year. And they taught such a great multitude, that it was at Antioch that the disciples were first known by the name of Christian.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now in these days, prophets from Jerusalem went over to Antioch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And one of them, named Agabus, rising up, signified through the Spirit that there was going to be a great famine over the entire world, which did happen under Claudius.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then the disciples declared, according to what each one possessed, what they would offer to be sent to the brothers living in Judea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And so they did, sending it to the elders by the hands of Barnabas and Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Although this famine did occur under Claudius, it will occur more generally over the world, twice. First, during the first part of the tribulation, there will be a severe famine; but this famine will be less harmful in the poorer nations and more harmful in the wealthy nations. Last, there will be a great famine, over nearly the whole world, during the time of the Antichrist&#8217;s reign, especially during the last half of that reign.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now at the same time, king Herod extended his hand, in order to afflict some from the Church.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then he killed James, the brother of John, with the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And seeing that it pleased the Jews, he set out next to apprehend Peter also. Now it was the days of Unleavened Bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So when he had apprehended him, he sent him into prison, handing him over into the custody of four groups of four soldiers, intending to produce him to the people after the Passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And so Peter was detained in prison. But prayers were being made without ceasing, by the Church, to God on his behalf.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when Herod was ready to produce him, in that same night, Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, and was bound with two chains. And there were guards in front of the door, guarding the prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And behold, an Angel of the Lord stood near, and a light shined forth in the cell. And tapping Peter on the side, he awakened him, saying, &#8220;Rise up, quickly.&#8221; And the chains fell from his hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the Angel said to him: &#8220;Dress yourself, and put on your boots.&#8221; And he did so. And he said to him, &#8220;Wrap your garment around yourself and follow me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And going out, he followed him. And he did not know this truth: that this was being done by an Angel. For he thought that he was seeing a vision.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And passing by the first and second guards, they came to the iron gate which leads into the city; and it opened for them by itself. And departing, they continued on along a certain side street. And suddenly the Angel withdrew from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Peter, returning to himself, said: &#8220;Now I know, truly, that the Lord sent his Angel, and that he rescued me from the hand of Herod and from all that the people of the Jews were anticipating.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And as he was considering this, he arrived at the house of Mary, the mother of John, who was surnamed Mark, where many were gathered and were praying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then, as he knocked at the door of the gate, a girl went out to answer, whose name was Rhoda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when she recognized the voice of Peter, out of joy, she did not open the gate, but instead, running in, she reported that Peter stood before the gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But they said to her, &#8220;You are crazy.&#8221; But she reaffirmed that this was so. Then they were saying, &#8220;It is his angel.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But Peter was persevering in knocking. And when they had opened, they saw him and were astonished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But motioning to them with his hand to be silent, he explained how the Lord had led him away from prison. And he said, &#8220;Inform James and those brothers.&#8221; And going out, he went away to another place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then, when daylight came, there was no small commotion among the soldiers, as to what had happened concerning Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when Herod had requested him and did not obtain him, having had the guards interrogated, he ordered them led away. And descending from Judea into Caesarea, he lodged there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now he was angry with those of Tyre and Sidon. But they came to him with one accord, and, having persuaded Blastus, who was over the bedchamber of the king, they petitioned for peace, because their regions were supplied with food by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then, on the appointed day, Herod was clothed in kingly apparel, and he sat in the judgment seat, and he gave a speech to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then the people were crying out, &#8220;The voice of a god, and not of a man!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And immediately, an Angel of the Lord struck him down, because he had not given honor to God. And having been consumed by worms, he expired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But the word of the Lord was increasing and multiplying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then Barnabas and Saul, having completed the ministry, returned from Jerusalem, bringing with them John, who was surnamed Mark.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;caligas&#8217; is &#8216;boots,&#8217; not &#8216;sandals.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> They did not mean literally, an angel, but his ghost (so they thought).</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now there were, in the Church at Antioch, prophets and teachers, among whom were Barnabas, and Simon, who was called the Black, and Lucius of Cyrene, and Manahen, who was the foster brother of Herod the tetrarch, and Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now as they were ministering for the Lord and fasting, the Holy Spirit said to them: &#8220;Separate Saul and Barnabas for me, for the work for which I have selected them.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then, fasting and praying and imposing their hands upon them, they sent them away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And having been sent by the Holy Spirit, they went to Seleucia. And from there they sailed to Cyprus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when they had arrived at Salamis, they were preaching the Word of God in the synagogues of the Jews. And they also had John in the ministry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when they had traveled throughout the entire island, even to Paphos, they found a certain man, a magician, a false prophet, a Jew, whose name was Bar-Jesu.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And he was with the proconsul, Sergius Paulus, a prudent man. This man, summoning Barnabas and Saul, wanted to hear the Word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But Elymas the magician (for so his name is translated) stood against them, seeking to turn the proconsul away from the Faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then Saul, who is also called Paul, having been filled with the Holy Spirit, looked intently at him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and he said: &#8220;So full of every deceit and of all falsehoods, son of the devil, enemy of all justice, you never cease to subvert the righteous ways of the Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And now, behold, the hand of the Lord is upon you. And you will be blinded, not seeing the sun for a length of time.&#8221; And immediately a fog and a darkness fell over him. And wandering around, he was seeking someone who might lead him by the hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the proconsul, when he had seen what was done, believed, being in wonder over the doctrine of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when Paul and those who were with him had sailed from Paphos, they arrived at Perga in Pamphylia. Then John departed from them and returned to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Yet truly, they, traveling on from Perga, arrived at Antioch in Pisidia. And upon entering the synagogue on the Sabbath day, they sat down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then, after the reading from the Law and the Prophets, the leaders of the synagogue sent to them, saying: &#8220;Noble brothers, if there is in you any word of exhortation to the people, speak.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then Paul, rising up and motioning for silence with his hand, said: &#8220;Men of Israel and you who fear God, listen closely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The God of the people of Israel chose our fathers, and exalted the people, when they were settlers in the land of Egypt. And with an exalted arm, he led them away from there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And throughout a time of forty years, he endured their behavior in the desert.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And by destroying seven nations in the land of Canaan, he divided their land among them by lot,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>after about four hundred and fifty years. And after these things, he gave them judges, even until the prophet Samuel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And later on, they petitioned for a king. And God gave them Saul, the son of Kish, a man from the tribe of Benjamin, for forty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And having removed him, he raised up for them king David. And offering testimony about him, he said, &#8216;I have found David, the son of Jesse, to be a man according to my own heart, who will accomplish all that I will.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>From his offspring, according to the Promise, God has brought Jesus the Savior to Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>John was preaching, before the face of his advent, a baptism of repentance to all the people of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then, when John completed his course, he was saying: &#8216;I am not the one you consider me to be. For behold, one arrives after me, the shoes of whose feet I am not worthy to loosen.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Noble brothers, sons of the stock of Abraham, and those among you who fear God, it is to you the Word of this salvation has been sent.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For those who were living in Jerusalem, and its rulers, heeding neither him, nor the voices of the Prophets that are read on every Sabbath, fulfilled these by judging him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And although they found no case for death against him, they petitioned Pilate, so that they might put him to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when they had fulfilled everything that had been written about him, taking him down from the tree, they placed him in a tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Yet truly, God raised him up from the dead on the third day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And he was seen for many days by those who went up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem, who even now are his witnesses to the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And we are announcing to you that the Promise, which was made to our fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>has been fulfilled by God for our children by raising up Jesus, just as it has been written in the second Psalm also: &#8216;You are my Son. This day I have begotten you.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Now, since he raised him from the dead, so as to no longer return to corruption, he has said this: &#8216;I will give to you the holy things of David, the faithful one.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And also then, in another place, he says: &#8216;You will not allow your Holy One to see corruption.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For David, when he had ministered to his generation in accordance with the will of God, fell asleep, and he was placed next to his fathers, and he saw corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Yet truly, he whom God has raised from the dead has not seen corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Therefore, let it be known to you, noble brothers, that through him is announced to you remission from sins and from everything by which you were not able to be justified in the law of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>In him, all who believe are justified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Therefore, be careful, lest what was said by the Prophets may overwhelm you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>&#8216;You despisers! Look, and wonder, and be scattered! For I am working a deed in your days, a deed which you would not believe, even if someone were to explain it to you.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Then, as they were departing, they asked them if, on the following Sabbath, they might speak these words to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And when the synagogue had been dismissed, many among the Jews and the new worshipers were following Paul and Barnabas. And they, speaking to them, persuaded them to continue in the grace of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Yet truly, on the following Sabbath, nearly the entire city came together to hear the Word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Then the Jews, seeing the crowds, were filled with envy, and they, blaspheming, contradicted the things that were being said by Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Then Paul and Barnabas said firmly: &#8220;It was necessary to speak the Word of God first to you. But because you reject it, and so judge yourselves unworthy of eternal life, behold, we turn to the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>For so has the Lord instructed us: &#8216;I have set you as a light to the Gentiles, so that you may bring salvation to the ends of the earth.&#8217;&#160;&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Then the Gentiles, upon hearing this, were gladdened, and they were glorifying the Word of the Lord. And as many as believed were preordained to eternal life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Now the word of the Lord was disseminated throughout the entire region.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>But the Jews incited some devout and honest women, and the leaders of the city. And they stirred up a persecution against Paul and Barnabas. And they drove them away from their parts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>But they, shaking the dust from their feet against them, went on to Iconium.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>The disciples were likewise filled with gladness and with the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> In the synagogues in that time period there would typically be some Hebrews (descendents of Abraham) and also some new converts to the Jewish faith, who were not of Hebrew descent. These latter Paul refers to as those who fear God.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now it happened in Iconium that they entered together into the synagogue of the Jews, and they spoke in such a way that a copious multitude of both Jews and Greeks believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Yet truly, the Jews who were unbelieving had incited and enflamed the souls of the Gentiles against the brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And so, they remained for a long time, acting faithfully in the Lord, offering testimony to the Word of his grace, providing signs and wonders done by their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then the multitude of the city was divided. And certainly, some were with the Jews, yet truly others were with the Apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now when an assault had been planned by the Gentiles and the Jews with their leaders, so that they might treat them with contempt and stone them,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>they, realizing this, fled together to Lystra and Derbe, cities of Lycaonia, and to the entire surrounding region. And they were evangelizing in that place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And a certain man was sitting at Lystra, disabled in his feet, lame from his mother&#8217;s womb, who had never walked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>This man heard Paul speaking. And Paul, gazing at him intently, and perceiving that he had faith, so that he might be healed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>said with a loud voice, &#8220;Stand upright upon your feet!&#8221; And he leaped up and walked around.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But when the crowds had seen what Paul had done, they lifted up their voice in the Lycaonian language, saying, &#8220;The gods, having taken the likenesses of men, have descended to us!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And they called Barnabas, &#8216;Jupiter,&#8217; yet truly they called Paul, &#8216;Mercury,&#8217; because he was the lead speaker.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Also, the priest of Jupiter, who was outside the city, in front of the gate, bringing in oxen and garlands, was willing to offer sacrifice with the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And as soon as the Apostles, Barnabas and Paul, had heard this, tearing their tunics, they leapt into the crowd, crying out</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and saying: &#8220;Men, why would you do this? We also are mortals, men like yourselves, preaching to you to be converted, from these vain things, to the living God, who made heaven and earth and the sea and all that is in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In previous generations, he permitted all nations to walk in their own ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But certainly, he did not leave himself without testimony, doing good from heaven, giving rains and fruitful seasons, filling their hearts with food and gladness.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And by saying these things, they were barely able to restrain the crowds from immolating to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now certain Jews from Antioch and Iconium arrived there. And having persuaded the crowd, they stoned Paul and dragged him outside of the city, thinking him to be dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But as the disciples were standing around him, he got up and entered the city. And the next day, he set out with Barnabas for Derbe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when they had evangelized that city, and had taught many, they returned again to Lystra and to Iconium and to Antioch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>strengthening the souls of the disciples, and exhorting them that they should remain always in the faith, and that it is necessary for us to enter into the kingdom of God through many tribulations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And when they had established priests for them in each church, and had prayed with fasting, they commended them to the Lord, in whom they believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And traveling by way of Pisidia, they arrived in Pamphylia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And having spoken the word of the Lord in Perga, they went down into Attalia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And from there, they sailed to Antioch, where they had been commended to the grace of God for the work which they had now accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when they had arrived and had gathered together the church, they related what great things God had done with them, and how he had opened the door of faith to the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And they remained for no small amount of time with the disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Literally, the text says &#8216;an assault of the Gentiles and Jews,&#8217; but the meaning is that Gentiles and Jews were the ones  planning the assault, so the translation rephrases to make this clear. Also, the verb &#8216;factus esset&#8217; might seem to mean that they had already made such an assault, but instead the meaning is that they made a plan to carry out the assault. So the most literal translation is not always the most accurate.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Corrected in the Latin and English according to the 1590 Sixtus V edition.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And certain ones, descending from Judea, were teaching the brothers, &#8220;Unless you are circumcised according to the custom of Moses, you cannot be saved.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Therefore, when Paul and Barnabas made no small uprising against them, they decided that Paul and Barnabas, and some from the opposing side, should go up to the Apostles and priests in Jerusalem concerning this question.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore, being led by the church, they traveled through Phoenicia and Samaria, describing the conversion of the Gentiles. And they caused great joy among all the brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when they had arrived in Jerusalem, they were received by the church and the Apostles and the elders, reporting what great things God had done with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But some from the sect of the Pharisees, those who were believers, rose up saying, &#8220;It is necessary for them to be circumcised and to be instructed to keep the Law of Moses.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the Apostles and elders came together to take care of this matter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And after a great contention had taken place, Peter rose up and said to them: &#8220;Noble brothers, you know that, in recent days, God has chosen from among us, by my mouth, Gentiles to hear the word of the Gospel and to believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And God, who knows hearts, offered testimony, by giving the Holy Spirit to them, just as to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he distinguished nothing between us and them, purifying their hearts by faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now therefore, why do you tempt God to impose a yoke upon the necks of the disciples, which neither our fathers nor we have been able to bear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But by the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, we believe in order to be saved, in the same manner also as them.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the entire multitude was silent. And they were listening to Barnabas and Paul, describing what great signs and wonders God had wrought among the Gentiles through them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And after they had been silent, James responded by saying: &#8220;Noble brothers, listen to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Simon has explained in what manner God first visited, so as to take from the Gentiles a people to his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the words of the Prophets are in agreement with this, just as it was written:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>&#8216;After these things, I will return, and I will rebuild the tabernacle of David, which has fallen down. And I will rebuild its ruins, and I will raise it up,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>so that the rest of men may seek the Lord, along with all the nations over whom my name has been invoked, says the Lord, who does these things.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>To the Lord, his own work has been known from eternity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because of this, I judge that those who were converted to God from among the Gentiles are not to be disturbed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but instead that we write to them, that they should keep themselves from the defilement of idols, and from fornication, and from whatever has been suffocated, and from blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For Moses, from ancient times, has had in each city those who preach him in the synagogues, where he is read on every Sabbath.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then it pleased the Apostles and elders, with the whole Church, to choose men from among them, and to send to Antioch, with Paul and Barnabas, and Judas, who was surnamed Barsabbas, and Silas, preeminent men among the brothers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>what was written by their own hands: &#8220;The Apostles and elders, brothers, to those who are at Antioch and Syria and Cilicia, brothers from the Gentiles, greetings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Since we have heard that some, going out from among us, have troubled you with words, subverting your souls, to whom we gave no commandment,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>it pleased us, being assembled as one, to choose men and to send them to you, with our most beloved Barnabas and Paul:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>men who have handed over their lives on behalf of the name of our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Therefore, we have sent Judas and Silas, who themselves also will, with the spoken word, reaffirm to you the same things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For it has seemed good to the Holy Spirit and to us to impose no further burden upon you, other than these necessary things:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>that you abstain from things immolated to idols, and from blood, and from what has been suffocated, and from fornication. You will do well to keep yourselves from these things. Farewell.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And so, having been dismissed, they went down to Antioch. And gathering the multitude together, they delivered the epistle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when they had read it, they were gladdened by this consolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But Judas and Silas, being also prophets themselves, consoled the brothers with many words, and they were strengthened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then, after spending some more time there, they were dismissed with peace, by the brothers, to those who had sent them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But it seemed good to Silas to remain there. So Judas alone departed to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And Paul and Barnabas remained at Antioch, with many others, teaching and evangelizing the Word of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then, after some days, Paul said to Barnabas, &#8220;Let us return to visit the brothers throughout all the cities in which we have preached the Word of the Lord, to see how they are.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Barnabas wanted to take John, who was surnamed Mark, with them also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But Paul was saying that he ought not to be received, since he withdrew from them at Pamphylia, and he had not gone with them in the work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And there occurred a dissension, to such an extent that they departed from one another. And Barnabas, indeed taking Mark, sailed to Cyprus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Yet truly, Paul, choosing Silas, set out, being delivered by the brothers to the grace of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And he traveled through Syria and Cilicia, confirming the Churches, instructing them to keep the precepts of the Apostles and the elders.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The figurative meaning of this four-fold prohibition (idols, blood, suffocated bodies of animals, fornication) refers to abstaining from the abomination of desolation, a false Eucharist. The abomination is idolatry, it is blood and meat (but not the true body and blood of Christ), and it is connected with severe sexual immorality.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then he arrived at Derbe and Lystra. And behold, a certain disciple named Timothy was there, the son of a faithful Jewish woman, his father a Gentile.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The brothers who were at Lystra and Iconium rendered good testimony to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Paul wanted this man to travel with him, and taking him, he circumcised him, because of the Jews who were in those places. For they all knew that his father was a Gentile.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And as they were traveling through the cities, they delivered to them the dogmas to be kept, which were decreed by the Apostles and elders who were at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And certainly, the Churches were being strengthened in faith and were increasing in number every day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then, while crossing through Phrygia and the region of Galatia, they were prevented by the Holy Spirit from speaking the Word in Asia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But when they had arrived in Mysia, they attempted to go into Bithynia, but the Spirit of Jesus would not permit them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then, when they had crossed through Mysia, they descended to Troas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And a vision in the night was revealed to Paul of a certain man of Macedonia, standing and pleading with him, and saying: &#8220;Cross into Macedonia and help us!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then, after he saw the vision, immediately we sought to set out for Macedonia, having been assured that God had called us to evangelize to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And sailing from Troas, taking a direct path, we arrived at Samothrace, and on the following day, at Neapolis,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and from there to Philippi, which is the preeminent city in the area of Macedonia, a colony. Now we were in this city some days, conferring together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then, on the Sabbath day, we were walking outside the gate, beside a river, where there seemed to be a prayer gathering. And sitting down, we were speaking with the women who had assembled.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And a certain woman, named Lydia, a seller of purple in the city of Thyatira, a worshiper of God, listened. And the Lord opened her heart to be receptive to what Paul was saying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when she had been baptized, with her household, she pleaded with us, saying: &#8220;If you have judged me to be faithful to the Lord, enter into my house and lodge there.&#8221; And she convinced us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then it happened that, as we were going out to prayer, a certain girl, having a spirit of divination, met with us. She was a source of great profit to her masters, through her divining.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>4</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This girl, following Paul and us, was crying out, saying: &#8220;These men are servants of the Most High God! They are announcing to you the way of salvation!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now she behaved in this way for many days. But Paul, being grieved, turned and said to the spirit, &#8220;I command you, in the name of Jesus Christ, to go out from her.&#8221; And it went away in that same hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But her masters, seeing that the hope of their profit went away, apprehended Paul and Silas, and they brought them to the rulers at the courthouse.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>5</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And presenting them to the magistrates, they said: &#8220;These men are disturbing our city, since they are Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they are announcing a way which is not lawful for us to accept or to observe, since we are Romans.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And the people rushed together against them. And the magistrates, tearing their tunics, ordered them to be beaten with staffs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when they had inflicted many scourges on them, they cast them into prison, instructing the guard to watch them diligently.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And since he had received this kind of order, he cast them into the interior prison cell, and he restricted their feet with stocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then, in the middle of the night, Paul and Silas were praying and praising God. And those who were also in custody were listening to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Yet truly, there was a sudden earthquake, so great that the foundations of the prison were moved. And immediately all the doors were opened, and the bindings of everyone were released.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then the prison guard, having been jarred awake, and seeing the doors of the prison open, drew his sword and intended to kill himself, supposing that the prisoners had fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But Paul cried out with a loud voice, saying: &#8220;Do no harm to yourself, for we are all here!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then calling for a light, he entered. And trembling, he fell before the feet of Paul and Silas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And bringing them outside, he said, &#8220;Sirs, what must I do, so that I may be saved?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So they said, &#8220;Believe in the Lord Jesus, and then you will be saved, with your household.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And they spoke the Word of the Lord to him, along with all those who were in his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And he, taking them in the same hour of the night, washed their scourges. And he was baptized, and next his entire household.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And when he had brought them into his own house, he set a table for them. And he was joyous, with his entire household, believing in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when daylight had arrived, the magistrates sent the attendants, saying, &#8220;Release those men.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But the prison guard reported these words to Paul: &#8220;The magistrates have sent to have you released. Now therefore, depart. Go in peace.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>But Paul said to them: &#8220;They have beaten us publicly, though we were not condemned. They have cast men who are Romans into prison. And now they would drive us away secretly? Not so. Instead, let them come forward,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and let us drive them away.&#8221; Then the attendants reported these words to the magistrates. And upon hearing that they were Romans, they were afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And arriving, they pleaded with them, and leading them out, they begged them to depart from the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And they went away from the prison and entered into the house of Lydia. And having seen the brothers, they consoled them, and then they set out.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> It is not clear from the text whether she was faithful to the Jewish faith, or was one of the faithful (i.e. a convert to Christianity).</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> This decision at Jerusalem, made by Peter and the Apostles and elders (i.e. Bishops), was perhaps the first dogmatic decree of an Ecumenical Council.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> It was a Jewish custom, and apparently a custom of some early Christians, to go for a prayerful or meditative walk on the Sabbath.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="4">
      <content> This girl is said to have the spirit of a python because the python in Greek mythology was associated with divination.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="5">
      <content> The word &#8216;forum&#8217; often refers to a marketplace, but in this context it refers to a place for judgment and justice, such as a court house.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when they had walked through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they arrived at Thessalonica, where there was a synagogue of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then Paul, according to custom, entered to them. And for three Sabbaths he disputed with them about the Scriptures,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>interpreting and concluding that it was necessary for the Christ to suffer and to rise again from the dead, and that &#8220;this is the Jesus Christ, whom I am announcing to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And some of them believed and were joined to Paul and Silas, and a great number of these were from the worshipers and the Gentiles, and not a few were noble women.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But the Jews, being jealous, and joining with certain evildoers among the common men, caused a disturbance, and they stirred up the city. And taking up a position near the house of Jason, they sought to lead them out to the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when they had not found them, they dragged Jason and certain brothers to the rulers of the city, crying out: &#8220;For these are the ones who have stirred up the city. And they came here,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and Jason has received them. And all these men act contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying that there is another king, Jesus.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And they incited the people. And the rulers of the city, upon hearing these things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and having received an explanation from Jason and the others, released them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Yet truly, the brothers promptly sent Paul and Silas away by night to Beroea. And when they had arrived, they entered the synagogue of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But these were more noble than those who were at Thessalonica. They received the Word with all enthusiasm, daily examining the Scriptures to see if these things were so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And indeed, many believed among them, as well as not a few among the honorable Gentile men and women.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then, when the Jews of Thessalonica had realized that the Word of God was also preached by Paul at Beroea, they went there also, stirring up and disturbing the multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And then the brothers quickly sent Paul away, so that he might travel by sea. But Silas and Timothy remained there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then those who were leading Paul brought him as far as Athens. And having received an order from him to Silas and Timothy, that they should come to him quickly, they set out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now while Paul waited for them at Athens, his spirit was stirred up within him, seeing the city given over to idolatry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And so, he was disputing with the Jews in the synagogue, and with the worshipers, and in public places, throughout each day, with whomever was there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now certain Epicurean and Stoic philosophers were arguing with him. And some were saying, &#8220;What does this sower of the Word want to say?&#8221; Yet others were saying, &#8220;He seems to be an announcer for new demons.&#8221; For he was announcing to them Jesus and the Resurrection.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And apprehending him, they brought him to the Areopagus, saying: &#8220;Are we able to know what this new doctrine is, about which you speak?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For you bring certain new ideas to our ears. And so we would like to know what these things mean.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>(Now all the Athenians, and arriving visitors, were occupying themselves with nothing other than speaking or hearing various new ideas.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But Paul, standing in the middle of the Areopagus, said: &#8220;Men of Athens, I perceive that in all things you are rather superstitious.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For as I was passing by and noticing your idols, I also found an altar, on which was written: TO THE UNKNOWN GOD. Therefore, what you worship in ignorance, this is what I am preaching to you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the God who made the world and all that is in it, the One who is the Lord of heaven and earth, who does not live in temples made with hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Neither is he served by the hands of men, as if in need of anything, since it is he who gives to all things life and breath and all else.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And he has made, out of one, every family of man: to live upon the face of the entire earth, determining the appointed seasons and the limits of their habitation,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>so as to seek God, if perhaps they may consider him or find him, though he is not far from each one of us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>&#8216;For in him we live, and move, and exist.&#8217; Just as some of your own poets have said. &#8216;For we are also of his family.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Therefore, since we are of the family of God, we must not consider gold or silver or precious stones, or the engravings of art and of the imagination of man, to be a representation of what is Divine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And indeed, God, having looked down to see the ignorance of these times, has now announced to men that everyone everywhere should do penance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For he has appointed a day on which he will judge the world in equity, through the man whom he has appointed, offering faith to all, by raising him from the dead.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And when they had heard about the Resurrection of the dead, indeed, some were derisive, while others said, &#8220;We will listen to you about this again.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So Paul departed from their midst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Yet truly, certain men, adhering to him, did believe. Among these were also Dionysius the Areopagite, and a woman named Damaris, and others with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The &#8216;worshipers&#8217; here are probably the pagan worshipers among the Gentiles, and the &#8216;Gentiles&#8217; are therefore those non-Jews who did not follow even a pagan religion.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The one out of whom God made every family of mankind is Adam.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After these things, having departed from Athens, he arrived at Corinth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And upon finding a certain Jew named Aquila, born in Pontus, who had recently arrived from Italy with Priscilla his wife, (because Claudius had ordered all Jews to depart from Rome,) he met with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And because he was of the same trade, he lodged with them and was working. (Now they were tentmakers by trade.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And he was arguing in the synagogue on every Sabbath, introducing the name of the Lord Jesus. And he was persuading Jews and Greeks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when Silas and Timothy had arrived from Macedonia, Paul stood firm in the Word, testifying to the Jews that Jesus is the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But since they were contradicting him and blaspheming, he shook out his garments and said to them: &#8220;Your blood is on your own heads. I am clean. From now on, I will go to the Gentiles.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And moving from that place, he entered into the house of a certain man, named Titus the Just, a worshiper of God, whose house was adjoined to the synagogue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now Crispus, a leader of the synagogue, believed in the Lord, with his entire house. And many of the Corinthians, upon hearing, believed and were baptized.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Paul, through a vision in the night: &#8220;Do not be afraid. Instead, speak out and do not be silent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For I am with you. And no one will take hold of you, so as to do you harm. For many of the people in this city are with me.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then he settled there for a year and six months, teaching the Word of God among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But when Gallio was proconsul of Achaia, the Jews rose up with one accord against Paul. And they brought him to the tribunal,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>saying, &#8220;He persuades men to worship God contrary to the law.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then, when Paul was beginning to open his mouth, Gallio said to the Jews: &#8220;If this were some matter of injustice, or a wicked deed, O noble Jews, I would support you, as is proper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Yet if truly these are questions about a word and names and your law, you should see to it yourselves. I will not be the judge of such things.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And he ordered them from the tribunal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But they, apprehending Sosthenes, a leader of the synagogue, beat him in front of the tribunal. And Gallio showed no concern for these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Yet truly, Paul, after he had remained for many more days, having said goodbye to the brothers, sailed into Syria, and with him were Priscilla and Aquila. Now he had shaved his head in Cenchreae, for he had made a vow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And he arrived at Ephesus, and he left them behind there. Yet truly, he himself, entering into the synagogue, was disputing with the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then, although they were asking him to remain for a longer time, he would not agree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Instead, saying goodbye and telling them, &#8220;I will return to you again, God willing,&#8221; he set out from Ephesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And after going down to Caesarea, he went up to Jerusalem, and he greeted the Church there, and then he descended to Antioch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And having spent some length of time there, he set out, and he walked in order through the region of Galatia and Phrygia, strengthening all the disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now a certain Jew named Apollo, born at Alexandria, an eloquent man who was powerful with the Scriptures, arrived at Ephesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He was learned in the Way of the Lord. And being fervent in spirit, he was speaking and teaching the things that are of Jesus, but knowing only the baptism of John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And so, he began to act faithfully in the synagogue. And when Priscilla and Aquila had heard him, they took him aside and expounded the Way of the Lord to him more thoroughly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then, since he wanted to go to Achaia, the brothers wrote an exhortation to the disciples, so that they might accept him. And when he had arrived, he held many discussions with those who had believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For he was vehemently and publicly reproving the Jews, by revealing through the Scriptures that Jesus is the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now it happened that, while Apollo was at Corinth, Paul, after he had journeyed through the upper regions, arrived at Ephesus. And he met with certain disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And he said to them, &#8220;After believing, have you received the Holy Spirit?&#8221; But they said to him, &#8220;We have not even heard that there is a Holy Spirit.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Yet truly, he said, &#8220;Then with what have you been baptized?&#8221; And they said, &#8220;With the baptism of John.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Paul said: &#8220;John baptized the people with the baptism of repentance, saying that they should believe in the One who is to come after him, that is, in Jesus.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon hearing these things, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when Paul had imposed his hands on them, the Holy Spirit came over them. And they were speaking in tongues and prophesying.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now the men were about twelve in all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then, upon entering the synagogue, he was speaking faithfully for three months, disputing and persuading them about the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But when certain ones became hardened and would not believe, cursing the Way of the Lord in the presence of the multitude, Paul, withdrawing from them, separated the disciples, disputing daily in a certain school of Tyrannus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now this was done throughout two years, so that all who were living in Asia listened to the Word of the Lord, both Jews and Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And God was accomplishing powerful and uncommon miracles by the hand of Paul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>so much so that even when small cloths and wrappings were brought from his body to the sick, the illnesses withdrew from them and the wicked spirits departed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then, even some of the traveling Jewish exorcists had attempted to invoke the name of the Lord Jesus over those who had evil spirits, saying, &#8220;I bind you by oath through Jesus, whom Paul preaches.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And there were certain Jews, the seven sons of Sceva, leaders among the priests, who were acting in this way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But a wicked spirit responded by saying to them: &#8220;Jesus I know, and Paul I know. But who are you?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the man, in whom there was a wicked spirit, leaping at them and getting the better of them both, prevailed against them, so that they fled from that house, naked and wounded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And so, this became known to all the Jews and Gentiles who were living at Ephesus. And a fear fell over them all. And the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And many believers were arriving, confessing, and announcing their deeds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then many of those who had followed odd sects brought together their books, and they burned them in the sight of all. And after determining the value of these, they found the price to be fifty thousand denarii.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In this way, the Word of God was increasing strongly and was being confirmed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then, when these things were completed, Paul decided in the Spirit, after crossing through Macedonia and Achaia, to go to Jerusalem, saying, &#8220;Then, after I have been there, it is necessary for me to see Rome also.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But sending two of those who were ministering to him, Timothy and Erastus, into Macedonia, he himself remained for a time in Asia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now at that time, there occurred no small disturbance concerning the Way of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For a certain man named Demetrius, a silversmith making silver shrines for Diana, was providing no small profit to craftsmen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And calling them together, with those who were employed in the same way, he said: &#8220;Men, you know that our income is from this craft.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And you are seeing and hearing that this man Paul, by persuasion, has turned away a great multitude, not only from Ephesus, but from nearly all of Asia, saying, &#8216;These things are not gods which have been made by hands.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thus, not only is this, our occupation, in danger of being brought into repudiation, but also the temple of the great Diana will be reputed as nothing! Then even her majesty, whom all of Asia and the world worships, will begin to be destroyed.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Upon hearing this, they were filled with anger, and they cried out, saying, &#8220;Great is Diana of the Ephesians!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And the city was filled with confusion. And having seized Gaius and Aristarchus of Macedonia, companions of Paul, they rushed violently, with one accord, into the amphitheater.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then, when Paul wanted to enter to the people, the disciples would not permit him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And some of the leaders from Asia, who were his friends, also sent to him, requesting that he not present himself in the amphitheater.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But others were crying out various things. For the assembly was in confusion, and most did not know the reason they had been called together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So they dragged Alexander from the crowd, while the Jews were propelling him forward. And Alexander, gesturing with his hand for silence, wanted to give the people an explanation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But as soon as they realized him to be a Jew, all with one voice, for about two hours, were crying out, &#8220;Great is Diana of the Ephesians!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when the scribe had calmed the crowds, he said: &#8220;Men of Ephesus, now what man is there who does not know that the city of the Ephesians is in the service of the great Diana and of the offspring of Jupiter?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Therefore, since these things are not able to be contradicted, it is necessary for you to be calm and to do nothing rash.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For you have brought forward these men, who are neither sacrilegious nor blasphemers against your goddess.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But if Demetrius and the craftsmen who are with him have a case against anyone, they can convene in the courts, and there are proconsuls. Let them accuse one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But if you would inquire about other things, this can be decided in a lawful assembly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For now we are in peril of being convicted of sedition over today&#8217;s events, since there is no one guilty (against whom we are able to provide evidence) in this gathering.&#8221; And when he had said this, he dismissed the assembly.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Although the Church currently requires the Trinitarian formula for a valid Baptism, it is apparent from Scripture that some of the earliest valid Baptisms used only the name of Jesus.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> After being baptized, they were then given the Sacrament of Confirmation.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> A denarius was a decent day&#8217;s wage. Perhaps the equivalent today, very approximately, of about 80 dollars a day. Thus the value of those books (scrolls) was equivalent to about 4 million dollars.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then, after the tumult ceased, Paul, calling the disciples to himself and exhorting them, said farewell. And he set out, so that he might go into Macedonia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when he had walked through those areas and had exhorted them with many sermons, he went into Greece.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>After he had spent three months there, treacheries were planned against him by the Jews, just as he was about to sail into Syria. And having been advised of this, he return through Macedonia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now those accompanying him were Sopater, the son of Pyrrhus from Beroea; and also the Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus; and Gaius of Derbe, and Timothy; and also Tychicus and Trophimus from Asia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>These, after they had gone ahead, waited for us at Troas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Yet truly, we sailed from Philippi, after the days of Unleavened Bread, and in five days we went to them at Troas, where we stayed for seven days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then, on the first Sabbath, when we had assembled together to break bread, Paul discoursed with them, intending to set out the next day. But he prolonged his sermon into the middle of the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now there were plenty of lamps in the upper room, where we were gathered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And a certain adolescent named Eutychus, sitting on the window sill, was being weighed down by a heavy drowsiness (for Paul was preaching at length). Then, as he went to sleep, he fell from the third floor room downward. And when he was lifted up, he was dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When Paul had gone down to him, he laid himself over him and, embracing him, said, &#8220;Do not worry, for his soul is still within him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And so, going up, and breaking bread, and eating, and having spoken well on until daylight, he then set out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now they had brought the boy in alive, and they were more than a little consoled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then we climbed aboard the ship and sailed to Assos, where we were to take in Paul. For so he himself had decided, since he was making the journey by land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when he had joined us at Assos, we took him in, and we went to Mitylene.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And sailing from there, on the following day, we arrived opposite Chios. And next we landed at Samos. And on the following day we went to Miletus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For Paul had decided to sail past Ephesus, so that he would not be delayed in Asia. For he was hurrying so that, if it were possible for him, he might observe the day of Pentecost at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then, sending from Miletus to Ephesus, he called those greater by birth in the church.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when they had come to him and were together, he said to them: &#8220;You know that from the first day when I entered into Asia, I have been with you, for the entire time, in this manner:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>serving the Lord, with all humility and despite the tears and trials which befell me from the treacheries of the Jews,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>how I held back nothing that was of value, how well I have preached to you, and that I have taught you publicly and throughout the houses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>testifying both to Jews and to Gentiles about repentance in God and faith in our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And now, behold, being obliged in spirit, I am going to Jerusalem, not knowing what will happen to me there,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>except that the Holy Spirit, throughout every city, has cautioned me, saying that chains and tribulations await me at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But I dread none of these things. Neither do I consider my life to be more precious because it is my own, provided that in some way I may complete my own course and that of the ministry of the Word, which I received from the Lord Jesus, to testify to the Gospel of the grace of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And now, behold, I know that you will no longer see my face, all of you among whom I have traveled, preaching the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For this reason, I call you as witnesses on this very day: that I am clean from the blood of all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For I have not turned aside in the least from announcing every counsel of God to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Take care of yourselves and of the entire flock, over which the Holy Spirit has stationed you as Bishops to rule the Church of God, which he has purchased by his own blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>I know that after my departure ravenous wolves will enter among you, not sparing the flock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And from among yourselves, men will rise up, speaking perverse things in order to entice disciples after them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Because of this, be vigilant, retaining in memory that throughout three years I did not cease, night and day, with tears, to admonish each and every one of you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And now, I commend you to God and to the Word of his grace. He has the power to build up, and to give an inheritance to all who are sanctified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>I have coveted neither silver and gold, nor apparel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>as you yourselves know. For that which was needed by me and by those who are with me, these hands have provided.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>I have revealed all things to you, because by laboring in this way, it is necessary to support the weak and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, how he said, &#8216;It is more blessed to give than to receive.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And when he had said these things, kneeling down, he prayed with all of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then a great weeping occurred among them all. And, falling upon the neck of Paul, they kissed him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>being grieved most of all over the word which he had said, that they would never see his face again. And they brought him to the ship.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content>The expression "first Sabbath" refers to Easter Sunday, the commemoration of the first Christian Sabbath. In the year in question, Easter Sunday was celebrated some 12 (5 + 7) days or more after "the days of Unleavened Bread", which refers to Passover. It is unclear how Easter Sunday was calculated at that early time in the Church, but it did not always coincide with Passover.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after these things had happened, having reluctantly parted from them, we sailed a direct course, arriving at Cos, and on following the day at Rhodes, and from there to Patara.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when we had found a ship sailing across to Phoenicia, climbing aboard, we set sail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then, after we had caught sight of Cyprus, keeping it to the left, we sailed on to Syria, and we arrived at Tyre. For the ship was going to unload its cargo there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then, having found the disciples, we lodged there for seven days. And they were saying to Paul, through the Spirit, that he should not go up to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when the days were completed, setting out, we went on; and they all accompanied us with their wives and children, until we were outside of the city. And we kneeled down at the shore and prayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when we had said farewell to one another, we climbed aboard the ship. And they returned to their own.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Yet truly, having completed our journey by boat from Tyre, we descended to Ptolemais. And greeting the brothers, we lodged with them for one day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then, after setting out the next day, we arrived at Caesarea. And upon entering into the house of Philip the evangelist, who was one of the seven, we stayed with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now this man had four daughters, virgins, who were prophesying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And while we were delayed for some days, a certain prophet from Judea, named Agabus, arrived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And he, when he had come to us, took Paul&#8217;s belt, and binding his own feet and hands, he said: &#8220;Thus says the Holy Spirit: The man whose belt this is, the Jews will bind in this way at Jerusalem. And they will deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when we had heard this, both we and those who were from that place begged him not to go up to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Paul responded by saying: &#8220;What do you accomplish by weeping and afflicting my heart? For I am prepared, not only to be bound, but also to die in Jerusalem, for the name of the Lord Jesus.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And since we were not able to persuade him, we quieted, saying: &#8220;May the will of the Lord be done.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then, after those days, having made preparations, we ascended to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now some of the disciples from Caesarea also went with us, bringing with them a certain Cypriot named Mnason, a very old disciple, whose guests we would be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when we had arrived at Jerusalem, the brothers received us willingly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then, on the following day, Paul entered with us to James. And all the elders were assembled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when he had greeted them, he explained each thing that God had accomplished among the Gentiles through his ministry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And they, upon hearing it, magnified God and said to him: &#8220;You understand, brother, how many thousands there are among the Jews who have believed, and they are all zealous for the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now they have heard about you, that you are teaching those Jews who are among the Gentiles to withdraw from Moses, telling them that they should not circumcise their sons, nor act according to custom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>What is next? The multitude ought to be convened. For they will hear that you have arrived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Therefore, do this thing that we ask of you: We have four men, who are under a vow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Take these and sanctify yourself with them, and require them to shave their heads. And then everyone will know that the things that they have heard about you are false, but that you yourself walk in keeping with the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But, about those Gentiles who have believed, we have written a judgment that they should keep themselves from what has been immolated to idols, and from blood, and from what has been suffocated, and from fornication.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then Paul, taking the men on the next day, was purified with them, and he entered the temple, announcing the process of the days of purification, until an oblation would be offered on behalf of each one of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But when the seven days were reaching completion, those Jews who were from Asia, when they had seen him in the temple, incited all the people, and they laid hands on him, crying out:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>&#8220;Men of Israel, help! This is the man who is teaching, everyone, everywhere, against the people and the law and this place. Furthermore, he has even brought Gentiles into the temple, and he has violated this holy place.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>(For they had seen Trophimus, an Ephesian, in the city with him, and they supposed that Paul had brought him into the temple.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the entire city was stirred up. And it happened that the people ran together. And apprehending Paul, they dragged him outside of the temple. And immediately the doors were closed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then, as they were seeking to kill him, it was reported to the tribune of the cohort: &#8220;All Jerusalem is in confusion.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And so, immediately taking soldiers and centurions, he rushed down to them. And when they had seen the tribune and the soldiers, they ceased to strike Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then the tribune, drawing near, apprehended him and ordered that he be bound with two chains. And he was asking who he was and what he had done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then they were crying out various things within the crowd. And since he could not understand anything clearly because of the noise, he ordered him to be brought into the fortress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when he had arrived at the stairs, it happened that he was carried up by the soldiers, because of the threat of violence from the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For the multitude of the people were following and crying out, &#8220;Take him away!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And as Paul was beginning to be brought into the fortress, he said to the tribune, &#8220;Is it permissible for me to say something to you?&#8221; And he said, &#8220;You know Greek?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>So then, are you not that Egyptian who before these days incited a rebellion and led out into the desert four thousand murderous men?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But Paul said to him: &#8220;I am a man, indeed a Jew, from Tarsus in Cilicia, a citizen of a well-known city. So I petition you, permit me to speak to the people.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And when he had given him permission, Paul, standing on the stairs, motioned with his hand to the people. And when a great silence occurred, he spoke to them in the Hebrew language, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> This Philip was one of the first seven deacons. He was an Evangelist in that he preached the Gospel. He was not one of the four Evangelists who wrote the Gospels.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> It is not so much that the men were each murderers, but more that they were of murderous intention.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>&#8220;Noble brothers and fathers, listen to the explanation that I now give to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when they heard him speaking to them in the Hebrew language, they offered a greater silence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And he said: &#8220;I am a Jewish man, born at Tarsus in Cilicia, but raised in this city beside the feet of Gamaliel, taught according to the truth of the law of the fathers, zealous for the law, just as all of you also are to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I persecuted this Way, even unto death, binding and delivering into custody both men and women,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>just as the high priest and all those greater by birth bear witness to me. Having received letters from them to the brothers, I journeyed to Damascus, so that I might lead them bound from there to Jerusalem, so that they might be punished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But it happened that, as I was traveling and was approaching Damascus at midday, suddenly from heaven a great light shone around me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And falling to the ground, I heard a voice saying to me, &#8216;Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And I responded, &#8216;Who are you, Lord?&#8217; And he said to me, &#8216;I am Jesus the Nazarene, whom you are persecuting.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And those who were with me, indeed, saw the light, but they did not hear the voice of him who was speaking with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And I said, &#8216;What should I do, Lord?&#8217; Then the Lord said to me: &#8216;Rise up, and go to Damascus. And there, you shall be told all that you must do.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And since I could not see, because of the brightness of that light, I was led by the hand by my companions, and I went to Damascus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then a certain Ananias, a man in accord with the law, having the testimony of all the Jews who were living there,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>drawing near to me and standing close by, said to me, &#8216;Brother Saul, see!&#8217; And in that same hour, I looked upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But he said: &#8216;The God of our fathers has preordained you, so that you would come to know his will and would see the Just One, and would hear the voice from his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For you shall be his witness to all men about those things which you have seen and heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And now, why do you delay? Rise up, and be baptized, and wash away your sins, by invoking his name.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then it happened that, when I returned to Jerusalem and was praying in the temple, a mental stupor came over me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and I saw him saying to me: &#8216;Hurry! Depart quickly from Jerusalem! For they will not accept your testimony about me.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I said: &#8216;Lord, they know that I am beating and enclosing in prison, throughout every synagogue, those who have believed in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the blood of your witness Stephen was poured out, I stood nearby and was consenting, and I watched over the garments of those who put him to death.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And he said to me, &#8216;Go forth. For I am sending you to far away nations.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now they were listening to him, until this word, and then they lifted up their voice, saying: &#8220;Take this kind away from the earth! For it is not fitting for him to live!&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And while they were shouting, and tossing aside their garments, and casting dust into the air,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the tribune ordered him to be brought into the fortress, and to be scourged and tortured, in order to discover the reason that they were crying out in this way against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And when they had tied him with straps, Paul said to the centurion who was standing near him, &#8220;Is it lawful for you to scourge a man who is a Roman and has not been condemned?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Upon hearing this, the centurion went to the tribune and reported it to him, saying: &#8220;What do you intend to do? For this man is a Roman citizen.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the tribune, approaching, said to him: &#8220;Tell me. Are you a Roman?&#8221; So he said, &#8220;Yes.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And the tribune responded, &#8220;I obtained this citizenship at great cost.&#8221; And Paul said, &#8220;But I was born to it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Therefore, those who were going to torture him, immediately withdrew from him. The tribune was similarly afraid, after he realized that he was a Roman citizen, for he had bound him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But on the next day, wanting to discover more diligently what the reason was that he was accused by the Jews, he released him, and he ordered the priests to convene, with the entire council. And, producing Paul, he stationed him among them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Paul, gazing intently at the council, said, &#8220;Noble brothers, I have spoken with all good conscience before God, even to this present day.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the high priest, Ananias, instructed those who were standing nearby to strike him on the mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then Paul said to him: &#8220;God shall strike you, you whitewashed wall! For would you sit and judge me according to the law, when, contrary to the law, you order me to be struck?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And those who were standing nearby said, &#8220;Are you speaking evil about the high priest of God?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And Paul said: &#8220;I did not know, brothers, that he is the high priest. For it is written: &#8216;You shall not speak evil of the leader of your people.&#8217; &#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now Paul, knowing that one group were Sadducees and the other were Pharisees, exclaimed in the council: &#8220;Noble brothers, I am a Pharisee, the son of Pharisees! It is over the hope and resurrection of the dead that I am being judged.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when he had said this, a dissension occurred between the Pharisees and the Sadducees. And the multitude was divided.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For the Sadducees claim that there is no resurrection, and neither angels, nor spirits. But the Pharisees confess both of these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then there occurred a great clamor. And some of the Pharisees, rising up, were fighting, saying: &#8220;We find nothing evil in this man. What if a spirit has spoken to him, or an angel?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And since a great dissension had been made, the tribune, fearing that Paul might be torn apart by them, ordered the soldiers to descend and to seize him from their midst, and to bring him into the fortress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then, on the following night, the Lord stood near him and said: &#8220;Be constant. For just as you have testified about me in Jerusalem, so also it is necessary for you to testify at Rome.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when daylight arrived, some of the Jews gathered together and bound themselves with an oath, saying that they would neither eat nor drink until they had killed Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now there were more than forty men who had taken this oath together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And they approached the leaders of the priests, and the elders, and they said: &#8220;We have sworn ourselves by an oath, so that we will taste nothing, until we have killed Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Therefore, with the council, you should now give notice to the tribune, so that he may bring him to you, as if you intended to determine something else about him. But before he approaches, we have made preparations to put him to death.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But when Paul&#8217;s sister&#8217;s son had heard of this, about their treachery, he went and entered into the fortress, and he reported it to Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Paul, calling to him one of the centurions, said: &#8220;Lead this young man to the tribune. For he has something to tell him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And indeed, he took him and led him to the tribune, and he said, &#8220;Paul, the prisoner, asked me to lead this young man to you, since he has something to say to you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then the tribune, taking him by the hand, withdrew with him by themselves, and he asked him: &#8220;What is it that you have to tell me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then he said: &#8220;The Jews have met to ask you to bring Paul tomorrow to the council, as if they intended to question him about something else.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But truly, you should not believe them, for they would ambush him with more than forty men from among them, who have bound themselves by an oath neither to eat, nor to drink, until they have put him to death. And they are now prepared, hoping for an affirmation from you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And then the tribune dismissed the young man, instructing him not to tell anyone that he had made known these things to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then, having called two centurions, he said to them: &#8220;Prepare two hundred soldiers, so that they may go as far as Caesarea, and seventy horsemen, and two hundred spearmen, for the third hour of the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And prepare beasts of burden to carry Paul, so that they may lead him safely to Felix, the governor.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For he was afraid, lest perhaps the Jews might seize him and kill him, and that afterwards he would be falsely accused, as if he had accepted a bribe. And so he wrote a letter containing the following:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>&#8220;Claudius Lysias, to the most excellent governor, Felix: greetings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>This man, having been apprehended by the Jews and being about to be put to death by them, I rescued, overwhelming them with soldiers, since I realized that he is a Roman.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And wanting to know the reason that they objected to him, I brought him into their council.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And I discovered him to be accused about questions of their law. Yet truly, nothing deserving of death or imprisonment was within the accusation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And when I had been given news of ambushes, which they had prepared against him, I sent him to you, notifying his accusers also, so that they may plead their accusations before you. Farewell.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore the soldiers, taking Paul according to their orders, brought him by night to Antipatris.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the next day, sending the horsemen to go with him, they returned to the fortress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And when they had arrived at Caesarea and had delivered the letter to the governor, they also presented Paul before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And when he had read it and had asked which province he was from, realizing that he was from Cilicia, he said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>&#8220;I will hear you, when your accusers have arrived.&#8221; And he ordered him to be kept in the praetorium of Herod.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Each centurion was in charge of 100 soldiers.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> Here Scripture tells us that the tribune, Claudius, lied to the governor, Felix, making himself look good by saying that he know right away that Paul was a Roman, when such was not the case.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then, after five days, the high priest Ananias came down with some of the elders and a certain Tertullus, a speaker. And they went to the governor against Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And having summoned Paul, Tertullus began to accuse him, saying: &#8220;Most excellent Felix, since we have much peace through you, and many things may be corrected by your providence,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>we acknowledge this, always and everywhere, with acts of thanksgiving for everything.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But lest I speak at too great a length, I beg you, by your clemency, to listen to us briefly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>We have found this man to be pestilent, to be inciting seditions among all the Jews in the entire world, and to be the author of the sedition of the sect of the Nazarenes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And he has even been attempting to violate the temple. And having apprehended him, we wanted him to be judged according to our law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But Lysias, the tribune, overwhelming us with great violence, snatched him away from our hands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>ordering his accusers to come to you. From them, you yourself will be able, by judging about all these things, to understand the reason that we accuse him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And then the Jews interjected, saying that these things were so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then, since the governor had motioned for him to speak, Paul responded: &#8220;Knowing that you have been the judge over this nation for many years, I will give an explanation of myself with an honest soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For, as you may realize, it has only been twelve days since I went up to worship in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they did not find me in the temple arguing with anyone, nor causing a rally of the people: neither in the synagogues, nor in the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they are not able to prove to you the things about which they now accuse me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But I confess this to you, that according to that sect, which they call a heresy, so do I serve my God and Father, believing all that is written in the Law and the Prophets,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>having a hope in God, which these others themselves also expect, that there will be a future resurrection of the just and the unjust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And in this, I myself always strive to have a conscience that is lacking in any offense toward God and toward men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then, after many years, I went to my nation, bringing alms and offerings and vows,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>through which I obtained purification in the temple: neither with a crowd, nor with a commotion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But certain Jews out of Asia are the ones who should have appeared before you to accuse me, if they have anything against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Or let these ones here say if they have found in me any iniquity, while standing before the council.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For while standing among them, I spoke out solely about this one matter: about the resurrection of the dead. It is about this that I am being judged today by you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Felix, after having ascertained much knowledge about this Way, kept them waiting, by saying, &#8220;When Lysias the tribune has arrived, I will give you a hearing.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And he ordered a centurion to guard him, and to take rest, and not to prohibit any of his own from ministering to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then, after some days, Felix, arriving with his wife Drusilla who was a Jew, called for Paul and listened to him about the faith that is in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And after he discoursed about justice and chastity, and about the future judgment, Felix was trembling, and he responded: &#8220;For now, go, but remain under guard. Then, at an opportune time, I will summon you.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He was also hoping that money might be given to him by Paul, and because of this, he frequently summoned him and spoke with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then, when two years had passed, Felix was succeeded by Portius Festus. And since Felix wanted to show particular favor to the Jews, he left Paul behind as a prisoner.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> In other words, the guard did not need to guard him 24/7, but could take rest breaks for himself. This guard was merely to keep tabs on Paul, not to restrict his activities.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And so, when Festus had arrived in the province, after three days, he ascended to Jerusalem from Caesarea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the leaders of the priests, and those first among the Jews, went to him against Paul. And they were petitioning him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>asking for favor against him, so that he would order him to be led to Jerusalem, where they were maintaining an ambush in order to kill him along the way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But Festus responded that Paul was to be kept in Caesarea, and that he himself would soon go there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>&#8220;Therefore,&#8221; he said, &#8220;let those among you who are able, descend at the same time, and if there is any guilt in the man, they may accuse him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then, having stayed among them no more than eight or ten days, he descended to Caesarea. And on the next day, he sat in the judgment seat, and he ordered Paul to be led in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when he had been brought, the Jews who had come down from Jerusalem stood around him, throwing out many serious accusations, none of which they were able to prove.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Paul offered this defense: &#8220;Neither against the law of the Jews, nor against the temple, nor against Caesar, have I offended in any matter.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But Festus, wanting to show greater favor to the Jews, responded to Paul by saying: &#8220;Are you willing to ascend to Jerusalem and to be judged there about these things before me?&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But Paul said: &#8220;I stand in Caesar&#8217;s tribunal, which is where I ought to be judged. I have done no harm to the Jews, as you well know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For if I have harmed them, or if I have done anything deserving of death, I do not object to dying. But if there is nothing to these things about which they accuse me, no one is able to deliver me to them. I appeal to Caesar.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Festus, having spoken with the council, responded: &#8220;You have appealed to Caesar, to Caesar you shall go.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when some days had passed, king Agrippa and Bernice descended to Caesarea, to greet Festus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And since they remained there for many days, Festus spoke to the king about Paul, saying: &#8220;A certain man was left behind as a prisoner by Felix.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>When I was at Jerusalem, the leaders of the priests and the elders of the Jews came to me about him, asking for condemnation against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I answered them that it is not the custom of the Romans to condemn any man, before he who is being accused has been confronted by his accusers and has received the opportunity to defend himself, so as to clear himself of the charges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore, when they had arrived here, without any delay, on the following day, sitting in the judgment seat, I ordered the man to be brought.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But when the accusers had stood up, they did not present any accusation about him from which I would suspect evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Instead, they brought against him certain disputes about their own superstition and about a certain Jesus, who had died, but whom Paul asserted to be alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Therefore, being in doubt about this kind of question, I asked him if he was willing go to Jerusalem and to be judged there about these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But since Paul was appealing to be kept for a decision before Augustus, I ordered him to be kept, until I might send him to Caesar.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Agrippa said to Festus: &#8220;I myself also want to hear the man.&#8221; &#8220;Tomorrow,&#8221; he said, &#8220;you shall hear him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And on the next day, when Agrippa and Bernice had arrived with great ostentation and had entered into the auditorium with the tribunes and the principal men of the city, Paul was brought in, at the order of Festus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Festus said: &#8220;King Agrippa, and all who are present together with us, you see this man, about whom all the multitude of the Jews disturbed me at Jerusalem, petitioning and clamoring that he should not be allowed to live any longer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Truly, I have discovered nothing brought forth against him that is worthy of death. But since he himself has appealed to Augustus, it was my judgment to send him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But I have not determined what to write to the emperor about him. Because of this, I have brought him before you all, and especially before you, O king Agrippa, so that, once an inquiry has occurred, I may have something to write.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For it seems to me unreasonable to send a prisoner and not to indicate the accusations set against him.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The Romans tended to favor the Jews. This was partly because Claudius, a previous emperor, issued an edict giving the Jewish faith a protected status in the empire. It may also have been because the wives of many powerful Roman leaders either converted to Judaism or tended to show favor to the Jews.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The emperor referred to as Augustus is actually Nero; it was the custom for Roman emperors to name themselves according to various prior Caesars. Thus Nero called himself Nero Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus, after the emperors Augustus, and Claudius, and Julius Caesar, and the general Germanicus.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Yet truly, Agrippa said to Paul, &#8220;It is permitted for you to speak for yourself.&#8221; Then Paul, extending his hand, began to offer his defense.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>&#8220;I consider myself blessed, O king Agrippa, that I am to give my defense today before you, about everything of which I am accused by the Jews,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>especially since you know everything that pertains to the Jews, both customs and questions. Because of this, I beg you to listen to me patiently.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And certainly, all the Jews know about my life from my youth, which had its beginning among my own people in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They knew me well from the beginning, (if they would be willing to offer testimony) for I lived according to the most determined sect of our religion: as a Pharisee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And now, it is in the hope of the Promise which was made by God to our fathers that I stand subject to judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>It is the Promise that our twelve tribes, worshiping night and day, hope to see. About this hope, O king, I am accused by the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Why should it be judged so unbelievable with you all that God might raise the dead?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And certainly, I myself formerly considered that I ought to act in many ways which are contrary to the name of Jesus the Nazarene.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>This is also how I acted at Jerusalem. And so, I enclosed many holy persons in prison, having received authority from the leaders of the priests. And when they were to be killed, I brought the sentence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And in every synagogue, frequently while punishing them, I compelled them to blaspheme. And being all the more maddened against them, I persecuted them, even to foreign cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thereafter, as I was going to Damascus, with authority and permission from the high priest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>at midday, O king, I and those who were also with me, saw along the way a light from heaven shining around me with a splendor greater than that of the sun.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when we had all fallen down to the ground, I heard a voice speaking to me in the Hebrew language: &#8216;Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me? It is hard for you to kick against the goad.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then I said, &#8216;Who are you, Lord?&#8217; And the Lord said, &#8216;I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But rise up and stand on your feet. For I appeared to you for this reason: so that I may establish you as a minister and a witness concerning the things that you have seen, and concerning the things that I will show to you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>rescuing you from the people and the nations to which I am now sending you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>in order to open their eyes, so that they may be converted from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan to God, so that they may receive the remission of sins and a place among the saints, through the faith that is in me.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>From then on, O king Agrippa, I was not unbelieving to the heavenly vision.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But I preached, first to those who are at Damascus and at Jerusalem, and then to the entire region of Judea, and to the Gentiles, so that they would repent and convert to God, doing the works that are worthy of repentance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>It was for this reason that the Jews, having apprehended me when I was in the temple, attempted to kill me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But having been aided by the help of God, even to this day, I stand witnessing to the small and the great, saying nothing beyond what the Prophets and Moses have said would be in the future:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>that the Christ would suffer, and that he would be the first from the resurrection of the dead, and that he would bring light to the people and to the nations.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>While he was speaking these things and presenting his defense, Festus said with a loud voice: &#8220;Paul, you are insane! Too much studying has turned you to insanity.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And Paul said: &#8220;I am not insane, most excellent Festus, but rather I am speaking words of truth and sobriety.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For the king knows about these things. To him also, I am speaking with constancy. For I think that none of these things are unknown to him. And neither were these things done in a corner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Do you believe the Prophets, O king Agrippa? I know that you believe.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Agrippa said to Paul, &#8220;To some extent, you persuade me to become a Christian.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Paul said, &#8220;I hope to God that, both to a small extent and to a great extent, not only you, but also all those who hear me this day will become just as I also am, except for these chains.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the king rose up, and the governor, and Bernice, and those who were sitting with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when they had withdrawn, they were speaking among themselves, saying, &#8220;This man has done nothing worthy of death, nor of imprisonment.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then Agrippa said to Festus, &#8220;This man could have been released, if he had not appealed to Caesar.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then it was decided to send him by ship to Italy, and that Paul, with the others in custody, should be delivered to a centurion named Julius, of the cohort of Augusta.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>After climbing aboard a ship from Adramyttium, we set sail and began to navigate along the ports of Asia, with Aristarchus, the Macedonian from Thessalonica, joining us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And on the following day, we arrived at Sidon. And Julius, treating Paul humanely, permitted him to go to his friends and to look after himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when we had set sail from there, we navigated below Cyprus, because the winds were contrary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And navigating though the sea of Cilicia and Pamphylia, we arrived at Lystra, which is in Lycia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And there the centurion found a ship from Alexandria sailing to Italy, and he transferred us to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when we had sailed slowly for many days and had barely arrived opposite Cnidus, for the wind was hindering us, we sailed to Crete, near Salmone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And barely being able to sail past it, we arrived at a certain place, which is called Good Shelter, next to which was the city of Lasea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then, after much time had passed, and since sailing would no longer be prudent because the Fast Day had now passed, Paul consoled them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and he said to them: &#8220;Men, I perceive that the voyage is now in danger of injury and much damage, not only to the cargo and the ship, but also to our own lives.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But the centurion put more trust in the captain and the navigator of the ship, than in the things being said by Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And since it was not a fitting port in which to winter, the majority opinion was to sail from there, so that somehow they might be able to arrive at Phoenicia, in order to winter there, at a port of Crete, which looks out toward the southwest and northwest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And since the south wind was blowing gently, they thought that they might reach their goal. And after they had set out from Asson, they weighed anchor at Crete.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But not long afterward, a violent wind came against them, which is called the Northeast Wind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And once the ship had been caught in it and was not able to strive against the wind, giving over the ship to the winds, we were driven along.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then, being forced along a certain island, which is called the Tail, we were barely able to hold on to the ship&#8217;s lifeboat.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When this was taken up, they used it to assist in securing the ship. For they were afraid that they might run aground. And having lowered the sails, they were being driven along in this way.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then, since we were being tossed about strongly by the tempest, on the following day, they threw the heavy items overboard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And on the third day, with their own hands, they threw the equipment of the ship overboard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then, when neither sun nor stars appeared for many days, and no end to the storm was imminent, all hope for our safety was now taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And after they had fasted for a long time, Paul, standing in their midst, said: &#8220;Certainly, men, you should have listened to me and not set out from Crete, so as to cause this injury and loss.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And now, let me persuade you to be courageous in soul. For there shall be no loss of life among you, but only of the ship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For an Angel of God, who is assigned to me and whom I serve, stood beside me this night,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>saying: &#8216;Do not be afraid, Paul! It is necessary for you to stand before Caesar. And behold, God has given to you all those who are sailing with you.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Because of this, men, be courageous in soul. For I trust God that this will happen in the same way that it has been told to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But it is necessary for us to arrive at a certain island.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then, after the fourteenth night arrived, as we were navigating in the sea of Adria, about the middle of the night, the sailors believed that they saw some portion of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And upon dropping a weight, they found a depth of twenty paces. And some distance from there, they found a depth of fifteen paces.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then, fearing that we might happen upon rough places, they cast four anchors out of the stern, and they were hoping for daylight to arrive soon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Yet truly, the sailors were seeking a way to flee from the ship, for they had lowered a lifeboat into the sea, on the pretext that they were attempting to cast anchors from the bow of the ship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So Paul said to the centurion and to the soldiers, &#8220;Unless these men remain in the ship, you will not be able to be saved.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then the soldiers cut the ropes to the lifeboat, and they allowed it to fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And when it began to be light, Paul requested that they all take food, saying: &#8220;This is the fourteenth day that you have been waiting and continuing to fast, taking nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For this reason, I beg you to accept food for the sake of your health. For not a hair from the head of any of you shall perish.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when he had said these things, taking bread, he gave thanks to God in the sight of them all. And when he had broken it, he began to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then they all became more peaceful in soul. And they also took food.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Truly, we were two hundred and seventy-six souls on the ship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And having been nourished with food, they lightened the ship, casting the wheat into the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And when day had arrived, they did not recognize the landscape. Yet truly, they caught sight of a certain narrow inlet having a shore, into which they thought it might be possible to force the ship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And when they had taken up the anchors, they committed themselves to the sea, at the same time loosing the restraints of the rudders. And so, raising the mainsail to the gusting wind, they pressed on toward the shore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And when we happened upon a place open to two seas, they ran the ship aground. And indeed, the bow, being immobilized, remained fixed, but truly the stern was broken by the violence of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Then the soldiers were in agreement that they should kill the prisoners, lest anyone, after escaping by swimming, might flee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>But the centurion, wanting to save Paul, prohibited it from being done. And he ordered those who were able to swim to jump in first, and to escape, and to get to the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And as for the others, some they carried on boards, and others on those things that belonged to the ship. And so it happened that every soul escaped to the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> In those days, the Mediterranean was not considered safe to sail during the winter months, from after the Fast Day (Yom Kippur) to early February, because of an increase in the number and severity of storms.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The word &#8216;scapham&#8217; does not refer to the ship &#8216;navem&#8217; that they were sailing, but to the smaller boat, usually hauled behind the larger boat, used for going ashore.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> They took the smaller boat used for going ashore into the larger boat and then they used it in strengthening the larger boat. They were afraid that they would hit a sandbar, partly because ships tend to ride low in the water during a storm (because they take on water), and because they had less control over its direction. They took down the sails, so that they would not be driven aground on the island.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28" preferred_title="Acts of the Apostles 28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after we had escaped, we then realized that the island was called Malta. Yet truly, the natives offered us no small amount of humane treatment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For they refreshed us all by kindling a fire, because rain was imminent and because of the cold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But when Paul had gathered together a bundle of twigs, and had placed them on the fire, a viper, which had been drawn to the heat, fastened itself to his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And truly, when the natives saw the beast hanging from his hand, they were saying to one another: &#8220;Certainly, this man must be a murderer, for though he escaped from the sea, vengeance will not permit him to live.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But shaking off the creature into the fire, he indeed suffered no ill effects.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But they were supposing that he would soon swell up, and then would suddenly fall down and die. But having waited a long time, and seeing no ill effects in him, they changed their minds and were saying that he was a god.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now among these places were estates owned by the ruler of the island, named Publius. And he, taking us in, showed us kind hospitality for three days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then it happened that the father of Publius lay ill with a fever and with dysentery. Paul entered to him, and when he had prayed and had laid his hands on him, he saved him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When this had been done, all who had diseases on the island approached and were cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And then they also presented us with many honors. And when we were ready to set sail, they gave us whatever we needed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And so, after three months, we sailed in a ship from Alexandria, whose name was &#8216;the Castors,&#8217; and which had wintered at the island.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when we had arrived at Syracuse, we were delayed there for three days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>From there, sailing close to the shore, we arrived at Rhegium. And after one day, with the south wind blowing, we arrived on the second day at Puteoli.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>There, after locating the brothers, we were asked to remain with them for seven days. And then we went on to Rome.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And there, when the brothers had heard of us, they went to meet us as far as the Forum of Appius and the Three Taverns. And when Paul had seen them, giving thanks to God, he took courage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when we had arrived at Rome, Paul was given permission to stay by himself, with a soldier to guard him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And after the third day, he called together the leaders of the Jews. And when they had convened, he said to them: &#8220;Noble brothers, I have done nothing against the people, nor against the customs of the fathers, yet I was delivered as a prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And after they held a hearing about me, they would have released me, because there was no case for death against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But with the Jews speaking against me, I was constrained to appeal to Caesar, though it was not as if I had any kind of accusation against my own nation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And so, because of this, I requested to see you and to speak to you. For it is because of the hope of Israel that I am encircled with this chain.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But they said to him: &#8220;We have not received letters about you from Judea, nor have any of the other new arrivals among the brothers reported or spoken anything evil against you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But we are asking to hear your opinions from you, for concerning this sect, we know that it is being spoken against everywhere.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when they had appointed a day for him, very many persons went to him at his guest quarters. And he discoursed, testifying to the kingdom of God, and persuading them about Jesus, using the law of Moses and the Prophets, from morning until evening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And some believed the things that he was saying, yet others did not believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And when they could not agree among themselves, they departed, while Paul was speaking this one word: &#8220;How well did the Holy Spirit speak to our fathers through the prophet Isaiah,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>saying: &#8216;Go to this people and say to them: Hearing, you shall hear and not understand, and seeing, you shall see and not perceive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For the heart of this people has grown dull, and they have listened with reluctant ears, and they have closed their eyes tightly, lest perhaps they might see with the eyes, and hear with the ears, and understand with the heart, and so be converted, and I would heal them.&#8217;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Therefore, let it be known to you, that this salvation of God has been sent to the Gentiles, and they shall listen to it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when he had said these things, the Jews went away from him, though they still had many questions among themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then he remained for two whole years in his own rented lodgings. And he received all who went in to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>preaching the kingdom of God and teaching the things which are from the Lord Jesus Christ, with all faithfulness, without prohibition.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The name Castor refers to a prominent star (the stars were used by sailors for navigation), and also to a figure in Greek mythology, one of the Gemini twins. Since the name in Latin is in the genitive case, it implies that the ship was considered to belong to, or to be under the protection of, these Greek mythological gods.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
</book>