<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Colossians 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, an Apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothy, a brother,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to the saints and faithful brothers in Christ Jesus who are at Colossae.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Grace and peace to you, from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ. We give thanks to God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, praying for you always.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For we have heard of your faith in Christ Jesus, and of the love that you have toward all the saints,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>because of the hope that has been stored up for you in heaven, which you have heard through the Word of Truth in the Gospel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This has reached you, just as it is present in the whole world, where it grows and bears fruit, as it has also done in you, since the day when you first heard and knew the grace of God in truth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>just as you learned it from Epaphras, our most beloved fellow servant, who is for you a faithful minister of Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And he has also manifested to us your love in the Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then, too, from the day when we first heard it, we have not ceased praying for you and requesting that you be filled with the knowledge of his will, with all wisdom and spiritual understanding,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>so that you may walk in a manner worthy of God, being pleasing in all things, being fruitful in every good work, and increasing in the knowledge of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>being strengthened in every virtue, in accord with the power of his glory, with all patience and longsuffering, with joy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>giving thanks to God the Father, who has made us worthy to have a share in the portion of the saints, in the light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For he has rescued us from the power of darkness, and he has transferred us into the kingdom of the Son of his love,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>in whom we have redemption through his blood, the remission of sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He is the image of the invisible God, the first-born of every creature.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For in him was created everything in heaven and on earth, visible and invisible, whether thrones, or dominations, or principalities, or powers. All things were created through him and in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he is before all, and in him all things continue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And he is the head of his body, the Church. He is the beginning, the first-born from the dead, so that in all things he may hold primacy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For the Father is well-pleased that all fullness reside in him,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and that, through him, all things be reconciled to himself, making peace through the blood of his cross, for the things that are on earth, as well as the things that are in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And you, though you had been, in times past, understood to be foreigners and enemies, with works of evil,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>yet now he has reconciled you, by his body of flesh, through death, so as to offer you, holy and immaculate and blameless, before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So then, continue in the faith: well-founded and steadfast and immovable, by the hope of the Gospel that you have heard, which has been preached throughout all creation under heaven, the Gospel of which I, Paul, have become a minister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For now I rejoice in my passion on your behalf, and I complete in my flesh the things that are lacking in the Passion of Christ, for the sake of his body, which is the Church.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For I have become a minister of the Church, according to the dispensation of God that has been given to me among you, so that I may fulfill the Word of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>the mystery which had remained hidden to past ages and generations, but which now is manifested to his saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>To them, God willed to make known the riches of the glory of this mystery among the Gentiles, which is Christ and the hope of his glory within you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>We are announcing him, correcting every man and teaching every man, with all wisdom, so that we may offer every man perfect in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>In him, too, I labor, striving according to his action within me, which he works in virtue.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;Father&#8217; is substituted for the pronoun &#8216;ipso,&#8217; in accord with Challoner.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The phrase &#8216;inimici sensu&#8217; is very unusual; I can find no other example of this phrase. The word &#8216;sensu&#8217; refers to the mind, or to qualities attributed to the mind, such as perception, feeling, understanding. The meaning is that they were understood to be enemies, or were perceived to be enemies, because of their evil works, but then they repented and were forgiven by Christ.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="Colossians 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For I want you to know the kind of solicitude that I have for you, and for those who are at Laodicea, as well as for those who have not seen my face in the flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>May their hearts be consoled and instructed in charity, with all the riches of a plenitude of understanding, with knowledge of the mystery of God the Father and of Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For in him are hidden all treasures of wisdom and knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now I say this, so that no one may deceive you with grandiose words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For though I may be absent in body, yet I am with you in spirit. And I rejoice as I gaze upon your order and its foundation, which is in Christ, your faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore, just as you have received the Lord Jesus Christ, walk in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Be rooted and continually built up in Christ. And be confirmed in the faith, just as you have also learned it, increasing in him with acts of thanksgiving.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>See to it that no one deceives you through philosophy and empty falsehoods, as found in the traditions of men, in accord with the influences of the world, and not in accord with Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For in him, all the fullness of the Divine Nature dwells bodily.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And in him, you have been filled; for he is the head of all principality and power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>In him also, you have been circumcised with a circumcision not made by hand, not by the despoiling of the body of flesh, but by the circumcision of Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>You have been buried with him in baptism. In him also, you have risen again through faith, by the work of God, who raised him up from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when you were dead in your transgressions and in the uncircumcision of your flesh, he enlivened you, together with him, forgiving you of all transgressions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and wiping away the handwriting of the decree which was against us, which was contrary to us. And he has taken this away from your midst, affixing it to the Cross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And so, despoiling principalities and powers, he has led them away confidently and openly, triumphing over them in himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore, let no one judge you as concerns food or drink, or a particular feast day, or feast days of new moons, or of Sabbaths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For these are a shadow of the future, but the body is of Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Let no one seduce you, preferring base things and a religion of Angels, walking according to what he has not seen, being vainly inflated by the sensations of his flesh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and not holding up the head, with which the whole body, by its underlying joints and ligaments, is joined together and grows with an increase that is of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So then, if you have died with Christ to the influences of this world, why do you still make decisions as if you were living in the world?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Do not touch, do not taste, do not handle these things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>which all lead to destruction by their very use, in accord with the precepts and doctrines of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Such ideas have at least an intention to attain to wisdom, but through superstition and debasement, not sparing the body, and they are without any honor in satiating the flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> In the phrase &#8216;firmamentum ejus,&#8217; the word &#8216;ejus&#8217; refers to &#8216;ordinem,&#8217; so that the phrasing is &#8216;your order and its foundation&#8230;&#8217;</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="Colossians 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore, if you have risen together with Christ, seek the things that are above, where Christ is seated at the right hand of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Consider the things that are above, not the things that are upon the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For you have died, and so your life is hidden with Christ in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When Christ, your life, appears, then you also will appear with him in glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Therefore, mortify your body, while it is upon the earth. For because of fornication, impurity, lust, evil desires, and avarice, which are a kind of service to idols,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>the wrath of God has overwhelmed the sons of unbelief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>You, too, walked in these things, in times past, when you were living among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But now you must set aside all these things: anger, indignation, malice, blasphemy, and indecent speech from your mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Do not lie to one another. Strip yourselves of the old man, with his deeds,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and clothe yourself with the new man, who has been renewed by knowledge, in accord with the image of the One who created him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>where there is neither Gentile nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, Barbarian nor Scythian, servant nor free. Instead, Christ is everything, in everyone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore, clothe yourselves like the elect of God: holy and beloved, with hearts of mercy, kindness, humility, modesty, and patience.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Support one another, and, if anyone has a complaint against another, forgive one another. For just as the Lord has forgiven you, so also must you do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And above all these things have charity, which is the bond of perfection.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And let the peace of Christ lift up your hearts. For in this peace, you have been called, as one body. And be thankful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let the word of Christ live in you in abundance, with all wisdom, teaching and correcting one another, with psalms, hymns, and spiritual canticles, singing to God with the grace in your hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Let everything whatsoever that you do, whether in word or in deed, be done all in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, giving thanks to God the Father through him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Wives, be submissive to your husbands, as is proper in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Husbands, love your wives, and do not be bitter toward them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Children, obey your parents in all things. For this is well-pleasing to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Fathers, do not provoke your children to indignation, lest they lose heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Servants, obey, in all things, your lords according to the flesh, not serving only when seen, as if to please men, but serving in simplicity of heart, fearing God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Whatever you do, do it from the heart, as for the Lord, and not for men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For you know that you will receive from the Lord the repayment of an inheritance. Serve Christ the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For whoever causes injury shall be repaid for what he has wrongfully done. And there no favoritism with God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="Colossians 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>You masters, supply your servants with what is just and equitable, knowing that you, too, have a Master in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Pursue prayer. Be watchful in prayer with acts of thanksgiving.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Pray together, for us also, so that God may open a door of speech to us, so as to speak the mystery of Christ, (because of which, even now, I am in chains)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>so that I may manifest it in the manner that I ought to speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Walk in wisdom toward those who are outside, redeeming this age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let your speech be ever graceful, seasoned with salt, so that you may know how you ought to respond to each person.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>As for the things that concern me, Tychicus, a most beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow servant in the Lord, will make everything known to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I have sent him to you for this very purpose, so that he may know the things that concern you, and may console your hearts,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>with Onesimus, a most beloved and faithful brother, who is from among you. They shall make known to you everything that is happening here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Aristarchus, my fellow prisoner, greets you, as does Mark, the near cousin of Barnabas, about whom you have received instructions, (if he comes to you, receive him)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Jesus, who is called Justus, and those who are of the circumcision. These alone are my assistants, unto the kingdom of God; they have been a consolation to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Epaphras greets you, who is from among you, a servant of Christ Jesus, ever solicitous for you in prayer, so that you may stand, perfect and complete, in the entire will of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For I offer testimony to him, that he has labored greatly for you, and for those who are at Laodicea, and for those at Hierapolis.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Luke, a most beloved physician, greets you, as does Demas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Greet the brothers who are at Laodicea, and Nymphas, and those who are at his house, a church.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when this epistle has been read among you, cause it to be read also in the church of the Laodiceans, and you should read that which is from the Laodiceans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And tell Archippus: &#8220;See to the ministry that you have received in the Lord, in order to fulfill it.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The greeting of Paul by my own hand. Remember my chains. May grace be with you. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> This first phrase could also be translated as: &#8216;Stand in prayer,&#8217; or &#8216;Be urgent in prayer,&#8217; or &#8216;Keep prayer always near,&#8217; or &#8216;Be ready to pray.&#8217;</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
</book>