<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Philemon 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy, a brother, to Philemon, our beloved fellow laborer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and to Apphia, most beloved sister, and to Archippus, our fellow soldier, and to the church which is in your house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Grace and peace to you, from God our Father and from the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I give thanks to my God, always keeping remembrance of you in my prayers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>(for I am hearing of your charity and faith, which you have in the Lord Jesus and with all the saints)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>so that the participation of your faith may become evident by the recognition of every good work which is in you in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For I have found great joy and consolation in your charity, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed by you, brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Because of this, I have enough confidence in Christ Jesus to command you concerning certain things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>but I beg you instead, for the sake of charity, since you are so much like Paul: an old man and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I beg you, on behalf of my son, whom I have begotten in my chains, Onesimus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>In times past, he was useless to you, but now he is useful both to me and to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So I have sent him back to you. And may you receive him like my own heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I myself wanted to retain him with me, so that he might minister to me, on your behalf, while I am in the chains of the Gospel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But I was willing to do nothing without your counsel, so as not to make use of your good deed as if out of necessity, but only willingly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So perhaps, then, he departed from you for a time, so that you might receive him again for eternity,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>no longer as a servant, but, in place of a servant, a most beloved brother, especially to me: but how much more to you, both in the flesh and in the Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore, if you hold me to be a companion, receive him as you would me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But if he has harmed you in any way, or if he is in your debt, charge it to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I, Paul, have written this with my own hand: I will repay. And I need not tell you, that you are also in debt yourself, to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So it is, brother. May I delight with you in the Lord! Refresh my heart in Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I have written to you, trusting in your obedience, knowing, too, that you will do even more than what I say.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But also, at once, prepare a lodging for me. For I am hoping, through your prayers, to present myself to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Greet Epaphras, my fellow captive in Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, my helpers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>May the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> Onesimus was a slave (or indentured servant) who fled, was converted to Christianity by Paul and others, and who then was sent back to his master. His transition from a slave to a servant is a figure for the transition that a person makes who is freed from the slavery of sin, so as to become the servant of all in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The last phrase &#8216;in Domino&#8217; was changed to &#8216;in Christo&#8217; in accord with the 1590 Sixtus V edition of the Vulgate.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
</book>