<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="1 Peter 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Peter, Apostle of Jesus Christ, to the newly-arrived elect of the dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia,</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>in accord with the foreknowledge of God the Father, in the sanctification of the Spirit, with the obedience and the sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ: May grace and peace be multiplied for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his great mercy has regenerated us into a living hope, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>unto an incorruptible and undefiled and unfading inheritance, which is reserved for you in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>By the power of God, you are guarded through faith for a salvation which is ready to be revealed in the end time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In this, you should exult, if now, for a brief time, it is necessary to be made sorrowful by various trials,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>so that the testing of your faith, which is much more precious than gold tested by fire, may be found in praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For though you have not seen him, you love him. In him also, though you do not see him, you now believe. And in believing, you shall exult with an inexpressible and glorious joy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>returning with the goal of your faith, the salvation of souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>About this salvation, the prophets inquired and diligently searched, those who prophesied about the future grace in you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>inquiring as to what type of condition was signified to them by the Spirit of Christ, when foretelling those sufferings that are in Christ, as well as the subsequent glories.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>To them, it was revealed that they were ministering, not for themselves, but for you those things which have now been announced to you through those who have preached the Gospel to you, through the Holy Spirit, who was sent down from heaven to the One upon whom the Angels desire to gaze.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For this reason, gird the waist of your mind, be sober, and hope perfectly in the grace that is offered to you in the revelation of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Be like sons of obedience, not conforming to the desires of your former ignorance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but in accord with him who has called you: the Holy One. And in every behavior, you yourself must be holy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>for it is written: &#8220;You shall be holy, for I am Holy.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And if you invoke as Father him who, without showing favoritism to persons, judges according to each one&#8217;s work, then act in fear during the time of your sojourning here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For you know that it was not with corruptible gold or silver that you were redeemed away from your useless behavior in the traditions of your fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but it was with the precious blood of Christ, an immaculate and undefiled lamb,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>foreknown, certainly, before the foundation of the world, and made manifest in these latter times for your sake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Through him, you have been faithful to God, who raised him up from the dead and gave him glory, so that your faith and hope would be in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So chastise your souls with the obedience of charity, in fraternal love, and love one another from a simple heart, attentively.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For you have been born again, not from corruptible seed, but from what is incorruptible, from the Word of God, living and remaining for all eternity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For all flesh is like the grass and all its glory is like the flower of the grass. The grass withers and its flower falls away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But the Word of the Lord endures for eternity. And this is the Word that has been evangelized to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> This letter is to the Christians who were formerly Jews, especially those living away from Jerusalem.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The Greek word &#8216;kairos&#8217; is translated here as &#8216;tempus.&#8217; In Greek &#8216;chronos&#8217; refers to time as in the time of day or a length of time; but kairos is used for the more abstract idea of opportunity or conditions or timing, as in the English expression &#8216;the right time.&#8217; So the translation here is not that the Prophets were seeking to know the date of the arrival of Christ, but rather what condition and circumstances would bring the Messiah. So tempus is translated as condition.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="1 Peter 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore, set aside all malice and all deceitfulness, as well as falseness and envy and every detraction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Like newborn infants, desire the milk of reasonableness without guile, so that by this you may increase unto salvation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>if it is true that you have tasted that the Lord is sweet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And approaching him as if he were a living stone, rejected by men, certainly, but elect and honored by God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>be also yourselves like living stones, built upon him, a spiritual house, a holy priesthood, so as to offer up spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God through Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because of this, Scripture asserts: &#8220;Behold, I am setting in Zion a chief cornerstone, elect, precious. And whoever will have believed in him will not be confounded.&#8221;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Therefore, to you who believe, he is honor. But to those who do not believe, the stone which the builders have rejected, the same has been made into the head of the corner,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and a stone of offense, and a rock of scandal, to those who are offended by the Word; neither do they believe, though they also have been built upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But you are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, an acquired people, so that you may announce the virtues of him who has called you out of darkness into his marvelous light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Though in past times you were not a people, yet now you are the people of God. Though you had not obtained mercy, yet now you have obtained mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Most beloved, I beg you, as new arrivals and sojourners, to abstain from carnal desires, which battle against the soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Keep your behavior among the Gentiles to what is good, so that, when they slander you as if you were evildoers, they may, by the good works that are seen in you, glorify God on the day of visitation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Therefore, be subject to every human creature because of God, whether it is to the king as preeminent,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>or to leaders as having been sent from him for vindication over evildoers, it is truly for the praise of what is good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For such is the will of God, that by doing good you may bring about the silence of imprudent and ignorant men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>in an open manner, and not as if cloaking malice with liberty, but like servants of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Honor everyone. Love brotherhood. Fear God. Honor the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Servants, be subject to your masters with all fear, not only to the good and meek, but also to the unruly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For this is grace: when, because of God, a man willingly endures sorrows, suffering injustice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For what glory is there, if you sin and then suffer a beating? But if you do well and suffer patiently, this is grace with God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For you have been called to this because Christ also suffered for us, leaving you an example, so that you would follow in his footsteps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He committed no sin, neither was deceit found in his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when evil was spoken against him, he did not speak evil. When he suffered, he did not threaten. Then he handed himself over to him who judged him unjustly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He himself bore our sins in his body upon the tree, so that we, having died to sin, would live for justice. By his wounds, you have been healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For you were like wandering sheep. But now you have been turned back toward the Pastor and the Bishop of your souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;super&#230;dificamini&#8217; is difficult to render exactly in English; it has the sense of building upon something else, i.e. Christ as the cornerstone, or of building up again and again.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The last part of the verse refers to those Jews who do not believe in Christ even though they also have been built upon him (since Christ is hidden throughout the Old Testament). They also are meant to be living stones placed upon the living Word of God, but they refuse to believe.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="1 Peter 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Similarly also, wives should be subject to their husbands, so that, even if some do not believe the Word, they may benefit without the Word, through the behavior of these wives,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>as they consider with fear your chaste behavior.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For you, there should be no unnecessary adornment of the hair, or surrounding with gold, or the wearing of ornate clothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Instead, you should be a hidden person of the heart, with the incorruptibility of a quiet and meek spirit, rich in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For in this way, in past times also, holy women adorned themselves, hoping in God, being subject to their own husbands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For so Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord. You are her daughters, well-behaved and unafraid of any disturbance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Similarly, you husbands should live with them in accord with knowledge, bestowing honor on the female as the weaker vessel and as co-heirs of the life of grace, so that your prayers may not be hindered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And finally, may you all be of one mind: compassionate, loving brotherhood, merciful, meek, humble,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>not repaying evil with evil, nor slander with slander, but, to the contrary, repaying with blessings. For to this you have been called, so that you may possess the inheritance of a blessing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For whoever wants to love life and to see good days should restrain his tongue from evil, and his lips, so that they utter no deceit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Let him turn away from evil, and do good. Let him seek peace, and pursue it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For the eyes of the Lord are upon the just, and his ears are with their prayers, but the countenance of the Lord is upon those who do evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And who is it who can harm you, if you are zealous in what is good?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And yet, even when you suffer something for the sake of justice, you are blessed. So then, do not be afraid with their fear, and do not be disturbed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But sanctify Christ the Lord in your hearts, being always ready to give an explanation to all who ask you the reason for that hope which is in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But do so with meekness and fear, having a good conscience, so that, in whatever matter they may slander you, they shall be confounded, since they falsely accuse your good behavior in Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For it is better to suffer for doing good, if it is the will of God, than for doing evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For Christ also died once for our sins, the Just One on behalf of the unjust, so that he might offer us to God, having died, certainly, in the flesh, but having been enlivened by the Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And in the Spirit, he preached to those who were in prison, going to those souls</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>3</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>who had been unbelieving in past times, while they waited for the patience of God, as in the days of Noah, when the ark was being built. In that ark, a few, that is, eight souls, were saved by water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And now you also are saved, in a similar manner, by baptism, not by the testimony of sordid flesh, but by the examination of a good conscience in God, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He is at the right hand of God, devouring death, so that we may be made heirs to eternal life. And since he has journeyed to heaven, the Angels and powers and virtues are subject to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The word &#8216;conversationem&#8217; in Latin can refer to conversation, but it more often refers to behavior or attitude.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The term &#8216;extrinsecus capillatura&#8217; refers to any unnecessary adornment of the hair; &#8216;extrinsecus&#8217; does not mean so much outer as beyond what is necessary. The word &#8216;cultus&#8217; is essential to the meaning of the last phrase. The wearing of garments is obviously not prohibited, but the wearing of &#8216;cultus&#8217; garments is prohibited, referring to overly embellished or overly ostentatious clothes.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="3">
      <content> This is one of the well-known references to Purgatory in Scripture.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="1 Peter 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Since Christ has suffered in the flesh, you also should be armed with the same intention. For he who suffers in the flesh desists from sin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>so that now he may live, for the remainder of his time in the flesh, not by the desires of men, but by the will of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the time that has passed is sufficient to have fulfilled the will of the Gentiles, those who have walked in luxuries, lusts, intoxication, feasting, drinking, and the illicit worship of idols.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>About this, they wonder why you do not rush with them into the same confusion of indulgences, blaspheming.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But they must render an account to him who is prepared to judge the living and the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For because of this, the Gospel was also preached to the dead, so that they might be judged, certainly, just like men in the flesh, yet also, so that they might live according to God, in the Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But the end of everything draws near. And so, be prudent, and be vigilant in your prayers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But, before all things, have a constant mutual charity among yourselves. For love covers a multitude of sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Show hospitality to one another without complaining.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Just as each of you has received grace, minister in the same way to one another, as good stewards of the manifold grace of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When anyone speaks, it should be like words of God. When anyone ministers, it should be from the virtue that God provides, so that in all things God may be honored through Jesus Christ. To him is glory and dominion forever and ever. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Most beloved, do not choose to sojourn in the passion which is a temptation to you, as if something new might happen to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But instead, commune in the Passion of Christ, and be glad that, when his glory will be revealed, you too may rejoice with exultation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If you are reproached for the name of Christ, you will be blessed, because that which is of the honor, glory, and power of God, and that which is of his Spirit, rests upon you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But let none of you suffer for being a murderer, or a thief, or a slanderer, or one who covets what belongs to another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But if one of you suffers for being a Christian, he should not be ashamed. Instead, he should glorify God in that name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For it is time that judgment begin at the house of God. And if it is first from us, what shall be the end of those who do not believe the Gospel of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And if the just man will scarcely be saved, where will the impious and the sinner appear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore, too, let those who suffer according to the will of God commend their souls by good deeds to the faithful Creator.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5" preferred_title="1 Peter 5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore, I beg the elders who are among you, as one who is also an elder and a witness of the Passion of Christ, who also shares in that glory which is to be revealed in the future:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>pasture the flock of God that is among you, providing for it, not as a requirement, but willingly, in accord with God, and not for the sake of tainted profit, but freely,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>not so as to dominate by means of the clerical state, but so as to be formed into a flock from the heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the Leader of pastors will have appeared, you shall secure an unfading crown of glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>1</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Similarly, young persons, be subject to the elders. And infuse all humility among one another, for God resists the arrogant, but to the humble he gives grace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And so, be humbled under the powerful hand of God, so that he may exalt you in the time of visitation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Cast all your cares upon him, for he takes care of you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Be sober and vigilant. For your adversary, the devil, is like a roaring lion, traveling around and seeking those whom he might devour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Resist him by being strong in faith, being aware that the same passions afflict those who are your brothers in the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But the God of all grace, who has called us to his eternal glory in Christ Jesus, will himself perfect, confirm, and establish us, after a brief time of suffering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>To him be glory and dominion forever and ever. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I have written briefly, through Sylvanus, whom I consider to be a faithful brother to you, begging and testifying that this is the true grace of God, in which you have been established.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The Church which is in Babylon, elect together with you, greets you, as does my son, Mark.</content>
    </verse>
    <fragment>
      <note_ref>2</note_ref>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Greet one another with a holy kiss. Grace be to all of you who are in Christ Jesus. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <note num="1">
      <content> The phrase &#8216;in cleris&#8217; refers to the ordained, as is clear from the subsequent verse, which calls Christ the leader of pastors. Therefore, the elders to whom Peter addresses himself are ordained men, i.e. priests and Bishops.</content>
    </note>
    <note num="2">
      <content> The word Babylon is here used to refer to Rome. Mark is the writer of the Gospel of Mark, who himself was a student of Peter. Mark is referred to as Peter&#8217;s son, because Mark was about the age of a son to Peter and because the relationship was like that of father and son in the Faith.</content>
    </note>
  </chapter>
</book>