<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again the Lord spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Sina, in the tabernacle of the testimony, on the first day of the second month, in the second year of their coming out of the land of Egypt, and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Take ye the sum of the whole congregation of Israel, according to pedigrees, and according to the houses of their patriarchal families, and according to the number of their names, according to their poll, every male</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>from twenty years old and upwards, every one who goeth out in the army of Israel; review them with their army. Thou and Aaron shall review them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and with you there shall be of the chiefs, one from each tribe. They shall be the chiefs of the patriarchal houses;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and these are the names of the men who shall attend you. Of the Reubenites, Elisur, son of Sedur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>of the Symeonites, Salamiel, son of Surisadai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>of the children of Judas, Naasson, son of Aminadab;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>of the children of Issachar, Nathaniel, son of Sogar;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>of the Zabulonites, Eliab, son of Chailon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>of the children of Joseph; of the Ephraimites, Elisama, son of Emiud; of the Manassites, Gamaliel, son of Phadassur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>of the Benjaminites, Abidon, son of Gadeoni;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>of the Danites, Achiezer, son of Amisadai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>of the Aserites, Phagiel, son of Echran;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>of the Gadites, Elisaph, son of Raguel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>of the Nephthaleimites, Achire, son of Ainan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>These are renowned men of the congregation, chiefs of the tribes according to their patriarchal families, the chiliarchs of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So Moses and Aaron took these men, who were expressly named,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and assembled all the congregation on the first day of the second month, and marshalled them according to their pedigrees, according to their families, according to the number of their names, from twenty years old and upwards, every male by their poll,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>as the Lord commanded Moses, and reviewed them in the wilderness of Sina.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And there were of the children of Reuben, Jacob's first born, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of names by their poll; all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>on the review of those of the tribe of Reuben, were forty six thousand five hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And of the Symeonites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names, according to their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>on the review of them, of the tribe of Symeon, were fifty nine thousand three hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And of the Gadites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Gad, were forty five thousand six hundred and fifty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And of the children of Judas, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll; all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>on the review of those of the tribe of Judas, were seventy four thousand six hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And of the Issacharites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Issachar, were fifty four thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And of the Zabulonites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Zabulon, were fifty seven thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And of the children of Joseph; Of the Ephraimites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Ephraim, were forty thousand five hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And of the Manassites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Manasses, were thirty two thousand two hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And of the Benjaminites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Benjamin, were thirty five thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And of the Danites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Dan, were sixty two thousand seven hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And of the Aserites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Aser, were forty one thousand five hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And of the Nephthaleimites, according to their pedigrees, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, according to the number of their names by their poll, all the males from twenty years old and upwards, every one who went out in the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>on a review of those of the tribe of Nephthaleim, were fifty three thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>This was the review which Moses and Aaron, and the chiefs of Israel made. The chiefs were twelve, a man for every tribe. They were of the patriarchal houses of their respective tribes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And the whole review of the Israelites, comprehending their army from twenty years old and upwards,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>every one who went out to be marshalled in Israel, was six hundred and three thousand five hundred and fifty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>But the Levites of the tribe of their father's house, were not reviewed among the Israelites:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>for the Lord had spoken to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>See that thou review not the tribe of Levi, nor take an account of them among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>But thou shalt set the Levites over the tabernacle of the testimony, and over all the utensils thereof, and over all the things which are in it. They shall carry the tabernacle, and all its utensils, and they shall minister therein, and encamp about the tabernacle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And when the tabernacle is to remove, the Levites shall take it down; and when the tabernacle is to be pitched, they shall set it up. And if any of another family come near, let him be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>And when the Israelites encamp, every man in his station, and every man according to his command, with their army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>let the Levites encamp before them, around the tabernacle of the testimony, that there may be no lapse committed by the children of Israel; and that the Levites themselves may guard the tabernacle of the testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>And when the Israelites had done according to all that the Lord commanded Moses,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>then the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Let the children of Israel encamp close to one another, by divisions, by standards, by the houses of their families, facing the tabernacle of the testimony. All around it the Israelites shall encamp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And they who encamp first, towards the east, shall be the division of the camp of Judas with their army; and the chief of the children of Judas shall be Naasson, son of Aminadab;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>his army; even they who were reviewed, being seventy four thousand six hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining, shall be the division of the tribe of Issachar, and the chief of the Issacharites shall be Nathaniel, son of Sogar;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>his army; even they who were reviewed, being fifty four thousand four hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining, shall be the division of the tribe of Zabulon, and the chief of the Zabulonites shall be Eliab, son of Chailon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>his army; even they who were reviewed, being fifty seven thousand four hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>all those of the camp of Judas who have been reviewed, amounting to one hundred and eighty six thousand four hundred, with their army, shall march in the van.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And their army on the south, shall be the divisions of the camp of Reuben, and the chief of the Reubenites shall be Elisar, son of Sedur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>his army, even they who have been reviewed, being forty six thousand five hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining him, shall be the division of the tribe of Symeon, and the chief of the Symeonites shall be Salamiel, son of Surisadai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>his army, even they who were reviewed, being fifty nine thousand three hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining shall be the tribe of Gad; and the chief of the Gadites, shall be Elisaph, son of Raguel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>his army, even they who were reviewed, being forty five thousand six hundred and fifty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>All those of the camp of Reuben who have been reviewed, amounting to one hundred and fifty one thousand four hundred and fifty, with their army, shall march as the second division.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then shall move the tabernacle of the testimony, and the camp of the Levites, as the centre division of the camps. As they encamp so they shall take up their march, every man in his rank, according to their companies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And on the west shall be the division of the camp of Ephraim, with their army; and the chief of the Ephraimites shall be Elisama, son of Emiud;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>his army, even they who were reviewed, being forty thousand five hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining, shall be the division of the tribe of Manasses, and the chief of the Manassites shall be Gamaliel, son of Phadassur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>his army, even they who were reviewed, being thirty two thousand two hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining, shall be the division of the tribe of Benjamin; and the chief of the Benjaminites shall be Abidon, son of Gadeoni;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>his army, even they who were reviewed, being thirty five thou 24 sand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>All those of the camp of Ephraim who have been reviewed, amounting to one hundred and eight thousand one hundred, with their army, shall march as the third division.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And on the north shall be the division of the camp of Dan; with their army; and the chief of the Danites shall be Achiezer, son of Amisadai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>his army, even they who were reviewed, being sixty two thousand seven hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining him, shall be the tribe of Aser; and the chief of the Aserites, shall be Phagiel, son of Echran;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>his army, even they who have been reviewed, being forty one thousand five hundred:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and they who encamp adjoining, shall be the division of the tribe of Nephthaleim, and the chief of the Nephthaleimites shall be Achire, son of Ainan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>his army, even they who were reviewed, being fifty three thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>All those of the camp of Dan, who have been reviewed, amounting to one hundred and fifty seven thousand six hundred, shall march as the rear division.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>This is the review of the children of Israel according to the houses of their families; the whole muster of the camps, comprehending their armies, being six hundred and three thousand five hundred and fifty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But the Levites were not reviewed among them, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And the children of Israel did all that the Lord commanded Moses. So they encamped according to their divisions, and so they set out on their march, every one in his rank, according to their communities, and according to the houses of their families.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now this is the genealogy of Aaron and Moses. On the day when the Lord spoke to Moses at mount Sina,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>these were the names of Aaron's sons, Nadab his first born, and Abiud, Eleazar and Ithamar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>These were the names of Aaron's sons who were anointed priests, whose hands were consecrated to minister in the priest's office.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But Nadab and Abiud died in the presence of the Lord, upon their offering strange fire before the Lord, in the wilderness of Sina, and they had no children; so Eleazar and Ithamar officiated as priests with their father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Take the tribe of Levi, and thou shalt present them before Aaron the priest, and they shall minister to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and keep his watches, and the watches of the children of Israel before the tabernacle of the testimony, to do the works of the tabernacle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now that they may keep all the utensils of the tabernacle of the testimony, and the watches of the children of Israel, as far as they respect all the works of the tabernacle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and that thou mayst give the Levites, to Aaron and his sons the priests; they are to be given to me as a gift from among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And thou shalt set Aaron and his sons over the tabernacle of the testimony, and they shall keep watch over their priesthood, and all that appertain to the altar, and that are within the veil; and if any one of another family touch these, he shall be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Behold I have taken the Levites from among the children of Israel, instead of all the first born males among the children of Israel. The Levites shall be the price of their redemption, and shall be mine;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for every first born belongeth to me. On the day when I smote every first born in the land of Egypt, I hallowed for myself all the firstlings in Israel. The firstlings both of man and beast shall belong to me. I am the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Sina, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Review the children of Levi, according to the houses of their families, according to their communities. Review them every male, from a month old and upwards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Accordingly Moses and Aaron reviewed them, at the command of the Lord, in the manner the Lord commanded them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now these were the sons of Levi by their names, Gerson, Kaath, and Merari.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And these are the sons of Gerson, according to their communities; Lobeni and Semei.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And these are the sons of Kaath according to their communities, Amram and Issaar, Chebron and Oziel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the sons of Merari, according to their communities, were Mooli and Mousi. These are the communities of the Levites, according to the houses of their families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>To the Gersonites belong the community of the Lobenites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the community of the Semeites. These are the communities of the Gersonites; and the review of them according to the number of every male, from a month old and upwards; on a review of them the number was seven thousand two hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now the Gersonites are to encamp behind the tabernacle, towards the west,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and the chief of the head of the family of the community of the Gersonites, was Elisaph son of Dael.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the charge of the Gersonites in the tabernacle of the testimony, was the tabernacle and the covering; and the curtain of the door of the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and the hangings of the court; and the curtain of the gate, of the court around the tabernacle; and the rest of the works thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>To the Kaathites belonged the community of the Amramites, and the community of the Issaarites, and the community of the Chebronites, and the community of the Ozielites. These are the communities of the Kaathites</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>according to the numeration; every male, from a month old and upwards, amounted to eight thousand six hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>These communities of the Kaathites, having the charge of the holy things, are to encamp on the south side of the tabernacle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and the chief of the head family of the communities of the Kaathites was Elisaphan, son of Oziel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and their charge was the ark, and the table, and the candlestick, and the altars, and the utensils of the sanctuary which were used in the priest's office; and the veil, and all the works thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the chief over the chiefs of the Levites, was Eleazar, the son of Aaron, set over them to superintend the watches of the holy things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>To the Merarites belonged the community of Mooli, and the community of Mousi. These are the communities of the Merarites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>The muster of them, comprehending every male from one month old and upwards, was six thousand two hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the chief of the head family of the community of the Merarites, was Suriel, the son of Abichail. They are to encamp on the north side of the tabernacle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and the review of the watch of the Merarites, had the charge of the tabernacle, and the bars thereof, and the pillars thereof, and the bases thereof, with all their appurtenances and works,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and the pillars of the court round about, with their stakes and their cords .</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>They who encamp in front of the tabernacle of the testimony, towards the east, were Moses and Aaron, and their sons, who have the superintendance of the watches of the sanctuary, for the purpose of guarding the things committed to the charge of the Israelites, and if any of another family touch them, he is to be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>The whole muster of the Levites, whom Moses and Aaron reviewed, by the command of the Lord, according to their communities; all the males, from a month old and upwards, were twenty two thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying, Review all the male first born of the children of Israel, from one month old and upwards, and take the number by name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And thou shalt take the Levites for me; I the Lord; instead of all the first born sons of Israel; and the cattle of the Levites instead of all the firstlings of the cattle belonging to the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>So Moses reviewed, in the manner the Lord commanded, all the male first born among the Israelites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>and all the first born males, numbered by name, from one month old and upwards, were twenty two thousand two hundred and seventy three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Whereupon the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Take the Levites, instead of all the first born of the children of Israel, and the cattle of the Levites, for the firstlings of their cattle; and the Levites shall belong to me; I the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And as redemption money for the two hundred and seventy three, of the first born, more than the Levites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>thou shalt take from the first born of the children of Israel, five shekels a poll. According to the holy didrachm, thou shall receive twenty oboli for a shekel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And thou shalt give the money to Aaron and his sons, as the redemption of the overplus among the Israelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>So Moses took the redemption money, for those who exceeded the redemption made by the Levites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>From the first born of the children of Israel he took the money, amounting to one thousand three hundred and sixty five shekels according to the holy shekel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>and gave the redemption money for the overplus to Aaron and his sons, by the command of the Lord, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Take the sum of the Kaathites, apart from the Levites, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>from twenty five years and upwards, to fifty years, every one who goeth in to minister; to do all the services of the tabernacle of the testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now these are the services of the Kaathites in the tabernacle of the testimony, a most sacred service.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When the camp is about to remove, Aaron shall go in with his sons, and they shall take down the covering veil, and with it cover the ark of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and put thereon the covering of blue skins; and over it they shall spread a mantle, wholly blue, and put in the staves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then over the presence table they shall spread a mantle, all of purple; upon it, and upon the platters, and the censers, and the goblets, and the libation cups, with which he maketh libations; and the loaves which are continually thereon shall be upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And they shall throw over it a scarlet mantle, and cover it, with a blue skin covering, and put in the staves to carry it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then they shall take a blue mantle, and cover the candlestick which giveth light with its lamps, and its snuffers, and its tweezers, and all the oil vessels, which they use in that service;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and they shall put it, and all the utensils thereof, into a blue skin covering, and lay it on the staves to carry it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>They shall then cover the golden altar with a blue mantle, and spread over it a skin covering of blue, and put in the staves thereof to carry it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they shall take all the utensils used in the service, all with which they minister in the holies, and put them into a blue mantle, and cover them with a skin covering of blue, and lay them on staves to carry them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then they shall put the cover on the altar, and cover it with a mantle, entirely of purple,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and they shall lay thereon all the utensils with which they minister at it, namely the censers, and the flesh forks, and the cups, and the cover, and the vials, and all the utensils of the altar; and they shall throw over it a skin covering of blue, and put in the staves to carry it. Then they shall take a purple mantle, and cover the laver and its base; and put it in a skin covering of blue, and put it on the staves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when Aaron and his sons have finished covering the holy things, and all the utensils, while the camp is removing, after this the sons of Kaath shall come in to carry them; but they shall not touch the holy things lest they die. These things the sons of Kaath shall take up in the tabernacle of the testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The overseer, Eleazar son of Aaron the priest, shall have the charge of the oil for light, and of the compound incense, and the daily sacrifice, and the anointing oil, and the oversight of the whole tabernacle, and all that are in it, in the sanctuary, in all the works thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>That you may not destroy this community of the tribe, namely the Kaathites, from among the Levites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>you must do this for them, that they may live and not die; When they go into the holy of holies, let Aaron and his sons go in before them; and they shall station them, every one according to what he is to carry:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And let them not go in abruptly, to view the holy things, so they shall not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Take the sum of the Gersonites; of them also according to the houses of their families, according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Review them, from twenty five years, and upwards, to fifty years of age, every one who goeth in to minister; to do his work in the tabernacle of the testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The service of the community of the Gersonites is the same, namely to serve and to carry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>They shall carry the skin coverings of the tabernacle of the testimony with its covering, the upper covering of blue which is upon it, and the curtain of the door of the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and the hangings of the court, both all that are for the tabernacle of the testimony, and those about it, and all the sacred implements which are used in the holy service.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>They shall act under the direction of Aaron and his sons, whatever may be the service of the Gersonites, in all their services, and in all their works. So thou shalt review them by name, having respect to all the burdens to be carried by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>This is the service of the Gersonites in the tabernacle of the testimony, and the superintendance of them shall be by the hand of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>With regard to the Merarites, review them according to their communities, according to the houses of their families;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>review them from twenty five years, and upwards, to fifty years of age; every one who goeth in to do the works of the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>to take charge of those things to be carried by them, according to all their works for the tabernacle of the testimony, namely the capitals of the tabernacle, and the bars, and the pillars thereof, the bases thereof, and the bases and pillars for the veil, and for the curtain of the door of the tabernacle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and the pillars of the court round about, with their bases, and the pillars for the curtain of the gate of the court, with their bases, and their pins, and their cords, and all the implements thereof, and all their services; review them by name, and all the implements which are to be under their charge, and to be carried by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>This service of the community of the Merarites, in all their works, for the tabernacle of the testimony, shall be under the superintendance of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Accordingly Moses and Aaron, and the chiefs of Israel, reviewed the Kaathites according to their communities, according to the houses of their families,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>from twenty five years old, and upwards, to fifty years of age, every one who went in to minister, and do service for the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and the number of them, according to their communities, was two thousand seven hundred and fifty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>This was the muster of the community of the Kaathites, comprehending every one who performed service for the tabernacle of the testimony, as Moses and Aaron reviewed them, at the command of the Lord, by the hand of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then the Gersonites were reviewed according to their communities, according to the houses of their families,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>from twenty five years, and upwards, to fifty years of age, comprehending every one who went in to serve, and perform works for the tabernacle of the testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And the muster of them, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, was two thousand six hundred and thirty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>This was the review of the community of the Gersonites, comprehending every one who performed service for the tabernacle of the testimony, whom Moses and Aaron reviewed, at the command of the Lord, by the hand of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Then was reviewed the community of the Merarites, according to their communities, according to the houses of their families,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>from twenty five years, and upwards, to fifty years of age, comprehending every one who went in to perform the holy works of the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And the muster of them according to their communities, according to the houses of their families, was three thousand two hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>This was the muster of the community of the Merarites, whom Moses and Aaron reviewed, at the command of the Lord, by the hand of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>All the Levites who were reviewed, whom Moses with Aaron and the chiefs of Israel reviewed by communities, by the houses of their families,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>from twenty five years, and upwards, to fifty years of age, comprehending every one who went in for the performance of works and for the business of carrying for the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>even all who were reviewed, were eight thousand five hundred and eighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>At the command of the Lord, by the hand of Moses, he reviewed them, man by man, for their works, and for the things which they were to carry. They were reviewed in the manner the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Give orders to the children of Israel, and let them send out of the camp every one who is a leper, and every one who hath a gonorrhea, and every one who is defiled by the dead;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>whether male or female, send them out of the camp, that they may not defile their camps in which I am present among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon the children of Israel did so. They sent them away out of the camp, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when they had done so, the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and say, When a man or a woman shall commit any sin incident to man; or by inadvertency overlook or commit a trespass,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>that person shall confess the sin which he or she hath committed, and make compensation for the trespass. Adding one fifth to the principal, he shall give it to the person against whom the trespass hath been committed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And if the man hath no kinsman to whom compensation can be made, the compensation, being given to the Lord, shall belong to the priest, over and above the ram of atonement, with which he shall make atonement for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And every dedication; whatever the children of Israel shall dedicate, and bring for the Lord, shall be for the priest;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>even every one's hallowed things shall be his; let who will give, they shall belong to the priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, If any man's wife transgress, and actually despise him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and any person lie with her carnally, and it escape the notice of her husband, and it be hid, and she be polluted, though there be no witness against her, and she be not caught in the act;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and a spirit of jealousy come upon him, and he be jealous of his wife, and she be polluted; or a spirit of jealousy come upon him, and he be jealous of his wife, though she be not polluted,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the man shall bring his wife to the priest, and shall bring as a gift for her the tenth of an ephah of barley meal; but he shall pour no oil on it, nor lay any frankincense on it; for it is a sacrifice of jealousy; a sacrifice of remembrance, to bring into remembrance a sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the priest shall bring her forward, and set her before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then the priest shall take pure spring water, in an earthen vessel, and having taken up some of the dust which is on the floor of the tabernacle of the testimony, the priest shall put it in the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the priest shall present the woman before the Lord, and uncover the woman's head. Then he shall put the sacrifice of remembrance; the sacrifice of jealousy into her hands; and in the hand of the priest shall be the water of discovery over which an imprecation is to be made;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the priest shall adjure the woman, and say to her, If no man hath lain with thee; if thou hast not transgressed, so as to be defiled, while under the jurisdiction of thy husband; be thou uninjured by this water of discovery, over which an imprecation is to be made:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but if thou hast transgressed, being a married woman, or art polluted, and any person besides thy husband hath lain with thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>(then the priest shall adjure the woman with solemn imprecations, and the priest shall say to the woman) the Lord make thee a curse and an imprecation in the midst of thy people, by causing thy thigh to rot, and thy belly to be inflamed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Let this water over which this imprecation is made, go into thy belly, to inflame thy belly, and rot thy thigh. And the woman shall say, Amen, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then the priest shall write these curses in a book, and dip it in the water of discovery, over which the imprecation was made,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and shall cause the woman to drink the water of discovery, over which the imprecation was made. And the water of discovery, over which the imprecation was made, shall go into her;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>(The priest shall take the sacrifice of jealousy out of the woman's hand, and lay the sacrifice before the Lord, and offer it on the altar;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and when the priest shall have taken a handful of the sacrifice, the memorial of it, and offered it on the altar, after this he shall cause the woman to drink the water)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and it shall come to pass that if she be defiled, and escape the notice of her husband, when the water of discovery, over which the imprecation was made, shall go into her, it shall inflame her belly, and her thigh shall rot, and the woman shall be a curse among her people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But if the woman be not polluted, and be pure, she shall be uninjured, and shall conceive seed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>This is the law of jealousy, when a woman who is married transgresseth and is polluted;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>or when a spirit of jealousy cometh on a man. When he is jealous of her, and shall set his wife before the Lord, the priest shall do to her all that this law directeth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>so shall the man be free from sin, and the woman shall bear her iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, When a man or a woman shall make a solemn vow to preserve the strictest purity for the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>they must abstain from wine, and strong drink. Such a one shall not drink vinegar made of wine, nor vinegar made of strong drink; nor shall such a one drink any thing made of the grape; nor eat any grapes, fresh pulled, or dryed, all the days of the vow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>From every thing produced from the grape, including wine; from the pulp to the stone,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>such a one shall abstain all the days of the purification. A razor shall not come upon his head, until the days which he hath vowed to the Lord be fulfilled. Being hallowed, he shall let the hair of his head grow</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>all the days of his vow to the Lord. He shall not come near any dead body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For a father or a mother, or for a brother or a sister, if they chance to die, he shall not defile himself; for the vow of his God is on his head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>All the days of his vow he shall be holy to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And if any one die suddenly by him, the head of his vow will be immediately defiled, he shall therefore shave his head on the day when he is cleansed. On the seventh day it shall be shaved,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and on the eighth day he shall bring two turtle doves, or two young pigeons to the priest, to the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and the priest shall offer one for a sin offering, and the other for a whole burnt offering; and the priest shall make atonement for him for the failures of which he hath been guilty by the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And on that day he shall hallow r his head which was consecrated to the Lord, for the days of his vow, and bring a lamb of the first year for a trespass offering: And the former days shall not be counted, because the head of his vow was defiled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now this is the law of him who hath made the vow; When the days of his vow are fulfilled; he shall bring to the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and present as his gift to the Lord, a lamb of the first year without blemish for a whole burnt offering, and a ewe lamb of the first year without blemish, for a sin offering, and a ram without blemish for an offering of thanksgiving,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and a basket of unleavened bread, of fine flour; the loaves tempered with oil, and unleavened cakes anointed with oil, and their sacrifice of flour and their libation:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and the priest shall offer them before the Lord. When he hath offered the sin offering and the whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>he shall then offer the ram, the sacrifice of thanksgiving to the Lord, with the basket of unleavened bread. And when the priest hath offered the sacrifice thereof, and the libation thereof,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>then he who made the vow shall have the head of his vow shaved at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony, and shall lay the hairs on the fire which is under the sacrifice of thanksgiving.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the priest shall take the boiled shoulder from the ram, and one unleavened loaf from the basket, and one unleavened cake, and lay them on the hands of him who made the vow, after he hath shaved his consecrated head;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and the priest shall offer these as a dedication laid on hands before the Lord. It shall be consecrated for the priest, over and above the breast, which was dedicated by being laid on hands, and the shoulder which was dedicated by setting it apart. And after these things, he who made the vow may drink wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>This is the law for him who hath made the vow; who may have vowed to the Lord; his gift to the Lord for his vow, besides what he may be able to do more, according to the nature of the vow which he may have made, according to the law of strict purity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Speak to Aaron and his sons and say, In this manner you shall bless the children of Israel, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The Lord bless thee and keep thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The Lord make his countenance to shine upon thee, and be gracious to thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The Lord lift up his countenance upon thee, and give thee peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So they shall put my name on the children of Israel; and I the Lord will bless them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now on the day when Moses finished the rearing up of the tabernacle, he anointed it, and hallowed it, and all the implements thereof; and the altar, and all its utensils; and when he had anointed them, and hallowed them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the chiefs of Israel, the twelve chiefs of the houses of their head families who were the chiefs of the tribes, the same who attended at the review, made an offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and brought as their gifts before the Lord, six covered waggons, and twelve oxen, a waggon from two chiefs, and an ox from each one. And when they had brought them before the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>the Lord spoke to Moses saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Receive them from them, and they shall be for the works of the service of the tabernacle of the testimony; and thou shalt give them to the Levites, to each community according to their service.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So Moses, having taken the waggons and the oxen, gave them to the Levites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>he gave two waggons and four oxen to the Gersonites, according to their service;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and four waggons and eight oxen, he gave to the Merarites, according to their service, by Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But to the Kaathites he gave none, because they having the sacred services of the sanctuary, are to carry on their shoulders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The chiefs tendered also an offering for the dedication of the altar, on the day he anointed it. But when the chiefs brought their gift over against the altar, at some distance from it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>the Lord said to Moses, One chief a day. Let them bring forward, every chief his gifts on his day, for the dedication of the altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So he who brought forward his gifts on the first day, was Naasson, son of Aminadab chief of the tribe of Judas;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and he offered as his gift, one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver cup of seventy shekels after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour, mixed up with oil, for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>one censer, of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Naasson, son of Aminadab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>On the second day Nathaniel, son of Sogar, the chief of the tribe of Issachar made his offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and he presented as his gift, one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour, mixed up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and one kid of the goats, for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Nathaniel son of Sogar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>On the third day the chief of the Zabulonites, Eliab, son of Chailon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>offered as his gift one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver cup of seventy shekels after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Eliab, son of Chailon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>On the fourth day the chief of the Reubenites, Elisur son of Sedur, offered as his gift</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>one silver charger the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year for a whole burnt offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Elisur son of Sedur.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>On the fifth day the chief of the Symeonites, Salamiel, son of Surisadai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>offered as his gift one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Salamiel, son of Surisadai.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>On the sixth day the chief of the Gadites, Elisaph son of Raguel, offered as his gift,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Elisaph, son of Raquel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>On the seventh day the chief of the Ephraimites, Elisama, son of Emiud,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>offered as his gift one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>and, for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Elisama, son of Emiud.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>On the eighth day the chief of the children of Manasses, Gamaliel, son of Phadassur,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>offered as his gift, one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour, made up with oil for a sacrifice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>and one kid of the goats, for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Gamaliel, son of Phadassur.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>On the ninth day the chief of the Benjaminites, Abidan, son of Gadeoni,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>offered as his gift, one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>one censer of two shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>one young bull of the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year for a whole burnt offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five lie-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Abidan, son of Gadeoni.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>On the tenth clay, the chief of the Danites, Achieser, son of Amisadai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>offered as his gift, one silver charger the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour, made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a whole burnt offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Achieser, son of Amisadai.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>On the eleventh day, the chief of the Aserites, Phagael, son of Echran,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="73">
      <content>offered as his gift, one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels; one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour, made up with oil, for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="74">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="75">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a whole burnt offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="76">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="77">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Phagael, son of Echran.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="78">
      <content>On the twelfth day, the chief of the Nephthaleimites, Achire, son of Ainan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="79">
      <content>offered as his gift, one silver charger, the weight of which was a hundred and thirty shekels, one silver cup of seventy shekels, after the holy shekel, both full of fine flour made up with oil for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="80">
      <content>one censer of ten shekels of gold, full of incense;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="81">
      <content>one young bull from the herd, one ram, one lamb of the first year, for a whole burnt offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="82">
      <content>and one kid of the goats for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="83">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of thanksgiving, two heifers, five rams, five he-goats, five ewe lambs of the first year. This was the gift of Achire, son of Ainan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="84">
      <content>This was the dedication of the altar, when he anointed it, from the chiefs of the Israelites, twelve silver chargers, twelve silver cups, twelve censers of gold,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="85">
      <content>each charger one hundred and thirty shekels, and each cup seventy shekels, all the silver of these vessels, two thousand four hundred shekels, and the shekels were after the holy shekel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="86">
      <content>twelve golden censers, full of incense; all the gold of the censers was one hundred and twenty shekels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="87">
      <content>All the cattle for the whole burnt offering were twelve young bulls, twelve rams, twelve lambs of the first year, with their sacrifices of flour and their libations; and twelve kids of the goats for the sin offering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="88">
      <content>All the cattle for the sacrifice of thanksgiving, were twenty four heifers, sixty rams, sixty he-goats, sixty ewe lambs of the first year, without blemish. This was the dedication of the altar. After filling his own hands, and after the anointing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="89">
      <content>when Moses went into the tabernacle of the testimony to speak to the Lord, he heard the voice of the Lord speaking to him, from above the propitiatory, which is over the ark of the testimony, between the two cherubims, and he answered him,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Speak to Aaron, and thou shalt say to him, When thou hast put on the side lamps, the seven lamps shall give light in a range with the front of the candlestick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And Aaron did so. On each side, on a range with the front of the candlestick, he lighted the lamps thereof as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now the workmanship of the candlestick was of solid gold; both its stem, and its lillies, were of one solid piece. He had made the candlestick according to the pattern which the Lord shewed Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Take the Levites from among the children of Israel, and purify them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And in this manner thou shalt perform their purification. Thou shalt sprinkle them with the water of purification, and a razor shall pass over their whole body, and they shall wash their clothes, and they will be clean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then they shall take a young bull from the herd, with his sacrifice, to wit, fine flour mixed up with oil; and thou shalt take a yearling bull from the herd for a sin offering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and bring the Levites before the tabernacle of the testimony, and assemble all the congregation of Israel's sons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and present the Levites before the Lord. And the sons of Israel shall lay their hands on the Levites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Aaron shall set the Levites apart before the Lord, as a gift from the sons of Israel; and they shall be set apart to perform the works of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the Levites shall lay their hands on the head of the young bulls. And thou shalt offer the one for a sin offering, and the other for a whole burnt offering, to make atonement for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then thou shalt place the Levites before the Lord, and before Aaron and before his sons, and give them as a gift before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>thou shalt separate the Levites from among the children of Israel, and they shall belong to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And after this, the Levites shall go in to do the works of the tabernacle of the testimony, when thou hast purified them, and given them up before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Because they are solemnly given up to me from among the children of Israel; I have taken them for myself from among the children of Israel, instead of all the males who are the first born of their mothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Because every first born among the children of Israel, whether of man or beast, belongeth to me (on the day when I smote all the first born in the land of Egypt, I hallowed them for myself)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and I have taken the Levites instead of all the first born among the children of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and have given the Levites as a gift to Aaron and his sons, from among the children of Israel, to do the works of the children of Israel at the tabernacle of the testimony, and to make atonement for the children of Israel; therefore none among the children of Israel shall come near the Holies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So Moses and Aaron, and all the congregation of the children of Israel, did to the Levites as the Lord commanded Moses in respect to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now when the children of Israel had done so to them, and the Levites were purified, and had washed their clothes, and Aaron had solemnly given them up in the presence of the Lord, and had made atonement for them to purify them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and, after this, the Levites had gone in to perform their service in the tabernacle of the testimony, in the presence of Aaron and his sons; when they had done thus for the Levites, as the Lord had commanded Moses in respect to them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>There is this further in respect to the Levites; from twenty five years and upwards, they shall go in to perform service at the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but after fifty years of age, they are to be withdrawn from the service, and work no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>As brothers, they are to keep watch at the tabernacle of the testimony, but not to perform laborious work. In this manner thou shalt dispose of the Levites among their watches.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now in the second year after their coming out of the land of Egypt, in the first month, the Lord spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Sina, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Give orders, and let the children of Israel keep the passover in its appointed season.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>On the fourteenth day of this first month, towards evening, thou shalt celebrate it in its season. According to its rites, and according to its institution, thou shalt celebrate it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Accordingly Moses spoke to the children of Israel to keep the passover</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>on the fourteenth day of the first month, in the wilderness of Sina. And when the children of Israel were doing as the Lord commanded Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>there were some men who were defiled by the dead body of a man, and could not keep the passover; so these men came to Moses and Aaron on that day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and said to them, We are defiled by the dead body of a man, must we therefore be deprived of the opportunity of offering our gift to the Lord, in its appointed season, among the children of Israel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>whereupon Moses said to them, Stand here; and I will hear what the Lord will command concerning you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and say, If any man among you, or among your posterity, happen to be defiled by the dead, or be on a far distant journey, he shall keep the passover to the Lord</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>in the second month. On the fourteenth day they shall keep it towards evening. They shall eat it with unleavened bread, and bitter herbs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>they shall not leave any of it till the morning; nor shall they break a bone of it. They shall keep it according to the ritual of the passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And if any man be clean, and not on a distant journey, and fail to keep the passover, that soul shall be cut off from among his people; because he did not offer this gift to the Lord, in its appointed time, such a man shall bear his sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And if there come to you a proselyte in your land, and he chuse to keep the passover to the Lord, he must keep it according to its ritual, and according to its institution. You shall have one law for the proselyte and for him born in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now on the day when the tabernacle was erected, the cloud covered the tabernacle; the house of the testimony: and in the evening there was over the tabernacle an appearance like that of fire, which continued till the morning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thus it was continually. The cloud covered it by day: and there was an appearance of fire during the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when the cloud ascended from the tabernacle, the Israelites thereupon began their march; and at what place soever the cloud halted there the Israelites encamped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>By the command of the Lord the Israelites were to encamp, and by the command of the Lord, they were to march. All the time the cloud overshadowed the tabernacle, the Israelites were to continue encamped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when the cloud was continued over the tabernacle many days, the Israelites were to keep the watch of their God, and not remove.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And such was to be the case when the cloud overshadowed the tabernacle but a few days. At the command of the Lord, they were to encamp; and at the command of the Lord, they were to march.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And this was to be the case when the cloud was from evening till morning. When the cloud ascended in the morning, they were to take up their march, whether it was day or night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But while the cloud continued to overshadow it, even for a month or more, the Israelites were to continue encamped, and not remove.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Because at the command of the Lord, they were to move, and at the command of the Lord, by the ministry of Moses, they kept the watch of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>therefore the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Make for thyself two silver trumpets. Thou shalt make them of ductile silver, each beaten out of one piece. And they shall serve thee to assemble the congregation, and to cause the camps to remove.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When thou shalt blow with them, all the congregation shall assemble at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>but when one is blown, all the chiefs, the leaders of Israel, shall come to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When you blow an alarm, the camps on the east shall begin their march;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and when you blow a second alarm, the camps on the south shall begin their march; and when you blow a third alarm, the camps on the west shall begin their march; and when you blow a fourth alarm, the camps on the north shall begin their march. They shall blow an alarm for their marching.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when you would assemble the congregation, you are to blow with them, but not an alarm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The sons of Aaron, the priests, shall blow the trumpets. This shall be a perpetual ordinance for you, throughout your generations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when you go out to battle in your land, against your enemies, who have risen up against you, you shall sound these trumpets, that you may be brought into remembrance before the Lord, and saved from your enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In the days of your rejoicings also, and at your festivals, and at your new moons, you shall blow the trumpets, at your whole burnt offerings, and at your sacrifices of thanksgivings; and it shall be a calling of you into remembrance before the Lord; I the Lord your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now in the second year, in the second month, on the twentieth day of the month, the cloud ascended from the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>whereupon the Israelites with their baggage, marched through the wilderness of Sina, and the cloud halted in the wilderness of Pharan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When the first had begun their march; when the van,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>the division of the camp of Judas, had marched, and at the head of it Naasson son of Aminadab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Issachar, Nathaniel son of Sogar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Zabulon, Eliab son of Chailon; then were the Gersonites, and the Merarites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>having taken down the tabernacle, to move on; carrying the tabernacle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when the division of the camp of Reuben had marched with their army, and at the head of it Elisur son of Sedur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Symeon, Salamiel son of Surisadai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Gad, Elisaph son of Raguel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>then were the Kaathites to move on, carrying the holy things, so that the tabernacle might be set up when they arrived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then were to march the division of the camp of Ephraim, with their army, and at the head of it Elisama son of Emiud;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Manasses, Gamaliel son of Phadassur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Benjamin, Abidan son of Gadeoni.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the division of the camp of Dan were to march the last of all the camps, with their army, and at the head of it Achiezer son of Amisadai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Aser, Phagael son of Echran;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and at the head of the army of the tribe of Nephthaleim, Achire son of Ainan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>These were the armies of the Israelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now when they began their march Moses said to Obad, son of Raguel the Madianite, the brother in law of Moses, We are now on our march to the place which the Lord said, This I will give you. Come with us and we will deal well with thee; for the Lord hath spoken good things concerning Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>In reply to which he said, I cannot go, but must return to my own land, and to my family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Whereupon Moses said, Thou must not leave us. Because thou hast been with us in the wilderness, therefore thou shalt be a senator among us,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and shalt share; if thou go with us, thou shalt indeed share in all those good things which the Lord will bestow upon us, and we will deal kindly with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So they removed from the mount of the Lord, three days' journey, and the ark of the covenant of the Lord went before them the three days' journey, to look out for them a resting place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Now while the cloud was overshadowing them by day, as they marched out of the camp,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when the ark set forward Moses said, Arise, O Lord, and let thine enemies be scattered. Let them who hate thee be put to flight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And when it halted he said, Return, Lord, to the thousand myriads of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>the people were wickedly murmuring before the Lord, and the Lord heard, and was provoked to wrath, and a fire from the Lord was kindled among them, and was consuming part of the camp,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>whereupon the people cried to Moses, and he prayed to the Lord, and the fire ceased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So the name of that place was called Burning, because a fire from the Lord had been kindled among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Again the mixed multitude which was among them had a longing desire, and even the children of Israel sat down and wept, saying, Who will give us flesh to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>We recollect the fish which we ate in Egypt for nothing; and the cucumbers, and the melons, and the leeks, and the onions, and the cloves of garlick;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but now our soul is dried up, and our eyes behold nothing but this manna.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now the manna was like a grain of coriander, and its colour was the colour of chrystal,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the people went out, and gathered it and ground it in mills, or beat it in mortars, and boiled it in pots, or made it up into cakes to be baked on the hearth; and in sweetness its taste was that of a sweet cake, made with oil;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and when the dew fell on the camp the manna came down with it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When Moses heard them weeping in their communities, every one at his tent door, though the Lord was greatly provoked to wrath, and in the view of Moses it was evil,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>yet Moses said to the Lord, Why hast thou afflicted thy servant; and why have I not found favour in thy sight, that thou shouldst lay upon me the weight of this people?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Have I conceived all this people? Or have I brought them forth, that thou sayest to me, Take them in thy bosom, and carry them, as a nurse would her sucking child, to the land which with an oath thou hast promised to their fathers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Whence can I have flesh to give to all this people? For they weep before me, saying, Give us flesh that we may eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I am not able alone to bear this people. It is a burden too heavy for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If thou deal thus with me, kill me outright, if I have found favour in thy sight, that I may not see my wretchedness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Whereupon the Lord said to Moses, Assemble before me seventy men of the elders of Israel, whom thou knowest to be elders of the people, and their scribes; and bring them to the tabernacle of the testimony, and let them stand there with thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and I will come down and talk with thee there, and I will take a portion of the spirit which is upon thee, and put it upon them; and they will help thee to bear the burden of this people, so that thou shalt not bear them thyself alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And thou shalt say to this people, Sanctify yourselves against to-morrow, and you shall eat flesh. Because you have wept before the Lord, saying, Who can give us flesh to eat? It is better for us to be in Egypt; therefore the Lord will give you flesh to eat, and you shall eat flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>You shall eat it, not one day, nor two days, nor five days, nor ten nor twenty days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>You shall eat it a whole month, until it come out at your nostrils, and become loathsome to you, because you have distrusted the Lord who is amongst you, and have wept in his presence, and said, Why did we come out of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thereupon Moses said, The people among whom I am, are six hundred thousand footmen, yet thou hast said, I will give them flesh to eat, and they shall eat it a whole month.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Must the flocks and the herds be slaughtered for them? Will even these suffice? Or should all the fish of the sea be collected for them, would this be sufficient for them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the Lord said to Moses, Cannot the hand of the Lord furnish a sufficiency? Thou shalt now see whether my word shall come to pass to thee or not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then Moses went out, and told the people the words of the Lord. And when he had assembled seventy men from among the elders of the people, and placed them around the tabernacle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>the Lord descended in a cloud, and spoke to him, and took a portion of the spirit which was upon him, and put it on the seventy elders. And soon as the spirit rested on them, they prophesied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now there were two who had not joined them, but were left in the camp. The name of the one was Eldad and the name of the other, Modad; and the spirit rested on them. They were of those who were written down, but they had not come to the tabernacle. And when they prophesied in the camp,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>there ran a young man, who told Moses, saying, Eldad and Modad are prophesying in the camp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Upon which Joshua the son of Nave, who was the chosen attendant of Moses, addressing him said, My lord Moses, forbid them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>But Moses said to him, Thou shouldst not envy, on my account. that the people of the Lord had all been made prophets when the Lord put his spirit on these!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then Moses went into the camp, accompanied with the elders of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and there went forth a wind from the Lord, and brought a flock of quails from the sea, and drove them upon the camp, a day's journey on this side, and a day's journey on that side, all around the camp about two cubits from the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Whereupon the people arose, and all that day, and all that night, and all the next day, they gathered the flocks of quails, and he who gathered the fewest collected ten cores.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Though they had heated for themselves kilns all around the camp, the flesh was already between their teeth before it was quite dead. Whereupon the wrath of the Lord was kindled against the people, and the Lord smote the people with a very great plague,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>so that the name of that place was called Monuments of longing desire; because they had there buried the people who had expressed such a longing desire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>From the Monuments of longing desire, the people removed to Aseroth;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and while they were at Aseroth, Mariam and Aaron spoke against Moses, because of the Ethiopian woman whom Moses had taken;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>because he had taken to wife an Ethiopian woman, therefore they said, Hath the Lord spoken to Moses only? Hath he not spoken to us also?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>(Now the man Moses was very meek, above all the men on the earth,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the Lord heard, the Lord immediately said to Moses, and Aaron, and Mariam. Come forth you three to the tabernacle of the testimony. And when they three came out to the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the Lord descended in a pillar of cloud, and stood at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, and Aaron and Mariam were called. And when they both came out</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>he said to them, Hear my words. If there be a prophet among you to the Lord, I will make myself known to him by a vision, and speak to him in sleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Not so with respect to my servant Moses. In all my house he is faithful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Mouth to mouth, I will speak to him personally, and not in dark sentences. He hath actually seen the glory of God. Why then were ye not afraid to speak against my servant Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the wrath of the Lord was upon them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and the cloud withdrew from the tabernacle, and behold Mariam was leprous like snow. When Aaron looked on Mariam, and behold she was leprous,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>he said to Moses, O my lord, impute not sin to us, because we have acted ignorantly; because we have sinned,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let her not be as dead, as an abortive, for it devoureth the half of her flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Whereupon Moses cryed to the Lord, saying, God, I beseech thee, heal her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the Lord said to Moses, If her father had spit in her face, would she not be ashamed seven days? Let her be set apart seven days, without the camp, and after that let her come in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So Mariam was set apart without the camp, seven days, and the people did not remove till Mariam was cleansed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And after this the people removed from Aseroth, and encamped in the wilderness of Pharan.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Send men, and let them examine for thee the land of the Chananites, which I am about to give to the children of Israel for a possession. Thou shalt send a man for every tribe; according to the communities of their patriarchal families, thou shalt send them, every one a leader among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So Moses sent them from the wilderness of Pharan, by the command of the Lord. All the men were principal officers of the children of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and these were their names; Of the tribe of Reuben, Samuel, son of Zachur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>of the tribe of Symeon, Saphat, son of Suri;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Of the tribe of Judas, Chaleb, son of Jephonne;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>of the tribe of Issachar, Ilaal, son of Joseph;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>of the tribe of Ephraim, Ause, son of Nave;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>of the tribe of Benjamin, Phalti, son of Raphu;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>of the tribe of Zabulon, Gudiel, son of Sudi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>of the tribe of Joseph; of the Manassites, Gaddi, son of Susi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>of the tribe of Dan, Amiel, son of Gamali;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>of the tribe of Aser, Sathur, son of Michael;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>of the tribe of Nephthaleim, Nabi, son of Sabi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>of the tribe of Gad, Gudiel, son of Makchi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>These were the names of the men whom Moses sent to examine the land: (now Moses had surnamed Ause, son of Nave, Joshua.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And upon sending them to view the land of Chanaan, Moses said to them, Having gone up through this wilderness, you shall go up to the mountain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and view the land, of what sort it is; and the people who are settled in it, whether they be strong or weak; whether few or many;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and what sort of a country it is in which they are settled, whether it is good or bad; and what sort of cities they inhabit, whether they dwell in cities with walls, or without walls;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and what the quality of the soil is, whether rich or poor; and whether there are trees there, or not. And having made a strict examination, you will bring with you some of the fruits of the land: (for their days, it being then the spring season, would reach to the time of the first ripe grapes.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So they went up, and viewed the country from the wilderness of Sin, as far as Roob on the way to Aimath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then they went up, on a course parallel with the front of the desart; then turned down to Chebron, where were the Achimans and the Sessians, and the Thelamins, descendants of Enach. Now Chebron was built seven years before Tanis in Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And having come to the valley of grapes, and viewed it, they cut there a branch with a cluster of grapes on it, and carried it on poles, with some pomegranates and figs:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and they called the name of that place, Valley of Grapes; because of the bunch of grapes which the children of Israel cut there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And having viewed the land, they set out thence on their return, after forty days,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and journeying on came to Moses and Aaron, and to all the congregation of the Israelites in the wilderness of Pharan Kades, and made report to them and to all the congregation, and shewed them the fruit of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And they gave him a minute detail and said, We went to the country to which thou didst send us, a land flowing with milk and honey, and this is the fruit of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But nevertheless because the nation which inhabiteth it is bold and the cities strong, defended with walls, and very large, and we have seen there the race of Enach;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and the Amalekites dwell in the land to the south, and the Chettites, and the Evites, and the Jebusites, and the Amorites, inhabit the hilly country; and the Chananites dwell on the sea shore, and along the river Jordan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>(Here Chaleb stilled the people before Moses, and said, We have only to go up, and we shall possess it, for we are stronger than they.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But the men who went up with him said) We will not go up; for we are not able to go up against that nation; for it is much more powerful than we are.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And they gave an astonishing account of the land which they had viewed, to the children of Israel, saying, The land through which we passed to view it, is a land which devoureth them who dwell therein; and all the people which we saw are men of immense stature.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>There indeed we saw the giants, and we were before them like grasshoppers; indeed we were nothing else before them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Upon this, all the congregation, raising their voices, shouted aloud, and</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the people wept that whole night. And all the Israelites murmured against Moses and Aaron; and the whole congregation said to them, that we had died in the land of Egypt, or even in this wilderness!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>If we must die, why doth the Lord lead us into that land to fall in battle? Our wives and our children will be for a prey. Now therefore it is better for us to return to Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then they said to one another, Let us appoint a leader, and return to Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon this Moses and Aaron fell on their faces before all the congregation of the children of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Joshua the son of Nave, and Chaleb the son of Jephonne, two of them who had viewed the land, rent their clothes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and spoke to all the congregation of the Israelites, saying, The land which we viewed is indeed a most excellent land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>If the Lord delighteth in us, he will lead us to that land, and give it to us. It is a land flowing with milk and honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Only rebel not against the Lord, and you need not be afraid of the people of the land, for they are food for us. For their time is over, and the Lord is with us. Fear them not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when all the congregation ordered to stone them with stones, the glory of the Lord appeared in the cloud, over the tabernacle of the testimony, to all the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the Lord said to Moses, How long shall this people provoke me? And how long will they disbelieve me, notwithstanding all the miracles which I have done among them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let me smite them with pestilence and destroy them, and I will make thee and the house of thy father a great nation and much more numerous than this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thereupon Moses said to the Lord, Though Egypt may publish that thou by thy mighty power didst bring this people out from among them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Nay though all the inhabitants of this land have heard that thou the Lord art among this people; that they with their eyes may behold thee, Lord, exposed to view; and that thy cloud hath stood over them, and that thou marchest before them in a pillar of cloud by day, and in a pillar of fire by night;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>yet when thou shalt destroy this people as one man, then will all the nations who have heard of thy name speak, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Because the Lord was not able to bring this people into the land which, with an oath, he promised them, he hath destroyed them in the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now therefore let thy power, Lord, be exalted. As thou hast spoken, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The Lord is long suffering, abundant in mercy and true, taking away iniquities, transgressions and sins; and, when he will not by purification clear the guilty, retributing the sins of fathers on children to the third and fourth generation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>forgive the sin of this people according to thy great mercy, as thou hast been gracious to them from Egypt even to this time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Moses, I am merciful to them according to thy word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But as I live, and my name liveth, and the glory of the Lord shall fill the whole earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>because all these men, who have seen my glory, and the wonders which I have done in Egypt, and in this wilderness, have actually tempted me now the tenth time, and have not hearkened to my voice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>they indeed shall not see the land which I, with an oath, promised their fathers. But with regard to their children who are here with me; as many as have not known good or evil; every one who is too young to be taught by experience, to them I will give the land. As for all them who have provoked me, they shall not see it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But with regard to my servant Chaleb, because there was a different spirit in him, and he followed me, him I will bring into the land to which he went, and his seed shall inherit it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now the Amalekites and the Chananites dwell in that valley, turn therefore to-morrow, and remove into the wilderness by the way to the Red sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>How long shall I bear with this wicked congregation? I have heard what they murmur before me; the murmuring of the Israelites which they have uttered concerning you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Say to them, As I live, saith the Lord, As you have spoken in my hearing, so will I actually do to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>In this wilderness your carcasses shall fall; the whole review of you; even all of you who have been reviewed, from twenty years old, and upwards, who have murmured against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>None of you shall come into that land, respecting which I stretched forth my hand to cause you to dwell therein, save only Chaleb son of Jephonne, and Joshua son of Nave.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But as for your children, which you said would be for a prey, them I will bring into the land, and they shall inherit that land which you have rejected.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Your carcasses shall fall in this wilderness, and in this wilderness</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>your children shall be fed forty years. They shall bear your whoredom until your carcasses are consumed in the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>According to the number of days in which you explored the land, counting each of the forty days a year, you shall bear your sins forty years, and shall know the vengeance of my wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>I the Lord have spoken. In this manner I will assuredly deal with this wicked congregation, which hath risen up against me. In this wilderness they shall be consumed, and there they shall die,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>with those men whom Moses sent to view the land, and who, on their return, murmured against it before the congregation, to raise an evil report concerning it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Now the men who spoke ill against the land were struck dead before the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and Joshua son of Nave and Chaleb son of Jephonne alone survived of all the men who had gone to view the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>When Moses rehearsed these words to all the children of Israel, the people mourned exceedingly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and rising early the next morning they went up to the top of the mountain, saying, Behold, here we are, we will go up to the place which the Lord hath said, for we have sinned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Though Moses said, Why do you transgress the command of the Lord? Things will not prosper with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Do not go up, for the Lord is not with you. You will therefore fall before the face of your enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Because the Amalekites and the Chananites are there before you, you will therefore fall by the sword. Because you have turned back, and disobeyed the Lord, therefore the Lord will not be among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Notwithstanding this, they obstinately went up to the top of the mountain; but the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and Moses, did not depart out of the camp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And the Amalekites and the Chananites, who were in ambush on the mountain, came down, and drove them back, and smote them even to Ermon. So they returned to the camp.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, When you are come into the land of your habitation, which I give you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and thou wilt offer whole burnt offerings to the Lord, whether it be an offering of homage, or a sacrifice to magnify a vow, or a free will offering; or at your festivals, to make a smell of fragrance to the Lord; if they be from the herds or the flocks,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>he who bringeth his gift to the Lord must also bring for a sacrifice of flour, the tenth of an ephah of fine flour, made up with the fourth of an hin of oil;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and for a libation you shall pour the fourth of an hin of wine upon the whole burnt offering, or upon the sacrifice; for every lamb you shall do this, as an offering of homage, a smell of fragrance for the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But for a ram, when you offer one, for a whole burnt offering, or for a sacrifice, thou shalt offer two tenths of fine flour, made up with the third of an hin of oil, for a sacrifice:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and for a libation you shall offer a third of an hin of wine, for a smell of fragrance to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And if you make your offering from the herds, for a whole burnt offering, or for a sacrifice to magnify a vow, or for an offering of thanksgiving to the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>he who offereth must bring, with the young bull, three tenths of fine flour mixed up with the half of an hin of oil, for a sacrifice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and the half of an hin of wine for a libation, as an offering of homage, a smell of fragrance for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thus thou shalt do for every young bull, or for every ram, or for every lamb, or kid of the goats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>According to the number which you offer, thus you shall do for every one, according to their number.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Every one born in the land shall prepare these things in this manner, when he maketh offerings of homage for a smell of fragrance for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And if there be a proselyte among you in your land, or whoever there may be among your generations, who will make an offering of homage, a smell of fragrance for the Lord, in the same manner as you do, so shall he do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The congregation is the Lord's. There shall be one law for you, and for the proselytes among you is a perpetual law for your generations. As you are, so shall the proselyte be before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>There shall be one law, and one rule of rectitude for you and for the proselyte settled among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Again the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, When you come to the land to which I am conducting you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>this must be done. When you are about to eat of the bread of the land, you shall set apart a separate portion as a dedication to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>As the first fruits of your dough you shalt set apart a loaf for this separate portion. As a dedication from the threshing floor, so shall you set this apart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>as the first portion of your dough, and you shall give it to the Lord as a dedication throughout your generations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And when you shall be guilty of a failure, and shall not have performed all these commands which the Lord hath delivered to Moses:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>even all that the Lord hath enjoined on you by the ministry of Moses, from the day the Lord gave them in charge to you, and thenceforward throughout your generations,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>then shall this be done. If, escaping the notice of the congregation, it hath been done inadvertently, the whole congregation shall offer a young bull from the herd, without blemish, for a whole burnt offering, for a smell of fragrance for the Lord, with its sacrifice, and its libation, according to the rule prescribed, and one kid of the goats for a sin offering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the priest shall make atonement for the whole congregation of the children of Israel, and it shall be forgiven them. Because it was done through inadvertency, and they have brought their gift, an offering of homage to the Lord for their sin before the Lord, for their involuntary acts;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>therefore forgiveness shall be extended to the whole congregation of the children of Israel, even to the stranger settled among you; because it was an act of ignorance in the whole people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And if any individual sin ignorantly, he shall bring a she-goat of the first year for a sin offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and the priest shall make an atonement for the person who hath been guilty through ignorance, and hath sinned inadvertently before the Lord. In making atonement for him who shall act inadvertently,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>there shall be the same law for the stranger among the children of Israel, and for the proselyte who hath joined them and sinned inadvertently, as for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But if any person, whether a native or a proselyte, shall presumptuously transgress, he provoketh God; that person shall be cut off from among his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Because he hath despised the statute of the Lord, and hath broken his commandments, that person shall be blotted out: his sin shall be upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>When the children of Israel were in the wilderness, they found a man gathering wood on the sabbath day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And they who found him gathering wood on the sabbath day, brought him before Moses and Aaron, and the whole congregation of the children of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and they committed him to custody, for it had not been determined what should be done to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Whereupon the Lord spoke to Moses, saying, Let the man be put to death. Let all the congregation stone him with stones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>So all the congregation led him out of the camp, and the whole congregation stoned him with stones without the camp, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Again the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them. Let them make for themselves tufts on the corners of their mantles, throughout all their generations; and on the tufts at the corners you shall put a blue ribbon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and have it on the tufts, that when you see them you may remember all the commands of the Lord, and do them, and not turn aside after your imaginations, and your own eyes, by following of which you have gone a whoring;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>that you may remember, and do all my commands, and be dedicated to your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>I am the Lord your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God. I the Lord am your God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Kore son of Issaar, son of Kaath, son of Levi, spoke, backed by Dathan and Abiron, the son of Eliab, and by Aun, son of Phaleth, son of Reuben,;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>when they rose up against Moses, with two hundred and fifty men of the sons of Israel, leaders of the congregation, eminent for counsel and men of renown;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>when they rose in a body against Moses and Aaron, and said, Be it known to you that the whole congregation are holy, and the Lord is among them. Why then do you set yourselves against the congregation of the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Moses, upon hearing this, fell on his face,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and spoke to Kore, and to all his company, saying, God hath seen and known who are his, and who are holy, and hath brought them near to himself. Even those whom he chose he hath brought near to himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Do this. Take for yourselves censers, thou Kore, and all you his company;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and put fire therein, and lay incense thereon before the Lord to-morrow. And let the man whom the Lord hath chosen be the holy man. Let this suffice you, ye sons of Levi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Moreover, Moses said to Kore, Hearken to me, ye sons of Levi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Is this a small thing to you, that the God of Israel hath separated you from among the congregation of Israel, and brought you near to himself, to perform the holy services of the tabernacle of the Lord, and to attend before the tabernacle to perform them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He hath indeed brought thee near, and all thy brethren the children of Levi with thee. And do you seek in this manner to officiate also as priests;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thou and all this thy company who are tumultuously assembled before God? As for Aaron, who is he that you murmur against him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Moses sent for Dathan and Abiron, the sons of Eliab; but they said we will not go up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Is it a small matter that thou hast been bringing us up to a land flowing with milk and honey, to kill us in this wilderness, that thou tyrannisest over us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou art a chief! And thou hast brought us to a land flowing with milk and honey! and hast given us a portion of land, and vineyards! Fain wouldst thou put out the eyes of these men! We will not go up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Upon this Moses was greatly incensed, and said to the Lord, Respect not their sacrifice. I have not taken from any of them an object of desire, nor have I injured any of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then Moses said to Kore, Hallow thy company and be ready before the Lord, thou and Aaron and they, to morrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And take every one his censer, and put incense thereon, and present before the Lord, every one, his censer, two hundred and fifty censers; thou also and Aaron, each his censer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when every one had taken his censer, and put fire therein, and laid incense on it, and Moses and Aaron stood at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and Kore had collected against them all his company, at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony, the glory of the Lord appeared to the whole congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Separate yourselves from among this congregation, and I will consume them all at once.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>At this they fell on their faces and said, God, the God of the spirits even of all flesh! If one man hath sinned, is the wrath of the Lord against the whole congregation?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Speak to the congregation, and say, Withdraw all around from the congregation of Kore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Accordingly Moses, arose, and went to Dathan and Abiron; and all the elders of Israel accompanied him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And he spoke to the congregation, saying, Separate yourselves from the tents of these wicked men, and touch not any of the things which belong to them, lest you be consumed with them in their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when they had drawn back, all around, from the tent of Kore, Dathan and Abiron came out, and stood at the doors of their tents, with their wives and their children, and their attendants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And Moses said, By this you shall know that the Lord hath sent me to do all these works, and that they are not of myself;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>If these men die the common death of all men; or if their visitation be according to the visitation of all men, the Lord hath not sent me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>but if the Lord demonstrate by a miracle, and the earth opening its mouth, shall swallow up them and their households, and their tents, and all that belong to them; and they go down alive to the mansion of the dead; then you will know that these men have provoked the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when he had made an end of speaking all these words, the earth was rent under them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and the earth opened; and it swallowed up them, and their households, and all the men who were with Kore, and all their cattle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And they, and all that belonged to them, went down alive to the mansions of the dead, and the earth covered them. And they were destroyed from among the congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And all the Israelites who were around them fled at their cry; for they said, Perhaps the earth may swallow us up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And there went forth a fire from the Lord, and consumed the two hundred and fifty men, who were offering incense!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and to Eleazar the priest, the son of Aaron, Gather up the brasen censers from among them who were burned; but as for the strange fire, scatter it there</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Because they have hallowed the censers of these sinful men with their lives, therefore make them up into thin plates, as a cover for the altar. Because they were presented before the Lord, therefore they are hallowed, and made a sign for the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>So Eleazar, the son of Aaron the priest, took the brasen censers which they who were burned up had presented; and of them made a cover for the altar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>a memorial to the children of Israel, that none of another family, who is not of the seed of Aaron, should come near to present incense before the Lord, lest he be like Kore, and his confederacy, as the Lord spoke to him by the ministry of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>On the next day, when the people murmured against Moses and Aaron, saying, You have slain the people of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>when, in their insurrection against Moses and Aaron, the congregation were rushing upon the tabernacle of the testimony, the cloud covered it, and the glory of the Lord appeared:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And Moses went in, with Aaron, in front of the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Withdraw from among this congregation, and I will destroy them all at once.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Whereupon they fell on their face. And Moses said to Aaron, Take the censer, and put therein fire from the altar, and throw incense on it, and carry it with all haste to the camp, and make atonement for them; for wrath is gone forth from the presence of the Lord, and hath begun to slay the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>So Aaron took as Moses commanded him, and ran into the congregation; (Now the destruction among the people had already begun) and he threw on the incense, and made atonement for the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>and stood between the dead and the living; and the plague ceased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Now they who died by the plague were fourteen thousand seven hundred, besides those who died on the account of Kore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>When Aaron returned to Moses to the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, and the plague had ceased,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and take of them a staff; a staff for every house of patriarchal families; from all the chiefs of the respective houses of patriarchal families twelve staves; and write every one's name on his staff;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and on the staff of Levi write Aaron's name; for he is one staff. The chief of the house of the head family in every tribe shall give;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and thou shalt lay them in the tabernacle of the testimony, over against the testimony. By these I will there make myself known to thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and it shall come to pass, that the staff of the man whom I will chuse, shall bloom: and I will remove from me this murmuring of the children of Israel, which they murmur against you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So Moses spoke to the children of Israel, and all the chiefs gave him, every one a staff; for every chief a staff, according to the houses of their patriarchal families, twelve staves, with Aaron's staff among theirs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And Moses laid the staves before the Lord in the tabernacle of the testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And on the next day when Moses went in, with Aaron, into the tabernacle of the testimony, behold Aaron's staff, for the house of Levi, had bloomed, and brought forth a bud, and had shot forth blossoms, and produced almonds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And Moses brought out all the staves from the presence of the Lord, before all the children of Israel. And when they saw and had taken, every one his staff,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the Lord said to Moses, Lay up Aaron's staff again before the testimonies, to be kept as a sign for the children of these rebellious men; and let their murmuring cease from me that they may not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So Moses and Aaron did as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when they had done so, the sons of Israel spoke to Moses, saying, Behold, we have been wasted, we have been destroyed, we have been cut off suddenly;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>every one who toucheth the tabernacle of the Lord dieth. Must we all die?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>whereupon the Lord spoke to Aaron, saying, Thou, and thy sons, and the house of thy father, shall bear the sins of the holy things; and thou, and thy sons, shall bear the sins of your priesthood;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>take therefore to thyself thy brethren, the tribe of Levi, the community of thy father, and let them be joined to thee, and perform holy service for thee. While thou, and thy sons with thee, are before the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>they shall keep guard for thee, and guard the tabernacle of the testimony: but let them not approach to the holy utensils, nor to the altar, lest they die, and you with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They shall be joined with thee, and shall keep guard over the tabernacle of the testimony, according to all the holy services of the tabernacle, and none of another family shall come to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And you shall keep the charge of the holy things, and of the altar, so that there shall not be wrath among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I have indeed taken your brethren, the Levites, from among the children of Israel, as a gift presented to the Lord to perform the services of the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore thou, and thy sons with thee, shall keep your priesthood, as far as the altar is concerned, and what is within the veil; and you shall perform these services as a privilege of your priesthood; and any one of another family who approacheth shall be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Moreover the Lord said to Aaron, Behold I have given you the charge of the separated portions taken from all the dedications made to me by the children of Israel. To thee I have given them for a reward; and to thy sons after thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let this therefore be your perpetual due from the hallowed dedications of the homage offerings; from all their gifts, and from all their sacrifices, and from all their trespass offerings, and from all their sin offerings. Whatever they give me, a portion of the hallowed things shall be for thee and thy sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In the holy place of the holies you shall eat them. Every male, namely, thou and thy sons shall eat them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>They shall be hallowed to thee. You shall have also a portion from the dedications which the Israelites make by setting apart, and from all the dedications made by being laid on hands; These I have given to thee, and thy sons, and thy daughters with thee, as an everlasting due. Every one in thy house, who is clean, may eat these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Every dedication of oil, and every dedication of wine, every dedication of food of all kinds which they give to the Lord, these I have given to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>All the first fruits in their land, which they bring for the Lord, shall belong to thee. Every one in thy house, who is clean, may eat these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Every thing which is devoted by the children of Israel shall belong to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And every firstling of all flesh, which they bring for the Lord, whether of man or beast, shall belong to thee: but the first born of man shall be redeemed, and thou shalt cause them to redeem the firstlings of all cattle which are not clean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now the redemption of the former, at a month old, shall be the set price of five shekels after the holy shekel, which is twenty oboli:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but the firstlings of kine, and the firstlings of sheep, and the firstlings of goats, thou shalt not suffer them to redeem. They are hallowed; therefore thou shalt pour out their blood before the altar, and offer their suet as an offering of homage, for a smell of fragrance for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the flesh shall be for thee. Like the dedicated breast, and like the right shoulder, it shall be thine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Every dedication of holy things, which the children of Israel set apart for the Lord, I have given to thee, and thy sons, and thy daughters, as an everlasting due. It is a covenant of salt for ever, before the Lord, with thee and thy seed after thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Moreover the Lord said to Aaron, Thou shalt have no inheritance in their land, nor shalt thou have a portion among them; for I am thy portion, and thy inheritance, among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And behold I have given the Levites all the tenth in Israel, as a portion for their services. Inasmuch as they are to perform service at the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the children of Israel are no more to come to the tabernacle of the testimony, to bear a sin which incurreth death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>but the Levites themselves are to perform the service of the tabernacle, and to bear their sins, this shall be a perpetual due for their generations, and they shall have no inheritance among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Because I have given the Levites for their portion the tithes of the children of Israel, which they set apart for the Lord, as a dedication, therefore I have said to them, they shall have no lot of inheritance among the Israelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Thou shalt speak to the Levites and say to them; When you take from the children of Israel the tenth which I have given you from them for a lot of inheritance, you shall set apart from it, as a dedication for the Lord, a tenth of the tenth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and these dedications of yours shall be reckoned to you as corn from the threshing floor, and as a dedication from the press.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thus you shall acquit yourselves of all the dedications of the Lord; of all your tenths which you receive from the children of Israel. And you shall give the dedication set apart from it for the Lord to Aaron the priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>From all your gifts you shall set apart a dedication for the Lord, and from all the first fruits, the hallowed part of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Moreover thou shalt say unto them, When you set apart the first fruits of it, then it shall be reckoned to the Levites as produce from the threshing floor, and as produce from the press.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And you may eat it every where, you and your households. Because it is your wages for your services which you perform at the tabernacle of the testimony;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>therefore you shall not bear sin by reason of it, because you have set apart the first fruits of it. But you must not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, lest you die.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>This is the purification of the law in respect to all the things which the Lord hath enjoined, saying, Speak to the children of Israel, and let them bring thee a red heifer, without blemish, which hath no spot in her, and on which there hath never been put a yoke.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And thou shalt give her to Eleazar the priest; and they shall lead her out of the camp, to a clean place, and kill her in his presence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Eleazar shall take some of the blood thereof, and shall sprinkle, over against the front of the tabernacle of the testimony, some of the blood thereof seven times.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then they shall burn her in his sight; and when her skin, and her flesh, and her blood, and dung, are burned,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>the priest shall take cedar wood, and hyssop, and scarlet yarn, and throw them into the midst of the cinders of the heifer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then the priest shall wash his clothes, and wash his whole body with water, and, after that, he shall come into</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the camp. And the priest shall be unclean until the evening. And he who burned her shall wash his clothes, and wash his body with water, and be unclean until evening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And a man who is clean shall gather up the ashes of the heifer, and lay them without the camp, in a clean place, and water of sprinkling shall be kept in store for the congregation of Israel. It is a purification.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And he who gathereth up the ashes of the heifer, shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. And it shall be for the children of Israel, and for the proselytes who have joined them, an everlasting ordinance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>that whoever toucheth the dead body of a man shall be unclean seven days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>He shall be purified on the third, and on the seventh day, then he shall be clean: but if he be not purified on the third, and on the seventh day, he shall not be clean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If any person, who hath touched the dead, die, without being purified, he hath defiled the tabernacle of the Lord; that soul shall be blotted out from among Israel. Because the water of sprinkling bath not been sprinkled on him, he is unclean. His impurity is still in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>This also is the law, that if any man die in a house, every one who goeth into the house, and all the things in the house, shall be unclean seven days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And every open vessel which hath not a cover fastened on it, is unclean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And every one who, in the open field, toucheth one slain, or dead, or a human bone, or a grave, shall be unclean seven days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now, for one who is unclean, they shall take some of the burnt ashes of the purification, and pour spring water thereon, in a vessel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and a man who is clean shall take hyssop, and dip it in the water, and sprinkle it on the house, and on the vessels, and on the persons who may be in the house, and on him who hath touched a human bone, or a man who hath been slain, or one dead, or a grave.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The clean person shall sprinkle it on the unclean, on the third day, and on the seventh day. And on the seventh day he shall purify himself^ and shall wash his clothes, and wash himself with water, and be unclean until evening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And whoever shall be defiled, and not purified, that soul shall be cut off from the congregation, because he hath defiled the holy things of the Lord. Because the water of sprinkling hath not been sprinkled on him, he is unclean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And it shall be an everlasting statute for you, that he who sprinkleth the water of sprinkling, shall wash his clothes; and he who toucheth the water of sprinkling shall be unclean until evening:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and whatever the unclean person toucheth shall be unclean; and the person who toucheth it shall be unclean until evening.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When the children of Israel, the whole congregation, came to the wilderness of Sin, in the first month, the people took up their abode at Kades; and there Mariam died, and there she was buried.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And there being no water for the congregation, they assembled tumultuously against Moses and Aaron;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the people reviled Moses, and said, that we had died in the destruction of our brethren before the Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Why have you brought the congregation of the Lord into this wilderness, to kill us and our cattle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Why is this? Have you brought us out of Egypt, that we might come to this vile place; a place where no seed can be sown, where there are no fig trees, nor vines, nor pomegranates, nor even water to drink?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon Moses and Aaron went from the presence of the congregation, to the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, and fell on their faces. And the glory of the Lord appeared to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Take thy staff, and assemble the congregation, thou, and Aaron thy brother; and speak to that rock before them, and it will give its water. And you shall bring water for them from that rock, and give drink to the congregation, and their cattle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So Moses took the staff which was before the Lord, as the Lord commanded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Moses and Aaron assembled the congregation, at some distance over against the rock, and he said to them, Hear me, ye rebels! Can we bring water for you out of this rock?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then Moses lifted up his hand, and smote the rock twice with the staff, and there gushed out much water, so that the congregation, and their cattle, drank.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Moses and Aaron, Because you have not believed, to sanctify me before the children of Israel, therefore you shall not lead this congregation into the land which I have given them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>This is the water of Strife, because the children of Israel uttered reproaches before the Lord, and he was hallowed among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then Moses sent messengers from Kades, to the king of Edom, saying, Thus saith thy brother Israel, Thou knowest all the trouble that hath befallen us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Our fathers went down in to Egypt, and we have sojourned in Egypt many years. And when the Egyptians ill treated us and our fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>we cried to the Lord, and the Lord hearkened to our voice; and having sent a messenger he hath brought us out of Egypt, and we are now at Kades, a city on the extremity of thy borders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Let us pass through thy land. We will not march through the fields, nor vineyards, nor drink water out of thy cisterns. We will march along the king's high way, and will not turn aside to the right, nor to the left, until we have passed thy borders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But Edom said to him, Thou shalt not pass through me. If thou attempt it, I will come out to meet thee in battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Whereupon the children of Israel said, Let us pass through along the mountains, and if I, or my cattle drink of thy water, I will make thee compensation. Grant but this. It is but a small matter. Let us march through along the mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But he said, Thou shalt not pass through me. And Edom came out to meet him with a great multitude, and a strong hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>As Edom would not grant Israel a passage through his borders, therefore they turned aside from him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and having removed from Kades, the Israelites; the whole congregation came to mount Hor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses and Aaron at mount Hor, on the borders of the land of Edom, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Let Aaron be gathered to his people. For you shall not enter the land which I have given the children of Israel for a possession, because you provoked me at the water of strife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Take Aaron thy brother, and Eleazar his son, and make them go up to mount Hor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>in the view of the whole congregation, and strip Aaron of his robes, and put them on Eleazar his son: and let Aaron be composed, and die there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So Moses did as the Lord commanded him; And having taken them up to mount Hor, in the view of the whole congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>he stripped Aaron of his garments, and put them on Eleazar his son. And Aaron died on the top of the mount. And Moses and Eleazar came down from the mount.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when all the congregation saw that Aaron was dead, the whole house of Israel mourned for Aaron thirty days.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When the Chananite, the king of Arad, who dwelt in front of the wilderness, heard that Israel was coming by the way of Atharim, he made war on Israel, and took some of them prisoners;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>whereupon Israel vowed a vow to the Lord, and said, If thou wilt deliver this people into my hand, I will devote them and their cities to destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the Lord hearkened to the voice of Israel, and delivered up these Chananites into their hands, and they anathematised them and their cities, and called the name of that place Anathema.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now when they had removed from mount Hor, by the way to the Red sea, and were marching round the land of Edom, the people became dispirited in the march,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and spoke against God, and against Moses, saying, Why hast thou brought us out of Egypt to kill us in this wilderness; for we have neither bread, nor water, and our soul loatheth this light food.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon the Lord sent the most deadly serpents among the people, and they bit the people. And when many of the children of Israel died,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>the people came to Moses and said, We have sinned, because we have spoken against the Lord, and against thee; pray therefore to the Lord? and let him take away the serpents from us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So Moses prayed to the Lord for the people, and the Lord said to Moses, Make thee a serpent, and put it on a standard; and it shall come to pass that when a serpent biteth a man, every one who is bitten shall live by looking at that.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So Moses made a serpent of brass, and put it on a standard, and it came to pass that when a serpent bit a man, he looked up to that serpent, and lived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the Israelites removed, and encamped at Oboth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and having removed from Oboth, they encamped at Achelgai, on the borders of the desart, which is in front of Moab, towards the rising of the sun.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And removing from that place, they encamped in the vale of Zared,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>from which they removed, and encamped on the banks of Arnon, in the wilderness, on the borders of the Amorites; for Arnon is the boundary of Moab, between Moab and the Amorites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For this cause it is said in a book, The war of the Lord burned Zoob and the vales of Arnon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And made the vales the habitation of Er; And he adjoineth the borders of Moab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thence they came to Well; this is the well concerning which the Lord said to Moses, Gather the people together, and I will give them water to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then sung Israel this song to the well, Begin to him the alternate song of the well.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Chiefs digged it: the kings of nations hewed it out, In their reign when they ruled over them. And from Well they moved on to Manthanaiem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and from Manthanaiem to Naaliel; and from Naaliel to Bamoth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and from Bamoth to Nepe, which is in that plain of Moab bordering on the craggy cliff, namely, that which looketh towards the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now Moses had sent messengers to Seon, king of the Amorites, with a message of peace, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Let us pass through thy land. We will march by the highway; we will not turn aside into the fields, nor into the vineyards; nor will we drink water out of thy; wells. Let us march along the king's highway. until we pass thy borders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But Seon would not grant Israel a passage through his territories. He indeed assembled all his people, and went out to the wilderness, to attack Israel, and came to Jessa, and drew up in array against Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Whereupon Israel smote him with the slaughter of the sword, and took possession of his land, from Arnon to Jabok, even to the Ammanites; for Jazer is the boundary of the Ammanites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So Israel took all those cities; and Israel dwelt in all the cities of the Amorites, in Hesebon, and in all those under the same dominion with it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>for Hesebon was the city of Seon the king of the Amorites. He indeed had made war on a former king of Moab, and had taken all his land from Aroer to Arnon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for this cause the poets say, Come to Hesebon that it may be rebuilded, And that the city of Seon may be inhabited.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For a fire went forth from Hesebon; And a flame from the city of Seon; Which devoured even to Moab; Which devoured the pillars of Arnon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Alas! for thee Moab! Thou wast undone, people of Chamos! Their sons were delivered up to save their lives; And their daughters were captives to Seon, king of the Amorites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And their seed was destroyed from Hesebon even to Daibon. And against Moab their wives rekindled a fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when Israel had taken possession of all the cities of the Amorites:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Moses sent to view Jazer, and they took it, and all the villages thereof, and drove out the Amorites who were there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then they turned and went up by the way of Basan. And when Og king of Basan came out to meet them, he and all his people, for battle at Adraim</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>the Lord said to Moses, Be not afraid of him; for into thy hands I will deliver him, and all his people, and all his land; And thou shalt do to him, as thou hast done to Seon, the king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Hesebon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>So he smote him, and his sons,, and all his people, until there was not one left to be taken alive. And they took possession of their land.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When the Israelites had removed, and pitched their tents on the west of Moab, along the Jordan, over against Jericho;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and Balak, son of Sepphor, had seen all that Israel had done to the Amorites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>though Moab was exceedingly afraid of the people because they were numerous, yet Moab was incensed at the sight of the Israelites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and said to the Senate of Madiam, Now will this congregation lick up all around us, as the ox licketh up the grass of the field. Now Balak, son of Sepphor, was at that time king of Moab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>he therefore had sent messengers to Balaam, son of Beor, at Pathoura, which is by the river of the land of the children of his people, to invite him to come to him, saying, Behold there is a people come out of Egypt; and lo! they have covered the face of this land, and are settled down near me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now therefore come, curse for me this people; for they are stronger than I. Perhaps I may be able to smite some of them, and drive them out of this land: for I know that they whom thou blessest are blessed, and they whom thou cursest are cursed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So the ambassadors of Moab, and the ambassadors of Madiam, went with the rewards of divination in their hands, and when they came to Balaam, and rehearsed to him the words of Balak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>he said to them, Tarry here this night, and I will give you an answer according to what the Lord shall say to me. So the chiefs of Moab tarried with Balaam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And God came to Balaam, and said to him, What would these men with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Balaam said to God, Balak son of Sepphor, king of Moab, hath sent them to me, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Behold there is a people come out of Egypt, who have covered the face of this land, and they are settled down near me; now therefore come and curse them for me; perhaps I may be able to smite them, and drive them out of this land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thereupon God said to Balaam, Thou shalt not go with them, nor curse that people, for they are blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So when Balaam arose in the morning, he said to the chiefs of Balak, Return speedily to your Lord, for God doth not permit me to go with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the chiefs of Moab arose, and went to Balak, and said to him, Balaam refuseth to come with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Balak sent again other princes, more in number, and of greater dignity than them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and they went to Balaam and said to him, Thus saith Balak, the son of Sepphor, I entreat thee delay not to come to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>for I will promote thee to great honour, and do for thee whatever thou sayest; therefore come, curse this people for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>In reply to which Balaam said to the princes of Balak, If Balak would give me his house full of silver and gold, I cannot transgress the word of the Lord God, to do any thing, small or great, of my own mere will.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now therefore tarry you also here this night, that I may know what the Lord will further say to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And God came to Balaam by night, and said to him, If these men come to call thee, arise and go with them: but what I say to thee, that thou shalt do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whereupon Balaam arose in the morning, and saddled his ass, and went with the princes of Moab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And God was angry, because he went of himself to him; and the angel of God arose to stop him on the way. Now he was mounted on his ass, and had two servants with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when the ass saw the angel of God standing opposite, in the way, with a drawn sword in his hand, the ass turned aside out of the way into the field; at which he struck the ass with his staff, to turn her into the road.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then the angel of God took a station between the rows of the vines, there being a hedge on this side, and a hedge on that.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And when the ass saw the angel of God, she threw herself against the wall, and bruised Balaam's foot against the wall. Where upon he struck her again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then the angel of God again retired, and stood in a narrow place, where there was no turning, to the right, or to the left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when the ass saw the angel of God, she lay down under Balaam; at which Balaam was in flamed with wrath, and gave the ass a severe blow with the staff.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thereupon God opened the mouth of the ass, and she said to Balaam, What have I done to thee that thou hast corrected me this third time?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Balaam said to the ass, because thou hast mocked me, and had I a sword in my hand I should now have run it through thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the ass said to Balaam, Am I not the ass on which thou hast ridden from thy youth even to this day? Did I ever through stubbornness, do such a thing as this to thee. And he said, No.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then God opened the eyes of Balaam; and when he saw the angel of the Lord standing opposite, in the way, with a drawn sword in his hand, he bowed down, and fell flat on his face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the angel of God said to him, Why didst thou strike thy ass three times? Behold I came out to stop thee, because thy journey is not seemly in my sight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and the ass, seeing me, turned aside from me these three times. And had she not turned aside from me I should now have killed thee; but I would have preserved her alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then Balaam said to the angel of the Lord, I have sinned inadvertently; for I did not know that thou stoodest in the way against me. Now therefore, if it is not agreeable to thee, I will turn back.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the angel of God said to Balaam, Go with these men; but whatever word I speak to thee be careful to deliver that. So Balaam went with the princes of Balak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And when Balak heard that Balaam was coming, he went out to meet him, to a city of Moab, which is on Arnon, which is a part of the boundary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Balak said to Balaam, Did I not send for thee? Why then didst thou not come to me? Am not I able to promote thee to honour?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And Balaam said to Balak, Behold now I am come to thee, shall I be able to say any thing? Whatever word God shall put in my mouth; that I will speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>So Balaam went with Balak, and when they came to the cities of Sheepcots,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Balak sacrificed sheep, and young bulls, and sent them to Balaam, and the princes with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And early next morning Balak took Balaam, and led him up to the top of the pillar of Baal, and from it shewed him some part of the people.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Whereupon Balaam said to Balak, Build for me here seven altars, and prepare for me here seven young bulls, and seven rams.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when Balak had done as Balaam had ordered him; and had offered a bull, and a ram, on each altar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>then Balaam said to Balak, Stand by thy sacrifice, and I will advance on. If God appear to me by any occurrence, whatever he shall shew me I will tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So Balak stood by his sacrifice. And Balaam went to inquire of God: and as he was going straight forward, God appeared to Balaam: And Balaam said to him, I have prepared seven altars, and offered a young bull, and a ram, on each altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And God put a word in the mouth of Balaam, and said, Return to Balak, and thus thou shalt say.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So he returned to Balak. Now he was standing by his whole burnt offerings, and all the princes of Moab with him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And a spirit of God came upon Balaam, and he took up his parable, and said, I am called from Mesopotamia by Balak; By the king of Moab from the mountains of the east, Come, saith he, Curse Jacob for me, And, come, for me devote Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>How can I curse him, whom the Lord doth not curse? Or how devote him whom God devoteth not?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For from the top of mountains I can see him; Even from hills I can observe him, Behold he shall dwell, as a people by themselves, And shall not be reckoned among the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Who hath accurately scanned the seed of Jacob? Who can count the communities of Israel? May my soul depart among the souls of the righteous! And my offspring be as the seed of these!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>At this Balak said to Balaam, What hast thou done to me? I sent for thee to curse my enemies, and behold thou hast pronounced a blessing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Balaam said to Balak, Must I not be careful to speak what God hath put in my mouth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Balak said to him, Come with me to yet another place, from which thou shalt not have a full view of them. Thou shalt see only a part of them, and not view them all; and curse them for me from that place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So he took him to a watch tower of the field on the top of a craggy cliff, and built there seven altars. And when he had offered a bull, and a ram, on each altar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Balaam said to Balak, Stand by thy sacrifice, and I will advance on, to inquire of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And God met Balaam and put a word in his mouth, and said, Return to Balak, and thus thou shalt speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So he returned to him. Now he was standing by his whole burnt offering, and all the princes of Moab with him. And Balak said to him, What hath the Lord spoken?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whereupon he took up his parable, and said, Stand up Balak and hear; Listen attentively as a witness, thou son of Sepphor!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>God is not like a man to be deceived; Nor like a son of man to be threatened. When he hath spoken, will he not perform? When he shall speak, will he not stand to it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Behold I am constrained to bless! Bless I will. Indeed I cannot avoid it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>There shall be no calamity in Jacob; Nor shall misery be seen in Israel. The Lord their God is with them; The glories of princes are among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The God who hath brought them out of Egypt, Is to them like the glory of a unicorn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For there is no augury used by Jacob; Nor divination among Israel. In due season it shall be told to Jacob, And to Israel, what God will execute.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Behold the people will rouse like a young lion; And, like an old lion, exult with pride. They will not go to rest till they devour prey; Until they have drunk the blood of the slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Upon this Balak said to Balaam, Thou shalt neither with curses, curse them for me; nor shalt thou with blessings bless them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>In reply to which Balaam said to Balak, Did I not tell thee saying, Whatever God shall speak, that I must do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then Balak said to Balaam, Come let me take thee to another place, that, if it please God, thou mayst curse them for me from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>So Balak took Balaam to the top of Phogor, which extendeth into the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Balaam said to Balak, Build me here seven altars, and prepare for me here seven young bulls, and seven rams.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And when Balak had done as Balaam ordered him, and had offered a bull, and a ram, on every altar,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Balaam, seeing that it was good in the sight of the Lord to bless Israel, did not go, as was customary with him, to look for omens; but turned his face towards the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when Balaam raised his eyes, and saw Israel encamped by tribes, a spirit of God came upon him, and he took up his parable, and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Balaam son of Beor saith; The man who seeth according to truth saith:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>It is the saying of him, who hath heard the oracles of the Almighty; Who in sleep hath seen a vision of God; whose eyes were opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>How beautiful are thy houses, Jacob! Thy tents, Israel!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Like shady forests, and like gardens by a river! And like tents which the Lord hath pitched! And like cedars by streams of water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>There shall come forth a man from his seed, And he shall rule over many nations: And a kingdom greater than Gog's shall be raised up; And his kingdom shall be enlarged</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>God hath led him out of Egypt; His glory is like that of the unicorn; He will eat up the nations of his enemies; And he will exhaust their fatness, And pierce his enemy with his darts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Couching down, he is gone to rest, like a lion; Yes like a young lion; who dare rouse him? Blessed are they who bless thee, And they who curse thee are already cursed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>At this Balak was inflamed with wrath against Balaam, and clapped his hands. And Balak said to Balaam, I sent for thee to curse my enemy, and behold thou hast blessed them a third time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now therefore flee to thy own place. I thought to promote thee to honour. But the Lord hath now deprived thee of that glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whereupon Balaam said to Balak, Did I not tell thy messengers whom thou sentest to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If Balak would give me his house full of silver and gold, I cannot transgress the word of the Lord, to do either good or evil, of my own mere will. Whatever God may order that I will speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And now, behold, I am quickly to return to my own place: come, let me inform thee what this people will do to thy people, in the latter days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then taking up his parable, he said, Balaam son of Beor saith; It is the saying of a man who is a true seer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Who heareth the oracles of God, And hath knowledge from the Most High; Who in sleep hath seen a vision of God, and whose eyes were opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I can point to him, though he is not now; I hail him happy tho? he is not near. A star will arise out of Jacob; There shall rise up a man out of Israel, And he will smite the princes of Moab, And plunder all the sons of Seth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And Edom shall be an inheritance, And Esau, his enemy, shall be a heritage. Though Israel hath done valiantly;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Yet one shall be raised up out of Jacob, Who will destroy him who escaped from a city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then having taken a view of Amalek he took up his parable and said, Amalek is the head of nations; But their seed shall be destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then having taken a view of the Kenite, he took up his parable and said, Strong is thy dwelling place. But though thou hast built thy nest upon a rock;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And though Beor hath crafty chickens; The Assyrians will captivate thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then looking at Og he took up his parable and said, Oh! Who can live when God will order such things!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For bands of Kitians will issue forth, And afflict Assur, and afflict Hebrews: And they themselves shall likewise be destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then Balaam arose, and went away, with a view to return to his own place, and Balak repaired home.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>While Israel abode at Sattin, the people profaned themselves to commit whoredom with the daughters of Moab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>who invited them to the sacrifices of their idols; and the people ate of their sacrifices, and worshipped their idols,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and Israel consecrated himself to Belphegor. Whereupon the wrath of the Lord was kindled against Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and the Lord said to Moses, Take all those leaders of the people and make a public example of them, for the Lord, in the face of the sun; so shall the wrath of the Lord be turned away from Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Moses said to the tribes of Israel, Kill ye, every one, him of his family, who hath consecrated himself to Belphegor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And behold there came a man of the children of Israel, who conducted his brother to a Madianitish woman in the sight of Moses, and before all the congregation of the sons of Israel, while they were weeping at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Upon seeing this, Phineas, son of Eleazar, son of Aaron the priest, started up from among the congregation, and taking a javelin in his hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>went after the man; the Israelite, into the bed chamber, and ran them both through, the man, the Israelite, quite through, and the woman into her belly. Whereupon the plague stopped from the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now they who had died of the plague were twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Phineas, son of Eleazar, son of Aaron the priest, hath stayed my wrath from Israel, by shewing a zeal for me among them, so that in my jealousy I have not utterly consumed the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore say, Behold I give him the covenant of peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>It shall be to him, and to his seed after him, an everlasting covenant of the priests' office, because he shewed a zeal for his God, and made atonement for the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now the name of the man; the Israelite, who was slain with the Madianitish woman, was Zambri, son of Salmon, the chief of the patriarchal house of the Symeonites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and the name of the Madianitish woman, who was slain, was Chasbi, a daughter of Sour, the chief of the clan of Ommath, which is the head family of Madiam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and say, Treat as enemies the Madianites, and smite them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for they are acting as enemies against you, with craftiness, in all their attempts to beguile you by means of Phogor, and by means of Chasbi, the daughter of a prince of Madiam, their sister, who was slain on the day of the plague, on account of Phogor.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And, after the plague, the Lord spoke to Moses, and Eleazar the priest, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Take the sum of the whole congregation of Israel, from twenty years old and upwards, according to the houses of their families, every one who goeth out to war in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Upon which, orders were issued by Moses, and Eleazar the priest, at Araboth-Moab, on the Jordan over against Jericho, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>From twenty years old and upwards, as the Lord commanded Moses. Now these were the sons of Israel who came out of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Reuben, Israel's first born. and the sons of Reuben, Enoch, and the community of the Enochites; to Phallus belonged the community of the Phalluites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>to Asron, the community of the Asronites; to Charmi, the community of the Charmites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>These are the communities of Reuben, and the muster of them was forty three thousand seven hundred and thirty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now of the Phalluites, Eliab was chief,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and the sons of Eliab were Namuel; and Dathan, and Abiron. These were the head families of the congregation. These were they who conspired against Moses and Aaron, in the company of Kore in the insurrection against the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the earth, opening its mouth, swallowed them up with Kore, at the time when his company died; when the fire consumed the two hundred and fifty, and they were made a sign;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>but the children of Kore died not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the children of Symeon were, the community of the Symeonites; from Namuel, the community of the Namuelites; from Jamin, the community of the Jaminites; from Jachin, the community of the Jachinites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>from Zara, the community of the Zaraites; from Saul, the community of the Saulites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>These communities of Symeon, from the muster of them, were twenty two thousand two hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The children of Gad, by their communities, were; from Saphon, the community of the Saphonites; from Aggi, the community of the Aggites; from Suni, the community of the Sunites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>from Azeni, the community of the Azenites; from Addi, the community of the Addites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>from Aroadi, the community of the Aroadites; from Ariel, the community of the Arielites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>these communities of the children of Gad, from the review of them, were forty thousand five hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the sons of Judas were Er and Aunan, but Er and Aunan died in the land of Chanaan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>so that these were the children of Judas, according to their communities; from Selom, the community of the Selomites; from Phares, the community of the Pharesites; from Zara, the community of the Zaraites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the Pharesites were; from Asron, the community of the Asronites; from Jamun, the community of the Jamunites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>These communities of Judas, according to the review of them, were seventy six thousand five hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the children of Issachar were, according to their communities; from Thola, the community of the Tholaites; from Phua, the community of the Phuaites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>from Jasub, the community of the Jasubites; from Samram, the community of the Samramites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>These communities of Issachar, from the review of them, were sixty four thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The children of Zabulon were, according to their communities; from Sared, the community of the Saredites; from Allon, the community of the Allonites; from Allel, the community of the Allelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>These communities of Zabulon, from the review of them, were sixty thousand five hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The children of Joseph by their communities were; Manasses and Ephraim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The children of Manasses were from Machir, the community of the Machirites. Galaad also being a son of Machir, from Galaad, the community of the Galaadites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And these also were Galaadites, from Achiezer, the community of the Achiezerites; from Cheleg, the community of the Chelegites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>from Esriel, the community of the Esrielites; from Sychem, the community of the Sychemites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>from Symaer, the community of the Symaerites; and from Opher, the community of the Opherites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Now Salpaad the son of Opher had no sons; but he had daughters, and these were the names of Salpaad's daughters, Maala and Nua, and Egla, and Melcha, and Thersa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>These communities of Manasses were, from the review of them, fifty two thousand seven hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And these were the children of Ephraim, from Suthala, the community of the Suthalites; from Tanach, the community of the Tanachites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>these also were Suthalites; from Eden, the community of the Edenites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>these communities of Ephraim were from the review of them, thirty two thousand five hundred. These were the communities of Joseph, by their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>The children of Benjamin, according to their communities were; of Bale, the community of the Balites; of Asuber, the community of the Asuberites; of Jachiran, the community of the Jachiranites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>of Sophan, the community of the Sophanites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>now Adar and Noeman being sons of Bale; of Adar, was the community of the Adarites; and of Noeman, the community of the Noemanites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>These Benjaminites, according to their communities were, from the review of them, forty five thousand five hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And the children of Dan, according to their communities, were of Same, the community of the Sameites. These were the communities of Dan, according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>All the communities of the Sameites were, according to the review of them, sixty four thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>The children of Aser, by their communities, were; from Jamin, the community of the Jaminites; from Jesu, the community of the Jesuites; from Baria, the community of the Bariaites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>from Chober, the community of the Choberites; from Melchiel, the community of the Melchielites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>now the name of Aser's daughter was Sara:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>these communities of Aser were from the review of them, fifty three thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>The children of Nephthaleim, by their communities, were; of Asiel, the community of the Asielites; of Gauni, the community of the Gaunites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>of Jeser, the community of the Jeserites; of Sellem, the community of the Sellemites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>These communities of Nephthaleim were from the review of them, forty five thousand four hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>This muster of the Israelites was six hundred and one thousand and seven hundred and thirty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Among these let the land be divided, that they may inherit it, by the number of names.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>To those who are many, thou shalt enlarge the inheritance; and to them who are few, thou shalt give the less inheritance. To every one, as they have been reviewed, their inheritance shall be given.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Among these names the land shall be parcelled out, by lot. They shall inherit according to the tribes of their patriarchal families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>By lot thou shalt parcel out their inheritance, to the many and the few.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>Now these were the children of Levi, according to their communities; of Gerson, the community of the Gersonites; of Kaath, the community of the Kaathites; of Merari, the community of the Merarites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>These are also communities of the children of Levi; the community of the Lobenites, the community of the Chebronites, the community of the Korites, the community of the Musites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>And Kaath begot Ambram, whose wife's name was Jochabed, a daughter of Levi and she bore these for Levi in Egypt; She bore by Ambram, Aaron, and Moses, and Mariam their sister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>And to Aaron were born Nadab and Abiud, and Eleazar and Ithamar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>But Nadab and Abiud died when they presented strange fire before the Lord, in the wilderness of Sina.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>From the review of them, they were twenty three thousand, including every male, from a month old and upwards; for they were not reviewed among the children of Israel; because there was no portion given them among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>Now this was the review of Moses and Eleazar the priest, who reviewed the Israelites at Arabeth-Moab, on the Jordan, over against Jericho;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>and among them there was not a man of those who had been reviewed by Moses and Aaron, when they reviewed the Israelites in the wilderness of Sina.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>Because the Lord said to them, they shall assuredly die in the wilderness; therefore there was not one of them left, save Chaleb son of Jephonne, and Joshua son of Nave.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then came the daughters of Salpaad, son of Opher, son of Galaad, son of Machir, of the community of Manasses, one of the sons of Joseph (now these were their names; Maala, and Nua, and Egla, and Melcha, and Thersa)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and standing before Moses, and before Eleazar the priest, and before the chiefs, and before the whole congregation, at the door of the tabernacle of the testimony, they said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Our father died in the wilderness, but he was not among the congregation which conspired against the Lord, in the assembly of Kore. Because he died for his own sin, and had no sons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>let not the name of our father be blotted out from among his community. Seeing he hath not a son, give us a possession among our father's brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Whereupon Moses laid their case before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The daughters of Salpaad have spoken right. Thou shalt give them the possession of an inheritance among their father's brothers, and vest in them their father's lot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And thou shalt say to the children of Israel, If any man die, and hath no son, you shall vest his inheritance in his daughter;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and if he hath no daughter, you shall give his inheritance to his brother; and if he hath no brothers, you shall</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>give his inheritance to his father's brother;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and if there be no brothers of his father, you shall give the inheritance to one of his house, who is the nearest of kin to him, of his tribe, that he may inherit what belonged to him. And this shall be to the children of Israel a rule of decision, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Moses, Go up that mountain which is on the bank of the Jordan; that mount Nabo, and take a view of the land of Chanaan, which I give to the children of Israel, by a possessory right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when thou hast seen it, thou shalt be gathered to thy people, as Aaron thy brother was gathered on mount Hor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>because you transgressed my command in the wilderness of Sin. When the people resisted the hallowing of me, you did not hallow me at the water before them. (This alludeth to the water of strife at Kades in the wilderness.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Upon this Moses said to the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let the Lord, the God of the spirits, and of all flesh, look out a man to be set over this congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>who shall go out before them, and come in before them; and who shall lead them out, and bring them in; so that the congregation of the Lord may not be like a flock which hath no shepherd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying, Take as thy associate Joshua, son of Nave, a man who hath a spirit in him, and thou shalt lay thy hands on him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and set him before Eleazar, the priest, and give him a charge before the whole congregation, and give a charge before them concerning</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>him. And thou shalt put some of thy glory on him, that the</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>children of Israel may hearken to him. And he shall stand before Eleazar, the priest, and they shall ask him the determination of the manifestations before the Lord. And at his command they shall go out; and at his command he, and all the children of Israel with him, even all the congregation, shall come in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So Moses did as the Lord commanded him; and having taken Joshua, he set him before Eleazar the priest, and before all the congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and laid his hands on him, and made him his associate, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Give a charge to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, You shall observe to bring me my gifts, my oblations, my homage offerings for a smell of fragrance at my festivals.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Moreover thou shalt say to them, These are the homage offerings which you shall present to the Lord; two lambs, of the first year, with out blemish, every day, for a continual whole burnt offering;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>the one lamb thou shalt offer in the morning, and the other in the evening;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and for a sacrifice of flour, thou shalt offer the tenth of an ephah of fine flour, mixed up with the quarter of an hin of oil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>It is the continual whole burnt offering, which was instituted at mount Sina, for a smell of fragrance for the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and for the libation thereof, thou shalt offer, with the first lamb, a quarter of an hin of wine. In the holy place thou shalt pour out as a libation the choicest wine to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And towards evening thou shalt offer the other lamb, with the like sacrifice, and the like libation; for a smell of fragrance for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And on the day of the sabbaths, you shall bring two lambs of the first year, without blemish, and two tenths of fine flour mixed up with oil, for a sacrifice, together with a libation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>as the sabbath whole burnt offering, for every sabbath, over and above the continual whole burnt offering with its libation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And at the new moons you shall offer a whole burnt offering to the Lord, two young bulls from the herd, one ram, seven lambs, of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>three tenths of fine flour, mixed up with oil, for each bull, and two tenths of fine flour, mixed up with oil, for the ram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and a tenth of fine flour, mixed up with oil, for every lamb, as a sacrifice for a smell of fragrance; an homage offering for the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and their libation shall be, the half of an hin of wine for each bull; and the third of an hin for the ram; and the fourth of an hin for every lamb. This shall be the whole burnt offering, month after month, for all the months of the year;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Also a kid of the goats, for a sin offering. This, with its libation, shall be offered to the Lord, over and above the continual whole burnt offering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And in the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, shall be the passover to the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and on the fifteenth day of the month shall commence the festival thereof. Seven days you shall eat unleavened bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now, this first day shall be solemnly set apart for you. You shall not do any kind of sacrificial service;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but you shall bring for whole burnt offerings; for an offering of homage to the Lord, two young bulls from the herd, one ram, seven lambs of the first year. You must see that they are without blemish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And their sacrifice shall be fine flour, mixed up with oil, three tenths for each bull, and two tenths for the ram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and thou shalt prepare a tenth for every one of the seven lambs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, to make atonement for you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>over and above the whole burnt offering which is to be made every morning, and which is a continual whole burnt offering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>After this manner you shall make daily offerings, during the seven days, as a gift; an offering of homage, for a smell of fragrance, to the Lord: Over and above the continual whole burnt offering, thou shalt offer it with its libation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the seventh of these days shall be solemnly set apart for you. On it you shall do no sacrificial work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And on the day of new things when you bring for the Lord the new sacrifice of the weeks, there shall be a solemn festival for you. You shall not do any kind of sacrificial service;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>but you shall bring, as whole burnt offerings, for a smell of fragrance to the Lord, two young bulls from the herd, one ram, seven lambs, of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>with their sacrifice of fine flour mixed up with oil; three tenths for each bull, and two tenths for the ram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and one tenth for every of the seven lambs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and one kid of the goats, for a sin offering, to make atonement for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Over and above the continual whole burnt offering, you shall offer me the sacrifice of these (and see that they be without blemish) together with the libations thereof.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And in the seventh month on the first day of the month, there shall be a solemn festival for you. You shall do no sacrificial work. It shall be to you a day of alarm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And you shall offer as whole burnt offerings; for a smell of fragrance to the Lord, one young bull from the herd; one ram, seven lambs, of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>with their sacrifice; fine flour mixed up with oil; three tenths for the bull, and two tenths for the ram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and a tenth for every one of the seven lambs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and a kid of the goats, for a sin offering, to make atonement for you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>over and above the whole burnt offerings of the new moon, with their sacrifices and their libations, and the continual whole burnt offering. And their sacrifices, and their libations, shall be according to what is prescribed for them, for a smell of fragrance to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the tenth of this month shall be a solemn day set apart for you, on which you shall afflict your souls, and do no kind of work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But you shall offer, as whole burnt offerings for a smell of fragrance for the Lord; as offerings of homage to the Lord, one young bull from the herd, one ram, seven lambs of the first year (you shall see that they be without blemish)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>with their sacrifice; fine flour mixed up with oil; three tenths for the bull, and two tenths for the ram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and a tenth for every one of the seven lambs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and a kid of the goats, for a sin offering, to make atonement for you, over and above the sin offering of the atonement, and the continual whole burnt offering. And the sacrifice of this, and the libation of this, shall be according to what is prescribed, for a smell of fragrance; an offering of homage to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And on the fifteenth day of this seventh month, there shall be a solemn festival set apart for you. You shall do no sacrificial work. And you shall celebrate this festival to the Lord seven days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And you shall bring, for whole burnt offerings; for an offering of homage; for a smell of fragrance to the Lord, on the first day, thirteen young bulls from the herd, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year, (they shall be without blemish)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>with their sacrifices; fine flour mixed up with oil; three tenths for every one of the thirteen bulls, and two tenths for each of the two rams,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and one tenth for every one of the fourteen lambs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And on the second day, twelve young bulls, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>with their sacrifice and their libation, for the bulls and the rams, and the lambs, according to their number agreeably to what is prescribed for them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings, with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And on the third day, eleven young bulls, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>with their sacrifices and their libations, for the bulls, and the rams, and the lambs, according to their number, agreeably to what is prescribed for them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings, with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And on the fourth day, ten young bulls, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>with their sacrifices and their libations, for the bulls and the rams, and the lambs, according to the number of them agreeably to what is prescribed for them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings, with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And on the fifth day, nine young bulls, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>with their sacrifices and their libations; for the bulls and the rams, and the lambs, according to the number of them agreeably to what is prescribed for them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings, with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And on the sixth day, eight young bulls, two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>with their sacrifices and their libations; for the bulls, and the rams, and the lambs, according to the number of them agreeably to what is prescribed for them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings, with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And on the seventh day, seven young bulls; two rams, fourteen lambs of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>with their sacrifices and their libations; for the bulls and the rams, and the lambs, according to the number of them agreeably to what is prescribed for them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings, with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And on the eighth day, you shall close the festival. On that day you shall not do any kind of sacrificial work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But you shall bring for whole burnt offerings; for a smell of fragrance; for offerings of homage to the Lord, one young bull, one ram, seven lambs of the first year, without blemish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>with their sacrifices and their libations, for the bull, and the ram, and the lambs, according to the number of them, agreeably to what is prescribed for them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and a kid of the goats for a sin offering, over and above the continual whole burnt offerings, with their sacrifices and their libations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>These you shall offer to the Lord at your festivals, over and above your vows, and your free will offerings, and your whole burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, and your libations, and your offerings of thanksgiving.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>So Moses spoke to the children of Israel according to all that the Lord commanded him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Moreover Moses spoke to the chiefs of the tribes of the children of Israel, saying, This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>If any man vow a vow to the Lord, or swear an oath, or bind himself with a solemn promise concerning his soul, he shall not break his word. Whatever hath proceeded from his mouth he shall do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And if a woman vow to the Lord, or bind herself with a solemn promise, in her father's house, in her youth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and her father hear her vows, and her promises with which she hath bound her soul, and hold his peace at her; all her vows, and all the promises with which she bound her soul, shall stand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They shall be binding on her. But if her father expressly disapprove on the day he heareth her vows and the promises, with which she hath bound her soul, they shall not stand. And the Lord will acquit her because her father hath disallowed her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And if she be married, and vows be upon her; according to the opening of her lips; with what promises soever she may have bound her soul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>if her husband shall hear, and hold his peace at her on the day when he heareth, so shall all her vows stand, and the promises shall stand with which she hath bound her soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But if her husband expressly disallow her on the day when he shall hear, none of her vows, and none of the obligations with which she hath bound her soul, shall be binding, because her husband disallowed her. And the Lord will acquit her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But the vows of a widow, or of one divorced; whatever vows she may have made to bind her soul, shall stand against her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And if her vow, or the obligation with which she bound her soul with an oath, be made in her husband's house;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and her husband shall hear, and hold his peace at her, and not disallow her; all her vows and all her promises with which she hath bound her soul shall stand against her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But if her husband on the day when he heareth, actually disannul all that may have proceeded out of her lips, of what nature soever her vows may be, or the obligations with which she bound her soul, they shall not be binding on her. Her husband hath made them void, and the Lord will acquit her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Every vow, and every binding oath to afflict her soul, her husband may establish, or make void.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And if he hold his peace at her, day after day, he shall establish upon her all her vows, and confirm the obligations upon her, because he held his peace at her on the day he heard them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And if her husband disannul them after the day when he heard, he shall bear the sin of this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>These are the judgments which the Lord gave in charge to Moses, between a husband and wife, and between a father and a daughter in her youth, in her father's house.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Avenge the cause of the children of Israel on the Madianites, and afterward thou shalt be gathered to thy people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon Moses spoke to the people, saying, Arm men from among you and array them before the Lord, against Madian, to pour vengeance from the Lord on Madian;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>a thousand from every tribe. You shall send them out of all the tribes to be drawn up in array.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So out of the thousands of Israel they numbered a thousand from a tribe; twelve thousand. They were armed for close engagement.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And Moses sent these; a thousand from every tribe; and with the army composed of them, Phineas, son of Eleazar, son of Aaron the priest, with the holy instruments; the trumpets for sounding a charge, in their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And they drew up in array against Madian, as the Lord commanded Moses, and slew every male;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and in the slaughter they slew the kings of Madian, Evin, and Rokon, and Sur, and Ur, and Robok, the five kings of Madian. They slew also Balaam, son of Beor, with the sword among their slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And having taken for a prey the women of the Madianites, and their furniture, and their cattle, and all their goods, and spoiled their army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and burned all their cities in which they dwelt, and all their sheepcots, with fire,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and taken all the prey thereof, and all the spoils thereof, both of man and beast,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>they brought to Moses, and Eleazar, and to all the Israelites, the captives, and the spoils, and the prey, to the camp at Araboth-Moab, on the Jordan, over against Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when Moses went out, accompanied with Eleazar the priest, and all the chiefs of the congregation, to meet them without the camp,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Moses was angry at the officers of the army; at the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds, who came from the war.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Moses said to them, Why have you saved all the women alive?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For they, by the direction of Balaam, were the cause of Israel's apostatizing, and transgressing the commands of the Lord, for the sake of Phogor: and there was a plague in the congregation of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now therefore kill every male among the captives. Kill also every woman, who hath lain with man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But save alive, for yourselves, every captive among the women, who hath not known a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And abide without the camp seven days. Every one who hath slain, or who hath touched one slain, must be purified on the third day, and on the seventh day, including yourselves and your captives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And you must purify every covering, and every vessel made of skin, and every hair cloth, and every utensil of wood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Eleazar the priest, said to the men of the army, who came from the war, This is the ordinance of the law, which the Lord gave in charge to Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Besides the gold, and the silver, and the brass, and the iron, and the lead, and the tin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>every thing which can pass through fire must be purified by fire; but the rest are to be purified by the water of purification only. Whatever cannot pass through fire must pass through water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And on the seventh day you must wash your clothes, and you shall be clean; and after that you may come into the camp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Take the sum of the captivated prey both of man and beast; thou, and Eleazar the priest, and the chiefs of the patriarchal houses of the congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And you shall divide the prey between the warriors who went to battle, and the whole congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And you shall set apart as a tribute to the Lord, from the warriors who went out to battle, one in five hundred from the captives, and from the beasts, namely, the cattle, and the sheep, and the asses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>These you shall take from their half, and give to Eleazar the priest, as a portion set apart for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And from the children of Israel's half thou shalt take one in fifty of the captives, and of the cattle, and the sheep, and the asses; of all these beasts. And these thou shalt give to the Levites, who keep the watch at the tabernacle of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So Moses and Eleazar the priest did as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the whole amount of the booty which the warriors had taken, was, of sheep six hundred and seventy five thousand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>of cattle seventy two thousand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and sixty one thousand asses;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and of the human species, namely, of the women who had not known man, all the souls were thirty two thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>So that the half which was the share of those who went to war, was, from the number of sheep, three hundred and thirty seven thousand five hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>of which the tribute for the Lord was six hundred and seventy five;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and of cattle, thirty six thousand, of which the tribute for the Lord was seventy two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and of asses, thirty thousand five hundred, of which the tribute for the Lord was sixty one;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and the human beings were sixteen thousand, of whom the tribute for the Lord was thirty two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And this tribute for the Lord, this dedication made to God by setting it apart, Moses gave to Eleazar the priest as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And from the half belonging to the children of Israel, between whom and the warriors Moses had made the division;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>now the congregation's half was three hundred and thirty seven thousand five hundred sheep,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>thirty six thousand cattle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>thirty thousand five hundred asses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>and of human beings, sixteen thousand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>from this half, belonging to the children of Israel, Moses took one in fifty, of man and beast, and gave them to the Levites, who kept the watch at the tabernacle of the testimony, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Then all the officers over the thousands of the army, the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>came to Moses, and said to him, Thy servants have taken an account of all the warriors who were with us, and there is not one of them missing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>We have therefore brought, as every man chanced to find a jewel of gold, either a necklace, or a bracelet, or a ring, or an ornament for the right arm, or a chain, to make atonement for us before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>So Moses and Eleazar the priest, received from them the gold; all the wrought jewels;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>and the whole amount of the gold, the dedication which they set apart for the Lord, was, sixteen thousand seven hundred and fifty shekels. This they received from the captains of thousands, and captains of hundreds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Of the spoil, which the warriors made every man for himself,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Moses and Eleazar the priest received the gold from the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds, and brought it into the tabernacle of the testimony, to be a memorial of the children of Israel before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="32">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, had a great multitude of cattle, and having taken a view of the country of Jazer, and the region of Galaad, and seen that it was a place fit for stock,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the Reubenites and the Gadites came to Moses, and to Eleazar the priest, and to the chiefs of the congregation and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Ataroth, and Daibon, and Jazer, and Namra, and Esebon, and Eleale, and Sebama, and Nabo, and Baian,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>the land which the Lord delivered up before the children of Israel, is a land fit for raising stock, and thy servants have cattle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>if therefore, said they, we have found favour in thy sight, let this land be given to thy servants for a possession, and cause us not to cross the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon Moses said to the Gadites and the Reubenites, Must your brethren go to war, and you sit still here?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Besides, why do you divert the thoughts of the Israelites from crossing over into the land which the Lord giveth them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Did not your fathers do so, when I sent them from Kades-Barne to view the land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When they had passed through the valley of grapes, and viewed the land, they discouraged the heart of the Israelites from going to the land which the Lord gave them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and the anger of the Lord was kindled that day, and he sware saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>These men who came up out of Egypt, from twenty years old and upwards, who know good and evil, shall not see the land, which I with an oath promised to Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob; (for they have not followed me)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>save Chaleb, son of Jephonne, who separated himself from them, and Joshua, son of Nave, because they followed the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, and he led them about in the wilderness forty years, until all that generation, who had done evil in the sight of the Lord, was consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Behold you are risen up in your fathers' stead, a set of sinful men, to augment the wrath of the Lord against Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For by turning away from him, to cause him to leave you still in the wilderness, you will transgress against the whole congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Upon this they came near to him, and said, We will build sheepcots here for our cattle, and cities for our families,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but we ourselves, completely armed, will march in the van before the children of Israel, until we bring them to their place. Our families indeed must dwell in walled cities, because of the inhabitants of the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>that we may not be under a necessity of returning to our houses, until the children of Israel are parcelled out, every one in his possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Moreover we will not take a share with them of the land beyond the river Jordan, because we have got our share on the eastern side of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then Moses said to them, If you will act agreeably to what you say; if you will arm yourselves for battle before the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and every one, completely armed, will cross the Jordan before the Lord, until his enemy be crushed before him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the land subdued before the Lord, after this you shall return, and be guiltless before the Lord, and acquitted by Israel, and this land shall be your possession before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But if you do not act in this manner, you will sin against the Lord, and you shall be sensible of your sin, when evils overtake you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Build therefore cities for your families, and sheepcots for your cattle, and perform what hath proceeded out of your mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the sons of Reuben and the sons of Gad spake to Moses, saying, Thy servants will do as our Lord commandeth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>our families, and our wives, and our cattle, shall remain in the cities of Galaad;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>but we thy servants will cross over, all armed, and arrayed for battle before the Lord, as our lord saith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Moses convened with them Eleazar the priest, and Joshua, son of Nave, and the chiefs of the patriarchal houses of the tribes of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and said to them, If the Reubenites and the Gadites cross the Jordan with you, every one armed for battle before the Lord, when you shall have subdued the land before you, you shall give them the land of Galaad for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But if they decline to cross with you, armed for battle before the Lord; you shall drive before you their families, and their wives, and their cattle, into the land of Chanaan, and they shall have a portion with you in the land of Chanaan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And the Reubenites and the Gadites answered, saying, All that our lord saith to his servants we will do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>We will cross over, completely armed before the Lord, into the land of Chanaan, and you shall give us our possession on this side of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So Moses gave them, namely, to the Gadites and the Reubenites, and to the half of the tribe of Manasses, one of the sons of Joseph, the kingdom of Seon, king of the Amorites, and the kingdom of Og king of Basan, the land and the cities, with the boundaries thereof, even the cities of the land round about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And the Gadites rebuilt Daibon, and Ataroth, and Aroer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and Sophar, and Jazer, and raised these, namely,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Namram and Baithara, fenced cities, and folds for sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And the Reubenites rebuilt Esebon, and Eleale, and Kariatham,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and Beelmeon, which they enclosed all around, and Sebama; and they named the cities which they rebuilt after their own names.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now a descendant of Machir, son of Manasses, had gone to Galaad, and taken it, and destroyed the Amorite who dwelt there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>So Moses gave Galaad to the community of Machir, son of Manasses, and they dwelt there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And Jair, of the tribe of Manasses, went and took their sheepcots, and called them the sheepcots of Jair.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And Nabau went and took Kaath, and its villages, and called them Naboth after his own name.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="33">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the encampments of the Israelites. When they came out of the land of Egypt, with their army, by the ministry of Moses and Aaron,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Moses committed to writing their removals and encampments, by the command of the Lord, and these are the encampments of their march.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They removed from Ramesses, in the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month. On the next morning after the passover, the Israelites came out with a high hand, in the sight of all the Egyptians,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>while they were burying their dead; all those whom the Lord had smitten; even all the first born of the land of Egypt. When the Lord had executed vengeance on their gods,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the children of Israel, removing from Ramesses, encamped at Sokchoth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And removing from Sokchoth, they encamped at Bouthan, which is a part of the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And they removed from Bouthan, and encamped at the mouth of Eirath, which is over against Beelsepphon. They encamped also over against Magdolus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And they removed from over against Eirath, and crossed through the midst of the sea, into the wilderness, and having marched three days' journey through the wilderness, they encamped at Bitterness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And they removed from Bitterness, and came to Ailam. Now at Ailam there were twelve fountains of water, and seventy palm trees. So they encamped there by the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And they removed from Ailam, and encamped by the Red sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And they removed from the Red sea, and encamped in the wilderness of Sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they removed from the wilderness of Sin, and encamped at Raphaka.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they removed from Raphaka, and encamped at Ailus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And they removed from Ailus and encamped at Raphadin, where there was no water for the people to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And they removed from Raphadin, and encamped in the wilderness of Sina.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And they removed from the wilderness of Sina, and encamped at The monuments of longing desire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And they removed from The monuments of longing desire, and encamped at Aseroth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And they removed from Aseroth, and encamped at Rathama.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And they removed from Rathama, and encamped at Remmon-Phares.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And they removed from Remmon-Phares, and encamped at Lebona.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they removed from Lebona, and encamped at Ressan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And they removed from Ressan, and encamped at Makellath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And they removed from Makellath, and encamped at Saphan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they removed from Saphan, and encamped at Charadath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And they removed from Charadath, and encamped at Makeloth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And they removed from Makeloth, and encamped at Kataath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And they removed from Kataath, and encamped at Tarath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And they removed from Tarath, and encamped at Mathekka.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And they removed from Mathekka, and encamped at Selmona.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And they removed from Selmona, and encamped at Masuruth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And they removed from Masuruth, and encamped at Banaia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And they removed from Banaia, and encamped at the mountain of Gadgad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And they removed from the mountain of Gadgad, and encamped at Etebatha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And they removed from Etebatha, and encamped at Ebrona.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And they removed from Ebrona, and encamped at Gasion-Gaber.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And they removed from Gasion-Gaber, and encamped in the wilderness of Sin. And they removed from the wilderness of Sin, and encamped in the wilderness of Pharan, this is Kades.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And they removed from Kades, and encamped at Or, the mountain bordering on the land of Edom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And Aaron the priest went up at the command of the Lord, and died there, in the fortieth year of the children of Israel's coming out of Egypt, in the fifth month, the first day of the month.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And Aaron was a hundred and twenty three years old when he died at mount Or.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And the Chananite king of Arad, whose fixed abode was in the land of Chanaan, received intelligence when the children of Israel were marching in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And they removed from mount Or, and encamped at Selmona.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And they removed from Selmona, and encamped at Phino.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And they removed from Phino, and encamped at Oboth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And they removed from Oboth, and encamped at Gai, on the borders of Moab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And they removed from Gai, and encamped at Daibon-gad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And they removed from Daibon-gad, and encamped at Gelmon-deblathaim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And they removed from Gelmon-deblathaim, and encamped on the mountains Abarim, over against Nabo.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And they removed from the mountains Abarim, and encamped on the west of Moab, by the Jordan, opposite to Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>And when they were encamped on the Jordan, from Aisimoth to Belsa, which is on the west of Moab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>the Lord spoke to Moses on the west of Moab by the Jordan, in front of Jericho, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, You are now going to cross the Jordan into the land of Chanaan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>You shall destroy all those who dwell in that land, from before you, and demolish their obelisks, and utterly destroy their molten images, and all their pillars you shall demolish. And when you have destroyed all the inhabitants of that land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>you shall dwell therein; for I have given you their land by lot,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>and you shall divide their land, by lot, among your tribes. To those who are more numerous you shall give a larger possession; and to those who are fewer in number you shall give a smaller possession. On whatever place any one's name falleth, there shall be his possession. According to the tribes of your families you shall possess it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>But if you do not destroy the inhabitants of the land from before you, it will come to pass, that those of them whom you shall leave, will be thorns in your eyes, and darts in your sides, and your mortal enemies in the land wherein you dwell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>And it will come to pass that I will deal with you as I determined to deal with them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="34">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Give a charge to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, You are about to enter the land of Chanaan. This you shall have for an inheritance, even the whole land of Chanaan, with its borders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And your southern border shall be, from the wilderness of Sin, until it joineth Edom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And your boundaries on the south shall be, from a part of the salt sea on the east, and that boundary shall encompass you on the south, to the ascent of Acrabin, and shall pass on to Ennak, and run along south of Kades-barne and come to the sheepcot of Arad, and pass along by Asemona:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and from Asemona the boundary shall wind round along the brook of Egypt, and its termination shall be the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then you shall have the sea for a boundary. The great sea shall bound you: this shall be your western boundary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And your boundary on the north shall be this; from the great sea you shall measure off for yourselves, along the range of mountains;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>from mountain to mountain you shall measure off for yourselves: beginning at the bay of Emath, and extending along the border of Saradak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the boundary shall come out along the borders of Dephrona and its termination shall be Arsenain. This shall be your northern boundary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then you shall measure off for yourselves the eastern boundary from Arsenain to Sepphamar; and from Sepphamar</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>the boundary shall run down to Bela, on the east of the fountains, then down along the borders of Bela, on the eastern side of the sea of Chenerith;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>then down the Jordan; and its termination shall be the salt sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>This shall be your land and these its boundaries round about. So Moses gave a charge to the Israelites saying, This is the land which you shall parcel out, by lot, in the manner the Lord hath commanded it to be given to the nine tribes, and to the half of the tribe of Manasses;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>because the tribe of the Reubenites, and the tribe of the Gadites, according to the houses of their families, and the half of the tribe of the Manassites, have received their allotments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>two tribes, and the half of a tribe, have received their lots on the south east side of the Jordan, in front of Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>These are the names of the men who shall parcel out the land for you; Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nave,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And you shall take one chief of a tribe to divide the land among you by lot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And these are the names of the men; Of the tribe of Judas, Chaleb son of Jephonne;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>of the tribe of Symeon, Salamiel son of Samiud;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>of the tribe of Benjamin, Eldad son of Chaslon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>of the tribe of Dan, chief Bakchir, son of Egli;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>of the children of Joseph; of the tribe of the Manassites, chief Aniel, son of Suphi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>of the tribe of the Ephraimites, chief Kamuel, son of Sabathan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>of the tribe of Zabulon, chief Elisaphan, son of Pharnach;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>of the tribe of Issachar, chief Phaltiel, son of Oza;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Of the tribe of Aser, chief Achior, son of Selemi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>of the tribe of Nephthaleim, chief Phadael, son of Jamiud.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>To these the Lord gave it in charge to parcel out to the Israelites their allotments in the land of Chanaan.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="35">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses, on the west of Moab, by the Jordan, over against Jericho, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Command the children of Israel; and let them give the Levites, out of the lots of their possession, cities to dwell in. They shall also give the Levites the suburbs of these cities round about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The cities shall be for them to dwell in; and the suburbs thereof shall be for their cattle, even for all their beasts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now the suburbs of the cities, which you shall give to the Levites, shall be from the wall of the city, outwards, two thousand cubits all around.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thou shalt therefore measure off, outwards from the city, on the east side two thousand cubits, on the south side two thousand cubits, on the west side two thousand cubits, and on the north side two thousand cubits, and in the middle of this shall be your city;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and you shall give these suburbs of the cities with the cities, to the Levites. Six of the cities which you shall give shall be cities of refuge for the manslayer to flee to, and besides these you shall give forty two cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>All the cities, which you shall give to the Levites, shall be forty eight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>These cities with their suburbs, even the cities which you shall give, shall be from the possessions of the children of Israel. They shall give the Levites, out of their cities, many from those who have many, and few from them who have few; from every one according to the inheritance which they possess.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel, and thou shalt say to them, You are about to cross the Jordan into the land of Chanaan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and you will set apart for yourselves cities, which shall be your places of refuge, to which the manslayer may flee. When any person killeth another unwittingly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>those cities will be places of refuge from the avenger of blood, that the manslayer may not die, until he stand before the congregation for trial.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Therefore, with regard to the cities which you shall give, six shall be your places of refuge;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>three of these cities you shall give on this side of the Jordan, and three such cities you shall give in the land of Chanaan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>They shall be a refuge for the children of Israel, and for the proselyte, and the sojourner among you. These cities are to be places of refuge, to which every one may flee who hath smitten a person unawares.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But if he hath smitten him with an instrument of iron, and he die, he is a murderer; let the murderer be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And if he hath smitten him with a stone out of his hand, by which he might be killed, and he die; he is a murderer; let the murderer be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And if he hath smitten him with any instrument of wood out of his hand, by which he might be killed, and he die; he is a murderer; let the murderer be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The avenger of blood himself shall kill him. When he meeteth him he shall slay him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And if, through hatred, he hath pushed him down, or thrown at him from ambush, any instrument whatever, and he die;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>or if on account of an old grudge he hath smitten him with his hand, and he die; let him who smote be put to death: he is a murderer; let the murderer be put to death. The avenger of blood shall slay the murderer when he meeteth him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But if on a sudden, not through malice aforethought, he hath pushed him down, or thrown any instrument at him, not from ambush,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>nor with any stone by which he might be killed, or not seeing him, and it light upon him, and he die, and he was not his enemy, nor seeking to do him any injury,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the congregation shall judge between him who smote, and the avenger of blood, according to these rules of decision;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and the congregation shall deliver the slayer from the avenger of blood, and the congregation shall send him back to the city of his refuge, to which he fled; and he shall dwell there, till the death of the high priest, whom they have anointed with holy oil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And if the manslayer go out of the bounds of the city of his refuge to which he fled,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and the avenger of blood find him out of the bounds of the city of his refuge, and the avenger of blood kill the slayer, he is not guilty of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For he should have remained in the city of refuge till the death of the high priest. After the death of the high priest the slayer may return to the land of his possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>These shall be your rules of decision, for your generations, in all your dwellings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>When any one hath slain a person, thou shalt put to death the murderer, by witnesses; but one witness shall not testify against a person to cause him to be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And you shall take no ransom for life from a manslayer who is guilty of death; for he must be put to death:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>nor shall you take any ransom from him who hath fled to a city of refuge, that he may dwell again in his land, until the death of the high priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So you will not pollute with blood the land in which you dwell; for this blood polluteth the land; and the land cannot be cleansed from the blood which is shed in it, but by the blood of him who shed it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>You must not defile the land in which you dwell; in which I dwell among you; for I the Lord dwell among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="36">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then came the chiefs of the community of the children of Galaad, son of Machir, son of Manasses, of the tribe of the children of Joseph, and spoke before Moses, and before Eleazar the priest, and before the chiefs of the patriarchal houses of the Israelites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and said, The Lord hath commanded our lord to give the land of inheritance by lot to the children of Israel; and the Lord hath commanded our lord to give the inheritance of Salpaad, our brother, to his daughters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now they may become wives to one of the communities of the Israelites, and their lot may be taken from the possession of our fathers, and added to the inheritance of that tribe among which they may be married; so their inheritance may be taken from the lot of our inheritance;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and though there may be a jubilee of the children of Israel, still their inheritance will be added to the inheritance of the tribe among whom they may have been married, and their inheritance will be taken from the inheritance of our patriarchal tribe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Whereupon Moses gave a charge to the children of Israel, by the command of the Lord, saying, In regard to what the tribe of the children of Joseph say,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded the daughters of Salpaad, saying, Let them marry whom they please, but they must marry men of the community of their father,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>so there shall be no transferring of inheritance among the children of Israel, from one tribe to another. Because the children of Israel must be kept together, every one in the inheritance of the patriarchal family of his tribe,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>therefore every daughter, who by being next of kin, inheriteth a possession among the tribes of Israel, must marry one of the community of her father, that the children of Israel may inherit by nearness of kin, every one the inheritance of his father's family:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>by which means the allotment will not be transferred from one tribe to another; but the Israelites will be kept together every one in his inheritance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Accordingly they did, for the daughters of Salpaad, in the manner the Lord commanded Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Thersa, and Egla, and Melcha, and Nua, and Maala, the daughters of Salpaad, were married to their cousins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>They were married to men of the tribe of Manasses, one of the sons of Joseph, and their inheritance was kept in the tribe, to which the community of their father belonged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>These are the commands, and the statutes, and the judgments, which the Lord gave in charge, by the ministry of Moses, on the west of Moab, on the Jordan, over against Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>