<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>These are the words which Moses spoke to all Israel, on the bank of the Jordan, west of the wilderness which reacheth to the Red sea, between Pharantophal and Lobon, and Aulon, and Katachrusea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>eleven days' journey from Choreb, the way by mount Seir to Kades-Barne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>In the fortieth year, the eleventh month, on the first day of the month, Moses spoke to all the children of Israel, according to all that the Lord had given him in charge to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>After he had smitten Seon king of the Amorites, who dwelt in Esebon; and Og, king of Basan, who dwelt at Astaroth and Edrain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Moses began, on the bank of the Jordan, in the land of Moab, to explain the law fully, saying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The Lord our God spoke to us at Choreb, saying, You have tarried long enough by this mount.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Turn; strike your tents, and march to the mountain of the Amorites, and to all the inhabitants around Araba; to the mountain and to the plain, and to the south, and to the land of the Chananites, on the sea shore, and to Antilibanus, till you reach the river; the great river Euphrates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Behold I have delivered up the land before you. Go in, and take possession of the land, which with an oath I promised to give to your fathers; to Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob; to them and their seed after them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then I spoke to you at that time, saying, I am not able alone to bear you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The Lord your God hath multiplied you; and behold you are this day like the stars of heaven for multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>May the Lord, the God of your fathers, add to you a thousand times as many as you are, and bless you as he hath promised you!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>How can I alone bear the burden of you, even the whole weight of you, and your contentions?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Appoint for yourselves men of wisdom, knowledge and understanding, for your several tribes, and I will make them leaders over you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And you answered me, and said, The thing which thou hast proposed to do is good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So I took from among you men of wisdom, knowledge, and understanding, and appointed them to be leaders over you; captains of thousands, and captains of hundreds, and captains of fifties, and captains of tens; and promulgators of the law for your judges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And I gave a charge to your judges at that time, saying, Hear the causes between your brethren, and judge righteously between every man and his brother, and the stranger who is with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou shalt not respect a person in judgment. Against the low and the high thou shalt pass sentence, and not be afraid of the face of man; for the judgment is God's. And if the matter be too hard for you, bring it to me, and I will hear it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when I had given you in charge, at that time, all the things which you were to do,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>we removed from Choreb, and marched through all that great and frightful wilderness which you saw, on the way to the mountain of the Amorite, as the Lord our God commanded us. And when we came to Kades-barne,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>I said to you, You are come to the mountain of the Amorite, which the Lord our God giveth you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Behold the Lord your God hath delivered up to you the land before you. Go up and take possession of it, as the Lord, the God of your fathers, commanded you. Fear not, nor be faint hearted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Whereupon you all came to me, and said, Let us send men before us, and let them traverse the land for us, and bring us word what way we shall go up, and to what cities we shall come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the proposal was agreeable to me. So I took from among you twelve men; a man for every tribe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they turned, and went up to the mountain, and came to the valley of the bunch of grapes. And when they had thoroughly viewed it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>they took in their hands some of the fruit of the land, and brought it to you, and said, The land is good, which the Lord our God giveth us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Notwithstanding this, you would not go up; but disobeyed the command of the Lord our God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and murmured in your tents, saying, Because the Lord hateth us he hath brought us out of the land of Egypt, to deliver us into the hands of the Amorites, to destroy us utterly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>wherever we go. When your brethren disheartened you, saying, It is a nation great and numerous, and stronger than we; and the cities are large, and walled up to the sky. Indeed we have seen there sons of giants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>I said to you, Be not terrified, nor afraid of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The Lord your God is marching before you. He will assist you in subduing them, according to all that he hath done for you in the land of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and in that wilderness, which you have seen in your march to this mountain of the Amorite. The Lord thy God will take charge of thee, as a man would of a son; as he hath done all the way you marched, till you came to this place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Notwithstanding this speech you did not confide in the Lord our God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>who was marching before you in the way to chuse a place for you, conducting you by night with fire, pointing out to you the way in which you were to march; and by day, with a pillar of cloud.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And the Lord heard the sound of your words, and being provoked to wrath, he sware saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Not one of these men shall see that good land which I, with an oath, promised their fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>save Chaleb son of Jephonne. He shall see it. And to him I will give the land to which he went up, and to his children, because he vindicateth the cause of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>With me also the Lord was angry on your account, and said, Neither shalt thou go in there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Joshua son of Nave who is thy attendant; he shall go thither. Encourage him, for he shall distribute it, by lot, to Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And with respect to your children, who do not know good or evil, they shall go thither, and to them I will give it, and they shall inherit it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>But as for you, turn, and march into the wilderness, by the way to the Red sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then you answered, and said, We have sinned before the Lord our God. We will go up, and fight according to all that the Lord our God commanded us. So, every one seizing his implements of war, you assembled tumultuously to go up the mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Whereupon the Lord said to me, Say to them, You shall not go up, nor fight; for I am not with you. And you should not be trodden down before your enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Accordingly I spoke to you; but you hearkened not to me; but transgressed the command of the Lord, and presumptuously ascended the mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And the Amorites, who dwelt on the mountain, came out to meet you, and pursued you, as bees would do, and slaughtered you from Seir to Herma.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Then you sat down, and wept before the Lord our God; but the Lord hearkened not to your voice, nor paid attention to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>So you abode at Kades many days, as many as you had staid there before.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then we turned, and took up our march into the wilderness, by the way to the Red sea, as the Lord spoke to me. And when we had been many days circling round mount Seir,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the Lord said to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>You have been long enough circling round this mountain, therefore turn northward,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and give thou a charge to this people, saying, You are about to march along by the borders of your brethren, the children of Esau who inhabit Seir. They will be afraid of you, and dread you exceedingly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>You must not come to battle with them; for I will not give you a foot of their land, because I have given mount Seir to the children of Esau for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Buy provisions of them for money, that you may eat, and receive of them water by measure, for money, that you may drink;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>(for the Lord our God had blessed thee in all the works of thy hands.) Recollect how thou didst traverse that great and frightful wilderness. Behold! for forty years the Lord thy God was with thee. Thou wast not in want of any thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when we had passed by our brethren the children of Esau, who inhabit Seir, by the way of Araba, from Ailon to Gesion-gaber, and wheeling about had crossed the wilderness of Moab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the Lord said to me, Act not as enemies against the Moabites; nor come to a battle with them; for I will not give you for a possession any of their land; for I have given Aroer to the children of Lot, that they may inherit it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>(Now the Ommins had formerly dwelt there, a nation great and numerous,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and mighty as the Enakims; they as well as the Enakims may be accounted Raphains; but the Moabites call them Ommins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And in Seir the Chorrites were formerly settled, but the children of Esau destroyed them, and rooted them out from before them, and dwelt in their stead, in the same manner as Israel hath done with the land of their possession which the Lord hath given them.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now therefore arise, and strike your tents, and cross the valley of Zaret.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now the time we spent from Kades-barne till we came to the valley of Zaret, was thirty eight years; until all the generation of the warriors had fallen, and died out of the camp. As the Lord had, with an oath denounced against them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the hand of the Lord was upon them to destroy them from among the host until they had all fallen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when all the warriors had fallen, and died from among the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the Lord spoke to me, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thou art now to pass by Aroer, along the borders of Moab;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>when you come near to the children of Amman you must not act hostilely against them, nor come to battle with them; for I will not give thee any of the land of the children of Amman for a possession; because I have given it for a possession to the children of Lot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>(It may be accounted the land of the Raphains, for the Raphains formerly dwelt there, but the Ammanites call them Zochommins</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They, as well as the Enakims, were a nation great and numerous, and much stronger than you; but the Lord destroyed them from before the Ammanites, and they took possession of the country, and have dwelt therein in their stead, even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The same was the case with the children of Esau who inhabit Seir, they, in like manner, destroyed the Chorrites from before them, and took possession of their country, and have dwelt therein, in their stead, even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So it was with the Evites when they dwelt in Asedoth even to Gaza, the Cappadocians, who came out of Cappadocia, rooted them out, and dwelt in their stead.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now therefore arise, strike your tents, and cross the vale of Arnon; behold I have delivered into thy hand Seon, king of Esebon, the Amorite, with his land. Begin to take possession. Join battle with him this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Begin to impress the fear of thee, and the dread of thee, on the face of all the nations under heaven. They who hear of thy name shall tremble, and be in anguish because of thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now I had sent messengers from the wilderness of Kedamoth to Seon, king of Esebon, with words of peace, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Let me pass through thy land. I will march along the highway, and not turn aside to the right, nor to the left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thou shalt sell me provisions for money, that I may eat; and thou shalt sell me water for money, that I may drink, just till I can march through on foot;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>as the children of Esau, who dwell in Seir, and the children of Moab, who dwell in Aroer have done to me, until I cross the Jordan, to the land which the Lord our God giveth us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But Seon, king of Esebon, would not consent that we should pass by him, for the Lord our God had emboldened his spirit, and made his heart obstinate, that he might be delivered into thy hands, as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me, Behold I have begun to deliver up before thee Seon, king of Esebon, the Amorite, and his land. Begin therefore to take possession of his land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>So Seon, king of Esebon, came out to meet us, he and all his people, to battle at Jassa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the Lord our God delivered him up before us. And we smote him and his sons, and all his people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and took all his cities at that time and utterly destroyed every city one after another; with their wives and children. We left none to be taken alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Besides making a prey of their cattle, we took the spoils of their cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>From Aroer, which is on the banks of the brook Arnon, including the city in the vale, even to mount Galaad, there was not a city which escaped us. The Lord our God delivered them all into our hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Moreover, when, without approaching the children of Amman, we had taken all his territories on the brook Jabok, and his cities in the hilly country, as the Lord our God commanded us,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>we turned and went up the way to Basan. And when Og, king of Basan came out to meet us, he and all his people, to battle at Edrain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the Lord said to me, Fear him not; for into thy hand I have delivered him, and all his people, and all his land; and thou shalt do to him as thou hast done to Seon, the king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Esebon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So the Lord our God delivered also into our hands Og, king of Basan, and all his people, and we smote him till there was none of his seed left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And we took all his cities at that time. There was not a city which we did not take from them; three score cities, the whole region of Argob, belonging to Og, king of Basan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>All the cities fortified with high walls, bars and gates, besides the towns of the Pherezites, which were very many,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>we utterly destroyed. As we had done to Seon, king of Esebon, we destroyed every city, one after another, and the women and children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But all the cattle, and the spoils of the cities, we took for ourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So, at that time, we took this land out of the hands of the two kings of the Amorites, who were on the banks of the Jordan, from the brook Arnon even to Aermon</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>(now the Phoenicians call Aermon Sanior and the Amorites call it Sanir)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>including all the cities of Misor, and all Galaad, and all Basan, as far as Elcha, and Adraim, the cities of the kingdom of Og in Basan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>(For besides Og, king of Basan, there was not one of the Raphains left. Behold his bed was a bed of iron. Behold it is in the citadel of the Ammanites. The length of it is nine cubits, and the breadth of it four cubits, after the cubit of a man.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And we took possession of this land, at that time, from Aroer, which is on the bank of the brook Arnon, and the half of mount Galaad; and I gave all the cities thereof to Reuben, and Gad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the rest of Galaad, and all Basan, the kingdom of Og, I gave to the half of the tribe of Manasses, with all the region of Argob, even all that part of Basan which is to be accounted the land of the Raphains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>(Now when Jair the Manassite took the region of Argob, even to the borders of Gergesi, and Machathi, he called it after his own name Basan-Thavoth-Jair which is now its name.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now when I gave Galaad to the Machirites</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and to Reuben and Gad, all below Galaad, to the brook Arnon, the middle of the brook being the boundary; and as far as Jabok, this brook being the boundary of the Ammanites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and Araba, and the Jordan the boundary of Machanareth, even to the sea of Araba, the salt sea below Asedoth, the Phasga of the East,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I gave you a charge at that time, saying, The Lord your God hath given you this land for a possession, you shall go armed before your brethren, the children of Israel, all of you who are fit for war,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>(but your wives, and your children, and your cattle, for I know that you have much cattle, are to dwell in your cities, which I have given you)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>until the Lord your God shall have given your brethren rest, as well as you; and until they shall have taken possession of the land which the Lord our God giveth them, on the other side of the Jordan. Then you shall return, every one to his possession which I have given you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And at the same time I gave a charge to Joshua, saying, Your eyes have seen all that the Lord our God hath done to these two kings. In the same manner the Lord our God will deal with all those kingdoms against which you are going to cross over.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>You shall not be afraid of them, for the Lord our God will fight for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I also supplicated the Lord, at that time, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Lord God, thou hast begun to shew thy servant thy majesty, and thy power, and thy mighty hand, and thy outstretched arm; for what god is there in heaven, or on earth, who can do as thou hast done, or according to thy majesty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Let me cross over, and see that land, that good land which is beyond the Jordan, and that goodly mountain Antilibanus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But the Lord overlooked me, because of you, and would not hearken to me. And the Lord said to me, Let this suffice thee. Speak no more on this subject.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Go up to the top of the craggy mountain, and raise thine eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and take a view of it with thine eyes; for thou shalt not cross this Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And give a charge to Joshua, and strengthen and encourage him; for he shall cross over before this people, and shall give them the possession of all this land which thou hast seen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So we halted at the forest, near the house of Phogor.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now therefore, hear, Israel, the rules of rectitude, and the judgments, which I this day teach you to practise, that you may live, and multiply, and go in, and possess the land, which the Lord the God of your fathers giveth you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You shall not add any thing to what I command you; nor shall you diminish from it. You shall keep the commandments of the Lord our God, which I, this day, give you in charge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Your eyes have seen all that the Lord our God did because of Beelphegor; that as for every man who went after Beelphegor; him the Lord our God destroyed from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But as for you who adhered to the Lord your God, you are all alive this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Behold, I have taught you rules of rectitude, and judgments, as the Lord commanded me; that you may act agreeably thereto, in the land to which you are going, to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore keep them, and practise them. For this will be your wisdom, and your understanding, in the sight of all the nations. Whoever shall chance to hear all these rules of rectitude, will say, Behold this is a wise and understanding people a great nation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For how great must that nation be, which hath God near them, as the Lord our God is on all occasions, if we call upon him!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And how great must the nation be, which hath such rules of rectitude, and such righteous judgments, as are contained in the whole law, which I this day lay before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Take heed to thyself, and keep thy soul diligently. Forget not all the things which thine eyes have seen, and let them not depart from thy heart all the days of thy life; that thou mayst impress upon thy children, and thy childrens' children,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>that day when you stood in the presence of the Lord our God at Choreb, on the day of the solemn assembly. For the Lord said to me, Assemble the people before me, and let them hear my words, that they may learn to fear me all the days they live on the earth. And let them teach their children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So you came near and stood at the foot of the mountain. Though the mountain was blazing with fire up to heaven, there was darkness, thick darkness, a turbid tempest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the Lord uttered to you, from the midst of the fire, the sound of words which you heard. You saw no similitude, but only heard a voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when he had declared to you his covenant, which he commanded you to perform, even the ten commandments, he wrote them on two tables of stone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the Lord commanded me at that time to teach you rules of rectitude, and judgments, for you to practise in the land to which you are going, to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Therefore watch your souls with diligence; for you saw no similitude on the day when the Lord spoke to you at Choreb, in the mount, out of the midst of the fire;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>that you may not transgress, and make for yourselves a graven image; any kind of image, the likeness of man or woman;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the likeness of any of the beasts which are on the earth; the likeness of any winged bird, which flieth in the air;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>the likeness of any reptile, which creepeth on the ground; the likeness of any fish which is in the waters below the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and that upon looking up to heaven, and seeing the sun, and the moon, and the stars, and all the host of heaven, thou mayst not be led astray, and worship them, and perform religious service to those things which the Lord thy God hath arranged in due order, for all the nations which are under heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>God hath indeed taken you and brought you out of the land of Egypt; out of the iron furnace; out of Egypt, to be to him a chosen people, as at this day;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but with me the Lord God was angry for the things spoken by you, and he solemnly said that I should not cross this Jordan, and that I should not enter that land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For I am to die in this land, and not to cross that Jordan; but you are to cross it. When you shall possess that good land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>take heed to yourselves, that you do not forget the covenant of the Lord our God, which he made with you, and transgress and make for yourselves a graven image of any of the things about which the Lord thy God hath given thee a charge;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>for the Lord thy God is a consuming fire; a zealous God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>If therefore, when you have begotten sons, and sons' sons, and have been long in the land, you transgress, and make a graven image; the likeness of any thing whatever, and do evil in the sight of the Lord your God, to provoke him to wrath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I call heaven and earth this day to witness against you, that you shall surely perish from the land, to which you are going, to cross the Jordan there to take possession of it. You shall not prolong your days therein, but shall be utterly rooted out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the Lord will scatter you among all the nations, and you shall be left few in number, among all the nations, to which the Lord will bring you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And there you shall serve other gods, the works of men's hands, stocks and stones, which can neither see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Yet there, on seeking the Lord your God you will find him, when you seek him with your whole heart and with your whole soul;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>In thy affliction, when all these things have come upon thee in the latter days, when thou shalt turn to the Lord thy God, and hearken to his voice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>because the Lord thy God is a merciful God; he will not forsake thee utterly, nor totally destroy thee. He will not forget the covenant of thy fathers, which the Lord confirmed to them with an oath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Enquire of the days which are past; those which were before thee, from the day God created man on the earth, and from one end of heaven to the other; hath there ever been any thing like this great thing? Hath any thing been heard like it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Hath any nation heard the voice of the living God, speaking out of the midst of the fire, as thou hast heard, and are still alive?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Or hath God come, and made trial to take for himself a nation out of the midst of a nation, by trials, and by signs, and by wonders, and by war, and with a strong hand, and an outstretched arm, and with great visions, according to all that the Lord our God hath done in Egypt, before thine eyes?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>So that thou must needs know that the Lord thy God is very God, and that there is none else besides him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>From heaven he caused his voice to be heard to instruct thee; and on earth he shewed thee his great fire. And thou hast heard his words out of the midst of the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Because he loved thy fathers, he chose you their seed after them; and by his mighty power he hath brought thee out of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>to destroy nations greater and mightier than thou art, before thee; to bring thee in, and give thee their land for a possession, as is the case with thee this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Know therefore this day, and revolve it in thy mind, that the Lord thy God is alone God, in the heaven above, and in the earth beneath, and that there is none other besides him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>You shall therefore keep his commandments, and his rules of rectitude, which I this day give you in charge, that it may be well with thee and with thy children after thee; that you may live long in the land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then Moses set apart three cities on the side of Jordan, towards the rising of the sun,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>for the slayer to flee to. Whoever should kill his neighbour unawares, and hated him not in times past, might flee to one of these cities, and live,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>namely, Bosor, in the wilderness, in the plain, for the Reubenites; and Bamoth, in Galaaditis, for the Gadites; and Gaulon, in Basan, for the Manassites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>This is the law which Moses laid before the children of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>these are the testimonies, and the rules of rectitude, and the judgments, which Moses delivered in his speech to the Israelites, after they came out of the land of Egypt</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>on the bank of the Jordan, in the vale near the house of Phogor, in the land of Seon, king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Esebon, whom Moses and the Israelites slew after their coming out of the land of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>when they took possession both of this land, and the land of Og king of Basan, the two kings of the Amorites, who were on the side of the Jordan towards the rising of the sun,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>from Aroer, which is on the border of the brook Arnon, to the mountain of Seon, which is Aermon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>comprehending all that part of Araba on the eastern bank of Jordan, below the cliff of Asedoth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Moses had convened all Israel, he said to them Hear, Israel, the rules of rectitude and the judgments, which I this day deliver in your hearing, that you may learn them, and may be careful to perform them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The Lord your God made a covenant with you at Choreb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>It was not only with your fathers that the Lord made this covenant, but with you also; with you who are all here alive this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Face to face the Lord spoke to you, at that mountain, out of the midst of the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I indeed stood between the Lord and you, at that time, to declare to you the words of the Lord, because you were terrified at the fire, and did not go up to the mountain;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and he said, I am the Lord thy God, who brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thou shalt have no other gods before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thou shalt not make for thyself an idol, nor the likeness of any thing in the heaven above, or of any of the things which are on the earth below, or which are in the waters below the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou shalt not worship them, nor serve them; for I am the Lord thy God, a zealous God, retributing, to them who hate me, the sins of fathers upon children, to the third and fourth generation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and shewing mercy for thousands of generations to them who love me, and keep my commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain; for the Lord thy God will not purify him who taketh his name in vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Keep the day of the sabbaths to hallow it, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Labour six days, and do all thy works;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but on the seventh day are the sabbaths for the Lord thy God. On it thou shalt not do any work; neither thou nor thy son, nor thy daughter, nor thy man servant nor thy maid servant, nor thine ox, nor thine ass, nor any of thy cattle, nor the proselyte who sojourneth with thee; that thy man servant, and thy maid servant, and thy labouring beast may rest as well as thou.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt, and that the Lord thy God brought thee out thence, with a strong hand and an outstretched arm; for this cause the Lord thy God hath commanded thee to keep the day of the sabbaths and hallow it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Honour thy father and thy mother, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee, that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayst live long in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou shalt not commit murder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thou shalt not commit adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou shalt not steal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thou shalt not covet thy neighbour's wife; thou shalt not covet thy neighbour's house, nor his field, nor his man servant, nor his maid servant, nor his ox, nor his ass, nor any of his cattle, nor any thing which is thy neighbour's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>These are the injunctions which the Lord delivered verbally, to all your congregation, at the mount, out of the midst of the fire. There was darkness, thick darkness, a turbid tempest, and a loud voice. And he added no more. And having written them on two tables of stone, he gave them to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now when you heard the voice from the midst of the fire (the mountain indeed was burning with fire) you came to me, even all the leaders of your tribes, and your elders,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and said, Behold the Lord our God hath shewn us his glory, and we have heard his voice from the midst of the fire. We have this day seen that God can speak to man, and he may live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now therefore let us not die, for this great fire will consume us, if we continue any longer to hear the voice of the Lord our God; and we shall die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For what mortal, who hath heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire, as we have, can live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Go thou near, and hear all that the Lord our God may say, and thou shalt rehearse to us all that the Lord our God may speak to thee, and we will hear and do it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And the Lord heard the sound of your words when you spoke to me. And the Lord said to me, I have heard the sound of the words of this people, even all that they have spoken to thee. All that they have said is right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>O that they may have their heart so disposed in them as to fear me, and to keep my commandments continually, that it may be well with them, and their children for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Go say to them, Return to your houses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But as for thee, Stand thou here with me, and I will speak to thee all the commandments, and the rules of rectitude, and the judgments, which thou shalt teach them; and let them act accordingly in the land which I give them for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Be careful therefore to do as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee. Turn not aside to the right, nor to the left,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>from walking in all the way which the Lord thy God hath commanded thee, that he may give thee rest, and that it may be well with thee, and that you may live long in the land, of which you shall take possession.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the commandments, and the rules of rectitude, and the judgments, which the Lord our God commanded you to be taught, that you may act conformably thereto in the land to which you are going, there to take possession of it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>that you may fear the Lord your God. You shall keep all his statutes, and his commandments, which I this day command you, both thou, and thy children, and thy children's children, all the days of thy life, that you may live many days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore hear, Israel, and be careful to perform; that it may be well with thee, and that you may be greatly multiplied, as the Lord, the God of thy fathers, hath promised to give thee a land flowing with milk and honey. These indeed are the rules of rectitude, and the judgments, which the Lord gave in charge to the children of Israel, in the wilderness, on their coming out of the land of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hear Israel! The Lord is our God. The Lord is one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And thou shalt love the Lord thy God with thy whole understanding, and with thy whole soul, and with thy whole might.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And these injunctions, which I this day give thee in charge, shall be in thy heart, and in thy soul;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and thou shalt impress them on thy children, and speak of them, when thou sittest at home, and when thou art walking abroad, and when thou liest down, and when thou risest up;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and thou shalt bind them for a sign on thy right hand, and it shall be immoveably before thine eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>You shall also write them on the posts of your houses and gates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when the Lord thy God hath brought thee into the land, which, with an oath he promised to thy fathers, to Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob, to give thee cities, great and beautiful, which thou hast not builded;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>houses full of all good things, which thou hast not filled; cisterns of hewn stone, which thou hast not hewed; vineyards, and olive yards which thou hast not planted; and when thou hast eaten, and art filled,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>take heed to thyself, that thou forget not the Lord thy God, who brought thee out of the land of Egypt; out of the house of bondage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou shalt fear the Lord thy God, and serve him alone, and cleave to him, and swear by his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Go not after other gods; after any of the gods of the nations around you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>(For the zealous God; the Lord thy God is among you) lest the Lord thy God, being provoked to wrath against thee, destroy thee from the face of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thou shalt not try the Lord thy God, as you tried him at Temptation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou shalt diligently keep the commandments of the Lord thy God; all the testimonies, and the rules of rectitude, which he shall give thee in charge;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and thou shalt do what is well pleasing and good in the sight of the Lord thy God, that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayst go in, and take possession of that good land, out of which the Lord hath, with an oath, promised your fathers</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>to drive all thine enemies from before thee, as the Lord hath spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when thy son shall, in time to come, ask thee, saying, What is the meaning of these testimonies, and these rules of rectitude, and these judgments, which the Lord our God hath enjoined on us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then thou shalt say to thy son, We were servants to Pharao, in the land of Egypt, and the Lord brought us out thence, with a strong hand, and with an outstretched arm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And when the Lord had shewn signs, and wonders, great, and grievous, in Egypt, on Pharao, and on his household, in our sight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>he brought us out thence, to give us this land, which, with an oath, he promised to give our fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and the Lord commanded us to practise all these rules; to fear the Lord our God, that it may be well with us always, that we may live, as we now do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For we shall find mercy, if we be careful to perform all these commandments in the sight of the Lord our God, as he hath commanded us.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when the Lord thy God hath brought thee into that land, to which thou art going, there to possess it, and hath removed from before thee mighty nations; the Chettite, and the Gergasite, and the Amorite, and the Chananite, and the Pheresite, and the Evite, and the Jebusite, seven nations, more numerous, and stronger than you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When the Lord thy God shall deliver them into thy hands, thou shalt smite them; thou shalt utterly destroy them; thou shalt not make a covenant with them. You shall neither shew them mercy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>nor contract marriages with them. Thou shalt not give thy daughter to his son, nor take his daughter for thy son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For she will cause thy son to apostatise from me, and to serve other gods, and the Lord will be provoked to wrath against you, and speedily destroy thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But in this manner thou shalt deal with them? their altars you shall destroy; their pillars you shall break to pieces; their groves you shall cut down; and the graven images of their gods you shall burn with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For thou art a people dedicated to the Lord thy God, and the Lord thy God hath chosen thee, to be a peculiar people to himself, in preference to all the nations which are on the face of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>It was not because you were the most numerous of all the nations, that the Lord preferred you, and made choice of you; for you are the fewest of all the nations:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but because the Lord loved you, therefore in performance of the oath which he swore to your fathers, the Lord led you out with a strong hand, and the Lord redeemed thee from the house of bondage, out of the hand of Pharao king of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Know therefore that the Lord thy God is the only God; the God to be confided in, who keepeth covenant and mercy for thousands of generations with them who love him, and keep his commandments;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and who requiteth to their face them who hate him, so as to destroy them. To them indeed who hate him he will not be slack; to their face he will requite them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore keep the commandments, and the rules of rectitude, and these judgments, which I this day command thee to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And it shall come to pass, that if you hearken to these rules, and keep and practise them, the Lord thy God will keep with thee the covenant, and the mercy, which he, with an oath, confirmed to your fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And he will love thee, and bless thee, and multiply thee; and he will bless the offspring of thy womb, and the product of thy land; thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil, thy herds of cattle, and thy flocks of sheep, in the land which he, with an oath, promised thy fathers to give thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou shalt be blessed above all the nations. There shall not be a male without a progeny, nor a female barren among you, or your cattle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Lord will remove from thee every malady, and will not lay upon thee any of the sore diseases of Egypt, which thou hast seen, which thou hast known: but will lay them upon all that hate thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And thou shalt consume all the spoils of the nations, which the Lord thy God giveth thee: Thine eye shall not have pity on them. And thou shalt not perform religious service to their gods; for this is a snare for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now if thou shouldst say in thy heart, This nation is stronger than I; how shall I be able to exterminate them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Be not afraid of them; but keep up a lively remembrance of all that the Lord thy God did to Pharao, and to all the Egyptians;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>the great trials which thine eyes have seen,; the signs and great wonders; the mighty hand, and the outstretched arm; As the Lord thy God brought thee out, so will the Lord your God deal with all the nations, of whom you are afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The Lord thy God will indeed send hornets against them, until they who are left, and hid from thee, are utterly destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thou shalt not be affrighted at them; for the Lord thy God; the Great and Mighty God, is with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The Lord thy God will indeed consume those nations from before thee, by little and little. Thou wilt not be enabled to destroy them at once, lest the land become a waste, and the wild beasts multiply against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But the Lord thy God will deliver them into thy hands, and thou shalt destroy them with a great destruction, until you may utterly exterminate them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When he shall deliver their kings into your hands, you shall destroy their name out of that place. None shall be able to stand before thee, until thou hast utterly destroyed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The graven images of their gods you shall burn with fire. Thou shalt not covet the silver nor the gold thereof. Thou shalt not take any of it for thyself, lest thou be ensnared by it. Because it is an abomination to the Lord thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>therefore thou shalt not bring an abomination into thy house; for thou wilt be an Anathema as well as it. Thou shalt utterly detest it, and hold it in utter abomination; for it is an Anathema, a devoted thing.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>All the commands which I this day give you in charge you shall be careful to perform, that you may live, and be multiplied, and go in, and possess the land which the Lord your God solemnly promised to your fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and thou shalt keep in remembrance all the way which the Lord thy God led thee in the wilderness, that he might afflict thee, and prove thee, and know what was in thy heart, whether thou wouldst keep his commandments or not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when he had afflicted thee, and suffered thee to hunger, then he fed thee with manna, which thy fathers knew not, that he might shew thee, that man can live not on bread only; but that man can live on any thing which God is pleased to appoint.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thy garments did not become too old for thee, nor were thy shoes worn out from under thee; nor the feet galled during the whole forty years;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>so that thou must know in thy heart, that as a man chastiseth his son, so the Lord thy God will chasten thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>keep therefore the commandments of the Lord thy God, by walking in his ways, and fearing him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For the Lord thy God will bring thee to a good, and extensive land, where there are brooks of water, and fountains from the deeps, issuing forth from the plains, and from the hills;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>a land of wheat, and barley, where there are vineyards, and fig trees, and pomegranates; a land of oil-olive and honey;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>a land wherein thou shalt eat bread, without scarcity, and in which thou shalt not want any thing; a land, the stones of which are iron, and out of the mountains of which thou shalt dig brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore when thou hast eaten, and art satisfied, thou shalt bless the Lord thy God in that good land, which he hath given thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Take heed to thyself, that thou forget not the Lord thy God, so as not to keep his commandments, and his judgments, and his rules of rectitude, which I this day command thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When thou hast eaten, and art satisfied, and hast built goodly houses, and dwelt therein,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and when thy herds, and thy flocks, are multiplied, and thou hast silver and gold in abundance, and all thy possessions are multiplied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>be not elated in heart, nor forget the Lord thy God, who brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>who conducted you through that great and frightful wilderness, where there were biting serpents and scorpions, and drought, where there was no water; who brought a fountain of water for thee out of a flinty rock;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>who fed thee in the wilderness with manna, which thou didst not know, and which was not known by thy fathers, that he might afflict thee, and try thee, and do thee good in thy latter days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Say not in thy heart, My own power, and the strength of my own hand hath procured me this great wealth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>but remember the Lord thy God, that it is he who giveth thee power to procure wealth, that he may establish the covenant which the Lord made with thy fathers, as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Indeed if thou forget the Lord thy God, and go after other gods, and serve them, and worship them, I call heaven and earth this day to witness against you, that you shall surely perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In like manner as the other nations which the Lord God destroyed before you, so shall you perish, because you have not hearkened to the voice of the Lord your God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hear, Israel! Thou art now about to cross the Jordan, to go in to possess nations much greater and stronger than you, large cities, which are walled up to the sky,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>a people great and numerous, and of great stature, the children of Enak, whom thou knowest, and of whom thou hast heard it said, Who can stand before the sons of Enak?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Know therefore this day, that the Lord thy God will himself march before thee. He is a consuming fire. He will destroy them. He will cause them to turn back from before thy face, and will destroy them speedily, as the Lord hath said to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now when the Lord thy God hath destroyed those nations from before thee, speak not in thy heart, saying, On the account of my righteousness the Lord hath brought me in to possess this good land. It is not on the account of thy righteousness, nor for the sanctity of thy heart, that thou goest in to possess their land; but, because of the wickedness of those nations, the Lord will drive them out from before thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and that he may establish his covenant which the Lord made with our fathers; with Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Know therefore this day, that it is not for thy righteousness that the Lord thy God giveth thee that good land for a possession; for thou art a stiffnecked people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Remember; never forget how often thou hast provoked to wrath the Lord thy God, in the wilderness. From the day you came out of Egypt, till your coming to this place, you have gone on in a course of rebellion against the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>At Choreb you provoked the Lord, so that the anger of the Lord was kindled against you, to destroy you utterly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When I went up the mountain to receive the tables of stone; the tables of the covenant which the Lord had made with you. Now I was on the mount forty days, and forty nights; I neither ate bread nor drank water;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and the Lord gave me the two tables of stone, written with the finger of God: upon them indeed were written all the words which the Lord had spoken to you at the mount, on the day of the solemn assembly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And after the forty days, and the forty nights, when the Lord gave me the two tables of stone; the tables of the covenant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the Lord said to me, Arise, go down quickly from this place: for thy people, whom thou hast brought out of Egypt, have transgressed. They have gone aside quickly out of the way, to which thou didst enjoin them, and have made for themselves a molten image.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Moreover the Lord spoke to me, saying, I have spoken to thee once and again and said, I have seen this people, and behold it is a stiffnecked people;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>now therefore let me utterly destroy them, and blot out their name from under heaven; and I will make thee a nation, great and powerful, and much more numerous than this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Whereupon I turned, and came down from the mount. Now the mount was blazing with fire up to heaven, and I had in my two hands the two tables of the testimonies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when I saw that you had sinned before the Lord your God, and that you had made for yourselves a molten image, and had turned aside from the way in which the Lord had commanded you to walk;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>having hold of the two tables, I threw them out of my hands and broke them before your eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then I made supplication before the Lord, a second time, as I had done before, forty days and forty nights; (I neither ate bread nor drank water); for your sins which you had committed by doing evil in the sight of the Lord God, to provoke him to wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Even now I tremble on account of the wrath and indignation. For the anger of the Lord was kindled against you, to destroy you utterly. But the Lord hearkened to me at that time also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Even against Aaron, his wrath was kindled to destroy him; But I prayed for Aaron also at that time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now I had taken your sin, the calf which you had made, and burned it with fire; and having stamped, and ground it, till it was very fine, and like dust, I threw the dust into the torrent which ran down out of the mount.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>At Burning also, and at Temptation, and at Monuments of longing desire, you provoked the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when the Lord sent you from Kades-barne, saying, Go up, and take possession of the land which I give you, you disobeyed the command of the Lord your God, and did not confide in him, nor hearken to his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>You have been disobedient to the commands of the Lord, from the day he made himself known to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When I was making supplication before the Lord, forty days, and forty nights, as I had done before (for the Lord spoke of destroying you utterly,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I prayed to God, and said, O Lord, thou king of all the gods, destroy not thy people, and thy heritage, whom thou hast redeemed, whom thou hast brought out of the land of Egypt, with thy mighty power, and with thy strong hand, and with thine outstretched arm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Remember Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob, thy servants, to whom thou didst swear by thyself. Look not upon the stubbornness of this people, nor upon their wickedness, and their sins,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>lest they who dwell in the land, out of which thou hast brought them, should speak, saying, Because the Lord was not able to bring them into the land which he promised them; and because he hated them, he led them out into the wilderness to kill them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now these are thy people, and thy inheritance, whom thou hast brought out of the land of Egypt, with thy mighty power, and with thy strong hand, and with thine outstretched arm.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time the Lord said to me, Hew thee out two tables of stone like the first, and come up to me on the mount; and thou shalt make thee an ark of wood,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and thou shalt write on these tables the words which were on the first tables, which thou didst break, and shalt put them in the ark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So when I had made an ark of incorruptible wood, and hewed two tables of stone, like the first, and had gone up the mount with the two tables in my hand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and he had written on these tables, according to the former writing, the ten commandments, which the Lord spoke to you at the mount, out of the midst of the fire; and the Lord had given them to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and I had turned, and come down from the mount, and had put these tables in the ark which I had made, and they were there as the Lord commanded me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>then the children of Israel removed out of Beroth, the country belonging to the children of Jakin, into Misidai, the country where Aaron died, and where he was buried, and Eleazar executed the office of priest in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thence they removed to Gadgad, and from Gadgad to Etabatha, a land abounding with streams of water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now the Lord, having at that time set apart the tribe of Levi to carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, to stand before the Lord, and to serve, and bless in his name, as they do at this day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>for this cause the Levites have no portion or lot among their brethren. The Lord is their portion, as he said to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When I had been on the mount forty days, and forty nights, the Lord hearkened to me at that time also, for the Lord was not willing to destroy you utterly;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and the Lord said to me, Go, march before this people, and let them go in, and take possession of the land which I solemnly promised their fathers to give them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now therefore, Israel, what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, and to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to serve the Lord thy God with thy whole heart, and with thy whole soul;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>to keep the commandments of the Lord thy God, and his rules of rectitude, which I this day command thee, that it may be well with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Behold the heaven, and the heaven of heavens, belong to the Lord thy God, the earth also, and all that are therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Nevertheless the Lord made choice of your fathers to love them; and he chose you, their seed, after them, in preference to all the nations, as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Circumcise therefore the stubbornness of your hearts, and be no more stiffnecked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For the Lord your God is God of gods, and Lord of lords; the God, great, and mighty, and awful. He respecteth not persons, nor taketh a bribe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He administereth justice to the stranger, and the orphan, and the widow, and loveth the stranger, in giving him food and raiment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Love ye therefore the stranger, for you were strangers in the land of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou shalt fear the Lord thy God, and serve him, and cleave to him, and swear by his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He is thy boast; and he is thy God, who hath done for thee those great, and those marvellous things which thine eyes have seen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>With seventy souls thy fathers went down to Egypt, and now the Lord thy God hath made thee like the stars of heaven for multitude.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore thou shalt love the Lord thy God, and keep his charges, and his rules of rectitude, and his commandments, and his judgments, continually.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You must now know, for I am not addressing your children, who have not known, nor seen, the chastisement of the Lord thy God, and his great acts, and his outstretched arm,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and his signs, and his wonders, which he did in the midst of Egypt, to Pharao, king of Egypt, and to all his land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and what he did to the army of the Egyptians; to their chariots, and their cavalry, and their host; how the Lord caused the water of the Red sea to overwhelm them, when they were pursuing you, and destroyed them even to this day:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and what he did to you in the wilderness, until you came to this place;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and what he did to Dathan and Abiron, the sons of Eliab, son of Reuben, whom the earth, opening its mouth, swallowed up, with their houses, and their tents, and all their substance with them, in the midst of all Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Because your eyes have seen all these great acts of the Lord which he hath done among you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>therefore you shall keep all his commandments which I this day give thee in charge, that you may live, and multiply, and go in, and possess that land to which you are going to cross the Jordan, there to take possession of it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>that you may prolong your days in that land, which the Lord, with an oath to your fathers, promised to give to them, and to their seed after them; a land flowing with milk and honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For the land to which you are going, to take possession of it, is not like the land of Egypt, from which you came out, where, when they have sown the seed, they can water it with their feet, like a garden of herbs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But the land to which you are going, to take possession of it, is a land of hills and dales, which drinketh up water from the rain of heaven;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>a land over which the Lord thy God keepeth a continual watch. The eyes of the Lord thy God are upon it, from the beginning of the year to the end thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And if you will hearken diligently to all the commands which I this day command thee, to love the Lord thy God, and to serve him with thy whole heart, and with thy whole soul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>he will give rain for thy land in due season; the former and the latter rain; and thou shalt gather in thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He will also give grass in thy fields for thy cattle. But when thou hast eaten, and art full,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>take heed to thyself that thy heart be not elated; and that you do not transgress, and serve other gods, and worship them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>lest the Lord, being provoked to wrath against you, shut up heaven, so that there shall be no rain, and the land yield not its products, and ye quickly perish from that good land, which the Lord hath given you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore lay up these things in your heart, and in your soul, and bind them for a sign on your hand, that they may be immoveably before your eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And you shall teach them to your children, by speaking of them, when thou sittest at home, and when thou walkest abroad, and when thou liest down to sleep, and when thou risest up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And you shall write them on the door posts of your houses, and of your gates;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>that you may prolong your lives, that the days of your children in the land which the Lord solemnly promised your fathers to give them, may be as the days of heaven over the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For it shall come to pass, that if you hearken diligently to all these commands, which I this day enjoin you to do; to love the Lord our God, and to walk in all his ways, and to cleave to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>the Lord will drive out all those nations from before you, and you shall possess nations much greater and stronger than you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Every place on which you shall imprint the track of your feet shall; be yours, from the wilderness to Antilibanus, and from the river, the great river Euphrates, to the western sea. These shall be your boundaries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>None shall be able to stand before you. For the Lord your God will impress the fear of you, and the dread of you, on the face of all the land on which you shall tread, as the Lord hath said to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Behold I am going to lay before you this day the blessing and the curse;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>the blessing, if you will hearken to the commandments of the Lord your God, which I this day command you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and the curse, if you will not hearken to the commandments of the Lord our God, in all respects, as I this day command you; but turn aside out of the way to which I have enjoined you, and go to serve other gods, which you do not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when the Lord thy God hath brought thee to the land, to which thou art going to cross over, there to take possession of it, thou shalt put the blessing on mount Garazin, and the curse on mount Gaibal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Behold are not these on the bank of the Jordan, behind the road to the setting of the sun, in the land of the Chananites, whose dwelling is to the westward, adjoining Golgol, near the lofty oak? for you are going to cross the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When you have gone in, to possess the land which the Lord our God giveth you for a perpetual possession, and you shall dwell therein,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>be careful to perform all his commandments, and all these judgments, which I this day lay before you.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the commandments, and the judgments, which you shall be careful to execute, in the land which the Lord the God of your fathers giveth you for a possession, all the days you live in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You shall utterly destroy all those places, in which they whom you succeed, have worshipped their gods, on the lofty mountains, and on the hills, and under every shady tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>You shall level their mounts, and break in pieces their pillars, and cut down their groves, and burn the graven images of their gods with fire, so that their name may be destroyed out of that place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>You shall not do to the Lord your God, in the manner they have done;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but you shall seek out and come to the place, which the Lord thy God shall make choice of, in one of your cities, to put his name there, and to be invoked;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and to that place you shall bring your whole burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, and your oblations, and your vows, and your free will offerings, and your thank offerings, and the firstlings of your herds, and flocks;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and you shall eat there before the Lord your God, and rejoice with your households, for all your possessions, and the labours of your hands, as the Lord thy God hath blessed thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>You shall not do all that we do here at this day; every one what is agreeable in his own sight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>for till now you have not come to the rest, and to the inheritance which the Lord your God giveth you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but when you cross the Jordan, and dwell in the land which the Lord our God giveth you for a possession; when he shall give you rest from all your enemies round about, and you shall dwell in safety, then there shall be a place, wherever the Lord thy God shall chuse, for his name to be invoked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>To that place you shall bring all that I this day command you, your whole burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, and your tenths, and the oblations of your hands, and the choice of all your gifts which you may vow to the Lord your God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and you shall rejoice before the Lord your God, you, and your sons, and your daughters, and your men servants, and your maid servants, and the Levite who is at your gates, because he hath no portion nor inheritance with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Take heed to thyself, that thou offer not thy whole burnt offerings in every place which thou mayst see;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but only in the place which the Lord thy God shall make choice of, in one of thy tribes. There you shall offer your whole burnt offerings, and there you shall do all that I this day command you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Nevertheless, to satisfy thy desire, thou mayst kill and eat flesh, in every city, according to the blessing of the Lord thy God, which he hath given thee. The unclean with thee, and the clean, may eat it together, as you now do a roebuck or a deer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>but you must not eat the blood: that you shall pour on the ground like water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou shall not be at liberty to eat, in thy cities, the tythe of thy corn, and of thy wine, and thine oil, nor the firstlings of thy herds, and thy flocks, nor any of thy vows, which you shall make, nor your thank offerings, nor the oblations of thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>These thou shalt eat no where but before the Lord, in the place which the Lord thy God shall chuse for himself; thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, thy man servant, and thy maid servant, and the stranger who is in thy cities. And when thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God, for all thy possessions and all the labours of thy hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>take heed to thyself, that thou neglect not the Levite, as long as thou livest in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the Lord thy God hath enlarged thy borders, as he hath said to thee, if thou shalt say, I will eat flesh; if thy soul desireth to eat flesh; thou mayst, to satisfy the longing of thy soul, eat flesh:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and if the place, which the Lord thy God may have chosen for his name to be invoked, be far from thee, thou mayst slay, in the manner I have commanded thee, some of thy herd or thy flock, which God hath given thee, and eat in thy cities, according to the longing of thy soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>As the roebuck and the deer is eaten so thou shalt eat it. The unclean and the clean may alike eat it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But be very cautious not to eat blood. For his blood is life. Life must not be eaten with the flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>You must not eat it. You must pour it out on the ground, like water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thou shalt not eat it, that it may be well with thee, and thy children after thee. If thou wouldst do what is good, and well pleasing in the sight of the Lord thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>over and above thy hallowed things, if any thou hast; thou shalt take thy vows, and come to the place which the Lord thy God may have chosen for his name to be there invoked, and having offered thy whole burnt offerings,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>thou shalt offer up the flesh at the altar of the Lord thy God, and pour out the blood of thy own sacrifices against the base of the altar of the Lord thy God, and eat the flesh of these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Observe and hear, that thou mayst do all the things which I command thee, that it may be well with thee, and with thy children after thee for ever. When thou hast done what is well pleasing and good in the sight of the Lord thy God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and when the Lord thy God shall have driven out from before thee the nations, to which thou art going, to take possession of their land, and thou shalt possess it, and dwell therein,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>take heed to thyself that thou seek not to follow them after they are driven out from before thee, saying, How did these nations sacrifice to their gods? I will sacrifice in like manner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Thou shalt not do so to thy God; for they sacrificed to their gods the abominations of the Lord, which he hated; for they burned their sons, and their daughters, with fire, to their gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Be careful to do every thing which I this day command you. Thou shalt not add to it, nor diminish from it.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>If a prophet should start up among you, or a dreamer of dreams, and give thee a sign or a wonder;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and the sign or the wonder should come to pass, which he mentioned to thee saying, Let us go and worship other gods which you do not know;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>you shall not hearken to the words of that prophet, or of that dreamer of dreams; for the Lord thy God trieth you, to know whether you love your God with your whole heart, and with your whole soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>You shall follow the Lord your God, and fear him, and hearken to his voice, and cleave to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And that prophet, or that dreamer, shall be put to death; for he hath spoken to lead thee astray from the Lord thy God, who brought thee out of the land of Egypt, who redeemed thee from bondage; to put thee out of the way in which the Lord thy God commanded thee to walk. So thou shalt remove evil from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And if thy brother, the son of thy father, or of thy mother, or thine own son, or daughter, or the wife in thy bosom, or a friend who is as thine own soul, speak privately to thee saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which neither thou nor thy fathers have known;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>any of the gods of the nations around you, of those near thee, or those far distant from thee, from one end of the earth to the other;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>thou shalt not consent, nor hearken to him; neither shall thine eye pity him, nor shalt thou spare him, nor conceal him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou shalt surely inform against him, and thy hands shall be upon him, among the foremost, to kill him, and afterwards the hands of the whole people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And they shall stone him with stones, and he shall be put to death, because he sought to make thee apostatise from the Lord thy God, who brought thee out of the land of Egypt; out of the house of bondage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So all Israel will hear, and be afraid, and no more proceed to do any such wickedness as this among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And if thou shalt hear it said, that in one of the cities, which the Lord thy God giveth thee to dwell in,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>there are wicked men gone forth among you, who have seduced all the inhabitants of their land, saying, Let us go and serve other gods, which you know not;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>thou shalt examine, and make inquiry, and search diligently: And behold, if the report is evidently true, and such abomination hath been committed among you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>thou shalt surely destroy all the inhabitants of that land, with the slaughter of the sword. With an Anathema thou shalt devote to destruction, it and all that are in it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And thou shalt collect all the spoils of it into the streets thereof, and burn with fire the city, and all the spoils thereof, with all the inhabitants, in the sight of the Lord thy God. And it shall be uninhabited for ever. It shall never be rebuilt any more;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>nor shall any thing of what is devoted to destruction cleave to thy hand, that the Lord may turn from the fierceness of his wrath, and shew thee mercy, and have compassion on thee, and multiply thee, in the manner he solemnly promised thy fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>if thou wilt hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep his commandments which I this day command you; to do what is comely and well pleasing in the sight of the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>You are the children of the Lord your God; you shall not make a baldness between your eyes for the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Because thou art a people dedicated to the Lord thy God, and the Lord thy God hath chosen thee to be a peculiar people to himself, above all the nations on the face of the earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>you shall not eat any abomination.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>These are the beasts which you shall eat, young beeves, and sheep, and goats,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>deer and roebucks, and the pygarg, and oryx, and camelopardal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>every beast which parteth the hoof, dividing it into two distinct hoofs, and which cheweth the cud; these among the cattle you may eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But of those which chew the cud, and of those which part not the hoof, dividing it into two distinct hoofs, these you shall not eat; the camel, and the hairy foot, and the choirogryllus. Because though they chew the cud they do not part the hoof, they are unclean to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the swine also, because, though it parteth the hoof and divideth it into distinct hoofs, yet it doth not chew the cud, it is unclean to you. You shall not eat their flesh, nor touch their dead carcasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And of all that are in the water, these you may eat. You may eat all that have fins and scales.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But all that have not fins and scales, you shall not eat; they are unclean to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Every clean fowl you may eat;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>now these are they which you shall not eat; the eagle and the ospray, and the cormorant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and the vulture, and the kite, and all of its species;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the ostrich, and the owl, and the gull,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and the heron, and the swan, and the ibis, and cataractes, and the hawk, and all of its species;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and the puet, and the night hawk, and the pelican, and the charadrius, and all of its species;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and the porphurion, and the bat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>All the creeping things which fly are unclean to you. You shall not eat any of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Every flying thing, which is clean, you may eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Every thing which dieth of itself you shall not eat. It may be given to the stranger, who is in thy cities, and he may eat it, or thou mayst sell it to the stranger. Because thou art a people dedicated to the Lord thy God, thou shalt not boil a lamb in the milk of its dam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thou shalt set apart the tenth of all the increase of thy seed, the product of thy field year after year;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and this thou shalt eat in the place which the Lord thy God shall chuse, for his name to be there invoked. Thither you shall bring the tenths of thy corn, and of thy wine, and thine oil and the firstlings of thy kine, and of thy flocks, that thou mayst learn to fear the Lord thy God always.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But if the way be too long for thee, and thou canst not carry them up, because the place is far distant from thee, which the Lord thy God hath chosen for his name to be there invoked; seeing the Lord thy God hath blessed thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>therefore thou shalt sell them for money; and thou shalt take the money in thy hand, and go to the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and thou shalt give this money for whatever thy soul may desire; for cattle, or for sheep, or for wine, or strong drink, or for any thing which thy soul may desire; and thou shalt eat there before the Lord thy God, and rejoice with thy household,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and the Levite who is in thy cities, because he hath no portion nor lot with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And, at the end of three years, thou shalt carry out all the tenth of thy products in that year, and lay it up in thy cities,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and the Levite shall come, because he hath no portion nor lot with thee, and the proselyte, and the orphan, and the widow, who is in thy cities, and they shall eat and be filled, that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all the works which thou dost.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Every seven years thou shalt make a release.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And this is the ordinance touching this release. Thou shalt remit every private debt which thy neighbour oweth thee, and shalt not demand it of thy brother; for the release for the Lord thy God is proclaimed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Of a stranger thou mayst demand what may be due to thee from him; but to a brother thou shalt make a release of what he oweth thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>because among you there is to be none in want; because the Lord thy God will, with blessing, bless thee in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance, that you may possess it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>if you will but hearken to the voice of the Lord your God, to keep, and perform, all these commandments which I this day command you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because the Lord thy God hath blessed thee in the manner he promised thee, therefore thou shalt lend to many nations and shalt not borrow, and thou shalt rule over many nations, and they shall not rule over thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If then there chance to be among you a needy person; one of thy brethren, in one of thy cities in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee thou shalt not harden thy heart, nor shut thy hand from thy brother who is in want.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thou shalt open thy hands liberally to him, and lend him what he is in want of, according to his necessity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Take heed to thyself that there be not a lurking thought in thy heart; a wicked suggestion, saying, The seventh year, the year of remission is near at hand. When thou shalt look with an evil eye at thy brother who is in want, and not give him, he will cry to the Lord against thee, and it will be a great sin in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thou shalt surely give him, and lend him freely, what he is in want of, according to his necessity. And thou shalt not be grieved at heart when thou givest to him; for on this account the Lord thy God will bless thee in all thy works, and in all the labours of thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Because thy land may never be without some indigent person in it, therefore I give thee a charge to do this thing, saying, Thou shalt open thy hands liberally to thy brother who is in want, and to the needy in thy land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And if thy brother, a Hebrew man, or a Hebrew woman, be sold to thee, he shall serve thee six years; and on the seventh thou shalt send him away from thee, free.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when thou shalt send him away free from thee, thou shalt not send him away empty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou shalt furnish him liberally with provision for the journey, from thy flock and from thy corn, and thy wine. According as the Lord thy God hath blessed thee, thou shalt give him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt, and that thence the Lord thy God redeemed thee; therefore I command thee to do this thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And if he shall say to thee, I will not go away from thee, because he hath loved thee, and thy family, and is well with thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>then thou shalt take an awl, and bore his ear against the door, and he shall be thy servant forever. And in the same manner thou shalt treat thy maid servant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>It shall not seem hard to thee that they are let go free from thee; for they have saved thee the wages of an hireling. He hath served thee six years. When the Lord thy God hath blessed thee in all thou doest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>every firstling of thy herds, and thy flocks, even all the males, thou shalt dedicate to the Lord thy God. Thou shalt not work a firstling bull, nor shear the firstlings of thy flock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou shalt eat them before the Lord, year after year, in the place which the Lord thy God shall chuse, thou and thy household.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But if any hath a blemish in it; if it be lame, or blind, or any way blemished, thou shalt not sacrifice it to the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In thy cities thou mayst eat it: the unclean with thee as well as the clean may eat it, like the roebuck or deer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But the blood you shall not eat. Thou shalt pour out that on the ground, like water.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Observe the month of New things, and keep the passover to the Lord thy God, because in the month of New things thou didst come out of the land of Egypt, by night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And at the passover thou shalt sacrifice to the Lord thy God, sheep, and kine, in the place which the Lord thy God shall chuse for his name to be there invoked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>At it thou shalt not eat leaven. Seven days, at it, thou shalt eat unleavened bread; the bread of affliction, because you came in haste out of Egypt, that you may remember the day of your coming out of the land of Egypt, all the days of your life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>No leaven shall be seen in all thy borders for seven days, and none of the flesh of that which you shall sacrifice on the evening of the first day shall be left till the morning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thou shalt not be at liberty to keep the passover in any of the cities which the Lord thy God giveth thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but only in the place which the Lord thy God shall chuse, for his name to be there invoked. Thou shalt kill the passover in the evening, at the setting of the sun, in the season thou didst come out of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when thou hast cooked, and roasted, and eaten it, in the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen, in the morning thou mayst return and go home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Six days thou shalt eat unleavened bread; and on the seventh day shall be the Exod; a festival to the Lord thy God. On it thou shalt not do any work, but what is necessary for life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Seven weeks thou shalt number for thyself; from thy first beginning to put the sickle to the harvest thou shalt begin to number the seven weeks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And thou shalt keep the festival of weeks, to the Lord thy God, according to the ability of thy hand; according to what the Lord thy God may have given thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And thou shalt rejoice before the Lord thy God, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, thy man servant, and thy maid servant, and the Levite, and the stranger, and the orphan, and the widow who is among you, in the place which the Lord thy God shall chuse for his name to be there invoked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And thou shalt remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt; therefore thou shalt keep, and perform, these commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The feast of tabernacles thou shalt keep for thyself seven days. When thou hast gathered in from thy threshing floor, and from thy press,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>thou shalt rejoice at this thy festival, thou and thy son, and thy daughter, thy man servant, and thy maid servant, and the Levite, and the stranger, and the orphan, and the widow, who is in thy cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Seven days thou shalt celebrate this festival to the Lord thy God, in the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen for himself. So when the Lord thy God shall bless thee in all thy productions, and in all the works of thy hands, and thou shalt be made glad,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>every male shall, three times in the year, appear before the Lord thy God, in the place which the Lord shall chuse; at the festival of unleavened bread, and at the festival of weeks, and at the festival of tabernacles. Thou shalt not appear before the Lord thy God empty handed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Every one of you shall bring according to the ability of his hand, according to the blessing of the Lord thy God, which he hath given thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thou shalt appoint for thyself judges, and promulgators of the law, in the cities which the Lord thy God giveth thee, in every tribe. And they shall administer just judgment to the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>They shall not wrest judgment, nor respect persons, nor shall they receive a gift. For gifts blind the eyes of the wise, and pervert the words of the righteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou shalt pursue righteously what is right, that you may live, and go in, and possess the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thou shalt not plant a grove for thyself, nor make for thyself a wood near the altar of thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>nor set up for thyself a pillar: these are things which the Lord thy God hateth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thou shalt not sacrifice to the Lord thy God a young bull, or a sheep, in which there is a blemish; any defect; for it is an abomination to the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>If there be found in any of thy cities which the Lord thy God giveth thee, a man, or a woman, who shall do evil in the sight of the Lord thy God, to transgress his covenant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and they have gone, and served other gods, and worshipped them, either the sun, or the moon, or any of the whole host of heaven, which he hath not commanded thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and information be given thee, and thou hast made strict inquiry, and behold the thing hath been actually done, and such an abomination hath been committed in Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>thou shalt bring out that man, or that woman, and you shall stone them with stones, till they die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>On the testimony of two or three witnesses the guilty person shall be put to death; but shall not be put to death on the testimony of one witness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the hand of the witness shall be upon him, among the first, to put him to death, and afterwards the hands of the people. So thou shalt remove the wickedness from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And if any cause which requireth judicial decision; an action of murder, an action of appeal, a case of leprosy, an action of plaint and denial; any causes which require decision in any of your cities, be too difficult for thee, thou shalt arise, and go up to the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and there come to the priests, the Levites, or to the judge, who ever he may be in those days, and they shall inquire, and declare to thee the sentence of judgment,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and thou shalt act according to what they declare to thee from the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen: and thou shalt be careful to do according to what is expounded to thee for law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>According to the law, and according to the sentence of judgment, which they tell thee, thou shalt do. Thou shalt not deviate from what</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>they tell thee, either to the right, or to the left. And if any man act presumptuously, so as not to hearken to the priest who hath stood to minister to the name of the Lord thy God; or to the judge who may be in those days; that man shall be put to death. So thou shalt remove the evil person from among Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and all the people, when they hear, will be struck with awe, and no more act presumptuously.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when thou art come to the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and hast taken possession of it, and dwelt therein, if thou shouldst say, I will set a chief over me, as the other nations around me do;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>thou shalt surely set, as chief over thee, him whom the Lord thy God shall chuse. Thou shalt appoint one of thy brethren chief over thee. Thou shalt not be at liberty to set a stranger over thee, because he is not thy brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Because he is not to multiply cavalry for himself, he must not even cause his people to go back to Egypt; in order that he may not multiply his cavalry: the Lord indeed hath said, You shall not henceforth return that way any more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Neither shall he multiply wives to himself; that his heart may not turn aside; nor shall he greatly multiply for himself silver and gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when he is settled in his government, he shall write for himself this repetition of the law in a book, from that which is in the custody of the priests, the Levites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And he shall keep it by him, and shall read therein all the days of his life, that he may learn to fear the Lord thy God, and to keep all these commandments, and execute all these judgments;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>that his heart may not be lifted up above his brethren; that he may not turn aside from these commandments, to the right, or to the left, to the end that he and his sons may long enjoy his government among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The priests, the Levites, even the whole tribe of Levi, shall have no portion, nor lot, with Israel. The homage offerings of the Lord are their lot. Them they shall eat;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and they shall not have a lot of inheritance among their brethren, The Lord himself is their lot of inheritance, as he hath said to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now this shall be the priest's due from the people; from them who offer sacrifices, whether a young bull, or a sheep, thou shalt give to the priest the shoulder, and the cheeks, and the maw.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thou shalt also give him the dedications of thy corn, and thy wine, and thine oil, and the dedications of the fleeces of thy flock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Because the Lord hath chosen him, out of all thy tribes, to stand before the Lord God, to minister and to bless, in his name; therefore with regard to him and his sons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>among the children of Israel, if, out of any one of all these cities of the children of Israel where he dwelleth, a Levite cometh, with all the desire of his soul, to the place which the Lord hath chosen,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>that he may minister to the name of the Lord his God, as all his brethren the Levites do, who attend there before the Lord thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>he shall eat the allotted portion, over and above what may come from the sale of his patrimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When thou art come into the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, thou shalt not learn to do after the abominations of those nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Let there not be found among you any one who purifieth his son, or his daughter, with fire; or who practiseth divinations, or consulteth omens, or augury,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>or maketh use of drugs to practise incantation, or a belly speaker, or an astrologer, or a necromancer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>for every one who practiseth such things is an abomination to the Lord thy God; for, because of these abominations, the Lord will root them out from before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou shalt be complete in the sight of the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For these nations which thou art about to possess will hearken to enchanters and diviners; but the Lord thy God hath not permitted thee to do so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The Lord thy God will raise up for thee, from among thy brethren, a prophet like me; to him you shall hearken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>According to all that thou didst request of the Lord thy God at Choreb, in the day of the solemn assembly, when you said, Let us no more hear the voice of the Lord thy God, and let us no more behold this great fire, lest we die,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the Lord then said to me, They have spoken right in all that they have said to thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I will raise up for them, from among their brethren, a prophet like thee, and I will put my words in his mouth, and he will speak to them as I command him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and whosoever will not hearken to what that prophet shall speak in my name, I will execute vengeance on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But the prophet who shall wickedly presume to speak a word in my name which I have not commanded him to speak, or who shall speak in the name of other gods, that prophet shall be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now if thou shalt say in thy heart, How shall I know the word which the Lord hath not spoken?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When the things which that prophet hath spoken in the name of the Lord shall not happen, nor come to pass, the Lord hath not spoken that word. The prophet hath spoken wickedly. You shall not spare him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when the Lord thy God hath destroyed the nations, whose land thy God giveth thee, and you have taken possession of it, and dwelt in their cities, and in their houses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>thou shalt set apart for thyself three cities, in the midst of that thy land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Make straight the way for thee, and divide into three districts, the bounds of thy land which the Lord thy God parcelleth out to thee: and in each district let there be a place of refuge for the slayer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And this shall be the ordinance for every slayer who may flee thither, and live. Whosoever shall smite his neighbour unawares, and hated him not in times past,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>for instance whosoever shall go with his neighbour into the forest to collect wood, and the hand of him who is cutting the wood with an axe being drawn back, the iron shall slip from the helve, and accidentally fall on his neighbour, and he die; such a one shall flee with speed to one of the cities, and live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Lest the avenger of blood pursuing, because his heart is inflamed, should overtake him, if the way be too long, and slay him, though he is not guilty of death, because he hated him not in time past;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for this cause I give thee this charge, saying, Thou shalt set apart three cities for thyself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when the Lord thy God shall enlarge thy borders, as he hath sworn to thy fathers, and the Lord hath given thee all the land which he promised to give thy fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>if thou wilt hearken to do all the commands which I this day give thee in charge, to love the Lord thy God, to walk in all his ways continually; thou shalt add three cities more for thyself, besides these three,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>so that guiltless blood may not be shed in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But there must not be among you one guilty of blood. If therefore there be among you a man who hateth his neighbour, and who shall lie in wait for him, and rise up against him, and smite him so that he die, and flee to one of these cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the senate of his city shall send and take him thence, and deliver him into the hands of the avenger of blood, and he shall be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thine eye shall not spare him. So shalt thou purge away guiltless blood from Israel, and it shall be well with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou shalt not remove the boundaries of thy neighbour, which thy fathers have settled at the distribution of the inheritances, which were given thee to possess in the land, which the Lord thy God hath given thee by lot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>One witness shall not be sufficient to testify against a man for any iniquity, or any crime, or any sin, which he may commit. By the mouth of two witnesses, or by the mouth of three witnesses, every thing shall be established.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And if a false witness rise up against a man, and accuse him of any crime,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the two men between whom is the controversy, shall stand before the Lord, and before the priests, and before the judges, who may be in those days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when the judges have made a strict examination, if the false witness hath testified falsehoods, and risen up against his brother;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>you shall do to him as he wickedly thought to do to his brother. So thou shalt remove the evil from among you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and the rest, when they hear, will be afraid, and thenceforth proceed no more to commit such evil among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thine eye shall not pity him; life for life; eye for eye; tooth for tooth; hand for hand; foot for foot.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When thou shalt go out to battle against thine enemies, and see horsemen, and charioteers, and a people more numerous than thou art; be not afraid of them; for the Lord thy God is with thee; he who brought thee up out of the land of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when thou art near coming to battle, the priest shall approach, and speak to the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and say to them, Hear, O Israel! You are now going to battle against your enemies; let not your heart be discouraged; fear not, nor be dismayed, nor turn aside from before them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>for the Lord your God goeth with you, to fight for you against your enemies, and to save you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then the scribes shall speak to the people, and say, If there be any man who hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it, let him go, and return to his house, lest he die in the battle, and another man dedicate it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Or is there any man who hath planted a vineyard, and hath not been regaled with it; let him go, and return to his family, lest he die in the battle, and another man be regaled with it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Or is there any man who hath betrothed a wife, and hath not taken her home; let him go, and return to his family, lest he die in the battle, and another man take her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the scribes shall further speak to the people, and say, Is there any man fearful, and faint hearted; let him go, and return to his family, lest he make the heart of his brother faint as his own.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when the scribes have done speaking to the people, they shall appoint the chiefs of the army to lead on the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when thou art come to a city, to fight against it, thou shalt call upon the inhabitants to come out peaceably.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And if they return thee a peaceful answer, and open to thee; all the people who are found therein shall be tributary to thee, and be thy subjects.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But if they hearken not to thee, and make war against thee, thou shalt besiege it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>until the Lord thy God deliver it into thy hands. And when thou hast smitten all the males therein with the slaughter of the sword,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>thou shalt take for thyself, besides the women and the children, all the cattle, and all spoils that are in the city, and eat all the prey of thine enemies, which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In this manner thou shalt treat all the cities which are at a great distance from thee, which are not of the cities of those nations whose land the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Of these you shall save none alive that breatheth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but, with an Anathema, thou shalt devote to destruction the Chettite and the Amorite, and the Chananite, and the Pherezite, and the Evite, and the Jebusite, and the Gergasite, as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>that they may not teach you all their abominations which they have performed to their gods; and that you may not sin before the Lord your God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now when thou shalt sit down before a city, many days, to war against it till it be taken, thou shalt not destroy the trees thereof by striking an ax against them. That especially, the fruit of which thou mayst eat, thou shalt not cut down. Doth any man wish to have a tree in the field for the purpose of a rampart for thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>let it be that only which thou knowest is not a fruit bearing tree. This thou mayst destroy and cut down, to build ramparts against the city which resisteth thee, until it be delivered up.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>If one be found slain in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee to possess; lying in the open field; and it is not known who smote him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>thy senate, and thy judges, shall come and measure the distance to the cities around the slain;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the senate of the city which is next to the slain, shall take a heifer from the herd, which hath never been worked, and which hath never drawn in a yoke;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and the senate of the city shall bring the heifer down to a rugged valley, which hath never been tilled, nor sowed, and they shall hamstring the heifer in the valley.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then the priests, the Levites, shall come near: because the Lord God hath chosen them to wait upon him, and to bless in his name, therefore by their mouth every cause of plaint and denial, as well as all cases of leprosy, are to be decided;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and the whole senate of the city which is nearest the person dead, shall wash their hands over the head of the heifer, which was hamstringed in the valley,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and shall answer, and say, Our hands have not shed this blood, and our eyes have not seen it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Be merciful to thy people whom thou, Lord, hast redeemed, that there may not be blood shed without cause among thy people Israel. So the blood shall be forgiven them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and thou shalt remove from among you the blood which was shed without cause, if thou do what is good, and well pleasing in the sight of the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when thou goest out to war against thine enemies, and the Lord thy God hath delivered them into thy hands, and thou hast taken their prey,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and hast seen, among the captives, a woman of a comely appearance, and hast loved her, and hast taken her to thyself for a wife,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and brought her home to thy house, thou shalt shave her head, and pare her nails,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and take from her the garments of her captivity, and she shall remain in thy house, and bewail her father, and her mother, a full month, and after that thou mayst go in unto her, and cohabit with her, and she shall be thy wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And in case thou dislike her, thou shalt send her away free. She shall not be sold for money. Thou shalt not deal falsely with her, because thou hast humbled her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If any man hath two wives, and one of them be beloved, and the other hated; and both the beloved, and the hated, bear him children, and the son of the hated be the first born,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>he shall not be at liberty, when he bequeatheth his substance to his children, to give the right of primogeniture to the son of the beloved, and overlook the son of the hated, who is the first born;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but shall acknowledge the son of the hated as his first born, by giving him a double portion of all that he hath, because he is the head of his children, and the rights of primogeniture belong to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If any man hath a stubborn, and rebellious son, who hearkeneth not to the voice of his father, nor to the voice of his mother; and they have corrected him, and he will not hearken to them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>his father and his mother shall take him, and bring him out to the senate of his city, and to the gate of the place;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and they shall say to the men of their city, This our son is stubborn and rebellious; he hearkeneth not to our voice. He is devoted to revelling and drunkenness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thereupon the men of his city shall stone him with stones, and he shall be put to death. So thou shalt remove the wicked from among you; and the rest, who hear, will be struck with awe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>If any man commit a sin incurring death; and he be put to death; and you hang him on a gibbet;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>his body shall not remain on the gibbet; but you shall bury it the same day. Because every one who is hanged on a gibbet is accursed of God; therefore you shall not defile the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possesion.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When thou seest thy brother's ox or sheep going astray, thou must not overlook them. Thou shalt surely bring them back to thy brother, and restore them to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And if thy brother be not near thee, and thou dost not know him; thou shalt take them home to thy house; and they shall be with thee, until thy brother seek them; then thou shalt restore them to thy brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>In like manner thou shalt do with his ass, and in like manner with his raiment, and in like manner with every thing which thy brother hath lost. Whatever hath been lost by him, if thou find it thou must not overlook it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When thou seest thy brother's ass, or his ox, fallen in the way, thou must not overlook them; thou shalt help him to lift them up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>A woman shall not wear what appertaineth to man, nor shall a man put on a woman's garment; for every one who doth such things is an abomination to the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If there chance to be before thee in the way, either in a tree, or on the ground, a bird's nest, with young or eggs; and the dam be sitting on the young, or on the eggs; thou shalt not take the dam with the young.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thou shalt let the dam go; but thou mayst take the young for thyself; that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayst prolong thy days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When thou buildest a new house, thou shalt make a battlement for thy roof, that thou mayst not occasion death by thy house, by any one's falling from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou shalt not sow thy vineyard, when the product of it is consecrated, with seed of another kind, that the seed which thou sowest may not be consecrated, with the product of thy vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thou shalt not plough with an ox and an ass together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thou shalt not wear, without scouring, a garment of wool and flax in the same piece.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thou shalt make bunches of ribbons on the four tufts of the mantles with which thou clothest thyself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If any man take a wife, and cohabit with her, and hate her,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and spread groundless reports concerning her, and give her an ill name, and say, I took this woman to wife, but when I came to her, I did not find her tokens of virginity;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>thereupon the father and mother of the damsel taking the tokens of their child's virginity, shall carry them to the senate, to the gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the father of the girl shall say to the senate, I gave this my daughter to that man for a wife; but he now hateth her,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and hath spread groundless reports concerning her, saying, I found not the tokens of virginity in thy daughter. Now these are the proofs of my daughter's virginity. And they shall spread the garment before the senate of the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whereupon the senate of the city shall take the man, and chastise him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and fine him a hundred shekels, and give them to the father of the young woman, because he brought an ill name on a virgin of Israel; and she shall be his wife. He shall not be at liberty to put her away all his days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But if his accusation be founded in truth, and proofs of virginity cannot be found for the young woman,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>they shall carry out the young woman to the doors of her father's house, and stone her with stones, till she die, because she hath committed folly in Israel, by making her father's house a place of prostitution. So thou shalt remove evil from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>If a man be found lying with a woman who is married, you shall put them both to death; both the man who lay with the woman, and the woman. So shalt thou take away evil from Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If a virgin be betrothed to a husband; and a man find her in a city, and lie with her,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>you shall bring them both out to the gate of the city, and stone them with stones, till they die: the young woman, because she did not cry aloud in the city, and the man because he humbled the wife of his neighbour. So thou shalt remove evil from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But if the man found the woman who was betrothed, in the field, and by force lay with her, you shall put him only to death who lay with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The young woman is not guilty of death. As when a man hath risen up against his neighbour, and killed him, even so is this matter:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for he found her in the field. The young woman who was betrothed, cried aloud, but there was none to help her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>If any man find a young woman, who is not betrothed, and by force lie with her, and be found,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>the man who hath lain with her shall pay the father of the young woman fifty didrachms of silver, and she shall be his wife: because he hath humbled her, he shall not be at liberty to put her away, all the days of his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>A man shall not take his father's wife, nor uncover his father's skirt.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A man who is made a eunuch by bruising, or by cutting, shall not come into the congregation of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>nor shall the son of a harlot come into the congregation of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>An Amorite, and a Moabite, shall not come into the congregation of the Lord: even to the tenth generation, they shall not come into the congregation of the Lord; nay; even for ever;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>because they did not meet you with bread and water on the way, when you were coming out of Egypt; and because they hired against thee, Balaam, son of Beor, of Mesopotamia, to curse thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but the Lord thy God would not hearken to Balaam. Nay, the Lord thy God turned the curses into a blessing, because the Lord thy God loved thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thou shalt not propose terms of peace with them, nor what is conducive to their welfare, all thy days, forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thou shalt not abominate an Idumean; for he is thy brother. Thou shalt not hold in abhorrence an Egyptian; because thou wast a sojourner in his land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>If either of these have sons, they may come into the congregation of the Lord, in the third generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When thou goest out to encamp against thine enemies, thou shalt be on thy guard against every evil thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If there be with thee a man who is unclean, by reason of any nightly pollution, he shall go out of the camp, or he shall not come into the camp;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>but towards evening he shall wash his body with water, and when the sun is set, he may come into the camp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Moreover thou shalt have a place without the camp, and thou shalt go out thither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And thou shalt have in thy girdle a spaddle, and when thou hast eased thyself abroad, thou shalt dig with it, and cover thy uncleanness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Because the Lord thy God walketh about in thy camp, to save thee, and subdue thine enemy before thee, therefore thy camp must be holy. There must be nothing unseemly seen with thee, that he may not turn away from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thou shalt not deliver up to his master, a servant who hath fled to thee, from his master.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He shall dwell among you wherever he pleaseth. Thou shalt not afflict him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>There shall not be a harlot of the daughters of Israel, nor a whoremonger of the sons of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>There shall not be a prostitute among the daughters of Israel, nor shall any of the Israelites be a votary of prostitution. Thou shalt not bring the hire of an harlot, nor the price of a dog, into the house of the Lord, for any vow, for both are an abomination to the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou shalt not take interest of thy brother, for money, nor for victuals, nor for any thing which thou mayst lend him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>To a stranger thou mayst lend on interest; but to thy brother thou shalt not lend on interest; that the Lord thy God may bless thee in all thy works, in the land to which thou art going to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>If thou vowest a vow to the Lord thy God, thou shalt not delay to pay it; for the Lord thy God will surely require it of thee; and it would be a sin in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>If thou dost not chuse to make a vow, it is no sin in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thou must be careful of what have proceeded from thy lips; and offer, in the manner thou hast vowed to the Lord thy God, the gift which thou hast promised with thy mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>If thou comest into thy neighbour's field of standing corn, thou mayst gather ears with thy hands; but thou shalt not put a sickle into thy neighbour's field of standing grain. And if thou comest into thy neighbour's vineyard, thou mayst eat grapes, till thy soul is satisfied, but thou shalt not put any into a vessel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>If any one hath taken a wife, and cohabited with her, and it should happen that she hath not found favour in his sight, because he hath found something unseemly in her, he may write her a bill of divorce, and put it into her hands, and send her away from his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And having gone away, she may become another man's wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But if her last husband hate her, and write her a bill of divorce and put it in her hands and send her away from his house; or if her last husband, who hath taken her to wife, die;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>her former husband, who put her away, shall not be at liberty to return and take her again to wife; for it is an abomination to the Lord thy God; and you must not defile the land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>If any man hath lately taken a wife, he shall not go out to battle, nor shall he be charged with any business. He shall be free at home one year, that he may cheer his wife whom he hath taken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thou shalt not take in pledge an upper, nor a lower milstone, for this is taking a man's life in pledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If any man be found stealing any of his brethren, the children of Israel, or, having got him in his power, selleth him, the thief shall be put to death. So shalt thou remove evil from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Take heed to thyself, that in the touch of the leprosy thou be very careful to act according to all the law which the priests, the Levites, may point out to you. Be careful to do in the manner I commanded you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Remember what the Lord thy God did to Mariam, on the way, as you were coming out of the land of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If a debt of any kind be due to thee from thy neighbour, thou shalt not go into his house to take his pledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thou shalt stand without, and the man who is thy debtor shall bring the pledge out to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And if the man be very poor, thou shalt not go to sleep with his pledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou shalt surely restore him his pledge at the going down of the sun, that he may sleep in his garment, and bless thee, and there shall be mercy for thee in the sight of the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou shalt not withhold the wages of a poor and needy man, whether he be one of thy brethren, or of the strangers who are in thy cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thou shalt pay him his wages on the very day: let not the sun set upon it. For he is poor, and dependeth on it; and he will cry to the Lord against thee, and it will be a sin in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Fathers shall not be put to death for children; nor the children for fathers. Every man shall be put to death for his own sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou shalt not pervert the judgment of the stranger, or the orphan, or the widow. Thou shalt not take the garment of a widow in pledge,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>but remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt, and that thence the Lord thy God redeemed thee; therefore I command thee to do this thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When thou reapest thy harvest in the field, if thou hast forgot a sheaf in thy field, thou shalt not turn back to take it up; it shall be for the stranger, and the orphan, and the widow, that the Lord thy God may bless thee, in all the works of thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when thou gatherest thine olives, thou shalt not turn back to gather what was left behind thee: it shall be for the stranger and the orphan and the widow;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and thou shalt remember that thou wast a stranger in the land of Egypt; there fore I command thee to do this thing. And when thou gatherest in the vintage, thou shalt not glean after thee. The gleanings shall be for the stranger, and the orphan, and the widow;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and thou shalt remember that thou wast a servant in the land of Egypt; therefore I command thee to do this thing.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When a controversy happeneth between men, and they have come to a trial, and the trial is over, and the righteous is acquitted, and the criminal known;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>in case the criminal deserve to be beaten, thou shalt make him lie down, before the judges; and they shall cause him to be beaten, in their presence, according to his wickedness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>With the number of forty stripes they may cause him to be beaten. They shall not exceed that. If thou shouldst proceed to inflict more stripes than these, thy brother will become vile in thy sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thou shalt not muzzle an ox treading out corn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When brothers dwell together, and one of them die, and hath no issue, the wife of him who died shall not marry a man abroad, who is not near of kin. The brother of her husband shall go in unto her, and take her to wife, and cohabit with her;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and the child which she shall bear shall go by the name of him who died, so that his name shall not be blotted out from among Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And if any man decline to take his brother's wife, the woman shall go to the gate, to the senate, and say, My husband's brother refuseth to raise up his brother's name in Israel. My husband's brother hath refused.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thereupon the senate of his city shall send for him, and say to him, Thou must stand up, and say, I will not take her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Upon which his brother's wife shall come, in the presence of the senate, and loose one shoe from his foot, and spit before his face, and addressing him, say, So shall be done to the man who will not build up his brother's house in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And his name shall be called in Israel, The house of him who had his shoe loosed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When men fight together; a man with his brother, if the wife of one of them come to rescue her husband out of the hand of him who is beating him, and stretching forth her hand? take hold of his privities,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>thou shalt cut off her hand. Thine eye shall not have compassion on her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou shalt not have in thy bag different weights, a great and a small;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>nor shall there be in thy house, different measures, a great and a small.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thou shalt have a just and true weight, and thou shalt have a just and true measure; that thy days may be long in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possession;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>for every one who doth these things; every one who committeth injustice, is an abomination to the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Remember what Amalek did to thee by the way, when thou wast coming out of the land of Egypt;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>how he rose up against thee, in the way, and smote thy rear, those who were fainty behind thee. Thou indeed wast hungry, and fainty, and he feared not God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore when the Lord thy God hath given thee rest from all thine enemies around thee, in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possession, thou shalt blot out the name of Amalek from under heaven. Thou must not forget.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now, when thou art come to the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for a possession, and hast taken possession of it, and dwelt therein;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>thou shalt take some of the first fruits of thy land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and put them in a basket, and go to the place which the Lord thy God hath chosen for his name to be there invoked;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and thou shalt go to the priest, who shall be in those days, and say to him, I acknowledge this day to the Lord my God, that I am come to the land which the Lord solemnly promised our fathers to give us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon the priest shall take the basket out of thy hands, and set it down over against the altar of the Lord thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and in the presence of the Lord shall answer, and say, My father left Syria, and went down into Egypt, and sojourned there, with a small number, and became there a great nation, and a vast multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when the Egyptians afflicted us, and humbled us, and imposed upon us hard labours,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and we cried to the Lord our God, the Lord heard our voice. When he saw our affliction, and our labour, and our oppression,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the Lord himself brought us out of Egypt with his great power, and with his strong hand, and outstretched arm, and with great visions, and with signs, and with wonders,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and brought us to this place, and gave us this land; a land flowing with milk and honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now therefore, behold, I have brought this offering of the products of the land, which thou, Lord, hast given me; a land flowing with milk and honey. Then thou shalt leave it before the Lord thy God; and when thou hast worshipped before the Lord thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>thou shalt regale thyself with all the good things which the Lord thy God hath given thee, thou, and thy family, and the Levite, and the proselyte who is with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when thou hast finished tything the tenth of all thy produce in the third year, thou shalt give another tenth to the Levite, and the proselyte, and the orphan, and the widow; that they may eat in thy cities, and be regaled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then thou shalt say before the Lord thy God, I have removed the hallowed things clean out of my house, and have given them to the Levite, and the proselyte, and the orphan, and the widow, according to all the commands which thou hast commanded me. I have not transgressed thy command, nor forgot it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have not, in my mourning, eaten any of them, nor offered any of them in homage to an unclean thing, nor given any of them to the dead. I have hearkened to the voice of the Lord our God. I have done as thou hast commanded me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Look down from thy holy habitation; from heaven, and bless thy people Israel, and this land which thou hast given them, as thou didst solemnly promise our fathers to give us a land flowing with milk and honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>This day the Lord thy God hath commanded thee to practise all these rules of rectitude and these judgments; you shall therefore keep, and perform them, with your whole heart, and with your whole soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou hast this day chosen God to be thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to keep his rules of rectitude, and his judgments, and to hearken to his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the Lord hath this day chosen thee to be a peculiar people to himself, as he hath said, that thou mayst keep his commandments,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and be, as he hath made thee, renowned above all the nations, and a boast, and glorious, and that thou mayst be a people dedicated to the Lord, as he hath spoken.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again Moses, with the senate of Israel, gave a charge, saying, You shall keep all these commandments which I this day command you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When you have crossed the Jordan, into the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee; thou shalt set up for thyself large stones, and plaister them with mortar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and thou shalt write on those stones all the words of this law. Soon as you have crossed the Jordan; when you are come to the land which the Lord the God of thy fathers giveth thee; a land flowing with milk and honey, as the Lord the God of thy fathers promised thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>you shall, immediately after your crossing the Jordan, set up these stones, which I this day command thee, at mount Garizin, and thou shalt plaister them with mortar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and build there an altar to the Lord thy God; an altar of stones. Thou shalt not lift up a tool upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Of unwrought stones thou shalt build the altar to the Lord thy God, and offer upon it whole burnt offerings to the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then thou shalt offer there a sacrifice of thanksgiving, and when thou hast eaten, and art filled, and hast rejoiced before the Lord thy God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>then thou shalt write upon the stones all this law, in the plainest manner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then Moses with the priests, the Levites, spoke to all Israel, saying, Be silent and hear, O Israel. Thou art this day made a people for the Lord thy God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>therefore thou shalt hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, and perform all his commandments, and his rules of rectitude, which I this day command thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then Moses gave a charge to the people that day, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Having crossed the Jordan, these shall stand on mount Garizin to bless the people; Symeon, Levi, Judas, Issachar, Joseph, and Benjamin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And these shall stand at the curse on mount Gaibal, Reuben, Gad, and Aser, Zabulon, Dan, and Nephthaleim:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and the Levites shall address all Israel, and say with a loud voice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Cursed the man who shall make a graven, or molten image, an abomination to the Lord, the work of the hands of artists; though he set it up in a secret place. And all the people shall answer and say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Cursed he who slighteth his father or his mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Cursed he who removeth his neighbour's land mark. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Cursed he who leadeth the blind out of the way. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Cursed he who perverteth the judgment of the stranger, or the orphan, or the widow. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Cursed he who lieth with his father's wife, because he hath uncovered his father's skirt. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Cursed he who lieth with any beast. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Cursed he who lieth with his sister, by the same father, or mother. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Cursed he who lieth with his daughter in law. And all the people shall say, Amen. Cursed he who lieth with the sister of his wife. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Cursed he who smiteth his neighbour secretly. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Cursed he who taketh bribes to slay an innocent person. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Cursed be every man who will not persevere in all the words of this law, to do them. And all the people shall say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now it shall come to pass, that if thou wilt hearken diligently to the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep and perform all these commandments which I this day give thee in charge, the Lord thy God will set thee high above all the nations of the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and all these blessings shall come upon thee, and find thee. If thou wilt hearken diligently to the voice of the Lord thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Blessed shalt thou be in the city; and blessed shalt thou be in the field;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>blessed shall be the fruit of thy body, and the products of thy land, and thy herds, and thy flocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Blessed shall be thy granaries, and thy stores.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Blessed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and blessed when thou goest out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>May the Lord thy God deliver up thine enemies, who rise up against thee, to be smitten before thee. They shall come out against thee one way, and flee before thee seven ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The Lord send upon thee the blessing in thy store houses, and on all the labours of thy hands, in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The Lord establish thee a holy people for himself, as he solemnly promised thy fathers. If thou wilt hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, and walk in all his ways,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>then shall all the nations of the earth see that thou art called by the name of the Lord, and they will be afraid of thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and the Lord thy God will multiply thee, for good, in the offspring of thy body, and in the increase of thy cattle, and in the products of thy ground, in the land which he solemnly promised thy fathers to give thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The Lord open for thee his good treasury, the heaven, to give thy land the rain in due season. May he bless all the works of thy hands, so that thou mayst lend to many nations, and not borrow of them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and that thou mayst rule over many nations, and they not rule over thee. May the Lord establish thee for a head and not for a tail, so that thou mayst be above, and not beneath. If thou wilt hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep all that I this day enjoin thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>thou wilt not turn aside from all the commandments which I this day command thee, either to the right, or to the left, to go after other gods, to serve them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But in case thou wilt not hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God to keep all his commandments which I this day give thee in charge, all these evils shall come upon thee and overtake thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Cursed shalt thou be in the city, and cursed thou in the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Cursed shall be thy granaries, and thy stores.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Cursed shall be the offspring of thy body, and the products of thy land, thy herds and thy flocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Cursed shalt thou be when thou comest in, and cursed thou when thou goest out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The Lord send upon thee want, and famine, and destruction on all the labour of thy hands, until he utterly root thee out, and until he destroy thee quickly, on the account of thy wicked devices. Seeing thou hast forsaken me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>may the Lord make the pestilence cleave to thee, until it utterly consume thee from the land to which thou art going, to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The Lord smite thee with anxiety, and fever, and chilness, and restlessness, and blasting, and mildew, that they may pursue thee until they utterly destroy thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when the heaven over thy head shall be brass, and the earth under thy feet iron,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>may the Lord thy God make the rain of thy land dust, so that dust from heaven may descend until it waste thee, and until it destroy thee speedily.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>May the Lord deliver thee up to slaughter before thine enemies, so that thou mayst go out one way to meet them, and flee seven ways from before them; and be a dispersion among all the kingdoms of the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and your dead carcasses be food for the birds of the air, and the wild beasts of the earth, and there be none to fray them away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The Lord smite thee with the Egyptian boil in thy seat, and with wild fire, and with itching, so that thou canst not be cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The Lord smite thee with madness, and blindness, and astonishment of heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>so that thou mayst grope about at noon day, as a blind man gropeth in darkness; and let him not prosper thy ways, so thou shalt then be injured, and spoiled continually, and there will be none to help thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Thou wilt take a wife, and another man shall have her. Thou wilt build a house, but shall not dwell therein. Thou wilt plant a vineyard, but shalt not gather the grapes thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Thy ox will be slaughtered before thy face, and thou shalt not eat thereof. Thy ass will be taken from thee, and shall not be restored; thy flocks will be given to thine enemies, and there shall be none to help thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>thy sons, and thy daughters, will be given to another nation, and thine eyes will melt in looking at them; there will be no strength in thy hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>A nation, which thou knowest not will eat the fruits of thy land, and all thy labours; and thou shalt be injured, and oppressed continually,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and driven to madness at the sight of thine eyes, which thou shalt see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The Lord smite thee with a grievous boil on thy knees, and on thy legs, so that thou canst not be healed, from the sole of thy feet to the crown of thy head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>The Lord carry away thee, and thy rulers, whom thou mayst set over thee, to a nation which neither thou nor thy fathers knew, that thou mayst there serve other gods; stocks and stones;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and be there for a bye word, and a proverb, and a public example to all the nations to which the Lord shall bring thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>There thou shalt carry out much seed into the field, and shalt bring little home, for the locust shall devour it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>thou shalt plant a vineyard and dress it; but shalt not press out wine, nor regale thyself from it; for worms shall eat it up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Thou shalt have plantations of olive trees, in all thy borders, but shalt not be anointed with oil, for thine olive tree shall cast its fruit:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>thou shalt beget sons and daughters, but shalt not have them with thee; for they shall go into captivity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>All thy trees and the products of thy land, shall be consumed with blasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>The stranger who is with thee shall rise higher and higher; but thou shalt fall lower and lower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>He shall lend to thee; and thou shalt not lend to him: He shall be head; and thou shalt be tail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>All these curses shall actually come upon thee, and pursue thee, and overtake thee, until he root thee out, and utterly destroy thee because thou didst not hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, to keep his commandments, and his rules of rectitude, which he commanded thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And they shall be signs for thee, and wonders for thine offspring forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Because thou didst not serve the Lord thy God with gladness, and with a good understanding, for the abundance of all things;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>therefore thou shalt serve thine enemies, whom the Lord will send against thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in want of all things, and thou shalt wear a yoke of iron on thy neck, until it utterly destroy thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>The Lord will bring against thee a nation from afar; from the extremity of the earth, with the impetuosity of an eagle; A nation whose voice thou shalt not understand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>a nation of an unblushing countenance, which will not respect the person of an elder, nor compassionate a youth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And it shall devour the increase of thy cattle, and the products of thy land, so as not to leave thee corn, wine, oil, herds or flocks, until it hath destroyed thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>and wasted thee in thy cities; until they have demolished thy high, and strong walls, in which thou hast placed thy confidence, throughout thy whole land. And when he shall afflict thee in thy cities which he hath given thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>in thy siege, and in the affliction, with which thine enemy shall afflict thee, thou shalt eat the offspring of thy body; the flesh of thy sons, and thy daughters, whom he gave thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>The tender, and very delicate man who is with thee, will look with an evil eye on his brother, and on the wife in his bosom, and the remaining children which may be left him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>so as not to give one of them any of the flesh of his sons, which he may be eating, because he hath nothing left him in the siege, and in that affliction of thine with which thine enemies will afflict thee, in all thy cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>And the tender, and very delicate woman among you, whose foot never ventured to tread the ground because of her delicateness, and effeminacy will look with an evil eye on her husband in her bosom, and on her son, and her daughter,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>even the female infant she bore, or the male child which she may have brought forth; for on the account of the want of all things, she will eat these secretly in thy siege, and in that affliction of thine with which thine enemy will afflict thee in thy cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>If thou wilt not hearken to do all the words of this law, which are written in this book, to fear this glorious, this wonderful name, The Lord Thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>the Lord will make thy plagues, and the plagues of thy seed, wonderful beyond conception; he will make them great, and marvellous, and thy diseases sore, and lasting,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>and will bring upon thee all the affliction of Egypt; that grievous affliction which thou didst dread on their account, and they shall cleave to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>The Lord will also bring upon thee every sickness, and every plague, which is not written, and every one which is written in this book of the law, until he root thee out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>And you shall be left few in number, instead of being, as you were, like the stars of heaven for multitude. Because thou didst not hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>therefore it shall come to pass, that as the Lord delighted in you to do you good, and to multiply you; so the Lord will rejoice over you, in rooting you out; and you shall be removed speedily from the land to which thou art going to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>And the Lord thy God will scatter thee among all the nations, from one extremity of the earth to the other; and thou shalt there serve other gods; stocks and stones, which neither thou, nor thy fathers have known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>But even among these nations he will not give thee rest, nor shall there be any rest for the sole of thy foot. Indeed the Lord will give thee there a strange trembling heart, and failing eyes, and a desponding soul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>and thy life shall hang in suspence before thine eyes, and thou shalt be in terror, day and night, and have no assurance of thy life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>In the morning thou wilt say; How will it be with me in the evening! And in the evening thou wilt say, How may it be with me in the morning! on account of the terror of thy heart with which thou shalt be affrighted, and on account of the sights of thine eyes which thou shalt see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>And the Lord will send thee back into Egypt, in ships, (by the way which I ordered thou shalt see it no more:) and thou shalt there be exposed to sale to your enemies, for bond men and bond women, and there will be no purchaser.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>These were the words of the covenant, which the Lord commanded Moses to state to the children of Israel, in the land of Moab, over and above the covenant which he had made with them at Choreb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then Moses called all the sons of Israel, and said to them, You have seen all the things which the Lord did in Egypt, before your eyes, to Pharao and his servants, and all his land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>those great trials which your eyes have seen, those signs, and those great wonders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now hath not the Lord God given you a heart to know, and eyes to see, and ears to hear, even at this day?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When he led you forty years in the wilderness, your clothes did not grow too old, nor were your shoes worn out from your feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>You did not eat bread, nor drink wine, nor strong drink, that you might know that the Lord lam is your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when you came to this place, and Seon, king of Esebon, and Og king of Basan, came out to meet us in battle, we smote them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and took their land, and I have given it to Reuben, and Gad, and to the half of the tribe of Manasses:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>you shall therefore be careful to perform all the words of this covenant. In order that you might fully comprehend all that you are to do,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>you have this day stood, all of you, before the Lord your God, the chiefs of your tribes, and your senate, and your judges, and your officers, every man of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>your wives, and your children, and the stranger who is in your camp, from the hewer of wood to the drawer of water,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>to enter into a covenant with the Lord your God, and into the curses which the Lord thy God this day stateth to thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>that he may establish thee a people for himself. So he himself will be thy God, as he said to thee, and as he hath sworn to thy fathers, Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now I make this covenant, and this oath, not with you only,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but both with those who are here this day, with you before the Lord your God, and with those who are not here with you this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Inasmuch as you know how we lived in the land of Egypt, and have seen, as we passed through the nations, through which you passed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>their abominations and their idols, wood and stone, silver and gold, which are among them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>is there any man among you, or any woman, or family, or tribe, whose understanding hath turned them from the Lord your God, to go and serve the gods of those nations? Is there any such root among you, springing up for gall and bitterness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now in case any one shall hear the words of this curse, and bless himself in his heart, saying, Good luck betide me! I will walk in the error of my own heart, that the sinner may not involve the guiltless in ruin with himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>God will not be propitious to him, but most assuredly the anger of the Lord, and his indignation, will then be kindled against that man; and all the curses of this covenant, which are written in this book, shall cleave to him; and the Lord will blot out his name from under heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The Lord will indeed separate him, from all the children of Israel, according to all the curses of this covenant, which are written in this book of the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And when the generations to come; your children who shall rise up after you, and the stranger who may come from a far distant country, will say; when they shall see the plagues of that land, and the diseases thereof, which the Lord hath sent upon it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>brimstone and burnt salt; when through the whole land there shall be no sowing; no natural productions, no verdure on it, a destruction like that of Sodom and Gomorra, Adama and Seboim, which the Lord overthrew with wrath and indignation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When all the nations shall say, Why hath the Lord dealt thus with this land? What hath occasioned this great fierceness of indignation?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then they will say, Because they forsook the covenant of the Lord, the God of their fathers, which he made with their fathers, when he brought them out of the land of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and went and served strange gods, which they did not know, and which he had not arranged for them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>therefore the Lord was provoked to wrath against this land, to bring upon it all the curses which are written in the book of the law;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and the Lord rooted them out from their land, with wrath, and anger, and very great indignation, and cast them out into another land, as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The things which are secret are for the Lord our God; but the things which are manifest are for us and our children forever, that we may perform all the words of this law;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>therefore when all these things have come upon thee, the blessing and the curse, which I have set before thee; and thou shalt receive them into thy heart, among all the nations where the Lord may have dispersed thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and shalt turn to the Lord thy God, and hearken to his voice, according to all that I this day command thee, with thy whole heart and with thy whole soul;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>the Lord will heal thy sins, and have compassion on thee, and gather thee again out of all the nations among which the Lord hath dispersed thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Though thy dispersion may have been from one end of the earth to the other, thence the Lord thy God will gather thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and thence the Lord thy God will take thee, and thence thy God will bring thee, into the land which thy fathers possessed, and thou shalt possess it: And he will deal kindly with thee, and make thee more numerous than thy fathers:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the Lord will purify thy heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love the Lord thy God with thy whole heart, and with thy whole soul, that thou mayst live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the Lord thy God will lay all these curses upon thine enemies, and upon them who hate thee, and have persecuted thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When thou shalt return, and hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, and perform these commandments of his, which I this day enjoin thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the Lord thy God will bless thee in every work of thy hands, in the offspring of thy body, and in the increase of thy cattle, and in the products of thy land; for the Lord thy God will turn again to rejoice over thee for good, as he rejoiced over thy fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>if thou wilt hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God to keep his commandments, and his rules of rectitude, and these judgments of his which are written in this book of the law; if thou wilt turn to the Lord thy God with thy whole heart, and with thy whole soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For this command which I this day give thee in charge is not grievous, nor is it far from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>It is not in heaven above, that thou shouldst say, Who will ascend for us into heaven, and bring it to us, that we may hear and do it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Nor is it beyond the sea, that thou shouldst say, Who will cross the sea for us, and bring it to us, and let us hear it, that we may do it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The word is very near thee, in thy mouth and in thy heart, and in thy hand, to do it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Behold I have this day set before thee Life and Death, Good and Evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If thou wilt hearken to the commandments of the Lord thy God which I this day enjoin thee, to love the Lord thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to keep his rules of rectitude, and his judgments, you shall live, and multiply, and the Lord thy God will bless thee in all the land to which thou art going, there to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But if thy heart turn aside, and thou wilt not hearken, but go astray, and worship other gods, and serve them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I announce to thee this day, that you shall surely perish, and shall not prolong your lives in the land, to which you are about to cross the Jordan, to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I call heaven and earth this day to witness against you, that I have set Life and Death, the Blessing and the Curse before you. Chuse thou life, that thou and thy seed may live,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>by loving the Lord thy God, and hearkening to his voice, and cleaving to him. For this is thy life, and the lengthening of thy days, to dwell in the land which the Lord solemnly promised thy fathers, Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob, that he would give them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Moses had finished speaking all these words, to all the children of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he said to them, I am now a hundred and twenty years old. I shall no more be able to go out, and come in before you: for the Lord hath said to me, Thou shalt not cross the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The Lord thy God, who goeth before thee, will himself drive out those nations from before thee, and thou shalt possess them; and Joshua is to go before thee, as the Lord hath spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The Lord thy God will indeed do to them as he did to Seon, and Og, the two kings of the Amorites, who were on this side the Jordan, and to their land; in the same manner as the Lord rooted them out,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and delivered them up to you. And you shall do to them as I have commanded you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Act manfully, and be strong; fear not, nor be faint hearted, nor terrified at them; for the Lord thy God, who goeth before you, is with you; is among you. May he never leave thee, nor forsake thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then Moses called Joshua, and said to him before all Israel, Be courageous, and strong; for thou shalt go before this people, into the land which the Lord solemnly promised your fathers to give them; and thou shalt put them in possession of it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the Lord, who marcheth with thee, will not leave thee nor forsake thee. Fear not, nor be dismayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now Moses had written the words of this law in a book; so he gave it to the priests, the children of Levi, who carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and to the elders of the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Moses gave them a charge on that day saying, At the end of every seven years, at the Solemnity of the release, during the festival of tabernacles,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>when all Israel assemble, to appear before the Lord your God, in the place which the Lord shall chuse; you shall read this law before all Israel, in their hearing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let the people be assembled, the men, and the women, and the children, and the proselyte who is in your cities, that they may hear, and that they may learn to fear the Lord your God; and let them hearken to do all the words of this law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And let their children who have not known, hearken, and learn to fear the Lord thy God, all the days they live in the land to which you are going, to cross the Jordan, there to take possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now when the Lord said to Moses, Behold the time of thy death approacheth, call Joshua, and stand at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony, and I will give him a charge; thereupon Moses went with Joshua to the tabernacle of the testimony, and they stood at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and the Lord descended in a cloud, and stood at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony, and while the pillar of the cloud stood at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the Lord said to Moses, Behold when thou sleepest with thy fathers, this people will rise up, and go a whoring after the strange gods of the land to which they are going. And when they forsake me, and break my covenant which I have made with them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I shall be provoked to wrath against them that day, and I will leave them, and turn away my face from them, and they shall be devoured. And when many evils and afflictions shall befal them, then will one say in that day, Because the Lord my God is not with me, these evils have befallen me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But I will turn away my face from them, on that day, because of all their wickedness which they have committed, because they have turned to strange gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now therefore write the words of this Ode and teach it to the children of Israel, and put it into their mouth, that this Ode may be an open witness for me among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For when I bring them into that good land, which I solemnly promised their fathers to give them, a land flowing with milk and honey, they will eat, and be satiated, and they will turn to strange gods, and serve them, and provoke me, and break my covenant;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but this Ode will rise up, and witness against them; for it shall never be forgotten out of their mouth, nor out of the mouth of their seed: for I know their wickedness, what they do even now before I have brought them into that good land which I solemnly promised their fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So Moses wrote the Ode that day and taught it to the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the Lord gave a charge to Joshua, and said, Be courageous, and strong, for thou shalt conduct the children of Israel into the land which the Lord solemnly promised them, and he will be with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now when Moses had made an end of writing all the words of this law in a book, even to the close,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>he gave a charge to the Levites, who carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Take this book of the law; and put it by the side of the ark of the covenant of the Lord your God; and it shall be there for a witness against thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for I know thy contentious disposition, and thy stiff neck. For even now while I am yet alive with you, you have been rebellious against God; how then can it be otherwise after my death?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Assemble before me the heads of your tribes, and your elders, and your judges, and your under officers, that I may speak in their hearing all these words and call heaven and earth to witness against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For I know that after my death you will commit iniquity, and turn aside out of the way which I commanded you, and evils will befal you in the latter days, because you will do evil before the Lord, to provoke him to wrath by the works of your hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then for a conclusion Moses spoke in the hearing of all the congregation the words of this Ode.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="32">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Listen, heaven, and I will speak, And let the earth hear the words of my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Let my doctrine be expected like rain, And my words distil as the dew; Like gentle rain on the tender herb, And like a heavy shower on the grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Since I have proclaimed the name of the Lord, Ascribe ye majesty to our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He is God, his works are perfect; All his ways are acts of judgment; A faithful God; he doth no injustice; Righteous and holy is the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They have sinned! blemished children are not his. Crooked and perverse generation!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Do ye thus requite the Lord? Are the people so foolish and unwise? Did not this thy father purchase thee? Did he not make and fashion thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Remember the days of old; Consider the years of ages past; Ask thy father; he can tell thee; Thine elders; they can inform thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When the Most High divided nations; When he dispersed the children of Adam, He settled the boundaries of nations, According to the number of God's messengers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the Lord's portion was his people Jacob; Israel was his lot of inheritance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He sustained them in the wilderness, In the drought of heat, in a land without water. He led them about, and instructed them; He kept them as the apple of his eye.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>As an eagle would defend his nest, And, when anxious for his young, would spread out his wings, and receive them, And bare them up on his shoulders;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The Lord alone conducted them, And there was not a strange god with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He brought them up to the strength of this land, He fed them with the products of the fields; They sucked honey out of a rock, And oil out of a flinty rock;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>With butter of kine, and with milk of sheep; With the fattest of lambs and rams, young bulls and goats, And with bread of the choicest wheat; And they drank wine, the pure juice of the grape.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>When Jacob had eaten and was filled, Then he who was beloved began to kick; He grew fat, waxed thick, and became corpulent, Then he forsook the God who made him; And apostatised from God his saviour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They exasperated me with strange gods, With their abominations they provoked me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They sacrificed to demons, and not to God; To gods, which they had never known, Which had started up, new and fictitious, Of which their fathers had no knowledge,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The God who begot thee, thou hast forsaken, And hast forgot the God who nourished thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the Lord saw, and was provoked to jealousy; He was provoked at the temper of his sons and daughters,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and said, I will turn away my face from them, And shew what shall befal them in the latter days. Because they are a perverse generation; Children, who have no faith in them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They have provoked me by what is not God; Have exasperated me with their idols; I therefore will provoke them by what is not a nation, By a foolish nation I will vex them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Since a fire is kindled because of my wrath, It shall burn down to the lowest Hades; It shall consume the land, and the products thereof; It shall set on fire the foundations of mountains:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I will assemble evils against them, And hurl my bolts at them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>While they are wasting by famine, and voracious birds; The burning carbuncle also shall be incurable; I will send against them the teeth of wild beasts, With the venom of serpents, trailing on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Abroad the sword shall bereave them of children, And in their chambers terror shall destroy. The youth shall perish with the young virgin, The sucking infant with the venerable sage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I had determined to disperse them, And cause the remembrance of them to cease among men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Had it not been for the temper of enemies; That the adversaries might not out live them; That they might not fall upon them at once; Lest they should say, Our own high hand, And not the Lord, hath done all this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>It is a nation devoid of counsel; There is no knowledge among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>They have not bent their minds to understand; Let them lay up these things for time to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>How could one man chase a thousand, And two put myriads to flight, Had not God cast them off; Had not the Lord delivered them up?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For their gods are not like our God; And our enemies are without understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>As their vine is from the vine of Sodom And their shoot from that of Gomorra; Their cluster of grapes will be a cluster of gall; A cluster of bitterness it shall be to them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Their wine shall be the venom of dragons; The incurable venom of asps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Behold! are not these things stored up with me? And sealed up among my treasures?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>In the day of vengeance I will requite, When their foot shall be supplanted. Because the day of destruction is nigh for them, Therefore at hand are the things prepared for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Because the Lord will judge his people; When he shall be appeased for his servants, (For he saw that they were enfeebled, Made faint by hostile invasions and dejected)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then the Lord said, where are their gods; The gods in which they placed their confidence?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>The fat of whose sacrifices you ate And drank the wine of their libations? Let them arise and help you, And let them be your protectors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>See! See! that I am the Self existent, And that there is no God besides me; I kill, and I can cause to live, I can smite and I can heal, And none can rescue out of my hand:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For I can lift up my hand to heaven, And swear by my right hand, and say, as I live forever,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>I will make my sword sharp as lightning, And my hand will support judgment; And I will execute vengeance on mine enemies, And make retribution to them who hate me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>I will make my arrows drunk with blood, And my sword shall devour flesh With the blood of slain and captives. From the head of enemy chiefs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Rejoice, heavens, with him, And let all the angels of God worship him: Rejoice, nations, with his people, And let all the children of God rely on him: For he avengeth the blood of his children, And will judge, and execute vengeance on his enemies, To them who hate him he will render retribution, And the Lord will purify the land of his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Now on that day when Moses had written this Ode and taught it to the children of Israel; and he, and Joshua the son of Nave, had come, and spoken all the words of this law in the hearing of the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Moses concluded his speech to all Israel with this address to them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Attend with your heart to all these words which I this day testify to you, and which you are to give in charge to your children, that they may keep, and perform all the words of this law;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>for this is not a vain thing for you; for it is your life; and, for the sake of this word, you shall prolong your days in the land to which you are going, to cross the Jordan to take possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to Moses that day, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Go up the mountain Abarim, to that mount Nabo, which is in the land of Moab, fronting Jericho, and take a view of the land of Chanaan, which I give to the children of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>and die on the mount to which thou goest up, and be gathered to thy people, in the same manner as thy brother Aaron died on mount Or, and was gathered to his people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>because you disobeyed my word among the children of Israel, at the water of strife, at Kades, in the wilderness of Sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Because you did not hallow me among the children of Israel, thou shalt see the land at a distance, but shalt not go in thither.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="33">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now this is the blessing with which Moses, the man of God blessed the children of Israel, before his death;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he said, The Lord came from Sina And shined upon us out of Seir; He hasted from mount Paran, With myriads from Kades; His angels with him on his right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He compassionated his people; All the sanctified are under thy sway, But these are immediately under thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>From His words Moses received the law Which he gave in charge to us, An inheritance for the assemblies of Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Let Him therefore be chief among the beloved. When the chiefs of peoples assemble with the tribes of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let Reuben live and not die, And Symeon though he be few in number.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now this was the blessing of Juda Hear, Lord, the voice of Juda! And until thou comest to his people; Let his hands contend for them, And be thou his help from enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And of Levi he said Assign ye to Levi his manifestations, And his truth to this man for the Holy One Whom they tried at Temptation. Whom they reviled at the water of Contradiction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>With regard to him who saith to his father and to his mother I have not beheld thee, And hath not acknowledged his brethren, And hath renounced his own children, He it is who hath observed thine Oracles And diligently kept thy covenant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Let them explain thy rules of rectitude for Jacob And thy law for Israel: Let them lay incense continually, When thou art angry, on thine altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Bless, Lord, his endeavours, And accept the works of his hands. Pierce the loins of enemies, Who have risen up against him: And let them who hate him never rise up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And of Benjamin he said, Beloved! He shall dwell securely under the Lord. God overshadoweth him continually, And hath taken up his rest between his shoulders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And of Joseph he said, His land is a special blessing of the Lord On account of heavenly seasons and dew, And on account of abysses of fountains from beneath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And on account of the productions, in due season Of the sun's revolutions and the changes of the moon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>As his land of plenty is beautified With summits of ancient mountains And with summits of everlasting hills;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So may the things acceptable To him who appeared in the bush, Come upon the head of Joseph; He indeed is glorified In being the head over brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>His beauty is that of a firstling bull, His horns are the horns of an Unicorn, With these he will push the nations at once, Even from the limits of the land. These are the myriads of Ephraim; And these the thousands of Manasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And of Zabulon he said, Rejoice, Zabulon, in thine outgoings; And let Issachar rejoice in his abodes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>They shall utterly root out nations. And there you shall invoke, And there offer the sacrifice of righteousness. For the riches of the sea shall feed thee, And a commerce with the dwellers on the sea coast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And of Gad he said Blessed is he who enlargeth Gad. Like a lion he lay down to rest, Having broken an arm and a chief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He took a view of his portion Because land was there divided. When chiefs assembled with the leaders of tribes; The Lord executed Justice And determined his cause with Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And of Dan he said Dan is a lion's whelp; He will make excursions beyond Basan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And of Nephthaleim he said, Nephthaleim hath abundance of good things; May he be filled with blessings from the Lord! He shall possess the west and the south.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And of Aser he said, Aser is blessed with children, He will be acceptable to his brethren. He shall bathe his foot in oil,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>His shoe shall be iron and brass. As thy days so shall be thy strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>There is none like the God of the Beloved. He who rideth on the heaven is thy helper, And he is mighty to give support.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The governance of God will protect thee When under the power of everlasting arms. He will drive out the enemy before thee, Saying, Be devoted to destruction!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And Israel shall dwell securely alone, In the land of Jacob, fed with corn and wine: And the heaven shall drop with dew for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Blessed art thou, Israel! Who is like thee, people saved by the Lord! Thy helper will protect thee, His sword shall be thy boast, Thine enemies shall submit to thee, And thou shalt ride upon their neck.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="34">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Moses went up from Araboth Moab to mount Nabo, to the top of Phasga, which is over against Jericho, and the Lord shewed him all the land of Galaad, even to Dan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and all the land of Nephthaleim, and all the land of Ephraim, and Manasses, and all the land of Juda, even to the farther sea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the wilderness, and the country around Jericho, the city of palm trees, even to Segor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the Lord said to Moses, This is the land which I solemnly promised to Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob, saying, To your seed I will give it. I have pointed it out to thine eyes, but thou shalt not go thither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So Moses the servant of the Lord died, by the command of the Lord, in the land of Moab;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and he was buried at Gai near the house of Phogor. But none knoweth his sepulchre at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Though Moses was an hundred and twenty years old, his eyes were not dim, nor was his natural strength abated.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the children of Israel mourned for Moses, in Araboth Moab, by the Jordan, over against Jericho, thirty days. And when the days of mourning for Moses were fulfilled,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>as Joshua son of Nave was filled with a spirit of wisdom, (for Moses had laid his hands upon him) the children of Israel hearkened to him, and did as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But there no more arose a prophet in Israel like Moses, whom the Lord knew face to face,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>in all the signs and wonders which the Lord sent him to do in the land of Egypt, on Pharao and his servants, and on all his land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the great miracles, and the strong hand, which Moses exhibited in the sight of all Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>