<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After the death of Moses, the Lord spoke to Joshua, son of Nave, the lieutenant of Moses, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>My servant Moses is dead, now therefore arise, and cross the Jordan, thou and all the people, into the land which I give them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Every place, on which you tread with the sole of your feet, I will give you, as I said to Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The wilderness, and yonder Antilibanus, to the river, the great river Euphrates, and to the farthest sea, at the setting of the sun, shall be your boundaries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Not a man shall withstand you all the days of thy life. As I was with Moses, so will I be with thee. I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Be strong and of good courage; for thou shalt parcel out to this people the land, which I solemnly promised their fathers to give to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Therefore be strong, and courageous, to watch, and to do as my servant Moses commanded. Thou must not deviate from them, to the right or to the left. That thou mayst clearly understand all that thou art to do:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the book of the Law must never be out of thy mouth. Thou must study it day and night, that thou mayst know how to do all that are written. Then shalt thou be prospered; and thou wilt make thy ways prosperous; and then thou shalt have a good understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Behold I have commanded thee; be strong and courageous: fear not, nor be dismayed; for the Lord thy God is with thee withersoever thou goest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon this Joshua gave orders to the officers of the people, saying;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Go through the camp of the people, and give them orders, saying, Prepare all necessary provisions; for in three days you are to cross the Jordan, to go in and take possession of the land which the Lord the God of your fathers giveth you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Joshua said to Reuben, and Gad, and to the half of the tribe of Manasses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Remember what Moses the servant of the Lord commanded you saying; The Lord your God hath given you rest, and hath given you this land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Let your wives, and your children, and your cattle abide in the land which he hath given you; but you, all your able bodied men, well equipt, shall cross over before your brethren, and assist them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>until the Lord our God shall give your brethren rest, as well as you; and until they possess the land which the Lord our God giveth them. Then you shall return, every one to his possession, which Moses gave you on the east side of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thereupon they answered and said to Joshua, All that thou commandest we will do. And wherever thou sendest us we will go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>As we have hearkened to Moses in all things, so will we hearken to thee. Let but the Lord our God be with thee, as he was with Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and whosoever shall disobey thee, and not hearken to all thy commands which thou shalt give him let him be put to death. But be thou strong and courageous.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now Joshua son of Nave had sent from Sat tin two young men to spy, saying, Go up, and take a view of the land, and particularly of Jericho. And the two young men, having set out, entered Jericho, and went to the house of a harlot, whose name was Rahab, and lodged there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And news being carried to the king of Jericho, saying, Some men of the children of Israel are come here to spy the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>the king of Jericho sent a message to Rahab, saying, Bring out the men, who came to thy house to night; for they are come to spy the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now the woman had taken the two men, and hid them: so she spoke to the messengers, saying, The men came to me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but at dark, when the gate was shutting, the men went out, and I do not know where they are gone. Pursue them: perhaps you may overtake them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now she had taken them up to the top of the house, and concealed them under flax, which was piled up for her on the top of the house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the men pursued them by the way to the Jordan, to the fords, and the gate was shut.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So when the pursuers were gone after them, she went up to the men, on the top of the house, before they had gone to sleep,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and said to them, I know that the Lord hath given you this land; for the dread of you is fallen upon us:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for we have heard that the Lord God dried up the Red sea on your account, when you came out of Egypt, and all that he hath done to the two kings of the Amorites who were on the borders of the Jordan, to Seon and Og, whom you have utterly destroyed:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and, upon hearing these things, we became faint hearted, and there was no spirit in any of us because of you. Since, then, the Lord your God is God in heaven above, and in the earth beneath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>swear now to me by the Lord your God, because I shew mercy to you, that you will shew mercy to my father's house;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and that you will save alive my father's household, my mother, and my brothers, and all my family, and all that belong to them, and that you will deliver my soul from death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the men said to her, Our life for yours even to death. Then she said to them. When the Lord delivereth up to you this city, you will deal mercifully and truly with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So she lowered them down through a window.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now she said to them, Flee to the mountains, lest the pursuers meet you, and hide yourselves there three days, until they who are in pursuit of you have returned, and afterwards you may go your way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the men said to her, We are sincere in the oath which we have sworn to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold when we enter any part of the city, thou shalt put up this signal; Thou shalt tye this scarlet rope to the window, through which thou shalt have let us down; and thou shalt bring thy father, and thy mother, and thy brothers, and all thy father's household, home to thy house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And it shall be that whoever goeth out of the door of thy house, into the street, shall incur the guilt of his own death, and we shall be clear of blame in regard to this oath which we have sworn to thee. But for all who are with thee in the house we will be answerable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But if any one injure us, or if thou disclose these our terms, we shall be clear of this oath to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And she said to them, Let it be as you say.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So she dismissed them, and they went away, and came to the hilly country, and stayed there three days. And the pursuers examined all the roads, but did not find them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then the two young men turned, and came down from the mountain, and crossed over to Joshua son of Nave, and told him all that had happened to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they said to him, Because the Lord hath delivered up all that land into our hands, therefore all the inhabitants of the land are in the utmost consternation because of us.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thereupon Joshua arose early next morning, and removed from Sattin; and having come to the Jordan, they halted there some time before they crossed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And after three days the officers went through the camp,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and gave a charge to the people, saying, When you see the Ark of the covenant of the Lord our God, and our priests, and the Levites carrying it, you shall remove from your places, and march after it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But let there be a considerable distance between you and it. You shall keep at the distance of about two thousand cubits. You must not come near it, that you may know the way you are to march; for you have never heretofore gone this way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Joshua said to the people, Purify yourselves against to-morrow; for to-morrow the Lord will do wonders among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when Joshua said to the priests, Take up the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and march before the people; and the priests had taken up the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and were marching before the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>the Lord said to Joshua, This day I begin to exalt thee in the sight of all the children of Israel, that they may know that as I was with Moses, so I will be with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now therefore command the priests who are carrying the ark of the covenant, and say, Soon as you are come to a part of the water of the Jordan, you shall halt at the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then Joshua said to the sons of Israel, Draw near, and hear the word of the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>By this you will know that the living God is among you, and that he will surely root out from before you the Chananite, and the Chettite, and the Pherezite, and the Evite, and the Amorite, and Gergasite, and the Jebusite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Behold the ark of the covenant of the Lord of the whole earth is about to cross the Jordan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and it shall come to pass, that when the feet of the priests who are carrying the ark of the covenant of the Lord of the whole earth shall rest in the water of the Jordan, the water of the Jordan shall fail, and the water which is coming down shall be stopped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So the people removed from their tents to cross the Jordan, and the priests carried the Ark of the covenant of the Lord before the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And soon as the priests who were carrying the ark of the covenant came to the Jordan, and the feet of the priests, who were carrying the ark of the covenant of the Lord, were dipped into a part of the water of the Jordan, though the Jordan overflowed all its banks, as in the days of wheat harvest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>yet the waters coming down from above stopped. They stopped like one solid mass, reaching a great way back, even to a part of Kariathiarim; and the water below flowed down into the sea of Araba, the salt sea, until it was entirely gone, and the people stood over against Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then the priests who carried the Ark of the covenant of the Lord, stood on dry ground, and all the children of Israel crossed over on dry ground, until all the people had finished crossing the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when all the people had entirely crossed the Jordan, the Lord spoke to Joshua, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Take men from among the people, one from every tribe,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and give them orders. And you shall take up, out of the middle of the Jordan, twelve smooth stones, and carry them with you, and place them in your encampment, wherever you encamp to night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So Joshua called out twelve men of eminent dignity from among the children of Israel, one from every tribe,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and said to them, Go on before me in the presence of the Lord, into the middle of the Jordan, and let every one take up thence a stone, and carry it on his shoulders, according to the number of the twelve tribes of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>that they may be to you an everlasting memorial; that when thy son shall hereafter ask thee, saying, What are these stones to us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>thou mayst explain them to thy son, and say, Because the river Jordan dried up at the presence of the Ark of the covenant of the Lord of the whole earth, when it crossed it, therefore you shall have these stones for an everlasting memorial for the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Accordingly these sons of Israel did as the Lord commanded Joshua, and having taken up twelve stones, out of the midst of the Jordan, as the Lord commanded Joshua, when the Israelites had done crossing, they carried them with them to the place of encampment, and deposited them there;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and Joshua caused twelve other stones to be placed in the Jordan, in the very spot under the feet of the priests who carried the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and they are there at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now the priests, who carried the ark of the covenant, stood in the Jordan, until Joshua had executed all that the Lord commanded him to declare to the people. And the people hasted and crossed over.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when all the people had done crossing, then the Ark of the covenant of the Lord crossed over, with the stones before them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, crossed over well armed before the children of Israel, as Moses had commanded them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Forty thousand, well equipped for war, crossed over before the Lord, in battle array, to the city Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>On that day the Lord magnified Joshua in the sight of the whole race of Israel, and they feared him, as they did Moses all the days of his life,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now when the Lord spoke to Joshua, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Command the priests who carry the ark of the covenant of the testimony of the Lord, to come up out of the Jordan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Joshua had commanded the priests, saying, Come up out of the Jordan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>it came to pass that as soon as the priests who carried the ark of the covenant of the Lord came up out of the Jordan, and had set their feet on the land, the water of the Jordan rushed impetuously to its place, and overflowed all its banks, as it did before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now the people came up out of the Jordan on the tenth day of the first month, and the children of Israel encamped at Galgala, on the eastern border of Jericho;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Joshua set up at Galgala, the twelve stones which he had taken out of the Jordan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and said, When your children ask you, saying, What stones are these?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Tell your children that Israel crossed that Jordan on dry ground,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>the Lord our God having dried up the water of the Jordan before them, until they crossed over, as the Lord our God had done to the Red sea, which the Lord our God dried up before us, until we passed through it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>that all the nations of the earth might know, that the power of the Lord is great, and that you may worship the Lord our God by every thing which you do.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when the kings of the Amorites, who were on the border of the Jordan, and the kings of Phoenicia, who were on the sea coast, heard that the Lord God had dried up the river Jordan before the Israelites, when they crossed, their hearts were melted, and they were struck with consternation, and there was no spirit in them because of the Israelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And at that time the Lord said to Joshua, Make thee stone knives of the hardest flint, and having again a fixed abode, circumcise the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So Joshua made sharp knives of stone, and circumcised the children of Israel at the place called Hill of foreskins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And in this manner Joshua purified the children of Israel; All who had been born on the way, and all who had formerly been uncircumcised, when they came out of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>all these Joshua circumcised; for Israel had been led about forty two years in the wilderness of Mabdaritis, therefore the most of them were uncircumcised,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>being the children of those warriors who came out of the land of Egypt, who disobeyed the commands of God, and to whom he denounced, that they should not see the land which the Lord solemnly promised their fathers that he would give; a land flowing with milk and honey;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and instead of them he raised up these their children, whom Joshua circumcised, because, being born on the way, they were uncircumcised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And being now circumcised, they were to continue there at rest, in the camp, until they were healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the Lord said to Joshua son of Nave, This day I have taken away from you the reproach of Egypt. So he called the name of that place Galgala.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And on the fourteenth of the same month, towards evening, the children of Israel pre 11 pared the passover, on the confines of Jericho, in the plain of Jordan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and ate of the corn of the land, unleavened cakes and parched corn. On that very day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>after they had eaten the corn of the land, the manna ceased, and there was no more a supply of manna for the children of Israel. So they foraged the country of the Phoenicians that year.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now when Joshua was by Jericho, he raised his eyes, and saw a man standing before him, with a drawn sword in his hand, upon which Joshua, advancing, said to him, Art thou one of us or of our enemies?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he said to him, I am the captain general of the host of the Lord, just arrived. At this Joshua prostrated himself, with his face to the ground, and said to him, My lord, what dost thou command thy servant?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Lord's captain general said to Joshua, Loose the sandals from thy feet, for the place on which thou didst stand is holy ground.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>(Now Jericho was shut up, and barricaded, so that none came out of it, nor went in.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Joshua, Behold, I deliver into thy hand, Jericho, and the king thereof, who is in it, and the mighty men of valour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore array thou the warriors around it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when you blow the trumpets,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>let all the people at the same time shout; and upon their shouting, the walls of the city will fall of their own accord; and all the people shall enter, every one straight forward into the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thereupon Joshua son of Nave went to the priests,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and spoke to them, saying, Order the people to march round, and encompass the city, and let the warriors march armed before the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and let the seven priests, who have the seven holy trumpets, march also before the Lord, and blow a long blast. And let the ark of the covenant of the Lord accompany them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let the warriors march before, and the priests follow in the rear, after the ark of the covenant of the Lord, blowing the trumpets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Joshua gave a charge to the people, saying, Shout not, nor let any one hear your voice, till the day when He shall command you to shout. Then you shall shout.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So when the ark of the covenant had gone round, it straightway returned to the camp, and lodged there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And on the second day Joshua arose, early in the morning, and the priests took up the ark of the covenant of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and the seven priests with the seven trumpets, marched on before the Lord and after them came the warriors, and all the rest of the multitude followed the ark of the covenant of the Lord. And the priests sounded the trumpets;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and all the multitude compassed the city six times, very near, and returned again to the camp. Thus they did six days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But on the seventh day; they arose very early, and went round the city that day seven times.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And, at the seventh round, the priests sounded the trumpets, and Joshua said to the Israelites, Shout, for the Lord hath delivered up the city to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And this city shall be an Anathema. It, and all that are in it, shall be devoted to the Lord of Sabaoth; save Rahab the harlot. Her you shall save alive, and all that are in her house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But be you very careful to abstain from the Anathema, lest peradventure you through covetousness, take something of what is devoted, and make the camp of the Israelites an Anathema, and destroy us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>All the silver, and the gold, and the brass, and the iron, shall be consecrated to the Lord, and carried to the Lord's treasury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then the priests sounded the trumpets; and when the people heard the trumpets, all the people together uttered a great, loud, and continued shout, whereupon the whole wall round about fell, and all the people went up into the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now when Joshua devoted it, and all that were in it, men and women, young and old, ox and ass, to the edge of the sword,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>he said to the two young men who had been sent as spies, Go to the house of the woman, and bring her out thence, with all that she hath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when the two young men, who had spied the city had gone to the house of the woman, and had brought out Rahab the harlot, and her father, and her mother, and her brothers, and her kindred, and all that were with her, and placed them without the camp of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the city was burned with fire, with all that were in it, save the silver, and gold, and the brass, and iron, which they gave to be carried to the treasury of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So Joshua saved Rahab the harlot, and all her father's household alive. And at this day they dwell among Israel, because she concealed the spies whom Joshua had sent to spy Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And on that day Joshua uttered an imprecation before the Lord, saying, Cursed be the man who shall rebuild this city. With his first born let him lay the foundation, and with his youngest son erect its gates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thus the Lord was with Joshua, and his fame spread through all the land.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But the children of Israel committed a great trespass. They set apart for themselves some of the Anathema. Achar son of Charmi, son of Zambri, son of Zara, of the tribe of Juda, had taken some of what was devoted, and the anger of the Lord was kindled against the children of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>so that when Joshua sent men to Gai, which is over against Baithel, saying, Take a view of Gai; and the men had gone up, and viewed Gai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and returned to Joshua, and said to him, Let not the whole people go up, but let only about two or three thousand go up, and storm the city; thou needest not lead the whole people thither, for they are few in number;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and about three thousand men had gone up, they fled before the men of Gai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and the men of Gai slew of them about thirty six men, and pursued them from the gate, and drove them from the steep. Whereupon the heart of the people was dismayed, and became like water;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Joshua rent his clothes. Now when Joshua had prostrated himself, with his face on the ground, before the Lord until evening, he and the elders of Israel, and they had put dust on their heads,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Joshua said, Alas, Lord! Why hath thy servant caused this people to cross the Jordan, to deliver them up to the Amorite to destroy us? Should we have tarried, and dwelt on the other side of the Jordan?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>What can I say, seeing Israel hath turned back from before his enemy?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When the Chananite, and all the inhabitants of this land hear this, they will encompass us, and drive us from this land. What then wilt thou do in respect to thy great name?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thereupon the Lord said to Joshua, Arise; why hast thou fallen on thy face?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This people hath sinned, and transgressed the covenant which I made with them. They have stolen some of what was devoted, and put it among their stuff;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>therefore the children of Israel cannot stand before the face of their enemies. They shall turn back before their enemies, because they are become devoted. I will no more be with you, unless you remove the Anathema from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Arise, hallow the people, and order them to hallow themselves, against to-morrow. Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel, The Anathema is among you. You cannot stand before your enemies, until you remove the Anathema from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>You shall therefore all assemble to-morrow, by tribes; and whatever tribe the Lord shall point out, you shall present it by communities; and whatever community the Lord shall point out, you shall present it by houses; and whatever house the Lord shall point out, you shall present it man by man;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and whoever is pointed out, he shall be burned with fire and all that he hath, because he hath transgressed the covenant of the Lord, and committed iniquity in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Accordingly Joshua arose early in the morning, and brought forward the people by tribes, and the tribe of Juda was pointed out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when it was presented by communities, the community of the Zaraites was pointed out;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and when it was presented man by man, Achar son of Zambri, son of Zara, was pointed out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Whereupon Joshua said to Achar, Give glory this day to the Lord God of Israel, and make confession, and tell me what thou hast done, and conceal it not from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Achar answered Joshua, and said, I have indeed sinned before the Lord, the God of Israel. Thus and thus have I done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I saw, among the spoil, a piece of tissue, and two hundred didrachms of silver, and an ingot of gold, of about fifty didrachms, and I coveted them, and took them, and behold they are hid in my tent, and the silver is hid under them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Joshua sent messengers, who ran to the tent, in the camp, and the things were hid in his tent, and the silver under them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So they took them out of the tent and brought them to Joshua, and the elders of Israel who laid them before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then Joshua took Achar, son of Zara, and led him up to the valley of Achor, with his sons, and his daughters, and his cattle, and his asses, and all his flocks, and his tent, and all his goods, and all the people accompanied him. And when he had led them up to Emek-Achor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Joshua said to Achar, Why hast thou destroyed us? The Lord destroy thee, as at this day! Then all Israel stoned him with stones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when they had raised over him a great heap of stones, the Lord ceased from the fierceness of his anger. For this cause he called that place Emek-Achor, which is its name at this day.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Joshua, Fear not, nor be dismayed. Take with thee all the men who are warriors, and arise, and go up to Gai. Behold I have delivered into thy hands, the king of Gai, and his land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and thou shalt treat Gai, as thou hast treated Jericho, and its king; but the plunder of the cattle thou shalt take for thyself. Lay thee an ambush for the city, behind it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So Joshua arose, and all the warriors, to go up against Gai. And Joshua chose out thirty thousand mighty men of valour, and sent them away by night;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and he gave them orders, saying, Lie in ambush behind the city; be not at a great distance from the city, and be all ready;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and I, and all the people who are with me, will advance to the city, and when the inhabitants of Gai come out to meet us, as before, we will flee from before them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and as they come after us we will draw them off from the city; for they will say, They are fleeing from us, as they did before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then you will rise from the ambush, and rush into the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Act agreeably to these orders; behold I have commanded you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So Joshua despatched them, and they went to lie in ambush, and took their station, between Baithel and Gai, on the west of Gai.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Joshua arose early next morning and reviewed the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and he and the elders went up before the people to Gai.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>All the warriors went up with him, and marching on, came before the city,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>on the east side, now the ambush was on the west side of the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when the king of Gai saw them, he hasted, and went out to meet them, straight to battle, he and all his people with him; for he did not know that there was an ambush behind the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>At their appearance Joshua and Israel retreated before them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and they pursued the Israelites, and were drawn off from the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>There was not a man left in Gai, who did not pursue Israel. Nay they left the city open, and pursued Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Joshua, Stretch forth thy hand, with the spear in thy hand, towards the city; for into thy hands I have delivered it, and the men in ambush will rise quickly from their place. So Joshua stretched forth his hand, with the spear towards the city;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the men in ambush immediately arose from their place. They started up at the instant he stretched forth his hand, and rushed into the city; and having taken it, they hasted and set it on fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the inhabitants of Gai looked back, they saw a smoke rising from the city, up to heaven, and had no where to flee, this way or that.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For when Joshua and all Israel saw that the men in ambush had taken the city, and that the smoke of the city ascended up to heaven, they turned, and smote the men of Gai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the others issued out of the city to meet them, so that they were in the midst of the army, some being on one side, and some on the other; and they smote them until there was not one left alive, nor any who escaped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>They took the king of Gai alive, and brought him to Joshua,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and when the Israelites had made an end of slaying all that were in Gai, and all that were in the plains, and on the mountain, at the steep, from which at the last they had driven them, Joshua returned to Gai, and smote it with the edge of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now they who fell on that day, including men and women, even all the inhabitants of Gai, were twelve thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Over and above the spoils which were in the city, the Israelites took all the prey for themselves,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>according to the command of the Lord, as the Lord commanded Joshua.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Joshua burned the city with fire, and made it an uninhabitable heap forever, as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And he hanged the king of Gai on a gibbet; and he continued on the gibbet till the evening. But, at the setting of the sun, Joshua gave orders, and they took down his body from the gibbet, and threw it into a pit; and raised over it a heap of stones, which remaineth to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>In the mean while Joshua built an altar to the Lord the God of Israel, on mount Garizin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>as Moses the servant of the Lord commanded Israel, as it is written in the law of Moses, an altar of unwrought stones which iron had never struck, and offered thereon whole burnt offerings to the Lord, and a sacrifice of thanksgiving.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And when Joshua had written on the stones the repetition of the law of Moses, in the presence of the children of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>then all Israel with their elders, and their judges, and their under officers, marched out, some on one side, and some on the other side of the Ark, which was at a distance before them; and the priests and the Levites carried the Ark of the covenant of the Lord; and the proselyte, as well as the home born, attended. One half were on mount Garizin, and the other half on mount Gaibal, as Moses the servant of the Lord commanded; first to bless the people;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and afterwards, as Joshua read all the words of that law, the blessings, and the curses, according to all that were written in the law of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>There was not a word of all that Moses commanded Joshua, which Joshua did not read in the hearing of all the congregation of Israel, to the men and women, and to the children, and the proselytes who sojourned with Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When the kings of the Amorites, who dwelt on the border of the Jordan, and those in the hilly country, and those in the plain, and those along the coast of the great sea, and those bordering on Antilibanus, namely the Chettites, and the Chananites, and the Pherezites, and the Evites, and the Amorites, and the Gergasites, and the Jebusites, heard of these things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>they assembled together to attack Joshua and Israel, all at the same time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now when the inhabitants of Gabaon heard all that the Lord had done to Jericho, and Gai, they acted with subtilty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They went and furnished themselves with provisions, and made other suitable preparations, and taking old bags on their shoulders, and old skins of wine which were cracked, and bound up,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and shoes for their feet, the under part of which were hollow, and the upper part old and clouted, and the garments they put on being worn out, and the bread for their journey dry, mouldy, and worm eaten,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>they came to Joshua, to the camp of Israel, at Galgala, and said to Joshua and Israel, We are come from a far distant land, now therefore make a covenant with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the children of Israel said to the Chorrite, Perhaps thou dwellest near me; how then can I make a covenant with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thereupon they said to Joshua, We are thy servants. And Joshua said to them, Whence are you? And whence come you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And they said, Thy servants are come from a very far distant country, because of the name of the Lord thy God; for we have heard of his name, and of all that he hath done in Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and what he hath done to the kings of the Amorites, who were on the border of the Jordan, to Seon king of the Amorites, and to Og the king of Basan, who dwelt at Asteroth and Edrain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>At the news of which, our elders and all the inhabitants of our land spoke to us saying, Take for yourselves provisions for the journey, and go and meet them, and say to them, We are thy servants; make a covenant with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>These loaves we took hot for our journey, on the day we set out to come to you; but now they are dry, and become mouldy;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>these skins of wine were filled new; but they are cracked; and these our garments, and our shoes, are worn out with the length of the journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the rulers took some of their provisions, and did not consult the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Joshua made peace with them, and they entered into a covenant with them to save their lives; and the chiefs of the congregation swore to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But three days after they had entered into covenant with them, they heard that they were in the neighbourhood, and dwelt close by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whereupon the children of Israel removed, and came to their cities. Now their cities were Gabaon, and Kephira, and Berot, and the cities of Jarim;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But the children of Israel did not make war on them, because all the chiefs had sworn to them by the Lord the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When all the congregation murmured at the chiefs, the chiefs said to all the congregation, We have sworn to them by the Lord the God of Israel; now therefore we cannot touch them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>This we will do. We will let them live and protect them; that there may be no wrath against us because of the oath which we have sworn to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They shall live; but they shall be hewers of wood, and drawers of water for all the congregation, as the chiefs have said to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For Joshua had called them, and said to them, Why did you impose upon me saying, We are far distant from thee, seeing you are our nearest neighbour?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now therefore you are cursed, and not one of you shall escape servitude; from being a hewer of wood, and a drawer of water, for me and my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they answered Joshua saying, We were told all that the Lord thy God commanded his servant Moses, to give you this land, and to extirpate us, and all the inhabitants thereof from before you, therefore we were in great terror for our lives because of you, and we did this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And now behold we are in your power, deal with us as you please, and as it seemeth good to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So they dealt with them in this manner, and Joshua saved them that day out of the hand of the Israelites, and they did not destroy them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And on that day Joshua made them hewers of wood, and drawers of water, for the whole congregation, and for the altar of God. For this cause the inhabitants of Gabaon are hewers of wood, and drawers of water, for the altar of God, even at this day, and are to be so for the place which the Lord will chuse.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when Adonibezek, the king of Jerusalem heard that Joshua had taken Gai, and utterly destroyed it; (As they had done to Jericho, and the king thereof, so had they done to Gai, and its king) and that the inhabitants of Gabaon had gone over to Joshua and Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>(Now there was a great dread on account of them, for he knew that Gabaon was a great city, like one of the chief cities, and that all the inhabitants thereof were men of valour;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Adonibezek, the king of Jerusalem sent to Elam, king of Chebron, and to Phedon, king of Jerimuth, and to Jephtha, king of Lachis, and to Dabin, king of Odollam, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Haste, come up to me, and help me, and let us smite Gabaon, for they have revolted to Joshua and the Israelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So the five kings of the Jebusites, the king of Jerusalem, and the king of Chebron, and the king of Jerimuth, and the king of Lachis, and the king of Odollam, went up, they and their people, and encamped about Gabaon, and besieged it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thereupon the inhabitants of Gabaon sent to Joshua, to the camp of Israel, at Galgala, saying, Slack not thy hands from thy servants. Come up to us with all speed, and help us, and deliver us; for all the kings of the Amorites who inhabit the hilly country are assembled against us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So Joshua went up from Galgala, he and all the people of war with him, every man of valour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the Lord said to Joshua, Be not afraid of them, for I have delivered them into thy hands. There shall not one of them be left before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when Joshua came upon them suddenly, having marched all night from Galgala,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the Lord struck them with a panic, on account of the children of Israel, and the Lord routed them, with a great slaughter, at Gabaon. And they pursued them by the way of the ascent of Oronin, and smote them even to Azeka, and to Makeda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And as they were fleeing from before Israel, at the descent of Oronin, the Lord poured a storm of hail stones from heaven upon them, all the way to Azeka; so that there were more who died by the hail stones, than the children of Israel slew with the sword in battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Joshua spoke to the Lord, on the day God delivered up the Amorite into the hand of Israel. When he had discomfited them at Gabaon, and they were routed before the children of Israel, Joshua said, Let the sun stand over against Gabaon, and the moon over against the valley of Ailon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So the sun stood still, and the moon in its station; until God executed vengeance on their enemies, the sun stood in the midst of heaven; it advanced not to the setting, to the end of a day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So that there never was such a day before, nor after it such an instance of God's hearkening to man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because the Lord fought conjointly with Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>therefore the five kings fled, and hid themselves in the cave at Makeda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when it was told Joshua, saying, The five kings are found hidden in the cave at Makeda,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Joshua said, Roll stones on the mouth of the cave, and set men to keep watch over them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but as for you, halt not; pursue your enemies, and attack their rear, and suffer them not to enter their cities; for the Lord our God hath delivered them into our hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when Joshua, and all Israel, had made an end of slaughtering them till they were utterly routed, and those who had escaped had got into fortified cities,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>all the people returned safe to Joshua to Makeda, and there was not a murmur on the tongue of any one among the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Joshua said, Open the cave, and bring out the five kings out of the cave.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So they brought the five kings out of the cave; the king of Jerusalem, and the king of Chebron, and the king of Jerimuth, and the king of Lachis, and the king of Odollam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when they had brought them out to Joshua, he called together all Israel, namely the chief commanders of the army who went out with him, and said to them, Go near, and put your feet on the necks of those men. And when they had gone near, and put their feet on their necks,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Joshua said to them, Fear them not, nor be dismayed. Be strong and of good courage; for thus will the Lord do to all your enemies, against whom you fight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So Joshua slew them, and hanged them on five gibbets, and they hung on the gibbets till evening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And at the setting of the sun Joshua gave orders, and they took them down from the gibbets, and threw them into the cave, and rolled stones on the cave, which still remain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now on that day they took Makeda, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed every thing therein which breathed. There was not one left who escaped or fled. And when they had done to the king of Makeda as they did to the king of Jericho,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Joshua, and all Israel with him, marched from Makeda to Lebna and besieged it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and the Lord delivered it into the hands of Israel, and they took it and the king thereof, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and every thing in it which had breath. There was not one left in it who escaped, or fled. And when they had done to the king thereof as they did to the king of Jericho,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Joshua, and all Israel with him, marched from Lebna to Lachis, and encamped about it, and besieged it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the Lord delivered Lachis into the hands of Israel; and they took it on the second day, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed it as they had done Lebna.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>At that time Elam, king of Gazer, having come up to assist Lachis, Joshua smote him with the edge of the sword, till there was none of them left who escaped, or fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then Joshua, and all Israel with him, went from Lachis to Odollam, and encamped about it, and besieged it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the Lord delivered it into the hand of Israel, and they took it that day, and smote it with the edge of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And when they had slain every living soul therein, as they had done at Lachis,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Joshua, and all Israel with him, went to Chebron, and encamped about it, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and every living soul therein. Not one escaped. As they had done to Odollam, they utterly destroyed it, and all that were in it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then Joshua, and all Israel, wheeled round to Dabir, and encamped about it, and took it, and the king thereof, and the villages thereof. And he smote it with the edge of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And they utterly destroyed it, and every soul in it. They did not leave one alive. As they had done to Chebron, and its king, so they did to Dabir, and its king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Thus did Joshua smite all the hilly country, and Nageb, and the plain, and Asedoth, and the kings thereof. They did not leave one of them alive. They utterly destroyed every one who breathed the breath of life, as the Lord God of Israel had commanded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>From Kades-barne to Gaza,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Joshua smote at one time all the land of Gosom, quite to Gabaon, all their kings, and their land, for the Lord the God of Israel fought for Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when Jabis, king of Azor, heard this, he sent to Jobab king of Maram, and to the king of Symoon, and to the king of Aziph,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and to the kings who bordered on great Sidon, to the hilly country, and to Araba over against Keneroth, and to the plain, and to Phenaeddor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and to the Chananites, on the eastern shore of the sea, and to the Amorites, on the sea shore, and to the Chettites, and the Pherezites, and the Jebusites, on the mountain, and to the Evites, and to those at the foot of Aermon, to the land of Massuma;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and they, and their kings with them, came out like the sand of the sea for multitude, with horses and chariots in great abundance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when all these kings had assembled, and formed a junction, and encamped at the water of Maron to fight against Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>the Lord said to Joshua, Be not afraid of them, for to-morrow, about this time, I will deliver them up vanquished before Israel. Thou shalt hamstring their horses, and burn their chariots with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So Joshua and all the warriors came upon them suddenly, at the water of Maron, and fell upon them in the hilly country:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the Lord delivered them into the hands of Israel, and they pursued them with slaughter, to great Sidon, and to Maseron, and to the plains of Massoch, eastward, and hewed them down till there was none of them left alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And Joshua did to them as the Lord commanded him. Their horses he hamstringed; and their chariots he burned with fire</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And at that time Joshua turned back, and took Asor, and the king thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>(Now Asor was formerly the head of all these kingdoms.) And they slew every living soul in it, with the sword, and utterly destroyed all, so that there was not one left in it alive. And they burned Asor with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Joshua took all the cities of those kingdoms, and the kings thereof, and smote them with the edge of the sword, and utterly destroyed them, as Moses the servant of the Lord had commanded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>(But Israel did not burn any of the cities which were built on lofty situations, except Asor; this alone Israel burned;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the Israelites took all the spoils thereof for themselves, and exterminated the inhabitants with the edge of the sword, until they destroyed them. They did not leave a breathing soul of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>As the Lord commanded his servant Moses, and as Moses gave it in charge to Joshua, so Joshua did. He left nothing undone of all that Moses commanded him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So Joshua took all the hilly country, and all the land of Nageb, and all the land of Gosom, and the plain, and that to the west, and the mountain of Israel, and the lowlands adjoining the mountain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>from mount Chelcha, and that which stretcheth up to Seir, even to Balagad, and the plains of Libanus, at the foot of mount Aermon. He took, and smote, and slew, all the kings thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Joshua indeed waged war against those kings for several years,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>so that there was not a city which Israel did not take. They took them all by battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For the Lord permitted them to assume courage to come to battle with Israel, that they might be utterly destroyed, that no mercy might be shewn them; but that they might be utterly destroyed, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>At that time also, Joshua went, and rooted out the Enakims from the hilly country, from Chebron, and from Dabir, and from Anaboth, and from the whole race of Israel, and from all the mountain of Juda. Them, with their cities, Joshua destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So that, by means of the children of Israel, there was not one of the Enakims left, except some who were in Gaza, and in Geth, and in Aseldo.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when Joshua had taken all the land as the Lord commanded Moses, he gave it for an inheritance to Israel, in parcels, according to their tribes; and the land rested from war.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the kings of the land, whom the Israelites slew, and whose land they possessed, on the east side of the Jordan, from the vale of Arnon to mount Aermon, comprehending all the land of Araba to the east;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Seon, king of the Amorites, who dwelt at Esebon; whose dominion extended from Arnon which is in the vale, along part of the vale, and the half of Galaad to Jabok, the boundary of the Ammonites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>comprehending Araba, to the east side of the sea of Cheneroth, and to the sea of Araba, the east side of the salt sea, the way in front of Aseimoth, that leading from Thaiman, at the foot of Asedoth Phasga:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and Og, king of Basan, who was a remnant of the giants, and who dwelt at Astaroth, and Edrain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and whose dominion extended from mount Aermon, and from Sekchai, over all the land of Basan, to the borders of Gergesi, and over Machi, and the half of Galaad, to the borders of Seon king of Esebon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>These, Moses the servant of the Lord, and the children of Israel, smote; and Moses gave this land for a possession to Reuben, and Gad, and to the half of the tribe of Manasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And these are the kings of the Amorites, whom Joshua and the children of Israel slew, on the west side of the Jordan, from Balagad in the valley of Libanus, to mount Chelcha, as you go up to Seir; and which Joshua gave for a possession to the tribes of Israel, according to their respective lots,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>comprehending the Chettites, and the Amorites, and the Chananites, and the Pherezites, and the Evites, and the Jebusites, on the mountains, and in the plains, and in Araba, and in Asedoth, and in the wilderness, and in Nageb:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the king of Jericho, and the king of Gai, which is near Bethel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the king of Jerusalem; the king of Chebron;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>the king of Jerimuth; the king of Lachis;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the king of Ailam; the king of Gazer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>the king of Dabir: the king of Gadir;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>the king of Ermath; the king of Ader;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the king of Lebna; the king of Odollam;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the king of Elath;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the king of Taphut, the king of Opher;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>the king of Ophek of Arok;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>the king of Asom;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>the king of Symoon; the king of Mambroth; the king of Aziph;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>the king of Kades; the king of Zachak;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>the king of Maredoth; the king of Jekom of Carmel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>the king of Odollam of Phennealdor; the king of Gei of Galilee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the king of Thersa; all these kings were twenty nine.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Joshua was now far advanced in years, therefore the Lord said to Joshua, Thou art advanced in years, and there is much land left to be taken possession of.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now this is the land which is left; the borders of the Philistines, the Geserites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the Chananites. The land from the desart which is before Egypt, to the borders of Akkaron, on the left of the Chananites, is set out to the five Satrapies of the Philistines, the Gazites and the Azotians, and the Askalonites, and the Getthites, and the Akkaronites, comprehending the Evaites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>From Thaiman, throughout the whole land, lieth Chanaan before Gaza. And the Sidonians extend to Aphek, and to the borders of the Amorites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now all the land of Galiath-phylistiim, and all Libanus, from the rising of the sun; from Galgal, at the foot of mount Aermon, to the bay of Aimath;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>all the inhabitants of the hilly country, from Libanus to Masereth-memphomaim; all the Sidonians; them I will myself drive out from before Israel; but distribute thou it, by lot, to Israel, as I have commanded thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now therefore divide this land, for a possession among the nine tribes, and the half of the tribe of Manasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thou shalt give it from the Jordan to the great sea, at the setting of the sun: that great sea shall be your boundary. To the two tribes of Reuben and Gad, and to the half of the tribe of Manasses, Moses hath given on the eastern border of the Jordan. Moses the servant of the Lord had given them</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>from Aroer, which is on the bank of the brook Arnon, that city which is in the middle of the vale, and all Misor from Maidaban;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>all the cities of Seon, king of the Amorites, who reigned at Esebon, to the borders, of the children of Ammon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Galaaditis; and the country of the Geserites, and the Machatites; all mount Aermon; and all Basanitis to Acha;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>all the kingdom of Og, in Basanitis, who reigned in Astaroth and Edrain, he was a remnant of the giants, and Moses smote him and destroyed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now the children of Israel had not destroyed the Gesirites, nor the Machatite, who was a Chananite. And the king of Gesiri, and the Machatite, still dwelt among the Israelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But to the tribe of Levi there was no possession given. The Lord, the God of Israel is himself their possession, as the Lord said to them. Now this was the distribution which Moses made to the children of Israel at Araboth-Moab, on the border of the Jordan, over against Jericho.;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>To the tribe of Reuben, according to their communities, Moses gave,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and these were their borders; from Aroer, which is in front of the vale of Arnon, including the city in the vale of Arnon, all the Misor to</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Esebon, and, all the cities in Misor, namely Daibon, and Baimon-baal, and house of Meelboth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and Basan, and Bakedmoth, and Maiphaad,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and Kariathaim, and Sebama, and Serada, and Sion on mount Enab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Baithphogor, and Asedothphasga, and Baithaseinoth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>even all the cities of Misor, and all the kingdom of Seon king of the Amorites, whom Moses slew, and with him the leaders of Madiam, Evi, and Robok, and Sour, and Our, and Robe, the chief; at the rifling of Sion, when the Israelites slew the inhabitants of Sion, and in the route,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Balaam son of Beor the prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>These were the borders of Reuben, and Jordan was a boundary. This was the possession of the children of Reuben, according to their communities, and these were their cities and their sheepcots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And to the children of Gad, according to their communities, Moses gave,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and these were their borders, Jazer, all the cities of Galaad, and the half of the land of Ammon, even to Araba, which is in front of Arad,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and from Esebon to Araboth, over against Massepha, and Botanim, and Maan to the border of Daibon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and Enadom, and Othargai, and Bainthanabra, and Sokchotha, and Saphan, and the residue of the kingdom of Seon, king of Esebon. And the Jordan is their boundary, to a part of the sea of Cheneroth, on the east side of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>This is the possession of the children of Gad, according to their communities, and according to their cities. According to their communities they can face their enemies; for their cities, and their sheepcots, were distributed according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And to the half of the tribe of Manasses, according to their communities, Moses gave,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and these were their borders; from Maan, all the kingdom of Basan, even all the kingdom of Og, king of Basan, and all the towns of Jair, which are in Basanitis, sixty cities,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and the half of Galaad, and in Astaroth, and in Edrain, the cities of the kingdom of Og, in Basanitis. These he gave to the Machirites, the children of Manasses, to one half of the Machirites, the children of Manasses, according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>These were they to whom Moses gave possessions on the east side of the Jordan, at Araboth; Moab, on the bank of the Jordan over against Jericho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are they of the children of Israel who got possessions in the land of Chanaan, to whom Eleazar the priest, and Joshua son of Nave, and the chiefs of the patriarchal families of the tribes of Israel, gave possessions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>They gave possessions by lot, as the Lord commanded by the hand of Joshua, to nine tribes and the half of a tribe on this side the Jordan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>but to the Levites he gave no lot among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because the children of Joseph were two tribes, Manasses and Ephraim; there was therefore no portion of land given to the Levites, but only cities to dwell in, with the suburbs thereof for their cattle; for they had cattle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>As the Lord commanded Moses, so the children of Israel did, when they divided the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now the children of Juda had come to Joshua at Galgal, and Chaleb the son of Jephonne, the Kenezite said to him, Thou knowest the word which the Lord said to Moses, the man of God, respecting me and thee at Kades-barne;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for I was forty years old, when Moses the servant of God sent me from Kades-barne to spy the land, and I made him a report to his mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>My brethren who went up with me disturbed the heart of the people; but I determined to follow the Lord my God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>so Moses solemnly promised that day, saying, The land to which thou hast gone up shall be thy lot, and thy children's forever, for a possession, because thou hast determined to follow the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now the Lord hath kept me alive as he said. This is the forty fifth year since the Lord spoke this word to Moses, and Israel commenced their wanderings in the wilderness. And behold I am now eighty five years of age;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>yet I am now as strong as when Moses sent me; as able now as then to go out and come in to battle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>now therefore I ask of thee that mountain, as the Lord said on that day; for thou didst hear the word on that day. The' Enakims indeed are now there; the cities are fortified and large; if then the Lord be with me, I will exterminate them, as the Lord said to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thereupon Joshua blessed him, and gave to Chaleb son of Jephonne, the Kenezite, Chebron for a possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For this cause Chebron had become the possession of Chaleb son of Jephonne, the Kenezite, at this day, because he followed the command of the Lord God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now the name of Chebron, formerly, was city Argob. It was the metropolis of the Enakims. Now when the land had rest from war,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>the borders of the tribe of Juda, according to their communities, were southward along the borders of Idumea, from the wilderness of Sin to Kades-barne;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and thence their southern boundary was to a part of the salt sea. From that extreme point which stretcheth to the south,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>the boundary beginneth its course over against the steep of Akrabin, and runneth round Sena, then goeth up south of Kades-barne, and runneth by Asoron, and goeth up to Sarada; and quitting this directly west of Kades,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>it proceedeth on to Selmona, and thence to the torrent of Egypt, and the termination of this their boundary was to be at the sea. This is their southern boundary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And their boundary on the east is the whole extent of the salt sea to the Jordan. And their boundary on the north, beginning at the head of the sea, and a part</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>of the Jordan, runneth up to Baithaglaam, and passeth along on the north side of Baitharaba; thence the boundary goeth up to the stone of Baion, son of Reuben;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>thence the boundary advanceth on to the fourth part of the valley of Achor, then goeth down to Galgal, which is over against the steep of Adammin, which is on the south side of the valley; thence it striketh off to the water of the fountain of the sun, and its termination there is to be the fountain Rogel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>thence the boundary goeth up to the valley of Ennom, on the south side of Jebus, which is Jerusalem; then the boundary turneth off to the top of the mountain which is to the west, in front of the valley of Ennom, which is the northern part of the land of Raphain;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and from the top of the mountain the boundary turneth off to the fountain of water, Naphtho; and thence to the mountain Ephron; thence the boundary is to stretch on to Baal, which is the city of Jarim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>then the boundary is to come round west of Baal, and pass on to mount Assar, on the back and north side of the city Jarim, which is Chaslon, and go down to the city of the sun, passing it on the south side;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>then the boundary goeth out back of Akkaron northward; thence the boundary is to pass on to Sokchoth, and thence turning southward, to pass on to Lebna. And the termination of this boundary is to be at the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And with regard to the western boundary, the great sea is to be that boundary. These were the boundaries of the children of Juda, according to their communities round about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now to Chaleb son of Jephonne he had given a portion in the midst of the children of Juda. By the command of God, Joshua had given him the city Arbok, the metropolis of Enak, the same is Chebron;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and Chaleb son of Jephonne had driven out thence the three sons of Enak, Sousi, and Tholami, and Achima.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when Chaleb went up thence, against the inhabitants of Dabir, (now the name of Dabir formerly was The City of Letters) Chaleb said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Whoever will take the city of letters and subdue it, I will give him my daughter Aschan for a wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whereupon Gothoniel son of Chenez, Chaleb's brother took it. So he gave him his daughter Aschan for a wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And as she was going out to him she consulted with him, saying, Let me ask a field of my father. And when she had cried aloud from the ass, and Chaleb said to her, What is the matter with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>she said to him, Give me a blessing. Seeing thou hast sent me to the land of Nageb, give me Botthanis. So he gave her the upper and lower Gonaithla.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>This was the lot of inheritance of the children of Juda;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and the cities belonging to the tribe of the children of Juda; on the borders of Edom, adjoining the wilderness, were Baiseleel, and Ara, and Asor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and Ikam and Regma, and Aruel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and Kades, and Asorionain, and Mainam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Balmainan, with their villages;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and the cities of the Aserons, which is Aser,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and Sen, and Salmaa, and Molada,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and Seri, and Baiphalath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and Cholaseola, and Bersabee, with their villages and sheepcots:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Bala, and Bakok, and Asom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and Elboydad, and Baithel, and Erma,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and Sekelak, and Macharim, and Sethannak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and Labos, and Sale, and Eromoth, twenty nine cities with their villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>In the plain, Astaol, and Raa, and Assa,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and Ramen, and Tano, and Iluthoth, and Maiani,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and Jermuth, and Odollam, and Membra, and Saocho, and Jaseka,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and Sakarim, and Gadera, with its villages; fourteen cities, with their villages:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Senna, and Adosan, and Magadalgad,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and Dalad, and Maspha, and Jachareel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and Basedoth, and Ideadalea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and Chabra, and Maches, and Maachos,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>and Geddor, and Bagadiel, and Noman, and Machedan; sixteen cities with their villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Lebna, and Ithak, and Anoch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>and Jana, and Nasib,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and Keilam, and Akiezi, and Kezib, and Bathesar, and Ailom, ten cities with their villages:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Akkaron, and the villages thereof, with their sheepcots;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>bordering on Akkaron, Gemna, and all that lay near Asedoth, with their villages;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Asiedoth, and the sheepcots thereof, Gaza, and the villages thereof, and its sheepcots, to the brook of Egypt; and the great sea is the boundary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And in the hilly country, Samir, and Jether, and Socha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>and Renna, and city of letters, this is Dabir,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>and Anon, and Es, and Man, and Aisam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>and Gosom, and Chalu, and Channa, and Gelom; eleven cities with their villages;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Airem, and Remna, and Soma,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>and Jemain, and Baithachu, and Phakua,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>and Eyma, and city Arbok, this is Chebron, and Soraith, nine cities with their sheepcots:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Maor, and Chermel, and Ozib, and Itan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>and Jariel, and Arikam, and Zakanaim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>and Gabaa, and Thamnatha, nine cities with their villages;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Ailua, and Bethsur, and Geddon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>and Magaroth, and Baithanam, and Thekum, six cities with their villages: Theko, and Ephratha, this is Baithlehem, and Phagor, and Aitan, and Kulon, and Tatam, and Thobes, and Karem, and Galem, and Thether, and Manocho, eleven cities with their villages:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>Kariath-baal, this is the city Jarim, and Sotheba, two cities with their sheepcots:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>and Baddargis, and Tharabaam, and Ainon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>and Aiochioza, and Naphlazon, and the cities Sadon and Agkades, seven cities with their villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>But the Jebusites dwelt in Jerusalem, and the children of Juda were not able to destroy them. So the Jebusites had dwelt in Jerusalem to this day.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the borders of the children of Joseph were from the Jordan, in front of Jericho eastward, and to go up from Jericho to the hilly country; the wilderness to Baithel-louza, and having come out to Baithel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the boundary is to run along the borders of Achatarothi,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and proceed westward, along the borders of Aptalim, till it reacheth the borders of lower Baithoron; and the termination thereof is to be at the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the children of Joseph, Ephraim and Manasses, got their possessions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the borders of the children of Ephraim, according to their communities were these. The boundary of their possession from the east were Ataroth, and Erok, till it reached the</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>upper Baithoron, and Gazara; then the boundary was to proceed westward to Ikasmon, on the north side of Therma, then to come round eastward to Thenasa, and Selles, and from the east border of that to pass on to Janoka,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and to Macho, and Ataroth, including their villages; then to come to Jericho, and terminate at the Jordan:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And from Taphu the boundary was to run westward by Chelkana and to terminate at the sea. This possession of the tribe of Ephraim, according to their communities,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>with the cities set apart for the children of Ephraim, in the inheritance of the children of Manasses, comprehended all their cities and their villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But Ephraim did not destroy the Chananites who dwelt in Gazer. So the Chananites have dwelt among the Ephraimites to this day.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the borders of the tribe of the children of Manasses were these; Because he was the first born of Joseph, Machir the first born of Manasses, the father of Galaad, being a man of war, had a possession in Galaaditis, and in Basanitis;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and the rest of the sons of Manasses had possessions according to their communities, namely, the sons of Jezi, and the sons of Kelez, and the sons of Jeziel, and the sons of Sychem, and the sons of Symarim, and the sons of Opher. These were the males according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now Salpaad, son of Opher, had no sons, but only daughters; and these were the names of the daughters of Salpaad, Maala, and Noua, and Egla, and Melcha, and Thersa;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and they stood before Eleazar the priest, and before Joshua, and before the chiefs and said, God hath, by the ministry of Moses, commanded to give us an inheritance among our brethren. Accordingly there was a possession given them, by the command of the Lord, among their father's brothers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and their lot happened to be on the borders of Anassa, the plain of Labek, a part of the land of Galaad, on the bank of the Jordan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>because the daughters of the children of Manasses had a possession in the midst of their brethren; and Galaad belonged to the rest of the children of Manasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now these were the borders of the children of Manasses; Delanath, which is in front of the children of Anath, and extendeth to the borders, to Jamin, and Jassib, to the fountain Thaphoth, is to belong to Manasses;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but Thapheth, which is within the bounds of the Manassites, is to belong to the children of Ephraim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thence the boundary is to go down to the vale of Karana, on the south side, over against the vale Jariel; but Tereminthus, which is within the bounds of a city of Manasses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>is to belong to Ephraim; then the border of Manasses runneth northward, to the brook, and his boundary is to be the sea. The south side belonged to Ephraim, and the north side to Manasses, and the sea was to be their boundary. And on the north they were to join upon Aser, and on the east upon Issachar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Manasses was to have in Issachar, and in Aser, Baithsan, with their villages, and the inhabitants of Dor, and its villages, and the inhabitants of Mageddo, and its villages; and the third part of Mapheta, and its villages;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>but the Manassites were not able to exterminate the inhabitants of these cities. The Chananites had begun to settle in that land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and when the Israelites became strong, they brought the Chananites into subjection, and did not utterly extirpate them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When the children of Joseph complained to Joshua, saying, Why hast thou given us but one lot, and one portion, to inherit, seeing I am a numerous people, and God hath blessed me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Joshua said to them, If thou art a numerous people, go up into the forest and clear it for thyself, if the mountain Ephraim be too narrow for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Whereupon they said we are not satisfied with mount Ephraim, and the Chananites, who dwell there in Baithsan, and its villages, and in the valley of Jezrael, have choice horses, and iron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But Joshua said to the children of Joseph, If thou art a numerous people, and hast great power, thou wilt not have one lot only,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for the forest will be thine. Though it is a forest thou canst clear it, and it shall be thine when thou hast rooted out the Chananites. For though they have choice horses, thou shalt excel them in strength.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When all the congregation of Israel assembled at Selo, and fixed there the tabernacle of the testimony, and the land was subdued under them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>but there still remained among the children of Israel seven tribes who had not received their portions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Joshua said to the children of Israel, How long will you be devoid of courage, to take possession of the land which the Lord our God hath given?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Appoint from among you three men of a tribe, and let them arise, and go through the land, and lay before me a draught of it, as it ought to be divided. And when they came to him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>he distinguished for them seven portions, saying, Let Juda stand. Their boundary is south of this. And let the children of Joseph stand. Their boundary is north of this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Divide ye therefore the land into seven parcels, and bring them to me, and I will cast the lot for you before the</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Lord our God; for the children of Levi are to have no lot among you; for the priesthood of the Lord is their portion; and Gad and Reuben, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, have received their possession on the eastern bank of the Jordan; that which Moses the servant of the Lord gave them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So the men prepared to set out, and when they were going to traverse the land, Joshua gave them a charge, saying, Go and traverse the land, and come to me, and I will here cast the lots for you before the Lord, at Selo.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So they went, and traversed the land, and when they had viewed it, and written it by cities in seven parcels in books, they brought them to Joshua,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and Joshua cast lots for them at Selo, before the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and the lot of the tribe of Benjamin came out first, according to their communities, and the bounds of their lot came out between the children of Juda,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and the children of Joseph; and these were their borders. On the north their boundary was to go up from the Jordan, back of Jericho, on the north side, and to run westward to the mountain, and come out at Mabdaritis-Baithon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>thence the boundary was to run to the border of Louza, back of Louza on the south side of it, this is Baithel; thence the boundary was to run down to Maatarob-Orech, by the high land which is south of the lower Baithoron;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>thence the boundary was to wind, and proceed to that part on the south which overlooketh the sea, from the mountain before Baithoron southward, and to terminate at Kariathbaal, that is Kariathiarim, a city of the children of Juda. This was the western part.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And with regard to the southern part; from a part of Kariathbaal, the boundary was to run to Gasin, by the fountain of water</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Naphtho; thence the boundary was to run down part of the way, that is, in front of the forest Sonnam, which is the northern part of Emek-raphain; thence down to Gehenna, back of Jebusi, south of it, down to the fountain Rogel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>then to turn off to the fountain Baithsamys, and pass on to Galiloth, which is over against the steep of Aithamin; then down to the stone of Baion, one of the sons of Reuben;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>then to run back of Baithabara, north of it, down to the border at the north end of the sea;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the termination of this boundary was to be at the north bay of the salt sea, and at the south end of the Jordan. This was the southern boundary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the Jordan was to be the eastern boundary. This was the inheritance of the children of Benjamin, and these their borders round about, according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the cities of the Benjaminites according to their communities were Jericho, and Bethegaio, and Amekasis,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and Baithabara, and Sara, and Besana,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and Aiein, and Phara, and Ephratha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Karapha, and Kephira, and Moni, and Gabaa, twelve cities with their villages:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Gabaon, and Rama, and Beerotha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and Massema, and Miron, and Amoke,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and Phira, and Kaphan, and Nakan, and Selekan, and Thareela,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and Jebus, this is Jerusalem, and Gabaoth-Jarim, thirteen cities with their villages. This was the inheritance of the children of Benjamin, according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Next came out the lot of the children of Symeon, and their inheritance was in the midst of the lots of the children of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And this was their lot; Bersabe, and Semao, and Keladam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and Arsola, and Bola, and Jason,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and Erthula, and Bula, and Erma,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and Sikelak, and Baithmachereb, and Sarsusin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Batheroth, with their fields, thirteen cities with their villages;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Eremmon, and Thalecha, and Jather, and Asan, four cities with their villages,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>around these their cities, as far as Balek on the way to Bameth southward. This was the inheritance of the tribe of the Symeonites according to their communities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>From the portion of Juda was taken the inheritance of the tribe of the Symeonites; because the portion of the children of Juda was too large for them, therefore the children of Symeon got an inheritance in the midst of their portion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the third lot came out for Zabulon, according to their communities; and these were to be the bounds of their inheritance:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Esedekgola, the sea and Magalda, were to be their boundaries, and their boundary was to join upon Baitharaba, at the valley which is in front of Jekman:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>then it turned up from Sedduck, from the east of Baithsamys, along the borders of Chaselothaith, and was to turn off to Dabiroth, and go up to Phaggai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>thence to come round on the other side, eastward, to Gebere, by the city Katesem, and pass on by Remmonaa Matharoza;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>then the boundary was to go round, northward, by Amoth, and the termination of it was to be at Gaphael.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Including Katanath, and Nabaal, and Symoon, and Jericho, and Baithman,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>this was the inheritance of the children of Zabulon, according to their communities, their cities and their villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the fourth lot came out for Issachar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and their borders were Jazel, and Chassaloth, and Sunam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and Agin, and Siona,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Reeroth, and Anachereth, and Dabiron, and Kison, and Rebes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and Remmas, and Jeon, and Tomman, and Aimerek, and Bersaphes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and their borders were to join on Gaithbor, and on Salim westward, and on Baithsamys, and the termination of their boundary was to be the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>This was the inheritance of the tribe of the children of Issachar, according to their communities, their cities and their villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And the fifth lot came out for Aser, according to their communities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And their borders were Exaleketh, and Aleph, and Baithok, and Neaph,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and Elimelech, and Amiel, and Maasa, and to join on Karmelo, westward, and on Sion and Labanath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and to turn from the rising of the sun, and Baithegeneth, and to join Zabulon, and Ekgai, and Phthaiel, on the north; then the boundary is to come to Saphthaibaithme, and Inael, and turn off to Chobamasomel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and Elbon, and Raab, and Ememaon, and Kanthan, till it reached great Sidon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then the boundary is to turn up to Rama, and to the fountain Masphasset, and the Tyrians; Then the boundary is to turn up to Jasiph; and the termination of it is to be the sea, including Apoleb, and Echozob,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and Archob, and Aphek, and Raau;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>this was the inheritance of the children of Aser, according to their communities, including their cities and their villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the sixth lot came out for Nephthaleim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and their borders were Moolam, and Mola, and Besemin, and Arme, and Naboch, and Jephthamai, even to Dodam, and the terminations were the Jordan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>then their boundary was to turn westward, by Aththabor, and then turn off to Jakana, and join Zabulon on the south, and Aser on the west, and Jordan on the east.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now the fenced cities of the Tyrians, were Tyre and Omathadaketh, and Kenereth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and Armaith, and Arael, and Asor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Kades, and Assari, and Bathaser,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and Keroe, and Megalaarim, and Baiththame, and Thessamus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>This was the inheritance of the children of Nephthaleim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And the seventh lot came out for Dan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>and their borders were Sarath, and Asa, and the cities Sammaus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and Salamin, and Ammon, and Silatha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>and Elon, and Thamnatha, and Akkaron,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and Alkatha, and Begethon, and Gebeelan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>and Azor, and Banaibakat, and Gethrimmon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>and on the west of Jerakon, the border near Joppa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Whereupon the children of Dan went and made war on Lachis, and took it, and smote it with the edge of the sword, and dwelt there, and called its name Lasen Dan. The Amorites continued also to dwell in Elom, and Salamin, but the hand of Ephraim was heavy upon them, and they were made tributaries to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>This was the inheritance of the tribe of the Danites, according to their communities, including their cities and their villages. (But the children of Dan did not root out the Amorites who distressed them on the mountains, and the Amorites did not suffer them to come down into the valley. Nay they took from them the border of their portion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Now when the children of Israel set out to enter into the land, according to their respective bounds, the Israelites gave Joshua son of Nave, a portion among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>By the command of God, they gave him the city which he asked, namely Thamnasarach, which is on mount Ephraim, and he rebuilt the city, and dwelt there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>These were the portions which Eleazar the priest, and Joshua son of Nave, and the chiefs of the patriarchal families, distributed by lot among the tribes of Israel, at Selo, in the presence of the Lord, at the doors of the tabernacle of the testimony. So they set out to take possession of the land.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the Lord had spoken to Joshua, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Speak to the children of Israel and say, Give the cities of refuge which I ordered you by Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>a refuge for the manslayer who hath killed a person unawares. And these cities shall be for you a refuge, that the slayer may not be put to death by the avenger of blood, until he stand before the congregation for trial;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and he had set apart Kades, in Galilee, on mount Nephthaleim, and Sychem, on mount Ephraim, and the city Arbok, which is Chebron, on the mountain of Juda:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And on the bank of the Jordan they had given Bosor, in the wilderness, in the plain, from the tribe of Reuben, and Aremoth in Galaad, from the tribe of Gad, and Gaulon in Basanitis from the tribe of Manasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>These are the cities renowned among the children of Israel and the proselytes who dwell among them, for every one who smiteth a person unawares to flee thither, that he may not die by the hand of the avenger of blood, until he stand before the congregation for trial.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the heads of the patriarchal families of the children of Levi came to Eleazar the priest, and Joshua the son of Nave, and to the chiefs of the patriarchal families, of the tribes of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and spoke to them at Selo, in the land of Chanaan, saying, The Lord, by the ministry of Moses, commanded to give us cities to dwell in, with the arable lands around for our cattle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>whereupon the children of Israel gave the Levites for a possession, by the command of the Lord, the following cities with their suburbs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the lot came out for the community of Kaath, and there fell by lot to the children of Aaron, the priests, who were Levites, out of the tribe of Juda, and from the tribe of Symeon, and from the tribe of Benjamin, thirteen cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and to the rest of the Kaathites out of the tribe of Ephraim, and out of the tribe of Dan, and from half of the tribe of Manasses by lot ten cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and to the Gersonites, from the tribe of Issachar, and from the tribe of Aser, and from the tribe of Nephthaleim, and from the half of the tribe of Manasses in Basan, thirteen cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And to the Merarites, according to their communities, from the tribe of Reuben, and from the tribe of Gad, and from the tribe of Zabulon, by lot, twelve cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>These cities, with their suburbs, the children of Israel gave by lot to the Levites, as the Lord commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So the tribe of the children of Juda, and the tribe of the children of Symeon, gave, and there were given from the tribe of the children of Benjamin, the following cities which were assigned</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>to the children of Aaron, of the community of Kaath, who were Levites; because the lot fell to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>they gave them Kariatharbok, the capital of the Enakims, which is Chebron, on the mountain of Juda. Now the suburbs around it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and the fields belonging to the city, and the villages thereof, Joshua had given to the children of Chaleb, son of Jephonne, for a possession;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>but to the sons of Aaron, they gave Chebron, the city of refuge for the manslayer, with what was set apart for it as such, and Lemma with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and Ailom with its suburbs, and Tema with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and Gella with its suburbs, and Dabir with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Asa with its suburbs, and Tanu with its suburbs, and Baithsamys with its suburbs, nine cities from these two tribes;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and from the tribe of Benjamin, Gabaon with its suburbs, and Gatheth with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and Anathoth with its suburbs, and Gamala with its suburbs, four cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>All the cities of the children of Aaron the priests were thirteen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And to the communities of the Kaathites, the Levites, the rest of the Kaathites, was assigned, from the tribe of Ephraim, the city of their priests;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and they gave them Sychem, the city of refuge for the manslayer with its appurtenances, and Gazara with its fields and its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and Baithoron with its suburbs, four cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and from the tribe of Dan, Elkothaim with its suburbs, and Gethedan with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Ailon with its suburbs, and Getheremmon with its suburbs, four cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and from the half of the tribe of Manasses, Tanach with its suburbs, and Jebatha with its suburbs, two cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>All the cities for the remaining communities of the Kaathites were ten, with their suburbs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And to the children of Gerson, the Levites, they gave out of the half of the tribe of Manasses, the city set apart for the manslayers, Gaulon in Basanitis with its suburbs, and Bosora with its suburbs, two cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and out of the tribe of Issachar, Kison with its suburbs, and Lebba with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and Remmath with its suburbs, and Fountain of letters with its suburbs, four cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and out of the tribe of Aser, Basellan with its suburbs, and Dabbon with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and Chelkat with its suburbs, and Raab with its suburbs, four cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and out of the tribe of Nephthaleim, Kades in Galilee, the city set apart for the slayer, with its suburbs, and Nemmath with its suburbs, and Themmon with its suburbs, three cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>All the cities of the Gersonites, according to their communities, were thirteen cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And to the community of the Merarites, the rest of the Levites, they gave out of the tribe of Zabulon, Maan with its suburbs, and Kades with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and Sella with its suburbs, three cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and on the bank of the Jordan, over against Jericho, out of the tribe of Reuben, the city of refuge for the slayer, namely, Bosor, in the wilderness, which is called Miso with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Jazer with its suburbs, and Dekmon with its suburbs, and Mapha with its suburbs, four cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and from the tribe of Gad, the city of refuge for the slayer, namely, Bamoth in Galaad with its suburbs, and Kamin with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and Esbon with its suburbs, and Jazer with its suburbs; all the cities four.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>All the cities for the children of Merari, according to their communities, being the remaining families of the tribe of Levi, were twelve cities with their borders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>All the cities of the Levites, in the midst of the possession of the children of Israel, were forty eight with the grounds appropriate to them, around these cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>All these cities had every one a circuit of ground around it. Now when Joshua had finished dividing the land among them by their borders, the children of Israel gave Joshua a portion, by the command of the Lord. They gave him the city which he asked. They gave him Thamnasachar on mount Ephraim, and Joshua rebuilt the city, and dwelt therein. And Joshua took the stone knives with which he had circumcised the children of Israel, who were born by the way in the wilderness, and deposited them at Thamnasachar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Thus the Lord gave Israel all the land which he solemnly promised to give to their fathers, and they took possession of it, and dwelt therein;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and the Lord gave them rest round about, as he sware to their fathers. Of all their enemies not one rose up against them. The Lord delivered all their enemies into their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>There was not a failure of any of the good things which the Lord spoke to the children of Israel. They were all accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Joshua convened the children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and the half of the tribe of Manasses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and said to them, You have hearkened to all that Moses the servant of the Lord commanded you; and you have obeyed my orders according to all that he commanded you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>You have not for these many years left your brethren: even to this day you have kept the command of the Lord your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now the Lord our God hath given our brethren rest as he promised them. Now therefore return and go to your homes, and to the land of your possession, which Moses gave you on the bank of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But be very careful to perform the commandments and the law which Moses the servant of the Lord charged you to do, to love the Lord our God, to walk in all his ways, to keep his commandments, and to cleave to him and serve him with your whole heart, and with your whole soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then Joshua blessed them and dismissed them, and they set out on their return to their homes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now to one half of the tribe of Manasses Moses had given a possession in Basanitis, and to the other half Joshua gave one on the western side of the Jordan, among their brethren. So when Joshua had sent them away to their homes, and blessed them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>they set out homewards with much wealth, for they had shared with their brethren, vast numbers of cattle, and a great abundance of silver, and gold, and iron, and raiment, the spoil of their enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when the children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, had set out from the children of Israel, at Selo in the land of Chanaan, to go to Galaad, to the land of their possession, which they had got from Moses by the command of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and were come to Galaad of the Jordan, which is in the land of Chanaan, the Reubenites and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses built there an altar by the Jordan; an altar great and conspicuous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when the Israelites heard it said, Behold the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses have built an altar on the borders of the land of Chanaan, at Galaad of the Jordan, on the bank of the children of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>all the Israelites assembled at Selo, to go up to war against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the children of Israel sent to the Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to the half of the tribe of Manasses, to the land of Galaad, Phineas, son of Eleazar, son of Aaron, the chief priest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and ten of the chiefs with him, a chief from the head family of every tribe of Israel. Now the chiefs of the head families are the chiliarchs of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when they came to the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, to the land of Galaad, they spoke to them, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thus saith the whole congregation of the Lord, What trespass is this which you have committed in the presence of the God of Israel, to turn away this day from the Lord, having built for yourselves an altar that you may apostatize from the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Is the sin of Phogor a small matter to you? Because we have not been cleansed from it even to this day, though there was a plague in the congregation of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>are you therefore now turned away from the Lord? For the consequence will be, if you this day apostatize from the Lord, there will be to-morrow wrath against all Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now if the land of your possession be too small for you, come over to the land of the possession of the Lord, where the tabernacle of the Lord is pitched, and take a possession among us, and do not become apostates from God, nor revolt from the Lord by building for yourselves an altar apart from the altar of the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Behold when Achar, son of Zara, committed a trespass in regard to the Anathema, was there not wrath against all the congregation of Israel, so that he perished not alone for his sin?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>In reply to this the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, said to the chiliarchs of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The Lord God is our God, and God himself our God hath seen, and Israel themselves may determine. If through apostacy we have trespassed in the sight of the Lord, let him not this day deliver us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Or if we have built an altar for ourselves, to apostatize from the Lord our God, or to offer thereon a sacrifice of whole burnt offerings, or to offer thereon a sacrifice of thanksgiving, let the Lord make inquisition.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Indeed from a sacred regard to this matter we have done this, saying, That your children may not hereafter say to our children, What have you to do with the Lord God of Israel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The Lord hath made the Jordan a boundary between us and you; so that you have no portion in the Lord. And so your children may make our children strangers, that they may not worship the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>we therefore determined to act in this manner; to build this altar, not for the purpose of homage offerings, nor for sacrifices;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>but that it may be a witness between us and you, and our posterity after us, of our right to perform the service of the Lord before him, with our homage offerings, and our incense offerings, and our sacrifices of thanksgiving; so that your children may not say to our children, You have no portion in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For we said, If it should ever happen that they should speak so to us, or to our posterity hereafter, they may say, Behold the similitude of the altar of the Lord which our fathers made, not for the purpose of homage offerings, nor for sacrifices, but to be a witness between you and us, and our children after us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>God forbid that we should turn away from the Lord, by apostatizing this day from the Lord, so far as to build an altar for the purpose of homage offerings, or incense offerings, or sacrifices of thanksgiving, over and above the altar of the Lord, which is before his tabernacle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>When Phineas the priest, and all the chief's of the congregation of Israel who were with him, heard the words which the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, had spoken, they were pleased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And Phineas the priest said to the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, This day we perceive that the Lord is with us, because you have not committed a trespass before the Lord, and because you have delivered the Israelites out of the hand of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>So Phineas the priest returned, with the chiefs, from the children of Reuben, and from the children of Gad, and from the half of the tribe of Manasses, from Galaad to the land of Chanaan, to the children of Israel, and brought them this answer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and it pleased them. Upon their delivering this message to the children of Israel, they blessed the God of the Israelites, and no more talked of going up against them to battle, to lay waste the land of the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and of the half of the tribe of Manasses. So they dwelt therein,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and Joshua gave a name to the altar of Reuben, and Gad, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, and said, It is a witness for them that the Lord is their God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now after many years, when the Lord had given Israel rest from all their enemies round about, Joshua being far advanced in years,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>convoked all the sons of Israel, their senate, and their chiefs, and their judges, and their under officers, and said to them, I am grown old, and am far advanced in years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now you have seen all that the Lord our God hath done to these nations for your sake; for it is the Lord your God who hath fought for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>You see that I have thrown in among the lots for your tribes, the nations which are left by you, with all the nations which I have exterminated between the Jordan and the great sea, which is to be your western boundary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The Lord our God will himself root them out from before you until they be destroyed. He will send the wild beasts against them, until they utterly destroy them and their kings from before you, so that you may possess their land, as the Lord our God hath spoken to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Be strong therefore to keep with all diligence, and to do all that are written in the book of the law of Moses, that you may not turn aside to the right, nor to the left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>That you may have no fellowship with those nations which are left, the names of their gods must not be mentioned among you; nor shall you perform religious service to them, nor worship them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but you shall cleave to the Lord our God, as you have done to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then will the Lord root them out from before you, though they are great and powerful nations. None indeed have been able to stand before you even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>One of you hath chased a thousand, because the Lord our God himself fought for you, as he promised you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore take good heed to love the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For if you turn away, and join yourselves with those nations which are left with you, and intermarry with them, and be mixed with them, and they with you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>be assured that the Lord will no more drive out those nations from before you; but they shall be to you snares and stumbling blocks, and nails in your heels, and darts in your eyes, until you be destroyed from this good land, which the Lord your God hath given you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>As for me, I am going speedily the way of all who are on the earth. Now you must know in your heart, and in your soul, that not one word hath failed of all that the Lord our God hath said. With respect to all that have come to us, not one of them have failed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now as all the good things, which the Lord hath spoken respecting you, have come to you, so the Lord God will bring upon you all the evil things, until he destroy you from this good land, which the Lord hath given you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>when you transgress the covenant of the Lord our God, which he hath commanded us, and go and serve other gods and worship them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again Joshua assembled all the tribes of Israel at Se lo, and having convened their elders, and their under officers, and their judges, and placed them before God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Joshua said to all the people, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, your fathers dwelt in old time Beyond the river, namely, Thara, the father of Abraham, and the father of Nachor. And they served other gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I took your father Abraham from Beyond the river, and led him through all this land, and multiplied his seed, and gave him Isaak;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and to Isaak, Jacob and Esau; and to Esau I gave mount Seir for a possession; but Jacob and his sons went down into Egypt, and became there a nation, great, numerous and powerful. And when the Egyptians afflicted them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I smote Egypt with signal miracles, which I did among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now after this he brought our fathers out of Egypt, and you marched into the Red sea; and when the Egyptians pursued our fathers, with horses and chariots, into the Red sea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and we cried to the Lord, he put a cloud and darkness between us and the Egyptians; and brought the sea upon them, and it overwhelmed them. Your eyes have seen all that the Lord did in the land of Egypt. And when you had been many years in the wilderness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>he brought us to the land of the Amorites, who dwelt on the border of the Jordan; and the Lord delivered them into our hands, and you took possession of their land, and extirpated them from before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when Balak, son of Sepphor, king of Moab, arose and drew up in array against Israel, and sent for Balaam to curse us,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the Lord thy God would not destroy thee, nay he caused him to bless us with blessings, and rescued us out of their hands, and delivered them up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when you crossed the Jordan, and came to Jericho, and the Amorites who inhabited Jericho, and the Chananites, and the Pherezites, and the Evites, and the Jebusites, and the Chettites, and the Gergasites, fought against us, the Lord delivered them into our hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Indeed he sent before you the hornet, and drove them out from before us, even the twelve kings of the Amorites, not with thy sword, nor with thy bow,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and hath given you a land, on which you did not bestow labour, and cities which you did not build, and you are settled therein, and are eating of vineyards, and olive yards, which you did not plant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now therefore fear the Lord, and serve him with sincerity and truth, and put away the strange gods which our fathers worshipped in beyond the river, and in Egypt, and serve the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But if it seemeth not good to you to serve the Lord, chuse for yourselves this day whom you will serve, either the gods of your fathers which were in beyond the river, or the gods of the Amorites, in whose land you dwell. But as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord; for he is holy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Upon this the people answered, and said, God forbid that we should forsake the Lord to serve other gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The Lord is our God. He is God. He hath brought up us and our fathers out of Egypt, and preserved us all the way we went, and among all the nations through which we passed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and the Lord hath driven out from before us the Amorites, and all the nations who dwelt in this land; therefore we will serve none but the Lord; for he is our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And Joshua said to the people, You may not be able to serve the Lord, because he is the Holy God, and will be zealous. He will not bear with your sins and your iniquities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When you forsake the Lord, and serve other gods, he will come and afflict you; and consume you, proportionally to the good he hath done you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the people said to Joshua, Nay, we will serve none but the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Joshua said to the people, You are witnesses against yourselves that you have chosen the Lord to serve him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now therefore put away the strange gods which are among you, and incline your heart to the Lord God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And the people said to Joshua, We will serve the Lord, and hearken to his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So Joshua made a covenant with the people that day, and gave it to them as a law, and a solemn decision at Selo, before the tabernacle of the Lord God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when he had written these words in the book of the laws of God, he took a great stone, and set it up under a fir tree which was over against the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and Joshua said to the people, Behold this stone shall be among you for a witness, that it hath heard all that were said by the Lord, for he hath this day spoken to you; and this shall be among you for a witness in the latter days, whenever you prove false to the Lord my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Joshua dismissed the people, and they departed every one to his place;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And after those things, Joshua the son of Nave, the servant of the Lord died at the age of a hundred and ten years;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and they buried him in the boundaries of his inheritance, at Thamnasachar, on mount Ephraim, north of mount Gaas. There they deposited with him, in the grave in which they buried him, the stone knives with which he had circumcised the children of Israel at Galgala, as the Lord commanded them, when he had brought them out of Egypt. And there they are at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and Israel served the Lord all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who out lived Joshua, and who had seen all the works of the Lord which he had done for Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now the children of Israel had brought up out of Egypt, the bones of Joseph, and they buried them at Sikimoi, in that portion of the field which Jacob purchased of the Amorites who dwelt at Sikimoi, for a hundred lambs, and which he gave to Joseph for an inheritance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And after these things, Eleazar son of Aaron, the chief priest, died, and was buried in Gabaar, which belonged to Phineas his son, which he had given him on mount Ephraim. At that time the children of Israel took up the ark of God, and carried it about among them. And Phineas officiated as priest in the room of his father Eleazar. And when he died, he was buried in Gabaar, which belonged to him. As for the children of Israel, they had gone to their several homes, and to their respective cities. And when the children of Israel fell to worshipping Astarte, and Astaroth, and the gods of the nations around them, the Lord delivered them into the hands of Eglon king of Moab, and he exercised dominion over them eighteen years.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>