<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now, after the decease of Joshua, the children of Israel inquired of the Lord, saying, Who shall go up for us as our leader against the Chananites, to conduct the war against them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the Lord said, Juda shall go up. Behold I have delivered the land into his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon Juda said to his brother Symeon, Come up with me in my lot, and let us array ourselves against the Chananites, and I will go up with thee in thy lot. So Symeon went up with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Juda went up, and the Lord delivered into their hands the Chananites, and the Pherezites, and they smote them in Bezek, to the number of ten thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When they came up with Adonibezek, in Bezek, they drew up in array against him, and smote the Chananites and the Pherezites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And Adonibezek fled, and they pursued him, and took him, and cut off his thumbs and his great toes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Whereupon Adonibezek said, Seventy kings, having their thumbs and their great toes cut off, have been under my table, gathering up the offals thereof; therefore as I have done, so hath God requited me: And they brought him to Jerusalem, and he died there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>(Now the children of Juda had fought against Jerusalem, and taken it, and smitten it with the edge of the sword, and burned the city with fire;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And, after that, the children of Juda had gone down to wage war with the Chananites, who inhabited the hilly country, and the south, and the plain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when Juda went against the Chananites who dwelt in Chebron, (the name of which city formerly was Kariath-arbok-sepher,) Chebron came out against them; and they smote Sessi, and Achiman, and Tholmi, descendants of Enak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and they went up thence against the inhabitants of Dabir, (now the name of Dabir formerly was Kariath-sepher city of letters)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and Chaleb said, whoever will smite the city of letters, and take it, I will give him my daughter Ascha for a wife;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>whereupon Gothoniel, the younger son of Kenez, Chaleb's brother, took it, and Chaleb gave him his daughter Ascha for a wife,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and when she was going home to him, Gothoniel persuaded her to ask a field of her father: so she murmured, and with a loud voice said, as she was riding, Thou hast sent me away to the land of the south. And Chaleb said to her, What is the matter with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Ascha said to him, Give me, I beseech thee, a blessing. Since thou hast sent me away to the land of the south, thou shouldst therefore give me a portion of water. Thereupon Chaleb gave her according to her desire, a portion of high lands, and a portion of low grounds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now the children of Jothor, the Kenite, Moses' father in law, went up from the city of palm trees, with the children of Juda, into the wilderness, which is in the south of Juda, at the steep of Arad, and dwelt with this tribe.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then Juda went with his brother Symeon, and smote the Chananites who dwelt in Sepheth, and utterly destroyed them, and called the name of that city Anathema.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Though Juda did not take possession of Gaza, nor the borders thereof, nor of Ascalon nor its borders, nor of Akkaron, nor its borders, nor of Azotus, nor the grounds about it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>yet the Lord was with him, and he took possession of the mountain, for they were not enabled to drive out the inhabitants of the vale, because Rechab dissuaded them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now when Chebron was given to Chaleb, as Moses had said, he had from thence taken possession of the three cities of the children of Enak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Neither did the children of Benjamin dispossess the Jebusites, who dwelt at Jerusalem; so the Jebusites have continued to dwell at Jerusalem, with the children of Benjamin, to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>With regard to the children of Joseph, they went up to Baithel, and the Lord was with them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and they encamped near, and kept a watch upon Baithel. (Now the name of that city formerly was Louza.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they who kept watch, looked, and behold a man came out of the city; and they took him, and said to him, Shew us the way into the city, and we will shew thee mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So he shewed them the entrance into the city, and they smote the city with the edge of the sword; but they suffered the man and his family to depart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the man went to the land of Chettin, and built there a city, and called its name Louza, and this continueth to be its name to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But Manasses did not take Baithsan, which is now called Scythopolis nor its towns; nor the lands about it; nor Thanek, nor any of its towns; nor the inhabitants of Dor, nor any of its towns; nor the inhabitants of Balak, nor any of the habitations about it, nor its towns; nor the inhabitants of Magedo, nor any of the habitations around it, nor its towns; nor the inhabitants of Jeblaam, nor any of its surrounding habitations, nor its towns; So the Chananites took the opportunity to settle in that land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>but when Israel grew strong, they subjected the Chananites to tribute, but did not utterly root them out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Neither did Ephraim drive out the Chananites who dwelt in Gazer. So the Chananites dwelt among them in Gazer, and became tributaries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Neither did Zabulon drive out the inhabitants of Kedron, nor the inhabitants of Domana; so the Chananites continued to dwell among them and became tributary to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Neither did Aser drive out the inhabitants of Akcho; but it became tributary to them; nor the inhabitants of Dor; nor the inhabitants of Sidon; nor the inhabitants of Dalaph; nor the Aschazites; nor the Chebdaites; nor the Naites; nor the Ereoites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>So Aser dwelt in the midst of the Chananites who inhabited that land, because he could not drive them out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Neither did Nephthaleim drive out the inhabitants of Baithsamys, nor the inhabitants of Baithanach. So Nephthaleim dwelt in the midst of the Chananites who inhabited that land. And the inhabitants of Baithsamys and Baitheneth became tributary to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>As for the children of Dan, the Amorites harassed them on the mountains, for they did not suffer them to go down into the vale.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the Amorites began to settle on the shelly mountains, on that frequented by bears, and on that frequented by foxes, namely on Myrsinoni, and on Thalabin. But the hand of the house of Joseph was heavy on the Amorites, and they became tributary to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Now the border of the Amorites reached from the steep of Akrabin, from that rock and upwards.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So there went up a messenger of the Lord from Galgal to Wailing, namely to Baithel, to the house of Israel, and said to them, Thus saith the Lord, I caused you to come up out of Egypt, and brought you into this land which I solemnly promised your fathers, and I said I will never break my covenant with you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>therefore you shall not make a covenant with the inhabitants of this land, nor worship their gods; but you shall break to pieces their graven images, and demolish their altars. But you have not hearkened to my voice. Because you have done these things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>therefore I have said, I will not drive them out from before you; but they shall be curbs for you; and their gods shall be to you a stumbling block.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the messenger of the Lord had spoken these words to all the children of Israel, the people wept aloud.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So they called the name of that place, Wailing, and there they sacrificed to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now when Joshua had dismissed the people, and every man had gone to his inheritance to take possession of the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>though the people served the Lord all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who had lived long with Joshua, and who knew all the great works which the Lord had done for Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>yet when Joshua son of Nave, the servant of the Lord, died, at the age of a hundred and ten years,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and they had buried him in the border of his inheritance at Thamnathares, on mount Ephraim, on the north side of mount Gaas;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and all that generation was gathered to their fathers, and another generation arose after them, who knew not the Lord, nor the works which he had done for Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>the children of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord, and served the Baalims.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>They forsook the Lord the God of their fathers, who had brought them out of the land of Egypt, and went after other gods, after some of the gods of the nations around, and worshipped them, and provoked the Lord to wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So when they forsook him, and served Baal, and the Astartees,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, and he delivered them into the hands of spoilers, who spoiled them, and sold them into the hands of their enemies round about, so that they could no longer stand before their enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Wherever they went, the hand of the Lord was against them for evil, as the Lord had spoken, and as the Lord had solemnly denounced to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But when he had afflicted them grievously, the Lord raised up Judges, and the Lord saved them out of the hands of those who spoiled them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When they indeed hearkened not to the judges, because they went a whoring after other gods, and worshipped them, and turned aside quickly out of the way in which their fathers had walked; did not act in obedience to the commands of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>still because the Lord raised up judges for them, therefore the Lord was with the judge, and saved them out of the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge, because the Lord was mollified by their groaning, by reason of them who oppressed them and afflicted them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But when the judge died, and they returned and corrupted themselves more than their fathers, by going after other gods to serve them, and worship them, and would not quit their devices, nor their perverse ways,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>then was the anger of the Lord kindled against Israel, and he said, Because this nation have forsaken my covenant, which I gave in charge to their fathers, and have not hearkened to my voice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>therefore I will not henceforth drive out from before them a man of those nations which Joshua son of Nave left in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He indeed had spared them, that by them he might prove Israel whether they would, or would not, keep the ways of the Lord to walk therein, as their fathers had kept them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and having determined to spare those nations so as not to root them out speedily, the Lord did not deliver them into the hands of Joshua.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the nations which the Lord spared to prove Israel; with an intent moreover, in regard to all those who would be unacquainted with the wars of Chanaan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to instruct in the art of war, not only the present, but the succeeding: generations of the children of Israel, who knew not these things:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>namely the five Satrapies of the Philistines, and all the Chananites, and the Sidonians, and the Evites who inhabited Libanus from mount Aermon to Laboemath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But while he was by them proving Israel, to know whether they would hearken to the commandments of the Lord, which he had given in charge to their fathers by the hand of Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the children of Israel dwelt among the Chananites, and the Chettites, and the Amorites, and the Pherezites, and the Evites, and the Jebusites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and they took their daughters to be their wives; and gave their daughters to their sons, and served their gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thus the children of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord. They forgot the Lord their God, and served the Baalims and the bowers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, and he delivered them into the hands of Cousarsathaim, king of Syrian Mesopotamia, and the children of Israel served him eight years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But when the Israelites cried to the Lord, he raised up a saviour for them, and delivered them, namely Gothoniel the youngest son of Kenez, Chaleb's brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The Spirit of the Lord came upon him, and he judged Israel, and went out to war against Cousarsathaim, and the Lord delivered Cousarsathaim, king of Syrian Mesopotamia, into his hands; and his hand prevailed against Cousarsathaim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and the land had rest Forty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But when Gothoniel son of Kenez died, the children of Israel proceeded to do evil in the sight of the Lord, and the Lord strengthened Eglon, king of Moab, against Israel, because they did evil in the sight of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and he gathered to him all the Ammonites, and the Amalekites, and came and smote Israel, and took possession of the city of palm trees;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and the children of Israel served Eglon king of Moab eighteen years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But when the Israelites cried to the Lord, he raised up for them a deliverer, namely Aod son of Gera, the Jeminite, a man who could use both hands alike. When the children of Israel sent presents by him to Eglon king of Moab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Aod made for himself a two edged dagger, a span long, and girded it under his military robe, on his right thigh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and went and presented the gifts to Eglon king of Moab. Now Eglon was a very polite man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>So when Aod had made an end of presenting the gifts, and had sent away the men who carried the presents,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>he himself returned from the sculptures which are back of Galgal. And Aod said, I have a private message to thee, king. Whereupon Eglon said to him, Be silent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when he had sent away from him all his attendants, Aod went in to him. Now he was sitting alone in his summer parlour, up stairs. And Aod said, I have a message of God to thee, O king. Upon which Eglon arose from his seat, near him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And as he was rising, Aod stretched forth his left hand, and took the dagger from his right thigh, and plunged it into his belly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and thrust the haft in also after the blade, and the fat closed upon the blade, for he did not draw the dagger out of his belly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then Aod went out by the stairs into the porch. He went out beyond the guards, having shut behind him the doors of the parlour, and bolted them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when he was gone, Eglon's servants came, but finding the doors of the parlour bolted, they said, Perhaps he is uncovering his feet in the summer parlour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And when they had waited till they were ashamed, and behold the parlour door is not opened, they took the key and opened it, and behold their lord was fallen; dead upon the floor!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But Aod escaped while they were in confusion, and none attended to him; and having passed the sculptures he got safe to Seteirotha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when Aod came to the land of Israel, he sounded a horn on Mount Ephraim: and the children of Israel went down with him from the mountain, and he before them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And he said to them, Follow me down, for the Lord God hath delivered our enemies; Moab into our hands. So they followed him down, and took possession of the fords of the Jordan before Moab, and suffered not a man to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And they slew of Moab that day about ten thousand men, their whole strength, even every man of valour. Not a man escaped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>So Moab was humbled that day, under the hand of Israel, and the land had rest eighty years. Now Aod judged them till he died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And after him arose Samegar, son of Dinach, who had slain of the Philistines six hundred men with an ox goad, and who also saved Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But the children of Israel proceeded again to do evil in the sight of the Lord, when Aod was dead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and the Lord delivered Israel into the hand of Jabin king of Chanaan, who reigned in Asor. Now the captain general of his army was Sisara, and he dwelt at Arisoth of the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the children of Israel cried to the Lord, for he had nine hundred chariots of iron, and he oppressed Israel grievously, twenty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now Debbora, a prophetess, the wife of Lapidoth, judged Israel at that time,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and had taken her seat under the palm grove of Debbora, between Rama and Baithel, on mount Ephraim; and the children of Israel went up to her for judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And Debbora sent for Barak, son of Abineem, of Kades-Nepthaleim, and said to him, Hath not the Lord God of Israel commanded thee? Go therefore to mount Thabor, and take with thee ten thousand men of the children of Nephthaleim, and of the children of Zabulon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and I will bring out to thee, to the brook Kison, Sisara the captain general of Jabin's army, with his chariots, and his multitude, and deliver him into thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Whereupon Barak said to her, If thou wilt go with me I will go; but if thou will not go, I will not go: for I do not know the day when the Lord would prosper the angel with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And she said I will certainly go with thee; but know, that in the journey which thou takest, the honour of the victory will not be thine; for the Lord will deliver Sisara into the hands of a woman. So Debbora arose, and went with Barak, of Kades.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Barak called out Zabulon and Nephthaleim from Kades, and there went up after him ten thousand men, and Debbora went up with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now Chaber, the Kinite, had removed from Kaina, from among the children of Jobab, Moses' father in law, and had pitched his tent in the oak grove which is near Kades.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when Sisara was told that Barak, son of Abineem, was gone up to mount Thabor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>he called out all his chariots, nine hundred chariots of iron, and all his people with him, from Arisoth of the nations to the brook Kison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And Debbora said to Barak, Arise, for this is the day, on which the Lord hath delivered Sisara into thy hand; for the Lord will march before thee. So Barak went down from mount Thabor with ten thousand men after him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Lord discomfited Sisara, and all his chariots, and all his host, with the edge of the sword, before Barak. And Sisara alighted from his chariot and fled on foot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And Barak pursued the chariots, and the army, to Arisoth of the nations. And the whole army of Sisara fell by the edge of the sword. There was not even a man left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now Sisara had fled, on foot, to the tent of Jael, the wife of Chaber the Kinite; for there was peace between Jabin king of Asor, and the house of Chaber the Kinite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And Jael went out to meet Sisara, and said to him, Turn in my lord; turn in to me. Be not afraid. So he turned in to her; into the tent; and she covered him with a mantle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And Sisara said to her Give me, I pray thee, a little water to drink, for I am thirsty. Whereupon she opened the milk vessel, and gave him drink, and then covered him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Sisara said to her, Stand, I pray thee, at the door of the tent, and if any man come to thee and ask thee, saying, Is there a man here? thou shalt say, There is not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Jael, the wife of Chaber, took the pin of the tent, and a mallet in her hand, and went in softly to him, and drove the pin into his temple, and it went through into the ground. And he fainted away, and was involved in darkness. And when he was dead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>behold Barak came in pursuit of Sisara. And Jael went out to meet him, and said to him, Come, and I will shew thee the man whom thou seekest. So he went in with her, and behold Sisara lay dead with the pin in his temples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So God, on that day, subdued Jabin king of Chanaan before the children of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and the hand of the Israelites prospered, and prevailed against Jabin king of Chanaan, until they utterly destroyed him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then sung Debbora, and Barak son of Abineem, on that day, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Revelation was revealed in Israel when the people offered thank offerings; Praise ye the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Hear, kings! and give ear, princes! I will sing to I am, to the Lord I am; I will sing to the Lord, the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Lord! in thy march out of Seir, When thou didst remove from the fields of Edom; The earth trembled, and heaven distilled dew; The clouds also distilled water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The mountains shook at the presence of the Lord Eloi, That Sina, at the presence of the Lord God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In the days of Samegar son of Anath; in the days of Jael; They forsook the high, ways and travelled in bye paths; They travelled in crooked winding roads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The mighty men of Israel were faint hearted; They were faint hearted till Debbora arose; Until there arose a mother in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>They had chosen new gods; Then was war made upon the cities of chiefs, if a buckler was seen, or a spear among forty thousand in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>My heart was fixed on what were enjoined Israel. Ye among the people who offer thank offerings, Praise ye the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Ye who have mounted your asses at noon day, Ye who sit in the seat of judgment, Ye who travel the high ways to the publick assemblies,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Make proclamation on the road, on account of the voice of them Who shout amidst the drawers of water. There let them rehearse gracious deliverances. Increase, Lord, gracious deliverances in Israel. Then went the people of the Lord down to their cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Awake, awake, Debbora! Awake, awake, utter a song. Arise, Barak! And lead thy captivity captive, son of Abineem</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then went down a remnant to the mighty: The Lord's people went down to him with my valiant men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Ephraim rooted out them in Amelek; After thee was Benjamin with thy people; With me went down the scouting Machirites, And from Zabulon, they who array with the marshal's staff.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The leaders in Issachar also were with Debbora and Barak. Thus was Barak in the vales. He had sent a courier to the factions of Reuben. The bold hearted are just setting out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Why did they tarry among their sheepfolds? Was it to hear the bleating of their flocks? For the divisions of Reuben, there were great searchings of heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Why abode Galaad beyond the Jordan where he dwelt? And why doth Dan sojourn in ships? Aser seated himself on the sea shore, And chuseth to dwell in his extreme borders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The people of Zabulon jeoparded their lives to death; And Nephthaleim came to the high places of the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Kings had drawn themselves up in array. Then fought the kings of Chanaan at Thanach; At the waters of Mageddo; They had not received the gift of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The stars from heaven were drawn up in array; From their orbits they fought against Sisara.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The torrent of Kison swept them away; The ancient torrent; the torrent Kison. My mighty soul shall trample them down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When the feet of the horse were entangled, with precipitate speed, they who were able, fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Curse Meroz, said the messenger of the Lord. Curse ye it bitterly. Cursed be every one who dwelleth therein, Because they came not to the help of the Lord; To the help of the Lord among the mighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Blessed among women be Jael the wife of Chaber the Kinite: Above women in tents may she be blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He asked for water; she gave him milk; From her churning vessel she brought him whey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>She stretched forth her left hand to the tent pin; And her right hand to the workman's mallet. And with the mallet she smote Sisara. She drove the pin into his head and smote him; She drove the pin quite through his temples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>At her feet he had thrown himself down; He prostrated himself, and fell asleep at her feet. Throwing himself down, he had prostrated himself. As he lay there he fell and finished his course.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Through a window the mother of Sisara looked earnestly; Out of that of an archer she cried, Why is his chariot so long a coming? Why tarry the wheels of his chariot?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Her wise ladies answered her; Nay she returned an answer to herself,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Shall they not find him dividing spoil? Will he shew compassion to the head of a man? Sisara shall have spoils of richest dyes; Spoils of richest dyes of needle work. Rich dyes of embroidery are the spoils for his neck!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So perish all thine enemies, Lord, But let them who love thee be like The going forth of the Sun in his might. So the land had rest forty years.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again the children of Israel did evil in the sight of the Lord, and the Lord delivered them into the hand of Madiam seven years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the hand of Madiam prevailed against Israel, so that because of Madiam, the Israelites made for themselves those dens which are in the mountains, and those caves and strong holds in cliffs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when the Israelites had sown, Madiam and Amelek came up, and the children of the east came up with them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and encamped against them, and destroyed their fruits, all the way to Gaza. In all the land of Israel they did not leave sustenance for life, nor among the herds a bull or a jack ass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For they came up with cattle. And their tents were pitched like locusts for multitude: and they and their camels were innumerable. And they came into the land of Israel, and wasted it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>so that Israel was greatly impoverished by the Madianites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when the children of Israel cried to the Lord because of Madiam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the Lord sent a prophet to the children of Israel, and he said to them, Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel. It was I who brought you up from the land of Egypt. I brought you out of a house of your bondage,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all those who are afflicting you, and drove them out from before you, and gave you this their land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and said to you, I the Lord am your God. You shall not fear the gods of the Amorites in whose land you dwell. But you have not hearkened to my voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then there came an angel of the Lord, and sat under the fir tree, which is at Ephratha, in the land of father Joas, the Esdrite. Now Gideon, his son, was beating out corn in the wine</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>press, with an intent to flee from before Madiam. And the angel of the Lord appeared to him, and said to him, The Lord</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>is with thee? the Mighty Lord of Hosts. Whereupon Gideon said to him, With me, my lord! But if the Lord is with us, why have these evils befallen us? And where are all his wondrous works, of which our fathers have told us, saying, Hath not the Lord brought us up out of Egypt? But he hath now cast us off, and delivered us into the hand of Madiam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the angel of the Lord turned towards him and said, Go in this thy might, and thou shalt save Israel out of the hand of Madiam. Behold I have sent thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Upon which Gideon said to him, Me, my lord! How can I save Israel? Behold my thousand is weak in Manasses; and I am the least in my father's house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the angel of the Lord said to him, The Lord will be with thee, and thou shalt smite Madiam like one man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whereupon Gideon said to him, If I have found favour in thy sight, and thou wilt now do for me all that thou hast said to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>go not away, I beseech thee, from this place till I come to thee, and bring out the sacrifice, and set it before thee. And he said, I will assuredly tarry till thou return.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thereupon Gideon went, and prepared a kid of the goats, and the unleavened cakes of an epha of barley meal; and having put the flesh in a basket, and the soup in a pot, he brought them out to him under the fir tree, and set them before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then the angel of God said to him, Take the flesh, and unleavened cakes, and lay them on that rock, and pour out the soup close by.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And when he had done so, the angel of the Lord stretched out the point of the staff in his hand, and touched the flesh and the unleavened cakes; and fire came up out of the rock, and consumed the flesh and the unleavened cakes; and the angel of the Lord vanished out of his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When Gideon saw that it was an angel of the Lord, he said, Alas! alas! Lord, my lord! For have I seen the angel of the Lord face to face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the Lord said to him, Peace be to thee. Fear not. Thou shalt not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Upon which Gideon built there an altar to the Lord, and called it, Peace of the Lord. To this day it is still at Ephratha, which belonged to father Esdri.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And on that same night the Lord said to him, Take the young bull; the bull belonging to thy father, the second bull of seven years old, and having demolished the altar of Baal which is for thy father, and destroyed the arbour near it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>thou shalt build an altar to the Lord thy God, on the top of Maozi, in the parade; and thou shalt take the second bull, and offer whole burnt offerings on the wood of the arbour which thou hast demolished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So Gideon took ten men of his servants, and did as the Lord had spoken to him. But as he was afraid of doing it by day, because of his father's house, and the men of the city, he did it by night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when the men of the city arose early in the morning, and lo! the altar of Baal was pulled down, and the arbour near it destroyed, and they saw the second bull which he had offered on the altar which he had built,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>they said one to another, Who hath done this? And when they had made diligent inquiry, and found, and knew that Gideon son of Joas had done the deed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>the men of the city said to Joas, Bring out thy son, and let him be put to death, because he hath pulled down the altar of Baal, and because he hath destroyed the arbour which was beside it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Whereupon Gideon son of Joas said to all the men who had risen up against him, Do you now plead for Baal, and will you save him? Whoever shall plead for Baal, let him be put to death this morning. If he is a god, let him plead for himself, because somebody hath pulled down his altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>So this gave him on that day the name of Jerobaal, as he said, Let Baal plead for himself, because this altar of his is pulled down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Now all Madiam, and Amalek, and the children of the east, had assembled together and encamped in the valley of Jesrael.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And the Spirit of the Lord came upon Gideon, and he sounded a horn, and called out Abiezer after him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>He also sent messengers to all Manasses, and through Aser, and through Zabulon, and through Nephthaleim. And when they came up to meet him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Gideon said to God, If thou wilt save Israel by my hand, as thou hast spoken,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>behold I lay this fleece of wool on the threshing floor; If there be dew on this fleece only, and all the ground be dry, then I shall know that thou wilt save Israel by my hand as thou hast spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>This was accordingly done. And when he arose early the next morning he pressed the fleece, and wringed out the dew from the fleece, a bowl full of water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Then Gideon said to God, Let not, I beseech thee, thy anger be kindled against me: let me, I pray thee, make one trial more with the fleece; and let it be dry on the fleece only, and on all the ground let there be dew.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And God did so that night; and it was dry on the fleece only, and on all the ground there was dew.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Jerobaal (the same is Gideon) arose early in the morning, and all the people with him, and they encamped by the well Arad. Now the camp of Madiam was to the north of him, at the foot of Gabaathamorai, in the valley.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the Lord said to Gideon, The people with thee are too numerous for me to deliver Madiam into their hands. Perhaps they may boast against me saying, My own hand hath saved me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now therefore speak in the hearing of the people, and say, If any man is fearful, or timorous, let him depart from mount Galaad. So there returned of the people twenty two thousand: and ten thousand were left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the Lord said to Gideon, The people are still too numerous: bring them to the water, and I will purge them there for thee. And it shall be that of whomsoever I say, This man shall go with thee; he shall go with thee. And of whomsoever I say, This man shall not go with thee; he shall not go with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So he took the people to the water. And the Lord said to Gideon, Whosoever shall lap of the water with his tongue, as a dog lappeth, him thou shalt set apart; likewise every one who shall bow down on his knees to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And it came to pass that the number of them who lapped, by putting their hand to their mouth, was three hundred men: but all the rest of the people bowed down on their knees to drink water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Gideon, By these three hundred men who have lapped I will save you, and deliver Madiam into thy hands. Let all those people therefore go, every man to his home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So they took the people's provisions at their hands, and their trumpets; and having dismissed all the rest of Israel, every man to his tent, he retained the three hundred. Now the camp of Madiam was below him in the vale.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And that night the Lord said to him, Arise, and go down through the camp, for I have delivered it into thy hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But if thou art afraid to go down; go thou, and thy servant Phara, to the edge of the camp,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and hear what they will say, and afterwards thy hands will be strengthened to go down into the camp. So he and his servant Phara went down to a company of fifty, who were in the camp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now Madiam, and Amalek, and all the children of the east lay along in the valley, like grasshoppers, for multitude, and their camels were innumerable. They were like the sand on the sea shore for multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when Gideon drew near, behold there was a man telling his comrade a dream. And he said, Behold I have had a dream. I thought I saw a cake of barley bread rolling about in the camp of Madiam, and it came to this tent, and smote it, and it fell. It indeed overturned it, and the tent fell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And his comrade answered, and said, Is not this the sword of Gideon, son of Joas the Israelite? God hath delivered into his hand Madiam and all this camp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when Gideon heard the dream, and the interpretation of it, he worshipped the Lord, and returned to the camp of Israel, and said, Arise, for the Lord hath delivered into our hand the camp of Madiam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then he divided the three hundred men into three companies, and put a trumpet in every man's hand, and empty pitchers with lamps in the pitchers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and said to them, Attend to me and do as I do. And whatever I do when I come to the edge of the camp, see that you do the same.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When I sound the horn, I and all with me; sound ye your horns, all around the camp, and say, For the Lord and for Gideon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So Gideon, and the three hundred men who were with him, came to the border of the camp, at the beginning of the middle watch, and having alarmed the guards, they sounded the horns, and shook the pitchers which were in their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the three companies had sounded the horns, they broke the pitchers, and held the flambeaus in their left hands, and their trumpets in their right, and shouted, A sword for the Lord and for Gideon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and stood every man in his place around the camp. And while the whole camp was running, and making signals, and fleeing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>they sounded the three hundred horns; and the Lord set every man's sword against his fellow throughout the whole camp. And when the host had fled as far as Bethseed, Tagaratha Abelmeoula near Tabath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>the men of Israel assembled from Nephthaleim, and from Aser, and from all Manasses, and pursued Madiam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Gideon sent messengers through all Ephraim, saying, Haste down to meet Madiam, and take possession of the waters, even to Baithera, and the Jordan. Upon which the men of Ephraim assembled, and, before the Madianites came up, got possession of the waters, even to Baithera, and the Jordan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and they took the princes of Madiam, Oreb and Zeb, and they slew Oreb at Sour Oreb, and Zeb they slew at Jakeph Zeph. And having pursued Madiam, they brought the heads of Oreb and Zeb to Gideon, from the border of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the man Ephraim said to Gideon, What is this that thou hast done to us in not calling upon us when thou wentest out to fight Madiam? And they spoke sharply to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But he said to them, What have I now done in comparison of you? Is not the gleaning of Ephraim better than the vintage of Abiezer?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The Lord hath delivered into your hand the princes of Madiam, Oreb and Zeb. Now what have I been enabled to do in comparison of you? And upon his saying this, their anger against him abated.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when Gideon came to the Jordan, and crossed it, he and the three hundred men who were with him, hungry, but still pursuing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>he said to the men of Sokchoth, Give, I pray you, bread to feed the people who follow me, for they are fainty, and behold I am pursuing Zebee and Salmana, the kings of Madiam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the chiefs of Sokchoth said, Is the hand of Zebee and Salmana now in thy hand, that we should give thy army bread?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thereupon Gideon said, For this, when the Lord hath delivered Zebee and Salmana into my hand, I will tear your flesh with the thorns of the wilderness, even with those of Barkenim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And he went up thence to Phanuel, and spoke to them in like manner; and the men of Phanuel answered him as the men of Sokchoth had done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Whereupon Gideon said to the men of Phanuel, When I return in peace, I will demolish that tower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now Zebee and Salmana were at Karkar, and their army with them, about fifteen thousand men, all who were left of the whole host of the foreign tribes, they who had fallen being a hundred and twenty thousand men who drew the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So Gideon went up by the way of them who dwell in tents, eastward of Nabai and Jegebal, and smote the camp, though the camp thought themselves secure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Zebee and Salmana fled, and he pursued them, and took the two kings of Madiam, Zebee and Salmana, and discomfited the whole host.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when Gideon, son of Joas, returned from the engagement, back from the engagement at Ares;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>he caught a young man of the men of Sokchoth, and inquired of him, and he wrote down for him the names of the chiefs of Sokchoth, and of their elders, seventy seven men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when Gideon came to the chiefs of Sokchoth, he said, Behold Zebee and Salmana, with whom you upbraided me, saying, Is the hand of Zebee and Salmana now in thy hand, that we should give bread to the men with thee who are fainty?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then he took the elders of the city, and scourged them with the thorns of the wilderness, even with those of Barkenim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when he had scourged the men of that city, in the midst of them, he demolished the tower of Phanuel, and slew the men of that city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then he said to Zebee and Salmana, What sort of men were they whom ye slew at Thabor? And they said, As thou art so were they. They resembled the children of a king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Whereupon Gideon said, They were my brothers, the sons of my mother. As the Lord liveth, if you had saved them alive, I would not have killed you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then he said to Jether his first born, Arise and slay them. But the youth drew not his sword, for he was afraid, for he was yet very young.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whereupon Zebee and Salmana said, Arise thou thyself, and fall upon us, for thou hast the strength of a man. So Gideon arose, and slew Zebee and Salmana, and took the ornaments which were on the necks of their camels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Israel said to Gideon, My lord, rule over us, both thou and thy son, and thy son's son, because thou hast saved us out of the hand of Madiam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But Gideon said to them, I will not rule over you. Nor shall my son rule over you. The Lord will rule over you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then Gideon said to them. I have a favour to ask of you. Give me every man the earrings of his spoils; for the enemy wore gold ear rings, because they were Ismaelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And they said, We will give them cheerfully. So he spread his mantle, and they threw thereon, every man, the ear rings of his spoils;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and the weight of the gold ear-rings, which he had requested, was a thousand seven hundred shekels of gold, exclusive of the necklaces, and bracelets, and the garments, and purple robes, which were on the kings of Madiam, and exclusive of the chains which were about the neck of their camels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And of this Gideon made an ephod, and set it up in his city in Ephratha; and all Israel went there a whoring after it, and it became a stumbling block to Gideon, and his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thus Madiam was subdued before the children of Israel, so that they never any more raised their head. And the land had rest forty years during the days of Gideon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Jerobaal son of Joas, went and dwelt at his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now Gideon had seventy sons who proceeded from his loins, for he had many wives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>He had moreover a concubine, in Sychem, and she also bore him a son, and called his name Abimelech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And Gideon son of Joas died in his city, and was buried in the tomb of his father Joas, in Ephratha Abiesdri.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And when Gideon was dead the children of Israel turned, and went a whoring after the Baalims, and made for themselves a covenant with Baal, that he should be their god.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>The children of Israel neither remembered the Lord God who had delivered them out of the hands of all those who afflicted them round about;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>nor did they deal kindly with the house of Jerobaal, namely Gideon, according to all the good which he had done for Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For when Abimelech, son of Jerobaal, went to Sychem, to his mother's brethren, and spoke to them, and to all the relations of the house of his mother's father, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Speak I pray you in the hearing of all the men of Sychem, Which is best for you; that seventy men, even all the sons of Jerobaal, should rule over you; or that one man should rule over you? Remember also that I am your bone and your flesh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>his mother's brethren spoke all these words for him in the hearing of the men of Sychem, and their heart inclined to follow Abimelech; for they said, He is our brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So they gave him seventy weight of silver, out of the house of Baal-berith; and Abimelech hired for himself vain profligate men, who followed him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and he went to his father's house at Ephratha, and slew his brothers, the sons of Jerobaal, seventy men, on one stone. Jotham indeed, the youngest son of Jerobaal was left, for he had hid himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then all the Sychemites, and all the house of Bethmaalo, assembled and went and proclaimed Abimelech king, near the oak grove, which was invented for the assembling at Sychem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When the news of this was told Jotham, he went and stood on the top of mount Garizin, and raising his voice, he wept, and said to them, Hear me, ye Sychemites, that God may hear you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The trees went forth to anoint a king over them, and they said to the olive, Reign thou over us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But the olive said to them, Shall I leave my fatness with which men honour God, and go to wave over the trees?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then the trees said to the fig tree, Come thou and reign over us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But the fig tree said to them, Shall I leave my sweetness, and good fruit, and go to wave over the trees?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the trees said to the vine, Come and reign over us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But the vine said to them, Shall I leave my wine, which cheereth gods and men, and go to wave over the trees?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then all the trees said to the bramble, Come thou and reign over us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Upon which the bramble said to the trees, If in truth you anoint me to reign over you, come and stand in my shade; if not, let a fire go out from me, and consume the cedars of Lebanon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now therefore if you have acted with truth and uprightness in making Abimelech king; and if you have dealt righteously with Jerobaal, and his house, or done to him according to the deserving of his hand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>As my father fought for you, and adventured his life, and delivered you out of the hand of Madiam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and you have risen up against my father's house, and have slain his seventy sons on one stone, and made Abimelech, the son of his concubine, king over the men of Sychem, because he is your brother;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>if therefore you have this day acted with truth, and uprightness, in regard to Jerobaal, and his house, may you have joy in Abimelech, and he have joy in you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but if not; may a fire come out from Abimelech, and consume the Sychemites, and the house of Bethmaalo; and may a fire come out from the Sychemites, and the house of Bethmaalo, and consume Abimelech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Jotham fled, and left his country, and went to Baier, and dwelt there for fear of his brother Abimelech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now when Abimelech had reigned three years over Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>God sent an evil spirit between Abimelech and the Sychemites, and the Sychemites dealt treacherously with the house of Abimelech,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>that he might bring the injustice done to the seventy sons of Jerobaal, and lay their blood, on the head of their brother Abimelech, who slew them, and on the Sychemites because they strengthened his hands to kill his brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the Sychemites set men in ambush for him on the tops of the mountains, and they robbed all that came along by them that way: and king Abimelech had information of this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But when Gaal son of Jobel came with his brethren, and joined the Sychemites, the men of Sychem put confidence in him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and went out into the fields, and gathered their vintage, and trod out their grapes, and uttered the usual shouts of joy, and carried offerings to the house of their god, and ate and drank, and cursed Abimelech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And Gaal son of Jobel said, Who is Abimelech? And who is the son of Sychem, that we should serve him? Is not this son of Jerobaal and Zebul his overseer; his slave, with all the men of Emmor, the property of father Sychem? Why then should we serve him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>that this people were under my hand! I would depose Abimelech, and say to him, Increase thy army, and come out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>When Zebul, the ruler of the city, heard the words of Gaal, son of Jobel, he was fired with indignation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and sent messengers secretly to Abimelech, saying, Behold Gaal, son of Jobel, with his brethren, are come to Sychem, and lo! they have set the city against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now therefore arise by night, thou, and the people with thee, and lie in wait in the fields;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>so that in the morning, soon as the sun is up, thou mayst rise betimes, and approach the city, and behold when he and the people with him go out, and meet thee, thou shalt do to him as the occasion may direct.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Accordingly Abimelech arose by night, and all the people with him, and lay in wait against Sychem, in four companies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And Gaal son of Jobel went out and stood at the entrance of the gate of the city, and Abimelech, and the people with him, arose from the ambush.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And when Gaal son of Jobel saw the people, he said to Zebul, Behold there are people coming down from the tops of the mountains. And Zebul said to him, Thou seest the shadow of the mountains like men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Gaal spoke again, and said. Behold there are people coming down, westward, from the middle ground, and there is another company coming by the way of Elon-maonenim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then Zebul said to him, Where is now thy mouth with which thou saidst, Who is Abimelech, that we should serve him? Is not this the people whom thou didst despise? Go out now, I pray thee, and fight them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Whereupon Gaal went out before the men of Sychem, and drew up in array against Abimelech,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and Abimelech pursued him, and he fled from before him, and there fell many wounded, even to the entrance of the gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then Abimelech went to Aremo, and Zebul expelled Gaal and his brethren, that they should not dwell in Sychem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And the next morning the people went out to the fields. When this was told Abimelech,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>he took the people, and divided them into three companies, and lay in wait in the fields. And when he had taken a view, and behold the people came out of the city, he rose upon them, and smote them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and Abimelech, and the officers who were with him, rushed forward and took post at the entrance of the gate of the city, and the two other companies5 fell upon all in the fields, and smote them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And Abimelech fought against the city the whole day, and having taken the city, he slew the people in it, and demolished the city, and sowed it with salt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Now when all the men of the tower of Sychem heard this, they repaired to the fort Baithel-berith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And when it was told Abimelech that all the men of the tower of Sychem were assembled together,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>he went up to mount Selmon, with all the people who were with him. And Abimelech took an ax in his hand, and cut a bough of a tree, and took it and put it on his shoulder, and said to the people who were with him, Haste and do as I; what you have seen me do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>So they cut every man a bough, and went after Abimelech, and piled them up against the fort, and set the fort on fire about them, so that all the men of the tower of Sychem died, about a thousand men and women.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Then Abimelech went from Baithel-berith, and encamped against Thebes, and took it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>But there was a strong tower in the midst of the city, and all the men and the women of the city fled thither, and shut the gate after them, and went up to the top of the tower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>And Abimelech came to the tower, and when they opposed him, Abimelech went near to the gate of the tower to set it on fire,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>and a woman threw a piece of a millstone upon Abimelech's head, and fractured his scull;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>whereupon he cried hastily to the young man who carried his armour, and said to him, Draw my sword, and kill me, that they may not say, A woman killed him. So his servant run him through, and he died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>And when the men of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, they went every man to his place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Thus God turned upon Abimelech the wickedness which he had committed against his father, in killing his seventy brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>God also turned upon the head of the men of Sychem all their wickedness, and upon them came the curse of Jotham son of Jerobaal.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after Abimelech, there arose to defend Israel, Thola son of Phuah, the son of his father's brother, a man of Issachar, and he dwelt at Samir on mount Ephraim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when he had judged Israel twenty three years, he died, and was buried at Samir.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And after him arose Jair, the Galaadite, and he judged Israel twenty two years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now he had thirty two sons, who rode on thirty two ass-colts, and they had thirty two cities, which are called, The folds of Jair, to this day, in the land of Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And Jair died, and was buried at Ramnon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the children of Israel proceeded again to do evil in the sight of the Lord, and served the Baals, and the Astartes, and the gods of Aram, and the gods of Sidon, and the gods of Moab, and the gods of Ammon, and the gods of the Philistines, and forsook the Lord, and did not serve him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Whereupon the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, and he delivered them into the hands of the Philistines, and into the hand of the children of Ammon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and they afflicted, and oppressed the children of Israel, at that time eighteen years, even all the children of Israel who were on the border of the Jordan, in the land of the Amorites, in Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Moreover the children of Ammon crossed the Jordan to fight against Juda, and Benjamin, and against Ephraim, so that the Israelites were grievously oppressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when the children of Israel cried to the Lord, and said, We have sinned against thee, because we have forsaken God, and served Baals,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>the Lord said to the Israelites, Did I not deliver you out of Egypt, and from the Amorites and the Ammonites, and the Philistines,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and the Sidonians, and Amalek, and Madiam, who afflicted you? When you cried to me, I saved you out of their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But you have forsaken me, and served other gods, therefore I will deliver you no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Go and cry to the gods which you have chosen for yourselves, and let them deliver you in the time of your tribulation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the children of Israel said to the Lord, We have sinned. Do thou thyself to us, whatever seemeth good in thine eyes, but deliver us this time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And they put away the strange gods from among them, and served the Lord alone. Whereupon his heart relented at the distress of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now the children of Ammon had gone up, and encamped in Galaad; and the children of Israel assembled and encamped at the watch tower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the people, the chiefs of Galaad, said to one another, Whoever will undertake to fight the children of Ammon, he shall be ruler over all the inhabitants of Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now Jephthae, the Galaadite, was at the head of an army. He was the son of a harlot, who bore Jephthae to Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Galaad's wife also bore him sons; and when the wife's sons grew up, they thrust out Jephthae, and said to him, Thou shalt have no inheritance in the house of our father; for thou art the son of a concubine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Upon which Jephthae fled from the face of his brothers, and dwelt in the land of Tob. And there were gathered to Jephthae men of desperate fortunes, who went out with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now when the children of Ammon came out in array to fight against Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the elders of Galaad went to bring Jephthae from the land of Tob,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and they said to him, Come and be our leader that we may fight the Ammonites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>whereupon Jephthae said to the elders of Galaad, Have you not hated me, and driven me from my father's house, and sent me away from you? Why then are you come to me now when you are in distress?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the elders of Galaad said to him, It is for this very reason, that we have now come to thee. Therefore thou must come with us, and fight the children of Ammon, and thou shalt be our chief over all the inhabitants of Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then Jephthae said to the elders of Galaad, If you take me back to fight the children of Ammon, and the Lord deliver them up before me, I shall be your chief?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the elders of Galaad said to him, Let the Lord be witness between us, if we do not according to this thy word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thereupon Jephthae went with the elders of Galaad, and the people made him head and leader over them. And when Jephthae had repeated all these his terms before the Lord, at Massepha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>he sent messengers to the king of the Ammonites, saying, What hast thou to do with me, that thou art come up against me to fight in my land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the king of the Ammonites said to Jephthae's messengers; Because Israel took my land when they came up out of Egypt, from Arnon to Jabok, and to the Jordan. Now therefore restore me those lands peaceably, and I will depart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thereupon Jephthae again sent messengers to the king of the Ammonites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and said to him, Thus saith Jephthae, Israel did not take the land of Moab, nor the land of the children of Ammon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For when they came out of Egypt, Israel marched through the wilderness to the sea of Siph, and came to Kades;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and Israel sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, Let me, I pray thee, march through thy land; but the king of Edom did not consent. They sent also to the king of Moab; but the king of Moab did not consent. So after halting at Kades,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Israel marched through the wilderness, and went round the land of Edom, and the land of Moab, and came eastward of Moab, and encamped on the bank of the Arnon, but did not enter the borders of Moab; for Arnon was the boundary of Moab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then Israel sent messengers to Seon, king of the Amorites; the king of Esebon, and said to him, Let us we pray thee pass through thy land to our place;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but Seon would not trust Israel to pass through along his border, but assembled all his people, and encamped at Jasa, and came to an engagement with Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the Lord God of Israel delivered into the hands of Israel, Seon and all his people, and they smote him. So Israel took possession of all the land of the Amorites, who inhabited the country</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>from Arnon to Jabok and from the wilderness to the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now therefore hath the Lord God of Israel removed the Amorites from before his people, and art thou to possess them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If thy god Chamos were to put thee in possession of any places, wouldst thou not possess them? And shall not we succeed all those whom the Lord our God hath removed from before us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Besides, art thou in any respect better than Balak, son of Sepphor, king of Moab? Did he ever contend with Israel, or go to war with them about this,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>all the while they lived in Esebon, and the borders thereof, and in the land of Aroer, and the borders thereof, and in all the cities along the Jordan, for three hundred years? Why didst thou not in all this time recover them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now therefore I call God to witness, that I have not sinned against thee, and that thou dealest wrongfully in going to war with me. Let the Lord, who is Judge, judge this day between Israel and the Ammonites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when the king of the Ammonites hearkened not to the message which Jephthae sent him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>the Spirit of the Lord came upon Jephthae, and he marched through Galaad, and Manasses, and passed the watch tower of Galaad, into the border of the children of Ammon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And Jephthae vowed a vow to the Lord, and said, If thou deliver the children of Ammon into my hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>it shall be, that whosoever cometh from the door of my house to meet me, when I return in peace from the children of Ammon, shall be for the Lord. Him will I dedicate as a whole burnt offering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And when Jephthae passed on to come to battle with the children of Ammon, the Lord delivered them into his hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and he smote them from Aroer all the way to Arnon, through the number of twenty cities, and even to Ebelcharmin, with a prodigious slaughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And when the children of Ammon were subdued before the children of Israel, and Jephthae came to Massepha, to his house, behold his daughter came out to meet him, with timbrels and choirs. Now she was his only child. Besides her, he had neither son nor daughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when he saw her he rent his clothes, and said, Alas! Alas! my daughter! Thou hast indeed troubled me; and thou thyself mayst be in trouble with me, for I have opened my mouth to the Lord against thee, and I cannot go back.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Upon which she said to him, Hast thou, my father, opened thy mouth to the Lord? Do to me according to what hath proceeded out of thy mouth, since the Lord hath executed vengeance for thee on thine enemies; on the children of Ammon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then she said to her father, Grant me; my father, I pray thee, this favour. Let me alone two months, and I will go up and down on the mountains, and bewail my virginity; I call God to witness, with only my female attendants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And he said, Go. So he sent her away two months, and she went with her female attendants, and bewailed her virgin state on the mountains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And at the end of two months she returned to her father and he performed with her his vow, which he had vowed; so she knew not a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And it was a custom in Israel, from year to year, for the daughters of Israel to go and bewail the daughter of Jephthae, the Galaadite, four days in the year.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the Ephraimites assembled, and went northward, and said to Jephthae, Why didst thou go to fight the Ammonites, and not call on us to go with thee? We will burn thy house over thee with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Jephthae said to them, When I and my people, and the children of Ammon, were at hard conflict, I called on you; but you did not save me out of their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So when I saw that thou wast not a deliverer, I put my life in my hand, and went against the Ammonites, and the Lord delivered them into my hand. Why then are you come up this day to fight against me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Jephthae re-assembled all the men of Galaad, and came to an engagement with Ephraim. And the men of Galaad smote Ephraim. Because they of Ephraim who were saved, said, You Galaadites belong partly to Ephraim, and partly to Manasses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore the Galaadites seized the passages of the Jordan before Ephraim; and when those of Ephraim who escaped, said, Let us cross over; the men of Galaad said to them, Art thou an Ephraimite?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when any said, No, then they said to him, say Stachys. And if he did not pronounce it distinctly, they took him, and slew him at the passages of the Jordan. So there fell of Ephraim, at that time, forty two thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And Jephthae judged Israel six years. Then Jephthae the Galaadite died, and was buried in his own city, Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And after him, Abaissan of Bethlehem, judged Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he had thirty sons and thirty daughters. His daughters he sent abroad, and he brought from abroad thirty daughters for his sons, and he judged Israel seven years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Abaissan died, and was buried in Bethlehem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And after him Ailom, the Zabulonite, judged Israel ten years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Ailom the Zabulonite died, and was buried in Ailom, in the land of Zabulon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And after him Abdon, son of Ellel, the Pharathonite, judged Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he had forty sons, and thirty grand sons, who rode on seventy colts; and he judged Israel eight years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Abdon, son of Ellel the Pharathonite, died, and was buried at Pharathon, in the land of Ephraim, on mount Amelek.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the children of Israel again proceeded to do evil in the sight of the Lord, and the Lord delivered them into the hand of the Philistines, forty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now there was a man of Saraa, a community of the Danites, whose name was Manoe; and his wife was barren, and never had a child.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And an angel of the Lord appeared to the woman, and said to her, Behold, thou art barren and hast never had a child. But thou shalt conceive a son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now therefore be careful not to drink wine, nor any fermented liquor, nor eat any thing which is unclean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For behold thou art with child, and shalt bear a son; and on his head a razor shall not come; for the child shall be a Nazarite to God from the womb. And he shall begin to save Israel out of the hand of the Philistines.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the woman went, and told her husband, saying, There came to me a man of God, and his visage was like that of an angel of God, very awful, so that I did not ask him whence he was, nor did he tell me his name. But he said to me, Behold thou art with</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>child, and shalt bear a son. Now therefore thou must not drink wine nor any fermented liquor, nor eat any thing unclean; for the child shall be consecrated to God, from the womb to the day of his death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Whereupon Manoe prayed to the Lord, and said, Lord Adonaie! grant me that the man of God, whom thou didst send, may come to us again, and instruct us what we shall do to the child which is to be born.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And God hearkened to the voice of Manoe, and the angel of God came again to the woman. Now she was sitting in the field, and Manoe her husband was not with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So the woman hasted, and ran and told her husband, and said to him, The man hath appeared to me, who came to me before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Upon which Manoe arose, and went with his wife, and when he came to the man, he said to him, Art thou the man who spoke to my wife? And the angel said, I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Manoe said, Now the thing will come to pass. How is the child to be educated, and what is he to do?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the angel of the Lord said to Manoe, He must abstain from all the things which I mentioned to this woman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He must eat nothing which proceedeth from the vine, nor drink wine, nor any fermented liquor, nor eat any thing which is unclean. He must observe all that I have commanded her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Manoe said to the angel of the Lord, Let us detain thee here till we set before thee a kid of the goats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the angel of the Lord said to Manoe, Though thou detain me I cannot eat of thy victuals; but if thou wouldst offer a whole burnt offering, offer it to the Lord. Because Manoe did not know that he was an angel of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore Manoe said to him, What is thy name, that when thy word cometh to pass we may honour thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the angel of the Lord said to Manoe, Why askest thou my name? It is indeed wonderful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then Manoe took the kid of the goats, with the sacrifice of flour, and carried them up upon the rock for the Lord. And he went apart to offer the sacrifice, while Manoe and his wife were looking on.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the flame ascended above the altar, up towards heaven, the angel of the Lord ascended in the flame. When Manoe and his wife saw this, they fell flat with their face to the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And as the angel of the Lord no more appeared to Manoe and his wife, Manoe then knew that he was an angel of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>whereupon he said to his wife, We shall surely die, for we have seen God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But his wife said to him, Had it been the will of the Lord to cause us to die, he would not have received at our hand a whole burnt offering, and a sacrifice; nor would he have shewed us all these things; nor would he, as on this occasion, have caused us to hear these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>So the woman bore a son, and called his name Sampson; and the child grew, and the Lord blessed him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and the Spirit of the Lord began to go out with him, at the camp of Dan, between Saraa and Esthaol.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And Sampson went down to Thamnatha, and saw at Thamnatha a woman of the daughters of the Philistines,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he came up, and told his father and his mother, and said, I have seen a woman at Thamnatha, of the daughters of the Philistines. Now therefore get her for me for a wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And his father and his mother said to him, Are there not daughters of thy brethren, or a woman among my whole tribe, that thou shouldst go to take a wife from among the uncircumcised Philistines? But Sampson said to his father, Get this woman for me; for she is right in my eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>His father and his mother did not know that it was of the Lord, that he was seeking to take vengeance on the Philistines. Now at that time the Philistines had dominion over Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Sampson went down, with his father and his mother to Thamnatha, and when he came to the vineyard of Thamnatha, behold, a young roaring lion met him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and the Spirit of the Lord came upon him, and he crushed him as one would a kid; though he had nothing in his hands. But he did not tell his father or his mother what he had done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So they went down, and spoke to the woman, and the matter was settled to Sampson's satisfaction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when he returned, the year after, to take his wife, he turned aside to see the carcase of the lion, and behold there was a swarm of bees, and honey in the lion's mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So he took out some of the combs in his hand, and went on eating; and when he came to his father and his mother, he gave them, and they ate thereof. But he did not tell them that he had taken the honey out of the lion's mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when his father went down to the woman, Sampson made an entertainment there seven days; for so young men usually do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now when they saw him, they made choice of thirty men to be with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Sampson said to them, I will propound to you a riddle; if you explain it during the seven days of the entertainment, or find out the meaning of it, I will give you thirty Sindons, and thirty suits of apparel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>but if you cannot tell me, you shall give me thirty Sindons and thirty changes of apparel. And they said, Propound thy riddle that we may hear it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then he said to them, What eatable came from the eater; and, from the fierce, what that is sweet?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when in the course of three days they could not explain the riddle, they on the fourth day said to Sampson's wife, Ask we pray thee thy husband, and get him to explain the riddle to thee, lest we burn thee and thy father's house with fire. Have you invited us to do us an injury?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So Sampson's wife wept before him, and said, Thou dost but hate me, and hast not loved me; for thou hast not told me the riddle which thou hast propounded to the children of my people. And Sampson said to her, If I have not told it to my father and my mother, should I tell thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But as she continued to weep before him, during the seven days, while the feast lasted, he at length on the seventh clay told her, because she importuned him; and she told the children of her people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>So the men of the city said to him on the seventh day, before the sun was set, What is sweeter than honey, and what fiercer than a lion? Upon which Sampson said to them, If you had not ploughed with my heifer, you would not have known my riddle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then the Spirit of the Lord came upon him, and he went down to Ascalon, and slew of them thirty men, and took their garments, and gave the suits to them who had expounded the riddle. And Sampson was filled with wrath, and went up to his father's house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Sampson's wife was married to one of those friends of his, with whom he had contracted friendship.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The next year, however, in the days of the wheat harvest, Sampson visited his wife with a kid of the goats, and said, Let me go in, to my wife, into the chamber; but her father would not suffer him to go in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And her father said, I thought that thou didst utterly hate her, therefore I gave her to one of thy friends. But is not her younger sister better than she? Let this one, I pray thee, be thine, instead of her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thereupon Sampson said to them, Now, at least for once, I must be justified by the Philistines in doing them an injury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Sampson went and caught three hundred foxes, and he took torches; and when he had turned tail to tail, he put a torch between every two tails, and tied them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and set fire to the torches, and let them go through the standing corn of the Philistines. And they burned both what was on the threshing floors, and the standing corn, and also the vineyards, and the olive trees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon the Philistines said, Who hath done this? And when they were told that it was Sampson, the son in law of Thamni, because he had taken his wife, and given her to one of his friends, the Philistines went up and burned her, and her father's house, with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And Sampson said to them, As you have served her, so I will take vengeance on you, and then I will be at rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So he smote them in combat with a great slaughter, and went down and dwelt in a hollow of the rock Etam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then the Philistines went up, and encamped in Juda, and spread themselves through Lechi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the chief of Juda said, Why are you come up against us? And the Philistines said, We are come up to bind Sampson, and to do to him as he hath done to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Upon this three thousand men of Juda went down to the hollow of the rock Etam, and said to Sampson, Dost thou not know that the Philistines have dominion over us? Why then hast thou done this to us? And Sampson said, As they did to me, so have I done to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then they said to him, We are come down to bind thee, and deliver thee into the hands of the Philistines. And Sampson said to them, Swear to me. Perhaps you yourselves will fall upon me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they said to him, No; we will only bind thee fast, and deliver thee into their hands; but we will not put thee to death. So they bound him with two new ropes, and brought him up from the rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when they came to Jaw bone, the Philistines shouted, and ran to meet him. And the Spirit of the Lord came upon him; and the cords which were on his arms became like tow, which is burned with fire; and the bands dropped from his hands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and he found the jaw bone of an ass lying there; so he stretched forth his hand, and took it up, and with it smote a thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And Sampson said, With the jaw of an ass I have utterly routed them; for with the jaw of an ass I have slain a thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when he had done speaking, he threw the jaw out of his hand, and called that place, Slaughter of the jaw.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And being very thirsty he wept before the Lord and said, Thou hast vouchsafed this great deliverance to the hand of thy servant; but now I must die of thirst, and fall into the hands of the uncircumcised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Whereupon God caused that pool at Jaw to break forth, and water flowed out of it, and he drank, and his spirit returned, and he revived. For this cause the name of that fountain which is at Jaw is now called, The fountain of the invoked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now when he had judged Israel in the days of the Philistines twenty years,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Sampson went to Gaza, and saw there a woman; a harlot, and went in to her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when the Gazites were told that Sampson was come there, they surrounded him, and lay in wait for him the whole night, at the gate of the city. They indeed kept quiet all the night, saying, When the dawn appeareth we shall kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But when Sampson had lain till midnight, he arose in the middle of the night, and took the doors of the city gate with the two posts, and lifted them up with the bar, and laid them on his shoulders, and went up to the top of the mountain which looked towards Chebron, and deposited them there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And after this he loved a woman at Alsorach, whose name was Dalida;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and the chiefs of the Philistines went up to her and said to her, Entice him, and see wherein his great strength lieth, and how we may prevail over him, and bind him so as to humble him; and we will give thee, every one of us eleven hundred pieces of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon this Dalida said to Sampson, Tell me, I pray thee, wherein thy great strength lieth, and with what thou couldst be bound so as to be humbled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And Sampson said to her, Were they to bind me with seven thongs, wet, but not rotten, I should lose my strength, and be as other men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So the chiefs of the Philistines brought her seven thongs, wet, but not rotten, and she bound him with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now she had men lying in wait in her chamber. Then she said to him, The Philistines are upon thee, Sampson. Upon which he broke the thongs, as one would break a thread of tow, when it is touched with fire. So his strength was not known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Dalida said to Sampson, Behold, thou hast deceived me and told me lies. Now therefore tell me with what thou canst be bound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And he said to her, Were they to bind me with new ropes which have never been used, I should lose my strength, and be like other men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So Dalida took new ropes, and bound him with them, and the men in ambush came out of the chamber and she said, The Philistines are upon thee, Sampson! Where upon he broke them from his arms like a thread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Dalida said to Sampson, Behold, thou hast deceived me and told me lies. Tell me, I pray thee, with what thou canst be bound. And he said to her, If thou wert to weave these seven locks of my head with the woof, and fasten them into the wall with that pin, I should be as weak as other men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So when he went to sleep, Dalida took the seven locks of his head, and wove them with the woof, and fastened them with the pin to the wall, and said, The Philistines are upon thee Sampson! Whereupon he roused from his sleep, and pulled the pin of the web out of the wall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Dalida said to Sampson, How canst thou say, I love thee, when thy heart is not with me? These three times thou hast deceived me, and hast not told me wherein thy great strength lieth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And as she continued to afflict him daily with her speeches, and press him, and tired him even to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>he at length told her all his heart, and said to her; There hath never come a razor on my head, because I am consecrated to God from my mother's womb. If therefore I were shaven, my strength would depart from me, and I would become weak, and be like all other men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When Dalida saw that he bad told her all his heart, she sent for the chiefs of the Philistines, and said, Come up this once more, for be hath told me all his heart. So the chiefs of the Philistines went up to her, and carried the money in their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when Dalida had lulled Sampson to sleep on her knees, she sent for a man, and be shaved off the seven locks of his head, and began to humble him; for his strength was gone from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when Dalida said, The Philistines are upon thee Sampson! He awoke from his sleep, and said, I will go out as at other times heretofore, and rouse myself. He indeed did not know that the Lord had departed from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then the Philistines seized him and put out his eyes, and carried him down to Gaza, and bound him with fetters of brass, and he was kept grinding in the prison house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now when the hairs of his head began to grow as when he was shaven,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>the chiefs of the Philistines assembled to offer a great sacrifice to their god Dagon, and to rejoice. And they said; God hath delivered Sampson, our great enemy into our hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when the people saw him, they sung praises to their god, saying, Our god hath delivered our enemy into our hands; him who wasted our land, and multiplied the number of our slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now when their heart was elated with joy, they said, Call Sampson from the prison, and let him make sport for us; so they called Sampson from the prison, and be made sport for them; and when they had beaten him with rods, they set him between the pillars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then Sampson said to the young man who had hold of his hand, Let go, that I may feel the pillars on which the house resteth, and lean upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now the house was full of men and women; and all the chiefs of the Philistines were there; and on the top of the house there were about three thousand men and women looking at Sampson's sports.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Sampson wept before the Lord, and said, Adonaie, Lord, remember me, I beseech thee, and strengthen me yet this once more, my God, that I may take vengeance on the Philistines for my two eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then Sampson took hold of the two pillars, on which the house rested, and by which it was supported. And having taken hold of one with his right hand, and of the other with his left,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>he said, Let me die with the Philistines, and strained with all his might, and the house fell upon the chiefs and on all the people in it. So that those whom Sampson slew at his death were more than those whom he had slain during his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And his brethren, and the house of his father, went down, and took him, and came up and buried him between Saraa and Esthaol in the tomb of his father Manoe. Now he had judged Israel twenty years.(The Idolatry of the house of Micah and of the Danites.)</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>There was a man of mount Ephraim, whose name was Micah;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he said to his mother, With regard to the eleven hundred pieces of silver which thou hadst taken for thyself, and for which thou didst lay me under a curse, and speak in my hearing, behold the money is in my possession. I took it. And his mother said, Blessed of the Lord is my son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when he gave his mother the eleven hundred pieces of silver, his mother said, I indeed had dedicated this money to the Lord, out of my hand, for my son to make a graven and a molten image.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now therefore I will give it to thee. So when he gave his mother the money, she took two hundred pieces of silver, and gave them to a silver smith, and of it he made a graven and a molten image, and it was in the house of Micah.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So the house of Micah was to him the house of a god. And he made an ephod and theraphin, and consecrated one of his sons, and he became his priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now in those days there was no king in Israel: every man did that which was right in his own eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And there was a young man of Bethlehem, a community of Juda, but he was a Levite and a sojourner there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And this man went from Bethlehem, the city of Juda, to sojourn wherever he could find a place, and came to mount Ephraim to the house of Micah, with a view to proceed on in his journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And Micah said to him, Whence comest thou? and he in reply, said, I am a Levite of Bethlehem Juda, and I am going to sojourn wherever I can find a place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Whereupon Micah said to him, Abide with me, and be to me a father and a priest, and I will give thee ten pieces of silver a year, and a suit of clothes, and thy victuals.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So the Levite went in and began his abode with the man; and he treated the youth as one of his sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when Micah had consecrated the Levite, and he became his priest, and was in Micah's house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Micah said, Now I know that the Lord will do me good, because I have got a Levite for a priest.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In those days there was no king in Israel; and in those days the tribe of Dan was seeking to take possession of a lot of inheritance for themselves; for even till that day they had not got possession of the inheritance in the midst of the tribes of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So the children of Dan sent from their communities five men of valour, from Saraa, and from Esthaol, to view the land and examine it thoroughly, and said to them, Go and examine the land thoroughly. And they went to Mount Ephraim, to the house of Micah.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when they lodged there, at the house of Micah, they perceived the voice of the young Levite, and turned aside there and said to him, Who brought thee here? and what art thou doing at this place? what business hast thou here?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And he said to them, Thus and thus hath Micah done to me, and hired me, and I am become his priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then they said to him, Inquire, we pray thee, of God, that we may know whether the journey in which we are engaged will be prosperous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the priest said to them, Go in peace. This journey of yours which you are going is before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So the five men proceeded on and came to Laisa, and saw the people there dwelling securely. Their manner of living was tranquil like that of the Sidonians. There was none to reprove; none in the land to put them to shame for any thing. Possessing wealth they were spending it luxuriously; and they were at a great distance from the Sidonians, and had no intercourse with any man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So the five men came to their brethren at Saraa, and Esthaol, and said to them, Why sit ye here?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Moreover they said, Arise and let us go up against them, for we have seen the land, and behold it is very good, but still you continue quiet. You should not delay any longer to go and take possession of that land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when you go, you will come upon a people living in security, though it is a large country; for God hath delivered it into your hands. It is a place where there is no want of any thing on earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then there went up thence, of the communities of Dan, from Saraa and Esthaol, six hundred men well equipt with all necessaries of war.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And in going up they encamped at Kariathiarim in Juda, for which cause that place is called The Camp of Dan to this day. Behold it is behind Kariathiarim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And from that place they passed through mount Ephraim, and came to the house of Micah.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the five men who had gone to spy the land of Laisa, addressing their brethren, said, You know that at this house there is an ephod, and a theraphin, and a graven and a molten image; now consider therefore what you are to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Upon this they turned aside, and went to the house of the young Levite, to the house of Micah, and saluted him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>While the six hundred Danites, who were equipt with implements of war, stood at the gate of the city,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the five men, who had gone to spy the land, went up and entered the house of Micah,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>while the priest was standing there, and took the graven image, and the ephod, and the theraphin, and the molten image. And when the priest said to them, What are you doing?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>they said to him, Hold thy peace, Put thy hand on thy mouth and come with us, and be to us a father and a priest. Is it better for thee to be the priest of the house of one man, than to be the priest of a tribe, and of the house of a community of Israel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the priest's heart was delighted. So he took the ephod, and the theraphin, and the graven, and the molten image, and went into the midst of the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they turned and went away, and sent the children, and the cattle, and the heavy baggage before them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And when they were at a considerable distance from the house of Micah, behold Micah and the men, the families adjacent to Micah's house, uttered the shout of war and overtook the Danites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Upon which the sons of Dan turned about and said to Micah, What is the matter with thee that thou hast raised the shout of war?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Micah said, Because you have taken my graven image, which I made, and the priest; and have gone away. What more could have happened to me? Why then do you say to me, Why dost thou shout?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the sons of Dan said to him, Let not thy voice be heard among us. Should warm spirited men come to an engagement with us they will endanger thy life, and the life of thy household.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then the sons of Dan proceeded on in their march. And when Micah saw that they were too strong for him, he returned to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So the sons of Dan took what Micah had made, and the priest who was with him, and went to Laisa, to a people living at ease, and in a state of security, and smote them with the edge of the sword, and burned the city with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>There was none to deliver them, for they were far from the Sidonians, and had no intercourse with any man. It is situate in the valley of the house of Raab. And they rebuilt the city, and dwelt therein,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and called the name of the city Dan after the name of their father Dan who was born to Israel. Now the name of that city formerly was Oulamais.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the children of Dan set up for themselves the graven image, and Jonathan, a Gersonite, son of Manasses, he and his sons were priests to the tribe of the Danites, even to the day of the capture of the Ark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>They indeed set up for themselves the graven image which Micah made, all the time the house of God was at Selom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In those days when there was no king in Israel, there was a certain Levite who dwelt on the side of mount Ephraim, and he took him a concubine from Bethlehem Juda,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and she went away from him to her father's house at Bethlehem Juda. And when she had been there four months,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>her husband arose and went after her, with an intent to speak affectionately to her, and bring her back to him. And he had a young man with him, and a couple of asses. And when she introduced him to her father's house, and the young woman's father saw him, he was rejoiced to meet him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And his father in law, the young woman's father, detained him, and he abode with him three days, and they eat, and drank, and lodged there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And on the fourth day, when they arose early in the morning, and he got up to depart, the father of the young woman said to his son in law, Comfort thy heart with a morsel of bread, and after that you shall go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So they two sat down, and eat and drank together, and the father of the young woman said to the man, Come I pray thee, stay all night and let thy heart be merry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when the man arose to depart, his father in law pressed him; so he sat down, and staid there that night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And he arose early in the morning of the fifth day with a view to depart; but the father of the young woman said, Comfort thy heart, I pray thee; and then travel on till the close of the day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when they two had eaten, and the man arose to depart, with his concubine and his servant, his father in law; the young woman's father said to him, Behold the day is spent till near afternoon, lodge here to-night, and let thy heart be merry, and set out on your journey early in the morning, and thou wilt reach thy home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But the man would not consent to stay all night, but arose and departed, and came over against Jebus that is Jerusalem. Now he had with him a couple of asses, saddled, for himself and his concubine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when they came to Jebus the day was far spent, so the servant said to his master, Come, I pray thee, and let us turn in to this city of the Jebusites, and lodge there;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But his master said, We will not turn aside to a strange city, in which there is none of the children of Israel, but go on to Gabaa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then he said to his servant, Come let us draw near to one of those places, that we may lodge either in Gabaa, or in Rama.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So they passed on, and proceeded in their journey, and the sun set upon them when they were near Gabaa, which is in Benjamin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Whereupon they turned aside thither, to go and lodge in Gabaa, and they went in, and sat down in the street of the city; but there was not a man who invited them to lodge at his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And behold there came an old man from his work, out of the field, late in the evening. Now the man was from mount Ephraim, and sojourned at Gabaa, but the men of the place were Benjaminites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when he raised his eyes, and saw a wayfaring man in the street of the city, the old man said, Whither art thou going, and whence comest thou?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And he said to him, We are on our way from Bethlehem of Juda to the side of mount Ephraim. I am of that place. I went to Bethlehem Juda, and am on my way home, but there is not a man who inviteth me to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I have indeed straw and provender for our asses, and bread and wine for myself and the handmaid, and the young man with thy servants. There is no want of any thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thereupon the old man said, Peace be to thee. But let all thy wants be upon me. But thou must not lodge in the street.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So he took him to his house, and provided a place for the asses. And when they had washed their feet, they ate and drank.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But while they were cheering their hearts, behold the men of the city; sons of transgressors, surrounded the house, and knocked at the door, and spake to the man, the master of the house, the old man, saying, Bring out the man who came to thy house that we may know him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Upon this the man, the master of the house, went out to them and said, Do not, my brethren; do not, I pray you, the man an injury after his entering my house. You must not commit such folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Behold here is my daughter, a virgin, and his concubine; I will bring them out, and you may humble them and do to them what seemeth good in your eyes, but to the man you must not do such an act of folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But the men would not hearken to him. Then the man took his concubine, and brought her out to them, and they knew her, and abused her the whole night till the morning. And soon as the day began to dawn they let her go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the woman went at the dawn of day and threw herself down at the door of the house where her husband was, until it should be light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when her husband arose in the morning, and opened the doors of the house, and went out with a design to proceed on in his journey, behold the woman, his concubine, was lying at the doors of the house with her hands on the threshold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And he said to her, Arise and let us depart. But she made no answer; for she was dead. So he took her up, upon the ass, and went to his place,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and took a knife, and laid hold on his concubine, and divided her into twelve pieces, and sent them through all the borders of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Whereupon every one who saw them said, There never was such a thing done or seen from the day the children of Israel came out of Egypt to this day. Appoint for yourselves a counsel over her and speak.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So all the children of Israel set out, and the congregation assembled as one man from Dan to Bersabee, and from the land of Galaad, before the Lord at Massepha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when all the tribes of Israel were drawn up before the Lord in the congregation of the people of God, there were four hundred thousand footmen who drew the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now the children of Benjamin heard that the Israelites were gone up to Massepha. Then the children of Israel who had come together said, Speak. Where was this wickedness done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon the man, the Levite, the husband of the woman who was slain, answered and said, I came to Gabaa of Benjamin, I and my concubine, to lodge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the men of Gabaa rose upon me, and beset me and the house by night. Me they would have killed, and my concubine they forced so that she died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon which I took my concubine, and divided her in pieces and sent them through all the borders of the inheritance of the children of Israel. Since they have occasioned a ferment and destruction in Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>behold you are all Israelites; Advise and consult here for yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then all the people arose as one man, and said, We will not, any of us go to his habitation, nor shall any of us return to his house;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and this is what shall be done to Gabaa; we will go up against it by lot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But let us take ten men for the hundreds through all the tribes of Israel, and a hundred for the thousands and a thousand for the ten thousands to collect provisions, and bring them to Gabaa of Benjamin, that we may do to it according to the abominable act which it hath committed in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when all Israel was united against that city, as one man,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the tribes of Israel sent men through all the tribe of Benjamin, saying, What wickedness is this which is done among you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now therefore deliver up those men, those sons of transgressors in Gabaa, that we may put them to death, and purge away evil from Israel. But the children of Benjamin would not hearken to their brethren the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Nay the children of Benjamin assembled from their cities to Gabaa, to go out to battle against the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the children of Benjamin, who came from their cities, were at that time reviewed, twenty three thousand men who drew the sword, exclusive of the inhabitants of Gabaa, who were also reviewed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Out of all the people seven hundred were selected, who used both hands alike. All these were men who could sling stones to a hair breadth, and not miss.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now the men of Israel had been reviewed, exclusive of Benjamin, four hundred thousand men, who drew the sword. All these were men of array.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And they arose, and went up to Baithel, and inquired of God. And the children of Israel said, Who shall go up as our commander in chief to battle against the children of Benjamin? And the Lord said Juda shall go up as commander in chief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And all the children of Israel arose in the morning, and encamped against Gabaa;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and all Israel went out to battle against Benjamin, and drew up for them before Gabaa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the children of Benjamin sallied from Gabaa, and destroyed of Israel that day on the field of battle twenty two thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But the men of Israel took courage, and proceeded again to set the battle in array in the same place where they had drawn up the first day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The sons of Israel had indeed gone up, and wept before the Lord till evening, and inquired of the Lord saying, Shall we again proceed to draw near to battle against the children of Benjamin our brethren And the Lord said, Go up against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>So the children of Israel advanced against the children of Benjamin the second day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the children of Benjamin came out from Gabaa to meet them on the second day, and destroyed of Israel again on the field of battle, eighteen thousand men. All these were men who drew the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Upon this all the children of Israel, even the whole people went up and came to Baithel, and wept, and sat there before the Lord, and fasted the whole day till evening, and offered whole burnt offerings and sacrifices before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For in those days the ark of the covenant of the Lord their God was there,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and Phineas son of Eleazar, son of Aaron, stood before it in those days. And the children of Israel inquired of the Lord saying, Shall we proceed again to go out to battle against the children of Benjamin our brethren? And the Lord said, Go up. To-morrow I will deliver them into your hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then the children of Israel set men in ambush all around Gabaa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the children of Israel went up against the children of Benjamin, the third day, and drew up in array before Gabaa as they had done once and again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And the children of Benjamin sallied out to meet the people, and were drawn clean out of the city, and began to smite some of the people dead, as in the first and second engagement in the high ways, which lead up, one to Baithel, and the other to Gabaa, through the fields, about thirty men of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the children of Benjamin said, They fall before us, as heretofore. Now the sons of Israel had said, Let us flee, and draw them clean out of the city into the high ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And when they had done so, and every man arose from his place, then they drew up in array at Baal-thamar, and the ambush of Israel came up from their place, from Maraagabo,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and there came over against Gabaa ten thousand men, chosen out of all Israel; and the battle was fierce, for they did not know that evil was coming upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the Lord smote Benjamin before the children of Israel. And the children of Israel destroyed of Benjamin that day twenty five thousand one hundred men. All these drew the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>When the children of Benjamin saw that they were smitten; now the Israelites had given way to Benjamin because they trusted to the ambush which they had laid for Gabaa;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>but when they retreated, the ambush was put in motion, and rushed forward against Gabaa, and poured into it, and smote the city with the edge of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>The children of Israel indeed had settled a signal of battle with the ambush, and that they should raise a counter signal of smoke from the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>So when the sons of Israel saw that the men in ambush had taken Gabaa, they halted, in order of battle. Now Benjamin had begun to smite dead of the men of Israel about thirty men, for they said, They fall again before us, as in the former engagement.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>But when the counter sign ascended over the city, higher and higher, like a pillar of smoke, Benjamin looked back, and behold, the destruction of the city ascended up to heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>So when Israel faced about, the men of Benjamin were struck with consternation, for they saw that evil was coming upon them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and they looked about before the children of Israel, towards the way of the wilderness, and fled. But the battle overtook them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And they surrounded and destroyed them who came from the cities. They cut down Benjamin and pursued them closely from Nua to over against Gabaa, towards the rising of the sun,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and there fell of Benjamin eighteen thousand men. All these were men of valour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Now the rest of them had looked about, and fled towards the wilderness to the rock of Remmon; but of them the children of Israel gleaned up five thousand men. And the children of Israel went down after them to Gedan, and smote of them two thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>So that all who fell of Benjamin were twenty five thousand men who that day drew the sword. All these were men of valour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And the remainder, being six hundred men, turned and fled to the wilderness, to the rock of Remmon, and abode at Rock Remmon four months.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And the children of Israel turned back upon the Benjaminites, and smote them with the edge of the sword, beginning at the city Methla, including cattle and every thing throughout all the cities. And the cities which they came to, they burned with fire.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the children of Israel had sworn at Massepha, saying, Not a man of us shall give his daughter to a Benjaminite to wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So when the people came to Baithel they sat there till evening before God, then raising their voice, they wept bitterly</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and said, Why Lord God of Israel hath this happened that there should be this day one tribe cut off from Israel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And on the day following the people arose early in the morning, and built there an altar, and offered whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then the children of Israel said, Who is there among all the tribes of Israel who came not up before the Lord at the general assembly? For they had denounced the great curse against those who came not up before the Lord to Massepha, saying, Let him assuredly be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now the children of Israel had felt compassion for Benjamin their brother, and said, There is now one tribe cut off from Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>What shall we do for wives for the few who are left, seeing we have sworn by the Lord, that we will not give them any of our daughters for wives?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So when they said, Who is there among the tribes of Israel who came not up before the Lord to Massepha? and behold not a man had come to the camp from Jabis Galaad to the general assembly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and the people were reviewed, and there was not a man of the inhabitants of Jabis Galaad;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the congregation sent thither twelve thousand men from among the young warriors, and gave them a charge saying, Go and smite the inhabitants of Jabis Galaad with the edge of the sword:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And this you shall do, You shall devote to destruction every male, and every woman who hath cohabited with man:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>but the virgins you shall preserve alive. And having done so they found among the inhabitants four hundred young virgins who had not cohabited with man, and brought them to the camp of Selom which is in the land of Chanaan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then all the congregation sent, and spoke to the children of Benjamin at Rock Remmon, and invited them to peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when Benjamin returned to the children of Israel at that time, the Israelites gave them the women whom they had saved alive from among the daughters of Jabis Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So they were pleased, and the people relented for Benjamin, because the Lord had made a breach among the tribes of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then the elders of the congregation said, What shall we do for wives for the rest? For all the women of Benjamin are destroyed:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>(Now they had determined that the inheritance of the Benjaminites should belong to them who had escaped, that a tribe might not be blotted out from Israel:)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for we cannot give them any of our daughters for wives; for we have sworn among the children of Israel, saying, Cursed be the man who giveth a wife to a Benjaminite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then they said, Behold there is a festival of the Lord at Selom, which is kept yearly, on the north of Baithel, towards the rising of the sun, on the high way which goeth up from Baithel to Sychem, and on the south of Lebona.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So they gave a charge to the Benjaminites saying, Go and lie in wait among the vineyards,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and watch, and behold when the daughters of the inhabitants of Selom go out to dance in choirs, start out from the vineyards, and seize for yourselves every man a wife from among the daughters of Selom, and go to the land of Benjamin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And when their fathers or their brothers come to us, to enter a complaint before us, we will say to them, Grant them as a favour to us, because we did not take every man a woman at the battle. Seeing you have not given them, you have, as it were, accidentally transgressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the children of Benjamin did so. And having taken wives according to their number from among the choirs whom they surprised, they went, and returned to their inheritance, and rebuilt their cities and dwelt therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And the children of Israel went at that time every man to his tribe, and to his kindred, and went out thence every man to his possession.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And in those days, there being no king in Israel, every man did what was right in his own eyes.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>