<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now after the death of Saul when David returned from the slaughter of the Amelekites, and had been at Sekelak two days,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>behold there came a man, on the third day, from the camp; from the people of Saul with his clothes rent, and earth on his head, and when he came to David he fell on the ground, and made obeisance to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And David said to him, Whence comest thou? And he replied, I have escaped from the camp of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon David said to him, What is the news? Tell me. And when he said, The people fled from the battle, and many of the people have fallen, and died; Saul also is dead, and his son Jonathan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>David said to the young man who told him, How knowest thou that Saul and his son Jonathan are dead?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the young man who told him said, By accident I happened to be on mount Gelbua, and behold Saul was leaning on his spear; and lo! the chariots and horsemen were close upon him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and when he looked back and saw me, he called me: and I said, Here I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then he said to me, Who art thou? and I said, I am an Amelekite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then he said to me, Stand over me, I pray thee, and kill me; for I am seized with a gloomy horror, because all my life is in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So I went up to him and killed him, for I am sure he could not live after he fell; and I took the crown which was on his head, and the bracelet which was on his arm, and have brought them here to my lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then David took hold of his garments, and rent them, and all the men who were with him rent their garments,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and beat their breasts, and wept, and fasted till evening for Saul, and for Jonathan his son, and for the people of Juda, and for the house of Israel, because they had been smitten with the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And David said to the young man who told him, Whence art thou? And he said, I am the son of a stranger; an Amelekite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And David said to him, How couldst thou not be afraid to lift up thy hand to kill the Lord's anointed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then David called one of his young men and said, Go near and fall upon him. So he smote him that he died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And David said to him, Thy blood be upon thy own head, for thy own mouth hath testified against thee, saying, I have slain the anointed of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then David sung this funereal Ode over Saul, and over Jonathan his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and gave orders that the children of Juda should learn it. Behold it is written in the book Straight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Erect, Israel, a monument for the dead; For the slain on thy lofty mountains. How are the mighty fallen!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Proclaim not ye the news in Geth; Tell it not as good news in the streets of Ascalon; Lest the daughters of the Philistines rejoice; Lest the daughters of the uncircumcised exult with joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>On you, mountains of Gelbua, let not dew descend; On you, let there be no rain, nor fields of first fruit offerings! For there the shield of the mighty was battered; The shield of Saul. Was he not anointed with oil?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>From the blood of the wounded; From the fat of the mighty, The bow of Jonathan recoiled not empty; The sword of Saul bended not in vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Saul and Jonathan were beloved; They were lovely and inseparable; Comely in their life; And in their death they were not divided. Than eagles they were swifter; And than lions more courageous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>O daughters of Israel, weep over Saul, Who adorned your dress with scarlet; Who put ornaments of gold on your apparel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>How are the mighty fallen! In the midst of the battle, Jonathan! On thy lofty mountains slain!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I mourn for thee, my brother Jonathan, To me thou wast very lovely. Thy love for me was wonderful; Far surpassing the love of women.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>How are the mighty fallen! And the weapons of war perished!</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now after these things David inquired of the Lord saying, May I go up to one of the cities of Juda? And the Lord said to him, Go up. And David said, Whither shall I go? And he said, To Chebron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So David went up to Chebron, with his two wives, Achinaam the Jezraelitess, and Abigaia late the wife of Nabal, the Carmelite,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the men who were with him, every one with his household, and they dwelt in the cities of Chebron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the men of Judea came, and anointed David there, to be king over the house of Juda. And when they told David, saying, The men of Jabis Galaad have buried Saul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>David sent messengers to the leaders of Jabis Galaad, and said unto them, Blessed are ye of the Lord, because you have shewn this kindness for your lord; for Saul, the anointed of the Lord; and have buried him and his son Jonathan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now therefore may the Lord deal mercifully and truly with you! As for me I will recompense you for this kindness, because you have done this thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now therefore let your hands be strengthened, and be ye valiant; for Saul your lord is dead, and the house of Juda have anointed me to be king over them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But Abenner, son of Ner, Saul's captain general, took Jebosthe, the son of Saul, and brought him from the camp to Manaem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and made him king over Galaaditis, and over Thasiri, and over Jezrael, and over Ephraim, and over Benjamin, and over all Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jebosthe the son of Saul, was forty years old when he began to reign over Israel, and when he had reigned two years, (except over the house of Juda who followed David;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>now the time which David reigned at Chebron over the house of Juda was seven years and six months)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Abenner, son of Ner, and the servants of Jebosthe, son of Saul, came out from Manaem to Gabaon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and Joab, son of Saruia, and the servants of David went out from Chebron, and they met each other at the pool of Gabaon, and sat down one on one side of the pool, and the other on the other side of the pool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And Abenner said to Joab, let the young men, I pray thee, arise and shew feats before us. And Joab said, let them arise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then there arose, and went over by number, twelve Benjaminites who were for Jebosthe, son of Saul, and twelve of the servants of David;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and they seized, every one with his hand, the head of his fellow, and plunged each his sword into his adversary's side, and fell together. So the name of that place was called, Portion of ill designs. It is near Gabaon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the battle became very furious that day. And Abenner, with the men of Israel, retreated before the servants of David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now there were there three sons of Saruia, Joab, and Abessa and Asael. And Asael was swift of foot as a wild roe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And Asael pursued Abenner, and turned not aside to the right, nor to the left from following him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Abenner looked back and said, Art thou Asael? And he said, I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Abenner said to him, Turn thee to the right, or to the left, and lay hold on one of the young men, and take his armour. But Asael would not turn aside from following him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And Abenner again said to Asael, Desist from following me, that I may not smite thee to the ground. For how then could I hold up my face to Joab? And what do these things tend to? Return to thy brother Joab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But he would not desist. So Abenner smote him with a back stroke of his spear, into the loin, and the spear passed quite through him, and he fell there and died under him. And every one who came to the place where Asael fell and died, stood still.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But Joab and Abessa continued the pursuit after Abenner, and as the sun was setting they had got as far as the hill Amman, which is in front of Gai, on the way to the wilderness of Gabaon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the Benjaminites who followed Abenner crouded together, and having formed themselves into one body, they stood on the summit of a hill.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then Abenner called to Joab, and said, Must the sword devour to a complete victory? Knowest thou not that in the last extremity it will be very bitter? How long shall it be ere thou command the people to return from pursuing our brethren?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Whereupon Joab said, As the Lord liveth, but for thy speech the people might, from the morning, have gone up every one from the pursuit of his brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Joab sounded a trumpet and the people halted, and did not pursue Israel, nor continue the battle longer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Abenner and his men bent their course homeward that whole night, and having crossed the Jordan and passed over the adjoining plain, they came to the camp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And when Joab returned from pursuing Abenner, and had assembled all the people, there were missing of David's servants nineteen men, including Asael.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But the servants of David had smitten of the children of Benjamin, even of Abenner's men, three hundred and sixty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then they took up Asael, and buried him in his father's tomb at Bethlehem. And Joab and the men who were with him, marched all night, and arrived at Chebron by break of day.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Though the war was lengthened out between the house of Saul and the house of David, yet the house of David grew stronger and stronger, but the house of Saul grew weaker and weaker.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For David had sons born to him in Chebron. His first born was Amnon, the son of Achinaam, the Jezraelitess;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and his second, Daluia, the son of Abigaia, the Carmelite, and his third, Abessalom, the son of Maacha, a daughter of Tholmi, king of Gessir,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and his fourth, Ornia, the son of Aggith, and the fifth, Saphatia, the son of Abital,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and the sixth Jetheraam, the son of Aigal, a wife of David. These were born to David at Chebron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But while the war continued between the house of Saul and the house of David, Abenner got a mastery over the house of Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now Saul had a concubine named Respha, a daughter of Jol. And Jebosthe the son of Saul, said to Abenner, Why hast thou gone in to my father's concubine?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For this Abenner was exceedingly enraged at Jebosthe, and said to him, Am I a dog's head? Have I now dealt kindly with the house of Saul, thy father, and with his brethren, and relations, and not gone over to the house of David, and dost thou question me now respecting an injury done to a woman?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>God do so to Abenner and more also, if, as the Lord hath sworn to David, I do not do so to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>to take the kingdom from the house of Saul, and set up the throne of David over Israel and over Juda, from Dan to Bersabee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So Jebosthe could no more controul Abenner in any thing, because he was afraid of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Abenner sent messengers to David at Thailam where he was, in all haste, saying, Make a covenant with me, and behold my hand shall be with thee, to bring over all the house of Israel to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>On which David said, Well, I will make a covenant with thee. But one thing I require of thee, and declare that thou shalt not see my face, unless thou bring Melchol the daughter of Saul, when thou comest to see me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then David sent messengers to Jebosthe, son of Saul, saying, Restore me my wife Melchol, whom I espoused at the price of a hundred foreskins of the Philistines.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Jebosthe sent, and took her from her husband, from Phaltiel son of Sella;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and her husband came with her, weeping behind her, till they came to Barakim, Then Abenner said to him, Go, return. So he returned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Abenner spoke to the elders of Israel, saying, Heretofore you sought to make David king over you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>now therefore do it; for the Lord hath spoken concerning David, saying, By the hand of my servant David I will save Israel out of the hand of the Philistines, and out of the hand of all their enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Abenner spoke also in the ears of Benjamin. And Abenner came to Chebron, to communicate to David what seemed good in the sight of Israel, and in the sight of the house of Benjamin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when Abenner came to David at Chebron, and twenty men with him, David made an entertainment for Abenner, and the men with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Abenner said to David, Let me, I pray thee, arise and go, and I will assemble all Israel before my lord the king, and make a covenant with him, and thou shalt reign over all that thy heart desireth. So David dismissed Abenner, and he departed in peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now behold David's servants, and Joab, were returning from an expedition, and bringing with them a great spoil; and Abenner was not with David at Chebron, for David had sent him away, and he was gone in peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So when Joab and all his army arrived, and they told Joab, saying, Abenner, son of Ner, came to David, and he hath sent him away, and he has gone in peace,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Joab went to the king, and said, What is this thou hast done? Behold Abenner came to thee! Why then hast thou sent him away? And he is gone in peace?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Dost thou not know the wickedness of Abenner son of Ner; that he came to deceive thee, and to know thy going out and thy coming in; and to know all that thou art doing?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then Joab went out from David, and sent messengers after Abenner, and they brought him back from the well of Seeiram, but David knew it not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when Abenner returned to Chebron, Joab took him aside in the gate to speak to him, and watching an opportunity, smote him there in the groin, and he died, for the blood of Asael the brother of Joab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when David afterward heard, he said, Guiltless am I and my kingdom, before the Lord for ever, from the blood of Abenner, son of Ner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Let it fall on the head of Joab, and on all his father's house! And may there never be wanting of the house of Joab, a person afflicted with a gonorrhea, or a leprosy, or one leaning on a staff, or falling by the sword, or lacking bread!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now Joab and his brother Abessa, bore a grudge against Abenner, because he had slain their brother Asael in the battle at Gabaon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then David said to Joab, and to all the people who were with him, Rend your garments and gird on sackcloth, and utter lamentations before Abenner. And king David walked after the bier,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and they buried Abenner at Chebron. And the king wept aloud over his grave, and all the people wept over Abenner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the king chanted a funeral song over Abenner, and said, As dieth a criminal should Abenner die?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Thy hands were not bound with chains; Nor thy feet with fetters. He did not bring thee forth as a criminal; Before sons of wickedness thou hast fallen:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now all the people had been assembled to bewail him; and when all the people came to induce David to eat the funeral bread while it was yet day, David sword, saying, God do so to me and more also, if I taste bread, or any thing else, till the sun is set.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And when the people knew this, they were well pleased with all that the king did before the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And all the people, and all Israel, that day perceived that the putting Abenner son of Ner to death, did not proceed from the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For the king said to his servants, Do you not know that a great leader hath this day fallen in Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and that though I am a relation, and constituted a king, yet these sons of Saruia are too hard for me? The Lord retribute to the doer of evil according to his wickedness?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jebosthe son of Saul, heard that Abenner, son of Ner, was dead at Chebron, his hands were enfeebled, and all the men of Israel were dismayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now Jebosthe, son of Saul, had two captains of bands. The name of the one was Baana, and the name of the other Rechab. They were sons of Remmon, the Berothite, of the children of Benjamin, for Beroth had been assigned to the Benjaminites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the Berothites had fled to Gothaim, and have continued to sojourn there even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Jonathan, son of Saul, had a son, who was lame in both his feet. He was five years old when the news of Saul and of his son Jonathan came from Jezrael, and his nurse took him up and fled, and as she was hasting to carry him off, he happened to fall, and became lame, so he was called Memphibosthe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the sons of Remmon, the Berothite, Rechab, and Baana, set out, and came in the heat of the day to the house of Jebosthe, while he was sleeping on his couch at noon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now behold the door keeper of his house had been cleaning wheat, and being drowsy, had fallen asleep. So Rechab and Baana, the brothers, escaped notice, and went into the house, while Jebosthe was asleep on his couch in his bed chamber.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And they smote him, and killed him, and cut off his head. And they took his head, and travelled all night, by the way leading westward,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and brought the head of Jebosthe to David at Chebron, and said to the king, Behold here is the head of Jebosthe son of Saul thine enemy, who sought thy life; but the Lord hath executed vengeance for our lord the king on his enemies as at this day; on Saul thine enemy, and on his seed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Whereupon David answered Rechab, and Baana his brother, the sons of Remmon, the Berothite, and said to them, As the Lord liveth who hath redeemed my soul from all affliction,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>when one told me that Saul was dead, and thought himself a messenger of good news to me, I apprehended him, and slew him at Sekelak, though he thought himself entitled to a reward from me for his good news.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But now wicked men have slain a righteous person, in his house, upon his bed. Now therefore I will avenge his blood on you and cut you off from the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then David gave orders to his servants, and they instantly slew them, and cut off their hands, and their feet, and hanged them up by the pool of Chebron. And they buried the head of Jebosthe in the grave of Abenner son of Ner.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then all the tribes of Israel came to David to Chebron and said to him, Behold we are thy bone and thy flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Heretofore, while Saul was king over us, It was thou who didst lead out and bring in Israel; and the Lord said to thee, Thou shalt feed my people Israel, and thou shalt be ruler over my people Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when all the elders of Israel came to David to Chebron, king David made a covenant with them at Chebron, before the Lord, and they anointed David to be king over all Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>David was thirty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned forty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Seven years and six months he reigned at Chebron over Juda, and he reigned thirty three years, over all Israel and Juda, at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>When David and his men went to Jerusalem, to the Jebusites who inhabited that land, it was said to David, Thou shalt not come here; for the blind and the lame are opposed to it, saying, David shall not come here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So when David took the fortress, Zion, the same is the city of David,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>on that day David said, Whoever smiteth the Jebusites, let him also dispatch with a dagger those lame and those blind, even them who hate the soul of David: for this cause they say, The blind and the lame shall not come into the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And David made his abode in the fort, so it was called the city of David. And David built the city, around the citadel and his own house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And David advanced in prosperity, and grandeur, and the Lord Almighty was with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Chiram, king of Tyre, sent messengers to David, with cedar timber, and carpenters, and masons, and they built a house for David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When David perceived that the Lord had prepared him to be king over Israel, and that his kingdom was exalted for the sake of his people Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>David took still more wives and concubines out of Jerusalem, after he came from Chebron. And David had still more sons and daughters born to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now these are the names of those who were born to him in Jerusalem. Sammus, and Sobab, and Nathan, and Solomon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and Ebear, and Elisue, and Naphek, and Jephies,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Elisama, and Elidae, and Eliphalath, Samae, Jesibath, Nathan, Galamaan, Jebar, Theesus, Eliphalat, Naged, Naphek, Jonathan, Leasamus, Baalimath, Eliphaath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over Israel, all the Philistines came up to seek David; and when David heard he went down to the fort.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the Philistines came, and made an irruption into the valley of the Titans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Whereupon David inquired of the Lord saying, Shall I go up against the Philistines? Wilt thou deliver them into my hands? And the Lord said to David, Go up; for I will assuredly deliver the Philistines into thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So David went out through Upper breaks, and smote the Philistines there. Whereupon David said, The Lord broke through the Philistine enemies before me, as waters burst through mounds. For this cause the name of that place, was called Upper Breaks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And there they left their gods; and David and the men who were with him took them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Again the Philistines proceeded to come up, and made another irruption into the valley of the Titans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when David inquired of the Lord, the Lord said, Thou shalt not go up to meet them in front. Wheel about from them, and come upon them near Wailing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when thou hearest the sound of a rustling in the grove of Wailing, then thou shalt go down against them; for the Lord will then go out before thee, to smite in the battle of the Philistines.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And David did as the Lord commanded him, and smote the Philistines from Gabaon to the land of Gazera.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again David assembled all the young men of Israel, about seventy thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And David arose, and set out on his march, he and all the people with him, and some of the chiefs of Juda, to bring up thence the ark of God, which is called by the name of the Lord of hosts enthroned on the cherubims, which are on it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And having put the ark of the Lord in a new car, they brought it from the house of Aminadab, who dwelt on the mount. And Oza, and his brothers the sons of Aminadab, led the car with the ark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>His brothers marched before the ark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And David and the Israelites played on high toned instruments of music, accompanied with songs, and on kinyras and on nablas, and on tympanums, and on cymbals, and on harps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But when they came to the threshing floor of Nachor, Oza stretched forth his hand upon the ark of God to stay it, and took hold of it, because the young bull shook it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the anger of the Lord was kindled against Oza, and he smote him there, by the ark of the Lord, in the presence of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now David was disheartened because the Lord had broke out upon Oza, and that place is to this day called Breach of Oza;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and David was afraid of the Lord that day, saying, How shall the ark of the Lord come to me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So David was not willing that the ark of the covenant of the Lord should turn aside to him, into the city of David, and David caused it to turn aside to the house of Abeddara, the Gethite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the ark of the Lord abode in the house of Abeddara the Gethite three months, and the Lord blessed the whole house of Abeddara, and all belonging to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when they told king David saying, The Lord hath blessed the house of Abeddara, and all belonging to him, on account of the ark of God, David went and brought up the ark of the Lord out of the house of Abeddara, into the city of David, with rejoicing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now there were with him seven choirs carrying the ark, and for a sacrifice a young bull and lambs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And David played on well tuned instruments of music before the Lord; and David having put on an unusual robe,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>he, and all the house of Israel, brought up the ark of the Lord, with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And as the ark was entering the city of David, Melchol the daughter of Saul looked out at a window, and saw king David dancing, and playing before the Lord, and despised him in her heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So they brought the ark of the Lord, and when they had set it in its place, in the middle of the tabernacle, which David had erected for it, David offered whole burnt offerings before the Lord, and peace offerings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when David had made an end of offering the whole burnt offerings, and the peace offerings, he blessed the people in the name of the Lord of hosts,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and distributed to all the people through the whole host of Israel, from Dan to Bersabee, both to the men and women, to every one a piece of bread, and a piece of roasted meat, and a sweet cake baked in the pan. Then all the people departed, every one to his house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and David returned to salute his household. And Melchol the daughter of Saul came out to meet David, and when she had saluted him, she said, How was the king of Israel glorified to-day in the eyes of his maid servants, disrobed as he was like one of the dancers!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whereupon David said to Melchol, I will dance before the Lord. Blessed be the Lord, who hath chosen me in preference to thy father, and in preference to all his house, to make me ruler over his people, over Israel. Wherefore I will play and dance before the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and I will again disrobe myself in the same manner, though I should be despicable in thy sight, and with the maidens, by whom thou hast intimated that I am not honoured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Hence Melchol the daughter of Saul had no child to the day of her death.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when the king was settled in his house, and the Lord had given him rest on every side, from all his enemies round about,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the king said to Nathan the prophet, Behold I dwell in a house of cedar, but the ark of God dwelleth in the midst of the tabernacle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Upon which Nathan said to the king, Whatever may be in thy heart, go and do; for the Lord is with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But that night a word of the Lord came to Nathan saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Go and say to my servant David, Thus saith the Lord, Art not thou to build me a house to dwell in?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because I did not dwell in a house from the day I brought the children of Israel out of Egypt even to this day, but continued walking about in a temporary abode and in a tabernacle</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>in all the places through which I passed with all Israel, did I ever speak to any tribe of Israel whom I commanded to feed my people Israel, and say, Why have you not built for me a house of cedar?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But now, thus shalt thou say to my servant David, Thus saith the Lord Almighty, I took thee from the sheepcot to be ruler over my people; over Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and I have been with thee whithersoever thou didst go, and have destroyed all thine enemies from before thee, and made thee renowned according to the renown of the great men on the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and plant them, and they shall dwell by themselves, and shall no more be in trouble; nor shall a son of wickedness any more humble them as heretofore,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>from the days I appointed judges over my people Israel: and I will give thee rest from all thine enemies, and the Lord will tell thee that thou art to build a house for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And it shall come to pass when thy days are fulfilled and thou shalt sleep with thy fathers, that I will raise up after thee the seed of thee who shall spring from thy loins, and I will establish his kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He shall build a house for my name, and I will raise up again his throne for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I will be to him a father, and he shall be to me a son. And when his iniquity shall come, I will correct him with a rod of men, and with scourges of the children of men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but I will not withdraw my mercy from him as I withdrew it from them whom I removed from my presence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>His house and his kingdom shall be established for ever before me and his throne shall be raised up again for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>According to all these words and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak to David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whereupon king David went in and sat down before the Lord, and said, Who am I, Lord, my Lord! and what is my house that thou hast loved me to such a degree!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Though I was contemptibly little before thee, Lord, my Lord! yet thou hast spoken respecting the house of thy servant for a great while to come. With regard to this law of the man, Lord, my Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>what more shall David presume to say to thee? Now then, thou, Lord, my Lord! knowest thy servant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and on account of thy servant thou hast done, and according to thine own heart hast made all this greatness in order to make known to thy servant</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>with respect to the magnifying of thee, my Lord! that there is none like thee, and that there is not a god besides thee among all that we have heard of with our ears.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Moreover what other nation is there on the earth like thy people Israel? How hath God gone before them to redeem a people for himself; to make thyself a name; to display majesty and an appearance of deity; to drive out from before thy people, whom thou hadst redeemed for thyself out of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>nations and wandering hordes! Thou indeed preparedst for thyself thy people Israel to be a people for ever, and thou, Lord! wast their God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now therefore, my Lord, confirm the word which thou hast spoken concerning thy servant and his house, confirm it everlastingly, Lord Almighty, O God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And now as thou hast spoken let thy name be magnified for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>O Lord Almighty, God of Israel, thou hast made a revelation to thy servant, saying, I am to build a house for thee; therefore thy servant hath found this disposition of his heart to make this prayer to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And now, Lord, my Lord, Thou art God, and thy words will be true, and thou hast spoken these good things respecting thy servant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>now then begin and bless the house of thy servant, that it may continue for ever before thee. Since thou Lord, my Lord, hast spoken, therefore with thy blessing, let the house of thy servant be blessed, that it may continue for ever.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this David smote the Philistines, and subdued them, and took the country, appurtenant to the cities, out of the hand of the Philistines.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>David also smote Moab, and measured them with lines, having caused them to dwell in the country, and there were two lines to be put to death, and two lines to be saved alive. So Moab became servants to David, and brought him gifts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>David also smote Adraazar, son of Raab king of Suba. As he was going to establish his authority over the river Euphrates,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>David intercepted a thousand of his chariots, and seven thousand cavalry, and twenty thousand infantry; and David destroyed all the chariots, except one hundred which he reserved for himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when Syria of Damascus came to assist Adraazar king of Suba, David smote of the Syrians twenty two thousand men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and David placed a garrison in Syria at Damascus, and the Syrians became servants to David and brought him gifts. So the Lord preserved David withersoever he went.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And David took the breastplates of gold, which were on the servants of Adraazar, king of Suba and brought them to Jerusalem. Now these were they which Susakim king of Egypt took when he came up against Jerusalem, in the days of Roboam son of Solomon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And from Metebak, and from the principal cities of Adraazar, king David took brass in great abundance, of which Solomon made the brazen sea, and the pillars, and the lavers, and all the vessels of brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when Thoou, the king of Emath, heard that David had smitten all the army of Adraazar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thoou sent his son Jedduram to king David to salute him courteously, and congratulate him for having fought Adraazar, and smitten him; for he was at enmity with Adraazar. And Jedduram brought with him vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and vessels of brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And king David dedicated these to the Lord, with the silver and the gold which he had dedicated out of all the cities which he had subdued;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Out of Idumea and Moab, and the children of Ammon, and the Philistines, and Amelek, and the spoils of Adraazar, son of Raab king of Suba.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thus David made himself renowned. And when he returned, he smote of the Idumeans at Gebelim, to the number of eighteen thousand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and placed garrisons in Idumea, throughout the whole extent of it. So all the Idumeans became servants to the king. And the Lord preserved David whithersoever he went.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And David reigned over all Israel. And David executed judgment and justice over all his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And Joab son of Saruia was at the head of the army, and Josaphat son of, Achilud was recorder,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and Sadok, son of Achitob, and Achimelech son of Abiathar, were priests; and Sasa was the scribe;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and Banaias son of Jodae was counsellor; and the Chelethites, and the Phelethites, and David's sons, were the palace guards.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And David said, Is there any yet left of the house of Saul, that I may shew him kindness for Jonathan's sake?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now there was a servant of the house of Saul, whose name was Siba. So they called him to David. And the king said to him, Art thou Siba? And he said, I am thy servant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the king said to him, Is there any man yet left of the house of Saul, that I may treat him with all the kindness possible? And when Siba said to the king, There is still a son of Jonathan who is disabled in his feet,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>the king said to Siba, Where is he? And Siba said to the king, Behold at the house of Machir, son of Amiel of Lodabar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thereupon king David sent for him from the house of Machir, son of Amiel of Lodabar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when Memphibosthe son of Jonathan, son of Saul was brought before king David, he fell on his face, and made obeisance to him. And when David said to him, Memphibosthe! He said, Here am I thy servant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then David said to him, Fear not; for I will indeed deal kindly with thee, for Jonathan thy father's sake, and restore thee all the fields of Saul thy grandfather, and thou shalt eat bread at my table continually.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Upon which Memphibosthe bowed down, and said, Who am I thy servant, that thou shouldst look on such a dead dog as I am?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then the king called Siba, the servant of Saul, and said to him, All that belong to Saul and his house I have given to thy master's son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore work thou the land for him; both thou and thy sons, and thy servants; and thou shalt bring in provisions for thy master's son, that he may have bread to eat. And Memphibosthe, thy master's son, shall eat bread continually at my table. Now Siba had fifteen sons, and twenty servants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Siba said to the king, According to all that the king hath commanded his servant, so will thy servant do. So Memphibosthe ate at David's table, like one of the king's sons;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and Memphibosthe had a young son whose name was Micha; and all the family of the house of Siba were servants of Memphibosthe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And Memphibosthe dwelt at Jerusalem, for he ate continually at the king's table, and was lame in both his feet.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now after this the king of the Ammonites died, and Annon his son reigned in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whereupon David said, I will shew kindness to Annon, son of Naas, as his father shewed kindness to me. So David sent his servants to comfort him for the death of his father. But when David's servants came to the land of the Ammonites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>the chiefs of the children of Ammon said to Annon their lord, Is it to honour thy father in thy presence, that David hath sent thee comforters? Is it not rather that they may examine the city and view it? It is indeed for the purpose of spying it, that David hath sent these servants of his to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Upon this Annon took David's servants, and shaved their beards, and cut off one half of their upper garments, even up to the loins, and sent them away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when David was informed touching his men, he sent to meet them, for the men had been greatly dishonoured, and the king said, Tarry at Jericho till your beards grow, and then return.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now when the children of Ammon saw that David's people were dishonoured, they sent, and hired the Syrians of Baithraam, and the Syrians of Suba and Roob, twenty thousand infantry, and of the king of Amelek, a thousand men, and of Istob twelve thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when David heard it, he sent out Joab, and all the army, even all the mighty men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the children of Ammon came out and drew up for battle before the gate of the city; and the Syrians of Suba, and Roob, with Istob, and Amelek, were by themselves in the fields.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When Joab saw that there was a front of battle against him both before and behind, he made a draught from among all the youth of Israel, and set them in array against the Syrians,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and he committed the residue of the people to his brother Abessa; and they drew up in array against the children of Ammon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Joab said, If the Syrians be too strong for me, you must come to my assistance; and if the children of Ammon be too strong for thee, we will come to save thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Act manfully, and let us shew our courage for our people and for the cities of our God. And the Lord will do what is good in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Joab, and all his people with him, advanced to battle against the Syrians, and they fled before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when the Ammonites saw that the Syrians fled, they also fled before Abessa, and entered the city. Whereupon Joab returned from the children of Ammon, and came to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now when the Syrians saw that they had given way before Israel, they assembled together,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Adraazar sent and collected the Syrians from the banks of the river Chalamak, and they came to Ailam, with Sobak, the commander in chief of Adraazar's army, at their head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When this was told David, he assembled all Israel, and crossed the Jordan, and came to Ailam; and the Syrians drew up in array against David, and fought him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But the Syrians fled before Israel, and David destroyed of Syria seven hundred chariots, and forty thousand horsemen. He smote also Sobak the commander in chief of the army, so that he died there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when all the kings who were vassals of Adraazar saw that they were smitten before Israel, they revolted, and joined Israel and served them. So Syria was intimidated from aiding the Ammonites any more.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when the season of the year returned for kings to go out to battle, David sent out Joab, and all his servants with him, and all Israel, and they destroyed the children of Ammon, and besieged Rabbath: but David abode at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And it happened, that one afternoon, David arose from his couch, and walked on the roof of the king's house, and from the top of the house he saw a woman bathing, and she was very beautiful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So David sent and sought out the woman, and one said, Is not this Bersabe, the daughter of Eliab, the wife of Ourias, the Chettite?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon David sent messengers, and took her, and went in unto her, and lay with her. And when she had purified herself from her uncleanness, she returned to her house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the woman conceived, and sent and told David, saying, I am with child.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon David sent to Joab, saying, Send Ourias the Chettite to me. So Joab sent Ourias to David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And on his arrival, Ourias went directly to him. And when David had inquired of the welfare of Joab, and the welfare of the people, and the success of the war,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>he said to Ourias, Go down to thy house and wash thy feet. So Ourias departed from the king's house, and there was sent after him a portion of meat from the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But Ourias laid himself down to sleep at the king's gate, with the servants of his lord, and did not go down to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when they told David, saying, Ourias did not go down to his house, David said to Ourias, Art thou not come from a journey, why then didst thou not go down to thy house?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Ourias said to David, The ark, and Israel, and Juda, dwell in tents, and my lord Joab, and the servants of my lord encamp on the ground, and shall I go down to my house to eat and drink, and lie with my wife? How can I do it? As thy soul liveth, I will do no such thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then David said to Ourias, Tarry here to-day also, and tomorrow I will dismiss thee. So Ourias tarried at Jerusalem that day and the morrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And David invited him, and he ate and drank in his presence. But though he caused him to drink, and made him drunk, yet he went out in the evening, to sleep on his bed with the king's servants, and did not go down to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And in the morning David wrote a letter to Joab, and sent it by the hand of Ourias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and in the letter he wrote, saying, Set Ourias in the front of the hottest battle, and retire from him, that he may be smitten and die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So in disposing the guards against the city, Joab stationed Ourias in the place where he knew there were men of valour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the men of the city sallied out, and fought with Joab, and some of the people of David's servants fell, and Ourias the Chettite died also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then Joab sent and told David all the circumstances of the battle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>which were to be delivered verbally to the king. And he gave a charge to the messenger, saying, When thou hast finished telling the king all the circumstances of the battle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>if it should happen that the king's anger rise, and he should say to thee, Why did you approach so near to the city to fight? Did you not know that they would shoot from the top of the wall?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Who smote Abimelech son of Jerobaal, son of Ner? Did not a woman throw a piece of a millstone on him from the top of the wall, so that he died at Thamasi? Why did you approach the wall? Then thou shalt say, Thy servant Ourias the Chettite is also dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So Joab's messenger went to Jerusalem to the king, and when he arrived and told David all that Joab mentioned to him; all the circumstances of the battle, David was inflamed with wrath against Joab, and said to the messenger, Why did you approach so near the city to fight? Did you not know that you would be smitten from the wall? Who smote Abimelech, son of Jerobaal? Did not a woman throw a millstone upon him from the wall, so that he died at Thamasi? Why did you approach so near the wall?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then the messenger said to David, The men took courage against us, and sallied out upon us into the field, and when we continued our pursuit of them, even to the doors of the gate,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the archers from the wall shot at thy servants, so that some of the king's servants were slain, and thy servant Ourias the Chettite is dead also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thereupon David said to the messenger, Thus shaft thou say to Joab, Let not this be grievous in thy sight; for the sword devoureth sometimes on one side, and sometimes on the other. Make thy battle strong against the city, and block it up, and enclose it with strong works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now when the wife of Ourias heard that Ourias her husband was dead, she mourned for her husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when her mourning was over, David sent and brought her to his house, and she became his wife, and bore him a son. But the deed which David had done appeared evil in the sight of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>therefore the Lord sent Nathan the prophet to David. And when he came to David he said to him, There were two men in the same city. The one was rich, and the other poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The rich man had flocks and herds in great abundance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>but the poor man had only one little ewe lamb, which he bought, and nourished, and fed: and it had grown up with him and his children in the same house. It ate of his bread, and drank of his cup, and slept in his bosom, and was to him like a daughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And there came a traveller to the rich man, and he spared to take of his own flocks, or of his own herds, to entertain the stranger; the wayfaring man, who had come to him; but took the poor man's lamb, and dressed it for the man who came to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And David was inflamed with indignation against the man to a great degree, and said to Nathan, As the Lord liveth, the man who hath done this is guilty of death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and shall make sevenfold restitution for the lamb, because he hath done such a deed and had no compassion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Whereupon Nathan said to David, Thou art the man who hath done this. Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel, I anointed thee to be king over Israel, and it was I who delivered thee out of the hand of Saul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and gave thee the house of thy master, and thy master's wives into thy bosom. I gave thee also the house of Israel and Juda, and if this had not been enough, I would have added still more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Why then hast thou despised the word of the Lord, to do evil in his sight? Thou hast slain Ourias the Chettite with the sword, and taken his wife to be thy wife. Thou hast indeed slain him with the sword of the Ammonites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now therefore the sword shall never depart from thy house. Because thou hast despised me, and taken the wife of Ourias the Chettite to be thy wife,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold I will raise up evils against thee out of thy own house; and I will take thy wives before thy eyes, and give them to thy neighbour, and he will lie with thy wives in the face of the sun.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thou indeed didst act secretly; but I will do this thing in the sight of all Israel, and in the face of yonder sun.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then David said to Nathan, I have sinned against the Lord. And Nathan said to David, The Lord hath put away thy sin. Thou shalt not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But because thou hast by this deed given great occasion to the enemies of the Lord to blaspheme, therefore thy son who is born to thee shall surely die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Nathan went to his house, and the Lord struck the child which the wife of Ourias the Chettite bore to David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And while it was sick David besought God for the child, and fasted and went in and lay on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when the elders of his house came to raise him from the ground, he would not consent, nor would he eat bread with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And on the seventh day the child died. And David's servants were afraid to tell him that the child was dead; for they said, Behold while the child was still living we spoke to him, but he would not hearken to our voice, how then must it affect him when we tell him, The child is dead!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But when David perceived that his servants were whispering, he conjectured that the child was dead, therefore David said to his servants, Is the child dead? And when they said, He is dead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>David arose, and washed, and anointed himself, and changed his clothes, and went into the house of God, and worshipped him. Then he went to his own house, and called for bread to eat. And when they had set bread before him, and he had eaten,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>his servants said to him, What is this that thou hast done for the child? While it was still living, thou didst fast, and weep, and kept thyself awake; but soon as the child is dead, thou hast risen up, and eaten, and drank.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And David said, While the child was still alive, I fasted and wept, because I said, Who knoweth but the Lord may have compassion on me, and the child may live?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But now it is dead, why then should I fast? Can I bring it back again? I shall go to it; but it will never return to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then David comforted his wife Bersabe, and went in unto her; and she conceived, and bore a son, and called his name Solomon. And the Lord loved him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and sent by the ministry of Nathan the prophet, and called his name Jeddedi, For the sake of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now Joab had fought at Rabbath of the Ammonites, and taken the royal city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Wherefore Joab sent messengers to David, and said, I have had a battle at Rabbath, and have taken the city of waters;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>now therefore assemble the rest of the people, and encamp against the city, and take it, lest I take the city, and it be called after my name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So David assembled all the people, and went to Rabbath, and fought against it and took it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And he took the crown of Molchom their king from his head. Now the weight of it was a talent of gold, with precious stones, and it was set on David's head. And he brought out the spoils of the city in great abundance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and he brought out the people who were in it, and put them to the saw, and to iron crows, and to pick axes of iron, and distributed them through brick yards. And when he had done the same to all the cities of the Ammonites, David, and all the people, returned to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this, Abessalom, a son of David, having a very beautiful sister whose name was Themar, Amnon the son of David fell in love with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Amnon was so distressed that he pined away on account of Themar his sister, for she was a virgin, and it appeared monstrous in the eyes of Amnon to have any thing to do with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now Amnon had a companion whose name was Jonadab. He was the son of Samaa the brother of David. And Jonadab was a man of great subtilty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and he said to him, What is the matter with thee, son of the king, that thou art so languishing for some time past? Why dost thou not tell me? And Amnon said to him, I am in love with Themar, the sister of my brother Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon this Jonadab said to him, Take to thy bed, and feign thyself sick, and when thy father cometh to see thee say to him, I pray thee, let Themar my sister come to me, and feed me; and let her prepare the victuals in my sight, that I may see, and eat out of her hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So Amnon went to bed, and feigned himself sick: and when the king came to see him, Amnon said to the king, I pray thee let Themar my sister come to me, and make a couple of cakes in my sight, that I may eat out of her hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And David sent to the house to Themar, and said, Go, I pray thee, to thy brother's house, and prepare something for him to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Accordingly Themar went to the house of Amnon, her brother, and he was a bed; and she took the dough, and kneaded it, and made it into cakes before his eyes, and stewed them</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and she took the pan and poured them out before him, but he would not eat. Then Amnon said, Go out every man from me. And when every one was gone out from him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Amnon said to Themar, Bring the victuals into the chamber that I may eat out of thy hand so Themar took the cakes she had made and carried them to her brother Amnon into the bed chamber.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But when she brought them to him, that he might eat, he took hold of her and said to her, Come, lie with me, my sister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And she said to him, No, my brother, thou must not dishonour me; for such a thing ought not to be done in Israel. Thou must not commit such folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>As for me where could I hide my dishonour? And with regard to thyself, thou wouldst be like one of the fools in Israel. Now therefore, speak I pray thee to the king; for he will not withhold me from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But Amnon would not hearken to her, but overpowered her by force, and dishonoured her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when he had lain with her, Amnon hated her with an exceeding great hatred; so that the hatred with which he hated her, was greater than the love with which he had loved her, and his last wickedness was greater than the first. And Amnon said to her, Arise and begone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Whereupon Themar said to him, To send me thus away is adding a still greater injury to that which thou hast already done me. But Amnon would not hearken to her voice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but called his servant who superintended his house, and said to him, Send away, I pray thee, this one from me, out of doors, and shut the door after her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now she had on an embroidered robe; for such was the dress which the king's daughters wore, who were virgins. So when the servant led her out, and shut the door after her,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Themar took ashes, and put them on her head, and tore in pieces the embroidered robe which she had on, and putting her hands on her head, she went on crying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Abessalom her brother said to her, Hath Amnon thy brother been with thee? Now therefore, my sister, hold thy peace. Because he is thy brother, thou must not mention this matter. So Themar abode as a widow in the house of her brother Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Though king David heard all these things, and was very angry, yet he would not grieve the spirit of his son Amnon because he loved him as being his first born.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>As for Abessalom he spoke not a word to Amnon, good or bad, for he hated Amnon for having dishonoured his sister Themar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now about two years after this Abessalom had sheep shearers at Belasor, in the borders of Ephraim; and Abessalom invited all the king's sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Abessalom went to the king, and said, Behold they are shearing thy servant's sheep, let the king I pray thee, and his servants, go with thy servant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But the king said to Abessalom, No, my son. We must not all go; for we must not overburthen thee. When he had pressed him, and he would not consent to go but blessed him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>then Abessalom said to him, If not; let my brother Amnon, I pray thee, go with us. And the king said, Why should he go with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But Abessalom pressed him, so he sent with him Amnon, and all the king's sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And Abessalom made a banquet like that of the king. And Abessalom gave a charge to his servants saying, Observe when the heart of Amnon is elated with wine, and I say to you, Smite Amnon; then put him to death. Be not afraid, for it is I who command you. Acquit yourselves like men, and be sons of valour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when the servants of Abessalom had done to Amnon as Abessalom had commanded them, all the king's sons arose, and mounted every man his mule, and fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And while they were on the road, the report came to David saying, Abessalom hath slain all the king's sons; there is not one of them left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Thereupon the king arose, and rent his garments, and lay on the ground, and all his servants stood around him, with their clothes rent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And Jonadab, son of Samaa, David's brother, addressing him said, Let not my lord the king suppose that he hath slain all the young men, the king's sons, for Amnon only is dead; for he hath been continually in the mouth of Abessalom from the day he dishonoured his sister Themar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Now therefore let not the king lay this to heart, saying, All the king's sons are dead; for there is none dead but only Amnon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and Abessalom hath made his escape. Then the servant who stood centinel raised his eyes, and looked, and lo, many people were coming down the side of the mountain by the way behind him, whereupon the centinel came, and told the king, saying, I have seen many people coming by the way of Oronen, from the side of the mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And Jonadab said to the king, Behold the king's sons are near at hand. It is as thy servant said.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And just as he had finished speaking, behold the king's sons came, and they raised their voice, and wept, and the king also, and all his servants, wept bitterly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Abessalom fled, and went to Tholmi, son of Emiud, king of Gedsur, to the land of Chamaachad. And king David mourned for his son all that year.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Now when Abessalom, who had left his country, and gone to Gedsur, had been there three years,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>king David was mollified so as to long for Abessalom, for he was comforted with respect to Amnon, seeing he was dead.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So when Joab, son of Saruia, perceived that the king's heart was set upon Abessalom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he sent to Thekoe, and brought thence a wise woman, and said to her, Feign thyself, I pray thee, to be a mourner, and put on mourning apparel, and anoint not thyself with oil, but be like a woman mourning for one who hath been long dead:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and thou shalt go to the king, and speak to him in this manner; So Joab put words in her mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the woman of Thekoe came to the king, she fell on her face on the ground, and made obeisance to him, and said, Save, king! save!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the king said to her, What is the matter with thee? To which she replied, I am a wretched woman, a widow. My husband died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And thy servant had two sons, and they quarrelled in the field, and there was none to part them, and one of them smote the other; his brother, and killed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And behold the whole family is risen up against thy servant, and say, Deliver up him who smote his brother, that we may put him to death, for the life of his brother whom he hath slain; for we will cut him off though he be your heir. Thus will they quench my coal, which is left, so that there will not be left to my husband a remnant, or a name, on the face of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thereupon the king said to the woman, Go in peace to thy house, and I will give orders concerning thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the woman of Thekoe said to the king, Upon me, my lord the king, be the iniquity, and upon my father's house; and let the king and his throne be guiltless!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then the king said, Let who will speak to thee, bring him to me, and he shall no more touch him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And she said, Let the king, I pray thee, make mention of the Lord his God, that though avengers of blood be multiplied to destroy, they shall not destroy my son. Whereupon he said, As the Lord liveth, there shall not a hair of thy son's head fall to the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the woman said, Let thy servant, I pray thee, speak a word to my lord the king, and he said, Speak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the woman said, Why hast thou come to such a determination against the people of God? Or is that word, That the king would not recal his own exile, a kind of trespass from the mouth of the king?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Because we must surely die, and be like water spilt on the ground, which cannot be gathered up again; and God can take away life when he is determined to remove an outcast from him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>now therefore in respect to the matter about which I came to speak to my lord the king, Because the people will see me, therefore thy servant will say, Pray speak to my lord the king; perhaps the king will grant the request of his servant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Because the king will hear, let him deliver his servant out of the hand of the man who seeketh to remove me and my son from the inheritance of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then the woman said, Let the word of my lord the king be, I pray, for a sacrifice; for since my lord the king is as an angel of God to discern what is good and what is bad, surely the Lord thy God must be with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then the king answered and said to the woman, Conceal not from me I pray thee, the thing which I shall ask thee. And the woman said, Pray let my lord the king speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the king said, Is not the hand of Joab with thee in this whole business? And the woman said to the king, As thy soul liveth, my lord the king, there is no turning to the right, nor to the left, from all that my lord the king hath spoken; for thy servant Joab commanded me, and he himself put all these words in the mouth of thy servant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>that this case might wear the appearance of the thing which thy servant Joab wished to have done. But my lord is wise as an angel of God, to know all the things on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then the king said to Joab, Behold I have done for thee according to this thy state of the case; bring back the young man, Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon which Joab fell on his face to the ground, and made obeisance, and blessed the king. And Joab said, Now thy servant knoweth that I have found favour in thy sight, my lord the king, because my lord the king hath granted the suit of his servant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then Joab arose and went to Gedsur, and brought Abessalom to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And the king said, Let him return to his house, and not see my face. So Abessalom returned to his house, and did not see the king's face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now in all Israel there was not a man so very comely as Abessalom. From the sole of his foot, to the crown of his head, there was not a blemish in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>When he polled his head, and at the beginning of every year he had it polled, because the hair was burthensome to him, and when he polled it he weighed the hair of his head, and it weighed two hundred shekels after the king's shekel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And to Abessalom there were born three sons and one daughter. The name of his daughter was Themar. She was a very beautiful woman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when Abessalom had dwelt two years at Jerusalem, and saw not the king's face,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Abessalom sent for Joab that he might send him to the king, but he declined coming to him. And when he had sent a second time, and he declined coming,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Abessalom said to his servants, See, the portion of land in the field adjoining mine is Joab's, and he hath barley there. Go and set it on fire. And when Abessalom's servants set the field on fire, the servants of Joab came to him with their clothes rent, and said, Abessalom's servants have burned the field with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Thereupon Joab arose, and went to Abessalom, and said to him, Why have thy servants set my field on fire?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And Abessalom said to Joab, Behold I sent to thee, saying, Come here that I may send thee to the king, saying, Why have I come from Gedsur? It was better for me to be there, as I have not yet seen the king's face. If indeed there be wickedness in me, put me to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then Joab went to the king, and delivered him this message, and he sent for Abessalom, and Abessalom went to the king, and made obeisance to him, and prostrated himself on the ground before him, and the king kissed him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after this, Abessalom procured for himself chariots, and horses, and fifty men to run before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Abessalom rose early in the morning, and took his stand at the place where the road turned off to the gate. And when any man who had a controversy came to the king for judgment, Abessalom called to him, and said, Of what city art thou? And when he said, Thy servant is of such a one of the tribes of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Abessalom said to him, Behold thy cause is good, and easily determined, but there is none appointed by the king to hear thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then would Abessalom say, that they would make me a judge in the land! In that case if any man had a defence to make, or a suit to prosecute, and would come to me, I would do him justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when any man came to make obeisance to him, he stretched forth his hand, and took him, and kissed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In this manner Abessalom acted to all Israel who were coming to the king for judgment, so that Abessalom won the hearts of the men of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And at the end of four years Abessalom said to his father, Let me I pray thee go and pay my vows at Chebron, which I vowed to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For when I dwelt at Gedsur, in Syria, thy servant vowed a vow, saying, If the Lord will bring me back to Jerusalem, I will serve the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the king said to him, Go in peace. So he arose and went to Chebron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now Abessalom had sent spies through all the tribes of Israel, saying, When you hear the sound of the trumpet, then say, Abessalom is king in Chebron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And there went with Abessalom two hundred chosen men out of Jerusalem. They indeed went in their simplicity, for they knew nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Abessalom sent for Achitophel, the Thekonite, the counsellor of David, from his own city, namely, from Gola, while he was sacrificing. So the conspiracy became strong, and the people who came, and they were many, were with Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And there came a messenger to David, saying, The heart of the men of Israel is gone after Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Upon this David said to all his servants who were with him at Jerusalem, Arise and let us flee, for there is no safety for us on account of Abessalom. Make haste to depart, lest he overtake us suddenly, and throw the blame on us, when he shall smite the city with the edge of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the king's servants said to the king, Whatever our lord the king chuseth, behold we thy servants are ready to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So the king and all his household, set out on foot, and the king left ten of his concubines to keep the house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when the king, with all his servants, on foot, had gone out, they halted at the farthest house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and all his servants passed on by him, namely, all the Chelethites, and all the Phelethites, and they halted near the olive yard, in the wilderness. And all the people passed by near him. Now all that were around him; all the nobles, and all the warriors, were six hundred men, and while these stood by him, all the Chelethites, and all the Phelethites, and all the Gethites; the six hundred men who had come on foot from Geth, marched on before the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the king said to Ethi the Gethite, Why shouldst thou go with us? Return and dwell with the king; for thou art a stranger, and hast come as an exile from thy own place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>As thou art come but yesterday, shall I to-day cause thee to move with us, and change thy abode? As for me, I will go where I can; but return thou and take back thy brethren with thee; and the Lord will deal mercifully and truly with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And Ethi answered the king, and said, As the Lord liveth, and as my lord the king liveth, whithersoever my lord goeth, whether to death or to life, there shall thy servant be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Whereupon the king said to Ethi, Come and march with me. So Ethi, the Gethite marched on with the king, and all his servants, and all the multitude who were with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And all the country wept with a loud voice, while all the people were crossing the brook Kedron. And when the king had crossed the brook Kedron, all the people, and the king, continued their march by the way to the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now behold Sadok, and all the Levites, were with him, carrying the ark of the covenant of the Lord from Baithar. And they set down the ark of God, and Abiathar went up, until all the people had done coming out of the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then the king said to Sadok, Carry back the ark of God into the city. If I find favour in the sight of the Lord, he will bring me back, and shew me it and its comeliness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But if he should say, I have no pleasure in thee, behold here am I. Let him do to me as seemeth good in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then the king said to Sadok the priest, See! thou returnest to the city in peace; and Achimaas, thy son, and Jonathan, the son of Abiathar; your two sons are with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>See! I will encamp at Araboth of the wilderness, until a message come from you to give me intelligence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So Sadok and Abiathar carried back the ark of God to Jerusalem, and it abode there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And David went up by the ascent of the olive orchards, weeping as he went up, and having his head covered, and walking barefoot. And all the people who were with him covered, every one, his head, and went up weeping as they went.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when it was told David that Achitophel was among the conspirators with Abessalom, David said, Confound, I beseech thee, Lord my God, the counsel of Achitophel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And David continued his march till he came to Ros, where he worshipped God. And behold Chousi, an old companion of David, met him there, with his clothes rent, and earth on his head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And David said to him, If thou go with me, thou wilt be a burden to me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>but if thou return to the city, and wilt say to Abessalom, Thy brothers are gone, and the king thy father is gone, and hath left me behind, now therefore, I am thy servant, king. Let me live. I have been thy father's servant hitherto; but now I am thy servant: thou mayst baffle for me the counsel of Achitophel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And behold there are there with thee, Sadok and Abiathar, the priests, so that whatever thou mayst hear from the king's household thou wilt tell to Sadok and Abiathar, the priests.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And behold they have there with them their two sons Achimaas, son of Sadok, and Jonathan, son of Abiathar, so that by them you can send to me every thing you may hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Accordingly, Chousi, David's companion, came to the city, just as Abessalom was entering Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when David had marched on a little way from Ros, behold Siba, the servant of Memphibosthe, came out to meet him with a couple of asses saddled, and on them two hundred loaves of bread, and a hundred clusters of dried grapes, and a hundred bunches of dates, and a nebel of wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the king said to Siba, What meanest thou by these? To which Siba replied, The asses are for the king's family to ride on, and the loaves and the dates for the young men to eat, and the wine for such as are fainty in the wilderness, to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the king said, But where is thy master's son? And Siba said to the king, Behold he abideth in Jerusalem; for he said, Now will the house of Israel restore me the kingdom of my father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon the king said to Siba, Behold all that belong to Memphibosthe are thine. And Siba having bowed down said, Let me find favour in thy sight, my lord the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when king David was going to Baurim, behold there came out thence a man of the family of the house of Saul, whose name was Semei, son of Gera. He came out, cursing David as he came,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and throwing stones at David, and at all the servants of king David. Now all the people, even all the mighty men, were on the right and left of the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And in this manner Semei expressed himself when he cursed him, Out! Out! thou man of blood! thou miscreant!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The Lord hath retorted on thee all the blood of the house of Saul. Because thou hast reigned in his stead, therefore the Lord hath delivered the kingdom into the hands of Abessalom thy son. And behold thou art in distress, because thou art a bloody man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Whereupon Abessa, son of Saruia said to the king, Why should this dead dog curse my lord the king? Let me go over, and I will take off his head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But the king said, What is it to me and you, sons of Saruia? Let him alone, and let him curse on; for the Lord hath told him to curse David, and who shall say Why hast thou done so?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then David said to Abessa, and to all his servants, Behold my own son, who is descended from my loins, seeketh my life, and how much more then may this Jeminite do it! Let him curse, for the Lord hath bidden him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Perhaps the Lord may look on my affliction, and return me good for his cursing this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So David and all his men proceeded on their march, and Semei went along the side of the mountain near him, cursing as he went, and throwing stones from the side of it, and casting up dust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when the king arrived, and all the people with him, being fatigued, they refreshed themselves there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now Abessalom and all Israel had come to Jerusalem, and Achitophel with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when Chousi, the old companion of David, came to Abessalom, Chousi said to Abessalom, God save the king!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whereupon Abessalom said to Chousi, Is this thy kindness for thy friend? Why hast thou not gone with thy friend?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And Chousi said to Abessalom, shall I not follow him whom the Lord hath chosen, and this his people; even all Israel? For him I will be; and with him I will abide.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And in the next place whom should I serve? Must it not be before his son? As I have served before thy father, so will I be before thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then Abessalom said to Achitophel, Consult among yourselves what we shall do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thereupon Achitophel said to Abessalom, Go in unto thy father's concubines, whom he hath left to keep his house; and all Israel will hear that thou hast dishonoured thy father, and the hands of all who are with thee will be strengthened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So they fixed up a tent for Abessalom on the top of the house, and Abessalom went in unto his father's concubines, in the sight of all Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now the advice which Achitophel gave in those first days, was as if one had consulted the oracle of God. Such was every advice of Achitophel both with David and with Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Achitophel said to Abessalom, Let me, I pray thee, chuse out for myself twelve thousand men; and I will arise and pursue David this very night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I will come upon him while he is weary, and weak-handed, and surprise him; so that all the people who are with him will flee. And I will smite the king alone,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and bring all the people back to thee, as a bride returneth to her husband. Thou seekest only the life of one man, therefore all the people may be at peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Though this reasoning seemed good in the sight of Abessalom, and in the sight of all the elders of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>yet Abessalom said, Call, I pray you, Chousi the Arachite, and let us hear also what he saith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when Chousi came to Abessalom, Abessalom spoke to him saying, In this manner Achitophel has spoken; shall we do as he adviseth? If not, speak thou.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Upon this Chousi said to Abessalom, The counsel which Achitophel hath given, is, for this once, not good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thou thyself, said Chousi, knowest thy father and his men, that they are very brave, and chafed in their minds like a bear bereaved of her whelps in the fields; or like a wild boar in the plain. And thy father is a man of war, and will not let the people rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For behold he is now hid in one of the mountains, or in some secure place, and it shall be that when he shall sally out on them at the first, every one who heareth will say, There hath been a slaughter among them who follow Abessalom:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>in which case the son of valour himself, whose heart is like the heart of a lion, will assuredly be dismayed. For all Israel know that thy father is a mighty man, and that they who are with him are sons of valour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This therefore is the counsel which I would give; Let all Israel be gathered to thee, from Dan to Bersabee, like the sand which is on the sea shore for multitude; and let thy presence go forth in the midst of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when we shall come upon him in one of the places where we may find him, we will encamp around him as the dew falleth on the ground. And we will not leave with him or the men who are with him so much as one man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And if he be shut up in any city, all Israel will take ropes to that city, and we will drag it into the ditch, so that there shall not be left so much as a stone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And Abessalom, and all Israel, said, The counsel of Chousi the Arachite is better than the counsel of Achitophel. For the Lord had determined to defeat the counsel of Achitophel, which was good, that the Lord might bring upon Abessalom all the consequent evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Chousi, the Arachite, said to Sadok, and Abiathar the priests, Thus and thus did Achitophel advise Abessalom and the elders of Israel; and thus and thus I have counselled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now therefore send speedily, and tell David and say, Lodge not to night at Araboth of the wilderness, but cross with all speed. Perhaps he may prevail with the king and all the people who are with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now Jonathan and Achimaas had taken their station at the fountain Rogel, and a girl went out, and gave them intelligence, and they went and told David, for they might not be seen entering the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But a servant saw them and told Abessalom. Now they two had set out with speed, and got to the house of a man at Bakurim, who had a well in his court and they went down into it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the woman took and spread a covering over the mouth of the well, and laid thereon balls of dough to dry; so that the thing was not known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the servants of Abessalom came to the woman, into the house and said, Where are Achimaas and Jonathan? The woman said, They went a little while ago over the water. And when they had sought, but did not find them, they returned to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And when they were gone, Achimaas and Jonathan came up out of the well, and went and told king David, and said to him, Arise and cross the water with all speed: for thus hath Achitophel counselled concerning you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Whereupon David arose, and the people who were with him, and they crossed the Jordan till the morning light, till there</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>was not one left, who had not crossed the Jordan. Now when Achitophel saw that his advice was not taken, he saddled his ass, and arose, and went to his house to his own city, and having given orders to his household he strangled himself, and died, and was buried in his father's tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And David continued his march to Manaim, and Abessalom crossed the Jordan, he and all Israel with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now Abessalom had set Amessai over the army in the room of Joab. Amessai was the son of a man whose name was Jether. He was a Jezraelite, and had married Abigaia, a daughter of Naas, and a sister of Saruia the mother of Joab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And all Israel with Abessalom encamped in the land of Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now when David came to Manaim, Ovesbi, son of Naas, of Rabbath of the Ammonites, and Machir, son of Amiel of Lodabar, and Berzelli, the Galaadite of Rogellim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>brought ten beds of double tapestry, and ten kettles and vessels of earthen ware, and wheat, and barley, and fine flour, and meal, and beans, and lentils,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and honey, and butter, and sheep, and curdled milk of kine, and presented them to David, and to the people who were with him, to eat. For they said, The people must be hungry and weary in the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when David had reviewed the people who were with him, and set over them captains of thousands, and captains of hundreds,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he sent forth the people, one third under the command of Joab; and one third under the command of Abessa, the son of Saruia, and brother of Joab, and one third under the command of Ethi the Gethite. And David said to the people, I myself will go out with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But they said, Thou must not go out. For if we should flee they will pay no regard to us; for if one half of us should die, they will not care for us: for thou art worth ten thousand of us. Now therefore it is best that thou shouldst be in the city to succour and help us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the king said, Whatever seemeth best in your eyes I will do. So the king stood by the side of the gate, and when all the people were marching out by hundreds, and by thousands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the king gave a charge to Joab, and to Abessa, and to Ethi saying, Spare, for my sake, the young man Abessalom. And all the people heard the king giving this charge to all the commanders respecting Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And all the people went out to the forest, in front of Israel, and the battle was fought in the forest of Ephraim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and Israel there gave way before the servants of David, and there was a great slaughter that day, to the amount of twenty thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For the battle was there scattered over the whole face of the ground, and the forest devoured more of the people than the sword destroyed that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And as Abessalom was advancing to meet the servants of David, being mounted on his mule, his mule entered the thickest copse of that great oak forest, and his head got entangled among the oaks so that he was suspended between heaven and earth, and the mule went from under him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And a man saw him, and told Joab, and said, Behold I saw Abessalom hanging among the oaks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Whereupon Joab said to the man who told him, And behold thou sawest! Why didst thou not smite him there to the ground; and I would have given thee ten pieces of silver, and a girdle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the man said, As I live, though I might have a thousand shekels of silver weighed into my hands, I would not lay my hands on the king's son. For in our hearing the king charged thee, and Abessa, and Ethi, saying, Spare, for my sake, the young man Abessalom; touch not his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now nothing can be hid from the king. Even thou thyself wouldst stand aloof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And Joab said, I myself will in this case, set the example. I will not boggle so in thy sight. Then Joab took three darts in his hand, and thrust them through Abessalom's heart, while he was still alive in the heart of the forest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when the ten young men, who carried Joab's arms, had surrounded and smitten Abessalom, and put him to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Joab sounded the trumpet, and the people returned from pursuing Israel; for Joab had mercy on the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he took Abessalom, and threw him into a great chasm in the forest, into the great pit, and piled over him a great heap of stones. And all Israel fled every man to his tent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now Abessalom had, in his life time, undertaken and erected for himself a monument in which he was to have been buried. So he erected this monument to supply the place of that in the king's dale, because, said he, he hath no son to keep up the remembrance of his name. And he called that monument, The hand of Abessalom, which name it retaineth to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then Achimaas son of Sadok said, Let me, I pray thee, run and tell the king good news, That the Lord hath delivered him out of the hand of his enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But Joab said to him, Thou wilt not be the messenger of good news today. At another time thou shalt carry good news. But this day thou canst not be the messenger of good news, because the king's son is dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Joab said to Chousi, Run and tell the king what thou hast seen. Whereupon Chousi bowed to Joab and set out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And Achimaas, son of Sadok, applied again, and said to Joab, Grant me leave that I also may run after Chousi. And Joab said, Why art thou so earnest to run, my son? Come, there is no good news worth thy going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And he said, But what if I can run? Then Joab said to him, Run. So Achimaas ran by the way leading to Kechar, and passed Chousi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now David was sitting between the two gates, and the watchman went up to the top of the gate, to the wall, and raising his eyes he looked and behold there was a man in his view running alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So the watchman cried, and told the king. And the king said, If he be alone, there is good news in his mouth. While he was advancing, and coming near,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>the watchman saw another man running, whereupon the watchman cried to the gate, and said, Behold there is another man running alone. And the king said, He also is a messenger of good news.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the watchman said, I see the running of the foremost is like the running of Achimaas son of Sadok. And the king said, He is a good man, and must therefore come with good news.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then Achimaas cried aloud, and said to the king, All is well. And when he had made obeisance to the king, with his face to the ground, he said, Blessed be the Lord thy God, who hath delivered up the men who lifted their hands against my lord the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then the king said, Is the young man Abessalom safe? And Achimaas said, I saw a great crowd when Joab the king's servant despatched thy servant, but I did not know what was there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then the king said, Turn aside, and stand here. And when he turned aside, and took his station,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>behold Chousi came, and said to the king, Good news to my lord the king; for the Lord hath this day delivered thee out of the hand of all who rose up against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the king said to Chousi, Is the young man Abessalom safe? And Chousi said, May all the enemies of my lord the king, and all who have risen against him for evil, be as that young man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>At this the king was much moved, and went up to the chamber, over the gate, and wept. And as he was going up he thus expressed himself, Oh, my son, Abessalom! Oh! my son! my son Abessalom! that they had slain me instead of thee; that I had died in thy stead! Oh Abessalom! my son! my son!</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When they told Joab the news, saying, Behold the king is weeping, and mourning for Abessalom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>so that the joy of the day is turned into sorrow to all the people, (For the people that day heard it said, that the king was in grief for his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>therefore the people were stealing into the city that day, as people do who are ashamed, when they flee in battle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and the king hid his face) therefore when the king cried with a loud voice saying, Oh! my son Abessalom! Oh! Abessalom my son!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Joab went to the king, into the house, and said, Thou hast this day put to shame the faces of all thy servants, who have this day delivered thee, and saved the lives of thy sons, and the lives of thy daughters, and the lives of thy wives, and thy concubines;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>by thy loving those who hate thee, and hating those who love thee. Thou hast indeed this day declared, that thou regardest neither thy officers, nor thy servants; for I am now convinced, that if Abessalom were alive, and we were now all dead, then all would be right in thine eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now therefore arise, and go out, and speak affectionately to thy servants; for I have sworn by the Lord, that if thou go not out immediately, there will not a man lodge with thee this night. And be assured that this will be worse for thee than all the evil that hath befallen thee, from thy youth even till now.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the king arose, and sat in the gate. And when all the people proclaimed the news, saying, Behold the king is sitting in the gate, then all the people entered the gate, in the presence of the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now when all Israel had fled, every man to his tent, all the people throughout all the tribes of Israel began to condemn themselves, saying, King David delivered us from all our enemies. Though he delivered us out of the hands of the Philistines, yet he hath now fled from the land, and from his kingdom, and from Abessalom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But Abessalom whom we anointed over us is dead in battle, now therefore, why are you silent about bringing the king back?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When this saying of all Israel came to the king, king David sent to Sadok, and to Abiathar the priests, saying, Speak to the elders of Juda, and say, Why are you the last to bring the king back to his house? The speech indeed of all Israel is come to the king, that he should return to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>You are my brethren; you are my bones, and my flesh. Why are you the last to bring the king back to his house?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And to Amessai you shall say, Art not thou my bone and my flesh? Now therefore, God do so to me and more also, if thou shalt not be captain general of the army before me continually, in the room of Joab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So when he had turned the heart of Juda, like that of one man, they sent to the king, saying, Return thou and all thy servants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So the king set out on his return, and came to the Jordan. And the men of Juda came to Galgala, to go and meet the king, and conduct him over the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And Semei, son of Gera the Jeminite, of Baurim, hastened and came down with the men of Juda, to meet king David;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and with him were a thousand men from Benjamin, and Siba the servant of the house of Saul, with his fifteen sons, and his twenty servants, and they acted as guides across the Jordan, before the king, and performed the service of bringing the king over.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when the raft went over to bring the king's household, and to do what was right in his sight, Semei son of Gera fell on his face before the king, while he was crossing the Jordan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and said to the king, Let not my lord, I pray thee, impute to me my transgression; nor call to remembrance what thy servant did perversely, on the day when my lord went out of Jerusalem, that the king should lay it to heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Because thy servant was conscious that he had sinned, therefore behold I am come, the first of all Israel, and of the house of Joseph, in coming down to meet my lord the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>To this Abessa son of Saruia, answered and said, Shall not Semei be put to death, because he cursed the anointed of2 the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But David said, What have you to do with me, ye sons of Saruia, that you are now laying snares for me? There shall not a man of Israel be this day put to death. For I do not yet know whether I am king over Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then the king said to Semei, Thou shalt not die. And the king swore to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Memphibosthe also, the grandson of Saul, came down to meet the king. Now he had not dressed his feet, nor pared his nails, nor trimmed his beard, nor washed his clothes, from the day the king went away, to the day he returned, in peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And when he came to Jerusalem, and waited on the king, and the king said to him, Why didst thou not go with me, Memphibosthe?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Memphibosthe said to the king, my lord the king, my servant deceived me. For thy servant said to him, Saddle me the ass, that I may mount thereon and go with the king. (For thy servant is lame.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But he acted deceitfully with thy servant, before my lord the king. But my lord the king is as an angel of God. Do therefore what is good in thy sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For all my father's house were but dead men before my lord the king, yet thou didst set thy servant among them who eat at thy table. What right then have I to cry any more to the king?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And the king said to him, What need of more words. I have said, Thou and Siba shall divide the fields.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Whereupon Memphibosthe said to the king, Nay, let him take all, seeing my lord the king is returned to his house in peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Berzelli, the Galaadite, also came down from Rogellim, and crossed the Jordan with the king, to convoy him over the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now Berzelli was a very old man, being then eighty years of age, and he had supplied the king and his household with provisions at Manaim, for he was a very wealthy man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>When the king said to Berzelli, Thou shalt come over with me, that I may nourish thy old age with me at Jerusalem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Berzelli said to the king, How many can the days of the years of my life be, that I should go with the king to Jerusalem?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>I am now eighty years of age. Can I distinguish between good and evil? Can thy servant any more relish what I eat or drink? Or can I any more hear the voice of singing men or singing women? Why then should thy servant be a burthen to my lord the king?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Thy servant will go a little way across the Jordan with the king; but why should the king make me such a recompence?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Let thy servant, I pray thee, stay, that I may die in my own city, near the tomb of my father and mother. And behold thy servant Chamaam shall go over with my lord the king. Do to him what is good in thy sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And the king said, Let Chamaam come over with me, and I will do for him what is good in my sight, and whatever thou requirest of me, I will do for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now all the people had crossed the Jordan, and when the king had crossed, he kissed Berzelli, and bade him farewell, and he returned to his place;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and the king proceeded on to Galgala, and Chamaam went with him. Now when all the tribe of Juda, and about half of the people of Israel, were advancing with the king,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>behold all Israel came to the king, and said to the king, Why have our brethren, the men of Juda, stolen thee away, and brought the king and his household over the Jordan?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Are all the men of David indeed with him? And all the men of Juda answered the men of Israel, and said, Because the king is near of kin to us, why should you be so angry at this matter? Have we eaten at the king's cost? Or hath he given us any gifts, or borne any burthen for us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And the men of Israel answered the men of Juda, and said, We have ten votes for the king, and we are elder than you, therefore we have more interest in David than you. Why then have you affronted us, and why was not our opinion taken before that of Juda, to bring the king back? Then the words of the men of Juda were fiercer than the words of the</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>men of Israel; and there happened to be there a turbulent man whose name was Sabee, son of Bochori, the chief of the Jeminites, and he sounded a trumpet, and said, We have no portion in David, nor inheritance in the son of Jessai. Every man to his tent, Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thereupon all Israel went up from following David, after Sabee, son of Bochori. But the men of Juda kept close by their king, from the Jordan to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when David came to his house at Jerusalem, the king took the ten women, his concubines, whom he had left to keep the house, and sent them to a house of confinement, and fed them, but did not go in to them. So they were kept confined to the day of their death, living as widows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then the king said to Amessai, Assemble for me all the men of Juda, and be thou here in three days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So Amessai went to assemble the men of Juda, but he tarried beyond the time which David set for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thereupon David said to Abessa Now will Sabee, son of Bochori do us more harm than Abessalom. Now therefore take thou with thee the servants of thy lord, and pursue him, lest he secure for himself cities of defence, that he may escape our notice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So there went out after him, Abessa's men, and Joab's men, and the Cherethites, and the Phelethites, and all the mighty men. And when they had marched out of Jerusalem in pursuit of Sabee, son of Bochori,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and were come to the great heap of stones at Gabaon, Amessai came in before them. Now Joab had a military robe girded on for his dress, and over it he was girt with a sword on his thigh in its sheath, and the sword dropped out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But as it dropped out and fell, therefore when Joab said to Amessai, art thou well my brother? and with his right hand took hold of Amessai's beard to kiss it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Amessai did not attend to the sword which was in Joab's hand. So Joab smote him with it into the belly, and his bowels gushed out on the ground, so that he did not repeat the blow. And while he was dying, Joab and Abessa, his brother, pursued after Sabee, son of Bochori,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and there stood by him one of the servants of Joab, who said, Whoever is for Joab, and whoever is for David, let him follow Joab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now Amessai was weltering in his blood in the middle of the road. And when the man saw that all the people halted, he drew Amessai out of the road, into the field, and threw a mantle over him, because he saw that all the people who came up stood still.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when he had removed him out of the road, then all the men of Israel proceeded on after Joab, in pursuit of Sabee, son of Bochori.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now he had passed through all the tribes of Israel to Abel and Bethmacha, and all the men at Charri had assembled and gone after him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when they came up with him they formed a siege against him in Abel and Bethmacha. And when they had levelled the bank before the city, and were got within the out works, and all the people who were with Joab, were labouring to throw down the wall,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>a wise woman cried with a loud voice from the wall, and said, Hear! Hear! Say, I pray you, to Joab, Come near hither that I may speak to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when he drew near to her, the woman said, Art thou Joab? And he said, I am. Then she said to him, Hear the words of thy servant. And when Joab said, I am hearkening,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>then she continued her speech, and said, They used heretofore to state an accusation, saying, He who is examined hath been examined both in Abel and Dan. If the liege men of Israel have been guilty of what is laid to their charge, let the examiners in Abel inquire in like manner whether they have been guilty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For my part I am for observing strictly the customs of Israel, which tend to peace; but thou art seeking to destroy a city; a mother city in Israel. Why wouldst thou swallow up an inheritance of the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In answer to which Joab said, Mercy on me! Mercy on me! Am I for swallowing up? Am I for destroying?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Is not this the case? There is a man of mount Ephraim; his name is Sabee son of Bochori, who hath lifted up his hand against king David. Only deliver him up to me, and I will depart from the city. And the woman said, Behold his head shall be thrown to thee over the wall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So the woman went to all the people. And when she had spoken to the whole city in her wisdom, they cut off the head of Sabee son of Bochori. And having cut it off, they threw it to Joab; whereupon Joab sounded a trumpet, and all the people withdrew from the city, and dispersed, every man to his tent, and Joab returned to Jerusalem to the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now Joab was over all the host of Israel, and Banaias son of Jodae was over the Cherethites and the Phelethites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Adoniram was over the tribute, and Josaphat son of Achiluth was recorder,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and Susa was scribe, and Sadok and Abiathar were priests,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and Iras the son of Jarim was priest for David.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the days of David there was a famine three years, year after year successively; whereupon David applied to the Lord, and the Lord said, On Saul and on his house be the iniquity, by the death of his descendants, because he put to death the Gabaonites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now the Gabaonites are not of the children of Israel, but a remnant of the Amorites, and the children of Israel had sworn to them; but Saul sought occasion to smite them, when he was courting popularity with the children of Israel and Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So king David sent for the Gabaonites, and said to them, What shall I do for you; and by what means can I make atonement, that you may bless the inheritance of the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the Gabaonites said to him, We have no controversy with Saul and his household, about gold or silver, nor is it for us to put to death a man in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the king said, What do you say, I must do for you? And they said to the king, The man who set himself against us, and persecuted us, and who formed pretences to exterminate us, him let us destroy, that he may not rise up in all the borders of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Give us seven men of his sons, and let us crucify to the Lord at Gabaon those of Saul who are the choice of the Lord. And the king said, I will give them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But the king had compassion on Memphibosthe, the son of Jonathan, Saul's son, on account of the oath of the Lord between them; namely between David and Jonathan, Saul's son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So the king took the two sons of Respha, the daughter of Aia, whom she bore to Saul, namely Ermoni and Memphibosthe, and the five sons of Michol the daughter of Saul, whom she bore to Esdriel, the son of Berzelli, the Mooulothite,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and delivered them into the hands of the Gabaonites, and they crucified them on the mount before the Lord. So these seven fell together. Now they were put to death in the days of the harvest of first fruits, in the beginning of the barley harvest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Respha, the daughter of Aia, took sackcloth, and fixed it up for herself, before the rock, in the beginning of the barley harvest, until water from heaven dropped upon them; and she suffered not the birds of the air to rest upon them by day, nor the beasts of the field by night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When David was told what Respha the daughter of Aia Saul's concubine had done; (now they were wasted away, and Dan son of Joa, of the race of the giants had taken them down.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>David went, and took the the bones of Saul, and the bones of Jonathan his son, from the men of Jabis Galaad, who had stolen them from the street of Baithsan, where the Philistines had fixed them on the day when the Philistines smote Saul at Gelbua;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and having brought thence the bones of Saul, and the bones of Jonathan his son, he gathered up the bones of them who had been crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And they buried the bones of Saul and the bones of Jonathan, and the bones of them who were crucified, in the land of Benjamin, on the one side, in the tomb of his father Kis. And when they had done all that the king commanded, God, after that, hearkened to the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>There was also another battle between the Philistines and Israel. David, and his servants with him, went down and fought the Philistines. And as David was advancing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesbi, who was of the race of Rapha, and the weight of whose spear was three hundred shekels, brass weight, and who was clad in armour, thought to have smitten David;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but Abessa, son of Saruia, came to his assistance, and smote the Philistine, and killed him. Then David's men swore, saying, Thou shalt not go out with us any more to battle, lest thou extinguish the lamp of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And after this there was another battle, at Geth, with the Philistines, in which Sobocha the Astatothite smote Seph, one of the descendants of Rapha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>There was also a battle with the Philistines at Rom, when Eleanan son of Ariorgim the Bethlemite, smote Lachmi, the brother of Goliath the Gethite, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver's beam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>There was also another battle at Geth, and there was a smooth man who had six fingers on each hand, and six toes on each foot, twenty four in all, and he was a descendant of Rapha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and defied Israel, but Jonathan son of Semei, David's brother, smote him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>These four descendants of the giants were born at Geth, and were of the house of Rapha, and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And David addressed the Lord in the words of this ode: on the day the Lord delivered him out of the hands of all his enemies, and out of the hand of Saul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he said in a psalm; Lord, Thou art my rock and my fortress. It is he who delivereth me; he shall be my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He will be my guard, in him I will trust; He is my defence, and the horn of my salvation; My helper and my refuge for safety. From an unrighteous man thou wilt save me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>On the Lord, who is praise worthy, I will call, And I shall be saved from mine enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Because troubles of death have surrounded me; Floods of iniquity have filled me with horror;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The pangs of death have compassed me about; The bitterness of death hath invaded me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>In my distress I will call on the Lord, And to my God I will cry aloud. From his holy temple he will hear my voice, My cry will certainly reach his ears.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The earth indeed was shaken; it trembled; The foundations of heaven were convulsed, and quivered, Because the Lord was incensed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>At his indignation a smoke ascended, A fire from his mouth devoureth. By it coals are kindled to a glow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He bowed the heavens and came down, And darkness was under his feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He sat on the cherubim, and flew, And appeared on the wings of wind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But he made darkness his covering; His pavilion around him was darkness of waters; He condensed it with clouds of air.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>From the flashing lightning before him Flaming fires were kindled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The Lord thundered from heaven, The Most High uttered his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He sent forth his bolts and scattered them: He darted his lightning, and confounded them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then were seen the outlets of the sea; And the foundations of the earth were disclosed, At the rebuke of the Lord; At the blast of the breath of his anger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He sent from on high and took me; He drew me out of many waters:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He delivered me from mine enemies' strength; From them who hated me; Because they were stronger than I.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The days of my distress came on me unawares, But the Lord was my firm support,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And brought me out to a roomy place, And delivered me, because he delighted in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The Lord rewarded me according to my righteousness; According to the cleanness of my hands he recompensed me</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Because I kept the ways of the Lord, And did not wickedly depart from my God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Because all his judgments were before me, And from his statutes I did not depart;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>I therefore shall be blameless before him, And I will guard myself from my iniquity;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the Lord will reward me according to my righteousness; According to the cleanness of my hands in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>With the beneficent thou wilt shew thyself beneficent, With an upright man thou wilt deal uprightly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>With a warrior thou wilt be a warrior, And with the wily thou wilt practice wiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thou wilt save the people who are dejected, But lofty countenances thou wilt bring down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Because thou, Lord, art my lamp, Therefore the Lord will illume my darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For by thee I can run like an honoured soldier, And overleap walls by the help of my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>He is mighty whose way is blameless. The word of the Lord is strong; is tried. He is the defender of all them who trust in him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Who is mighty, besides the Lord? Who can build up, but our God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He who strengthened me is the Mighty One, He hath cleared my way which is blameless.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Thou makest my feet like the feet of hinds, And steadiest me on the high places.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Thou instructest my hands for battle, And hast by my arm broken the bow of steel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Thou hast given me a guard for my safety; And thy attention hath enabled me</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>To enlarge my steps under me, So that my feet have not slipped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>I shall pursue my enemies and destroy them, And will not turn back till I consume them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>I will break them so that they shall not rise, When they shall have fallen under my feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For thou wilt gird me with strength for battle, And bend under me my antagonists.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Thou hast given me the back of my enemies; And them who hate me thou hast put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>They may cry aloud but there is no help; To the Lord, but he will not answer them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>I beat them small as the dust of the earth; I trampled them like the dirt of highways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>From the tumult of tribes thou wilt save me; Thou wilt keep me to be the head of nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>A people which I knew not shall be my slaves, Strangers have yielded me feigned obedience. Soon as they heard they became submissive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Strange children shall be exposed to contempt; They shall tumble down from their places of defence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Live the Lord! and blessed be he, my guard! Let my God, my safeguard, be exalted;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>The mighty Lord, who is my avenger. Who chastiseth the people under me, Who leadeth me out from my enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>From them who are stirred up against me Thou wilt raise me up. From the man of violence, thou wilt deliver me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>For this cause I will give thee thanks, Lord, among the nations. I will sing melodiously to thy name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>He is magnifying the deliverances of his own king, And shewing mercy to his anointed; To David and his seed forever.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these were the last words of David. Faithful is David the son of Jessai, And faithful the man whom the Lord hath set Over the anointed of the God of Jacob. And sweet are the psalms of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The Spirit of the Lord hath spoken by me, And his word was upon my tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The God of Israel saith to me, A watchman of Israel hath spoken a proverb. I said as a man, How can you strengthen the fear of an anointed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>With the light of the God of the morning. David. Prophet. Let the Sun rise in the morning betimes. Is not the Lord gone forth with splendour? Yes, like the spring of grass on the earth after rain;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For is not my house thus with the Almighty? For he hath made with me an everlasting covenant, Kept ready for every occasion; Because this is all my safety, and all my desire, That the transgressor may not flourish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>All such are like rejected thorns. Because they cannot be handled,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Nor can a man labour among them; Therefore pure iron, and the staff of a spear, Shall cause them to burn with fire, And they shall be burned to their shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>These are the names of David's worthies. Jebosthe, the Chananite, a chief of the third rank, who is also called Adinon the Asonite. This man drew his sword against eight hundred warriors at one time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And after him Eleanon (the son of a man who married his brother's wife to raise up seed for his brother) the son of Dudi, one of the three worthies with David. When he challenged the Philistines, and they had assembled for battle, and the men of Israel had gone up,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>he arose and made a slaughter among the Philistines, till his hand was tired, and glued to his sword, and the Lord wrought a great deliverance that day, and the people went after him only to spoil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And next to him was Samaias, son of Asa the Aruchite. When the Philistines had assembled to forage, where there was a piece of ground full of lentils, and the people fled before the Philistines;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>he stood like a pillar in the middle of the field, and defended it, and smote the Philistines, and the Lord wrought a great deliverance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>These three went down from the thirty, and came to David at Kason, to the cave of Odollam, when an army of the Philistines was encamped in the valley of Raphain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now David was then in the fortress, and there was a garrison of the Philistines then at Bethlehem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And David longed and said, Oh that I had some water to drink out of the well which is at Bethlehem; that by the gate!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Upon which these three worthies, notwithstanding the garrison of the Philistines then at Bethlehem, broke through the camp of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well at Bethlehem, by the gate. But when they got it, and came to David, he would not drink it, but poured it out as a libation to the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and said, Lord forbid that I should do this. Shall I drink the blood of these men, who have gone at the risk of their lives? So he would not drink it. These exploits were performed by these three men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now Abessa, the brother of Joab, son of Saruia, was a chief among the three. He also lifted up his spear against three hundred men, though he was wounded. So he had a name among the three;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and being higher in rank than any of the three, he became their chief, though he did not come up to those three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Banaias also, son of Jodae, of Kabeseel, was a man renowned for exploits. He smote the two sons of Ariel the Moabite. He went down also, and smote a lion in the midst of the pit on a snowy day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He smote also an Egyptian, a man of great stature. Though the Egyptian had in his hand a spear like the side of a ladder, he went down to him with a staff, and wresting the spear out of the hand of the Egyptian, he killed him with his own spear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>These exploits Banaias son of Jodae performed, and had a name among the three worthies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He was higher in rank than any of the three, though he did not come up to the three. And David appointed him Auditor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>These also were the names of king David's worthies, Asael the brother of Joab, he was among the thirty, Eleanon son of Dudi, who married his brother's wife at Bethlehem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Saima the Rudite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Selles the Kelothite; Iras of Iska, the Thekoite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Abiezer the Anothite, another of the sons of the Anothites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Ellon the Aoite; Neere the Netophatite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Esthai son of Riba of Gabaeth; son of Benjamin the Ephrathite; Asmoth the Bardiamite; Emasu the Salabonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Adroi of the brooks;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Gadabiel son of the Arabothite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>son Asan; son Jonathan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Samnan the Aradite; Amnan son of Arai the Saraouite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Aliphaleth son of Asbites; son of the Machachite; Eliab son of Achitophel the Gelonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Asarai the Karmelite, of Ouraioerchi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Gaal son of Nathana; Poludunameos son of Galaaddi; Elie the Ammonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Gelore the Bethorite, the armour bearer of Joab, son of Saruia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Iras the Etherite; Gerab the Ethinite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Ourias the Chettite. They were thirty seven in all.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, when one among them over persuaded David, saying, Go number Israel and Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When the king said to Joab, the captain general of his army, who was with him, Go, I pray thee through all the tribes of Israel and Juda, from Dan to Bersabee, and review the people, and let me know the number of them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Joab said to the king, The Lord God add to the people, how many soever they be, a hundred fold; and may the eyes of my lord the king see it! But why doth my lord the king set his mind upon this?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But the word of the king prevailed against Joab, and the officers of the army. So Joab and the chiefs of the army before the king, went out to review the people, Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And they crossed the Jordan, and encamped at Aroer on the right of the city, in the valley of Gad and Eliezer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then they went to Galaad, and to the land of Thabason, which is Adasai, and came to Danidan and Oudan; and having gone round Sidon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and come to Mapsar of Tyre, and to all the cities of the Evites, and the Chananites, they came to the south of Juda to Bersabee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So when they had gone round through all the land, they came to Jerusalem, at the end of nine months and twenty days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And Joab laid before the king the amount of the review of the people. And that of Israel was eight hundred thousand fighting men: and the men of Juda were five hundred thousand warriors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And David's heart smote him after this numbering of the people: and David said to the Lord, I have sinned greatly in what I have done. Now therefore, Lord, forgive, I beseech thee, the iniquity of thy servant, for I have acted very foolishly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when David arose in the morning, a word of the Lord came to the prophet Gad, the seer, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Go and speak to David, and say, Thus saith the Lord, Three things I am ready to bring upon thee, chuse therefore for thyself one of them, that I may do it to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So Gad went to David, and delivered the message, and said, Chuse what shall be done to thee. Shall three years of famine come on all thy land? Or wilt thou flee three months before thine enemies while they pursue thee? Or shall there be three days of pestilence in thy land? Now therefore consider; and see what answer I shall make to him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thereupon David said to Gad, I am in great straits on every side. Pray let me fall into the hands of the Lord; for very many and great are his mercies. But let me not fall into the hands of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now when David chose for himself the pestilence, it was the time of the wheat harvest. And the Lord sent a pestilence through Israel, from the morning till the hour of dining. And the slaughter began among the people, and there died of the people from Dan to Bersabee, seventy thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But when the angel of God stretched forth his hand against Jerusalem to destroy it, the Lord was moved with compassion at the calamity, and said to the angel who was making havock among the people, It is enough. Stay thy hand. Now the angel of the Lord was by the threshing floor of Orna the Jebusite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when David saw the angel who was smiting the people, he addressed the Lord, and said, Behold here am I who have transgressed! But as for this flock, what have they done? Let thy hand, I pray thee, be upon me, and upon my father's house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then Gad came to David that day, and said to him, Go up and erect an altar for the Lord, on the threshing floor of Orna the Jebusite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So David went up according to the word of Gad, as the Lord had commanded him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when Orna looked out, and saw the king and his servants coming up to him, he went out and bowed down to the king, with his face to the ground,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and said, Why is my lord the king come to his servant? And David said, To purchase of thee this threshing floor to build an altar to the Lord, that the slaughter among the people may be stayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Orna said to David, Let my lord the king take, and offer to the Lord what is agreeable to him. Behold here are cattle for a whole burnt offering, and the carts and the yokes of the cattle for fuel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>All these Orna hath given to the king. And may the Lord thy God, said Orna addressing the king, bless thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But the king said to Orna, No. Let me only purchase them of thee for their full value; for I cannot offer to the Lord my God a whole burnt offering which costeth me nothing. So David purchased the threshing floor, and the cattle, for fifty shekels of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And David built there an altar to the Lord, and offered whole burnt offerings and peace offerings. Now Solomon afterwards enlarged this altar; for at first it was small. Thus the Lord was entreated for the land, and the slaughter was stopped from Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>