<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Adam, Seth, Enos</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and Kainan, Maleleel, Jared,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Enoch, Mathusala, Lamech,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Noe: The sons of Noe, Sem, Cham, Japheth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The sons of Japheth Gamer, Magog, Madaim, Jovan, Elisa, Thobel, Mosoch and Thiras.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the sons of Gamer, Aschanaz and Riphath and Thorgama.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the sons of Jovan, Elisa and Tharsis, the Kitians and the Rhodians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the sons of Cham, Chus and Mesraim, Thud and Chanaan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the sons of Chus; Saba and Evila and Sabatha and Regma and Sebethacha; and the sons of Regma, Saba and Dadan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Chus also begot Nebrod, who began to be a giant hunter on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The sons of Sent, Ailam and Assur</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Arphaxad, Sala,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Eber, Phaleg, Ragan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Seruch, Nachor, Tharra,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And the sons of Abraham; Isaak and Ismael.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And these are their genealogies. Ismael the first born: Nabaioth and Kedar, Nabdeel, Massam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Masma, Iduma, Masse, Chondan, Thaiman,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Jettur, Naphes, Kedma. These were the sons of Ismael.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>With regard to the children of Chettura the concubine of Abraham; she bore to him, Zembram, Jexan, Madiam, Madam, Sobak, Soe. And the children of Jexan were Daidan and Sabai.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the children of Madiam were Gopher and Opher and Enoch and Abida and Eldada. All these were children of Chettura.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Moreover Abraham begot Isaak. And the sons of Isaak were Jacob and Esau.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the sons of Esau were, Eliphaz and Hague! and Jeul and Jeglom and Kore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And the sons of Eliphaz were Thaiman and Omar, Sophar and Gotham and Kenez and Thamna and Amelek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And the sons of Raquel, were Naches, Zare, Some and Mose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>The sons of Seir, Lotan, Sobal, Sebegon, Ana, Deson, Osar and Dison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And the sons of Lotan were Chorri and Aiman and the sister of Lotan, Thamna.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>The sons of Sobal were Alon, Machanath, Taibel, Sophi and Onan. And the sons of Sebegon were Aith and Sonan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>the sons of Sonan, Daison; and the sons of Daison, Emeron and Asebon and Jethram and Charran.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And the sons of Osar, were Balaam and Zukam and Akan. The sons of Disan were Os and Aran.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Now these were their kings: Balak son of Beor, the name of whose city was Dennaba.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And when Balak died Jobab, son of Zara of Bosorra, reigned in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And when Jobab died, Asom of the land of the Thaimanites reigned in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And when Asom died, Adad son of Barad who smote Madiam in the plain of Moab reigned in his stead; and the name of his city was Gethaim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And when Adad died, Sebla of Masekka reigned in his stead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And when Sebla died, Saul of Roboth which is by the river reigned in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>And when Saul died, Balaennor son of Achobar, reigned in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>And when Balaennor died, Adad son of Barad reigned in his stead; and the name of his city was Phogor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>The emirs of Edom were, emir Thamna, emir Golada, emir Jether,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>emir Elibamas, emir Elas, emir Phinon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>emir Kenez, emir Thaiman, emir Babsar, emir Magediel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>emir Zaphoin. These were the emirs of Edom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>These are the names of the sons Israel, Reuben, Symeon, Levi, Juda, Issachar, Zabulon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Dan, Joseph, Benjamin, Nephthaleim, Gad, Aser.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The sons of Juda. Er, Aunan, Selom. These three he had by a daughter of Sava, the Chananite. Now Er the first born of Juda was wicked in the sight of the Lord, and he slew him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Thamar his daughter in law bore to him Phares and Zara. All the sons of Juda were five.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The sons of Phares, were Esrom and Jemuel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the sons of Zara were Zambri and Aitham and Amuan and Chalchal and Darad, five in all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the sons of Charmi, Achar the troubler of Israel, who transgressed so as to be anathematised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the sons of Aitham, Azarias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the sons of Esrom who were born to him were Jerameel and Aram and Chaleb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Aram begot Aminadab, and Aminadab begot Naasson, the chief of the house of Juda;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Naasson begot Salmon and Salmon begot Boaz;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and Boaz begot Obed; and Obed begot Jessai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and Jessai begot Eliab his first born. Aminadab was his second son; Samaa his third;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Nathanial his fourth; Zebdai his fifth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Asam his sixth; David his seventh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And their sisters were Saruia and Abigaia. And the sons of Saruia were Abisa and Joab and Asael, three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Abigaia was the mother of Amessai; and the father of Amessai was Jothor, the Ismaelite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And Chaleb son of Esrom took to wife Gazuba, in addition to Jerioth, and these were her children, Jasar and Subab and Ardon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when Gazuba died Chaleb took to him Epbrath, who bore to him Or;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Or begot Onri; and Ouri begot Beseleel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And after that Esron went in to the daughter of Machir the father of Galaad and took her when he was sixty five years of age; and she bore to him Seruch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And Seruch begot Jair. He had twenty three cities in the land of Galaad,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and he took Gedsour and Aram, the villages of Jair which belonged to them, Kanath and the villages thereof, sixty cities. All these belonged to the children of Machir, the father of Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And after Esron died Chaleb went to Ephratha, and Esron's wife Abia bore to him Escho, the father of Thekoe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now these were the sons of Jarameel, the first born of Esron, Ram his first born, and Baana and Aram, and Asan his brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And Jerameel had another wife whose name was Atara. She was the mother of Ozom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the sons of Ram, the first born of Jerameel were Maas and Jamin and Akor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And the sons of Ozom were Samai and Jadae. And the sons of Samai, Nadab and Abisur;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and the name of Abisur's wife was Abichaia and she bore to him Achabar and Moel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the sons of Nadab were Salad and Apphain; and Salad died without issue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And the sons of Apphain were Isemiel; and the sons of Isemiel, Sosan; and the sons of Sosan, Dadai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and the sons of Dadai, Achisamas, Jether, Jonathan; and Jether died without issue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the sons of Jonathan were Phaleth and Osam. These were the Jerameelites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Now Sosan had no sons, but daughters only. And Sosan had an Egyptian servant whose name was Jochal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>To this Egyptian servant, Sosan gave his daughter for a wife and she bore to him Ethi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And Ethi begot Nathan; and Nathan begot Zabed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Zabed begot Aphamel; and Aphamel begot Obed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and Obed begot Jehu; and Jehu begot Azarias;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and Azarias begot Chelles; and Chelles begot Eleasa;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and Eleasa begot Sosomai; and Sosomai begot Salum;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>and Salum begot Jechemias; and Jechemias begot Elisama; and Elisama begot Ismael.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And the sons of Chaleb the brother of Jeremeel were Marisa his first born who was the father of Ziph. And the children of father Marisa were Chebron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And the sons of Chebron were Kore and Thapphus and Rekom and Samaa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And Samaa begot Raem the father of Jeklan; and Jeklan begot Samai:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And Maon was his son; and Maon was the father of Baithsur.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Moreover Gaipha the concubine of Chaleb bore Aram and Mosa and Gesue,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>from whom descended the sons of Addai, Ragem and Jotham and Sogar and Phalek and Gaipha and Sagae.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And Mocha another concubine of Chaleb bore Saber and Tharam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>She bore also Sagae the father of Madmena, and Saou the father of Machabena and the father of Gaibel. And Chaleb's daughter was Ascha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>These were children of Chaleb; the children of Or his first born by Ephratha, Sobal the father of Kariathiarim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Solomon the father of Baitha, Lammon the father of Baithalaem, and Arim the father of Bethgedor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>And Sobal the father of Kariathiarim had other sons namely Araa and Aisi and Ammanith</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>and Oumasphae, Poleisjair, Aithalim, Miphithim and Hesamathim and Hemasaraim, from whom branched out the Sarathaites and the Esthamites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>And the children of Solomon were Bethalaim the Netophatite, Ataroth of the house of Joab and the half of the Malathites, the Esarites</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>the families of the scribes who dwelt at Jabis; the Thargathites and Samathites and Sochathites. These comprehended under the name of Kinites were descended from Aimath the father of the house of Rechab.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the sons of David who were born to him at Chebron, Amnon his first born by Achinaam the Jezraelitess; Damniel his second son by Abigaia the Karmelitess;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Abessalom his third by Macha a daughter of Tholmai king of Gedsur; Adonia his fourth by Aggith;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>his fifth, Saphatia the son of Abital;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>his sixth, Jethraam by his wife Agla. These six sons were born to him in Chebron; for he reigned there seven years and six months. And in Jerusalem he reigned thirty three years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now these were the sons born to him in Jerusalem, Samaa, Sobab, Nathan and Solomon. (These four were by Bersabee the daughter of Amiel,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Ebaar and Elisa and Eliphaleth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and Nagai and Naphek and Japhie</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and Elisama and Eliada and Eliphala, nine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>All sons of David besides the sons of the concubines and Themar their sister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The sons of Solomon Roboam; Abia his son, Asa his son, Josaphat his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Joram his son, Ochosias his son, Joas his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Amasias his son, Azarias his son; Joatham his son;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Achaz his son; Ezekias his son; Manasses his son;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Amon his son; Josias his son;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and the sons of Josias were Joanan his first born, his second Joakim, his third Sedekias, his fourth Salum;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and the sons of Joakim were Jechonias his son, Sedekias his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and the sons of Jechonias were Asir, Salathiel his son;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Melchiram and Phadaias and Sanesar and Jekemia and Osamath and Nabadias:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the sons of Phadaias were Zorobabel and Semei. And the sons of Zorobabel were Mesollam and Anania and Salomethi their sister</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Asube and Ool and Barachia and Asadia and Asobed, five.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the sons of Anania were Phalettia and Jesias his son; Raphal his son; Orna his son; Abdia his son; Sechenias his son;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the son of Sechenias was Samaia; and the sons of Samaia, Chattus and Joel and Berri and Noadia and Saphath, six.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the sons of Noadia were Elithenan and Ezekias and Ezrikam, three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And the sons of Elithenan were Odolia and Eliasebon and Phadaia and Akub and Joanan and Dalaaia and Anan, seven.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the sons of Juda were Phares and Esrom, Charmi and Or, Soubal</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and Rada his son. And Soubal begot Jeth; and Jeth begot Achimas and Laad. These are the families of the Arathites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And these are the sons of Aitam; Jezrael and Jesman and Jebdas, and the name of their sister was Eselebbon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and Phanuel the father of Geddor; and Jaser the father of Osan. These were the sons of Or who was the first born of Ephratba and the father of Baithalaem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Asur also the father of Thekoe had two wives Aoda and Thoada;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Aoda bore to him Ochaia and Ephal and Thaiman and Aasther. All these were the children of Aoda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the children of Thoada were Sereth and Saar and Esthanam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And Koe begot Enob and Sabatha. And these are the families of brother Rechab son of Jarin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Igabes indeed was the most honourable of his brethren. Now his mother had called his name Igabes, saying, I have brought him forth Osgabes with sorrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Igabes called on the God of Israel, and said, If thou wilt bless me with blessings and enlarge my borders, let thy hand be with me, and give me knowledge that I may not debase myself. Accordingly God gave him all that he asked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Chaleb the father of Ascha begot Machir. He was the father of Assathon</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and begot Bethraian and Bessea and Thaiman the father of Poleosnaas the brother of Eselom the Kenezite. These were men of Rechab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the sons of Kenez were Gothoniel and Saraia. And the sons of Gothoniel, Athath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And Manathi begot Gophera. And Saraia begot Jobab the father of the Ageaddairites, for they were carpenters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the sons of Chaleb son of Jephonne were, Er, Ada and Noom. And the sons of Ada, Kenez,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and the sons of Aleel, Zib and Zepha and Thiria and Eserel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the sons of Esri, Jether, Morad and Apher and Jamon. And Jether begot Maron and Semei and Jesba the father of Esthaimon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And his wife Adia bore Jared the father of Gedor and Aber the father of Sochon and Chetiel the father of Zamon. And these were the sons of Betthia a daughter of Pharao whom Morad took,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the sons of his wife Iduia the sister of Nachaim the father of Keila, Garmi and Esthaimon, Nochathi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the sons of Semon were Amnon and Ana, son Phana and Inon. And the sons of Sei were Zoan and the Zoabites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The sons of Selom son of Juda were Er, the father of Lechab, and Laada father of Marisa. And the genealogies of the subordinate families of Ephrathabak, belonged to the house of Esoba,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>namely Joakim and the men of Chozeba, and Joas and Saraph who dwelt in Moab. Now Abederim Athukiim led them away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>These were potters who dwelt at Ataim and Gadira with the king, and having risen to eminence in his reign they settled there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The sons of Symeon were Namuel and Jamin, Jarib, Zares, Saul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Salem his son; Mabasam his son; Masma his son;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Amuel his son; Zakehur his son; Semei his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Semei had sixteen sons and six daughters; but their brethren had not many children; nor did all their families abound like the children of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now they dwelt in Bersabee and Molada, and in Esersaul</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and in Balaa, and in Aisem and in Tholad,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and in Bathuel and in Erma, and in Sikelag,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and in Baithmarimoth and Hemisuseosin, and the house of Baruseorim. These were their cities till the reign of king David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the folds for their cattle were Aitan and En, Remnon and Thokka, and Aisar, five cities</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>with all their folding places around these cities even to Baal. This was their possession and this their distribution into communities,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>including Mosabab and Jemoloch, and Josia son of Amassia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and Joel and Jehu, son Asabia, son Saran, son Asiel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and Elionai and Jokaba, and Jasuia and Asaia, and Jediel and Ismael, and Banaias</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Zuza son of Saphai, son of Alon, son of Jedia, son of Semri, son of Samaias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>These were they who having branched out under the names of chiefs in their families and in their patriarchal houses, were increased to a multitude</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and spread themselves in search of pastures for their cattle, till they came to Gerara to the east of Gai, where they found pastures,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>extensive and good, for the land before them was spacious and there was peace and tranquillity. Because they who dwelt there before them were of the children of Cham,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>therefore those above mentioned came in the days of Ezekias king of Juda, and smote their families, even the Minaians whom they found there, and utterly destroyed them even to this day, and dwelt in their stead, because there were pastures there for their cattle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And from among these five hundred of the Symeonites with Phalaettia and Noadia, and Raphaia and Oziel sons of Jessi, their chiefs, went to Mount Seir</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>and smote the remains of Amelek who had been left even to this time.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the sons of Reuben the first born of Israel; for he was the first born, but when he went up to his father's bed, his father gave his birth right to his son Joseph as the son of Israel: yet in the genealogy he did not attain the right of primogeniture;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for Juda being mighty in power prevailed over his brethren to have the Ruler appointed out of him, though the blessing was Joseph's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now the sons of Reuben, the first born of Israel, were Enoch and Phallus, Asrom and Charmi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The sons of Joel, Semei and Bania, his son. And the sons of Goug son of Semei,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Micha his son; Recha his son; Joel his son;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Beel his son, whom Thalgathphallasar, king of Assyria, carried away captive. He was the chief of the Reubenites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And his brethren in his patriarchal family in their classes according to their genealogies, were the chief Joel and Zacharias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and Balek Son Azouz, Son Sama, Son Joel. Now the Reubenites dwelt at Aroer, and at Nabau and Beelmasson,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and eastward to the edge of the wilderness which bordereth on the river Euphrates; for they had many cattle in the land of Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And in the days of Saul they made war on their neighbours; and all those who dwelt in tents on the east of Galaad fell by their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The children of Gad dwelt along side of them in the land of Basan, even to Sela;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Joel was the first born and Sapham the second, and Janin the muster master in Basan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And their brethren according to the houses of their patriarchal families were, Michael, Mosollam and Sebe, and Joree and Joachan, and Zue and Obed, seven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>These were the sons of Abichaia son of Ouri, son of Idai, son of Galaad, son of Michael, son of Jesai, son of Jeddai, son of Buz,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>brother's son of Abdiel, son of Gouni. He was the chief of the patriarchal house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They dwelt in Galaad, in Basan and in their towns, and occupied all the borders of Saron to the outlet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Of all these an account was taken in the days of Joatham king of Juda, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The Reubenites and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses who were fit for war, men wielding shields and swords and bending the bow and disciplined for battle, were forty four thousand seven hundred and sixty who marched out in array.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When they were at war with the Agarenians and the Itureans, and the Naphaisaians and the Nadabeans,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>they prevailed over them. And the Agarenians with all their tents, were delivered into their hands. For in the battle they cried to God and he hearkened to them, because they trusted in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So they took all their substance, five thousand camels, two hundred and fifty thousand sheep, two thousand asses, and a hundred thousand prisoners,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and many were slain; for the battle was from God. And they dwelt in their stead till the captivity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now the half of the tribe of Manasses inhabited, from Basan to Baal, Ermon and Sanir and Mount Aermon. And on Libanus they were very numerous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And these were the leaders of the house of their families, Opher and Sei, and Eliel and Jeremia, and Oduia and Jediel, men mighty in power, men of renown, chiefs of the houses of their families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But when they revolted from the God of their fathers and went a whoring after the gods of the people of the land, whom God had removed from before them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Phaloch king of Assur, and the spirit of Thaglaphalassar king of Assur, and he removed Reuben and Gad, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, and carried them to Chaach and Chabor, and to the river of Gozan, where they are to this day.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The sons of Levi were Gerson, Kaath and Merari.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the sons of Kaath, Ambram and Issaar, Chebron and Oziel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the children of Ambram were Aaron and Moses and Mariam. And the sons of Aaron, Nadab and Abiud, Eleazar and Ithamar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Eleazar begot Phineas; and Phineas begot Abisu;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Abisu begot Bokki, and Bokki begot Ozi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Ozi begot Zaraia; and Zaraia begot Mariel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Mariel begot Amaria; and Amaria begot Achitob;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Achitob begot Sadok; and Sadok begot Achimaas;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Achimaas begot Azarias; and Azarias begot Joanan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Joanan begot Azarias who officiated as priest in the house which Solomon built in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Azarias begot Amaria, and Amaria begot Achitob;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and Achitob begot Sadok; and Sadok begot Achimaas; and Achimaas begot Azarias; and Azarias begot Amarias; and Amarias begot Sadok; and Sadok begot Salom;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and Salom begot Chelkias; and Chelkias begot Azarias;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and Azarias begot Saraias; and Saraias begot Josadak;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and Josadak went into captivity with Juda and Jerusalem by the hand of Nabuchodonosar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The sons of Levi were Gerson, Kaath and Merari.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now these are the names of the sons of Gerson, Lobeni and Semei.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The sons of Kaath were Ambram and Issaar, Chebron and Oziel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The sons of Merari were Mooli and Musi. And these were the families of the Levites according to their families,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>To Gerson by Lobeni belonged Jeth his son, Zammath his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Joab his son, Addi his son, Zara his son, Jethri his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The sons of Kaath were Aminadab his son, Kore his son, Aser his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Elkana his son, Abisaph his son, Aser his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Thaath his son, Ouriel his son, Ozia his son, Saul his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And the sons of Elkana, Amessi and Achimoth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Elkana his son, Suphi his son, Kainaath his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Eliab his son, Jeroboam his son, Elkana his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>the sons of Samuel; the first born Sani and Abia</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The sons of Merari were Mooli, Lobeni his son, Semei his son, Oza his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Samaa his son, Aggia his son, Asaias his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Now these are they whom David set over the bands of singers in the house of the Lord, when the ark was at rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And they ministered before the tabernacle of the testimony with musical instruments, until Solomon built the house of the Lord in Jerusalem, and they attended their service according to their order,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and these are they who attended with their sons; Of the sons of Kaath, Aiman, who sung to the psaltery, the son of Joel, son of Samuel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>son of Elkana, son of Jeroboam, son of Eliel, son of Thou,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>son of Suph, son of Elkana, son of Maath, son of Amathi,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>son of Elkana, son of Joel, son of Azarias, son of Saphanias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>son of Thaath, son of Aser, son of Abiasaph, son of Kore,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>son of Issaar, son of Kaath, son of Levi, son of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and his brother Asaph who stood on his right; Asaph was the son of Barachias son of Samaa,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>son of Michael, son of Baasia, son of Melchia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>son of Athani, son of Zaaras,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>son of Adai, son of Aitham, son of Zammam, son of Semei,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>son of Jeth, son of Gersom, son of Levi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And the sons of Merari, their brethren who were on their left, were Aitham son of Kisa, son of Abai, son of Maloch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>son of Asebi,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>son of Amessia, son of Bani, son of Semer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>son of Mooli, son of Musi, son of Merari, son of Levi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Now their brethren the Levites according to the houses of their families, were appointed to all the work of the service of the tabernacle of the house of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>And Aaron and his sons, who were to burn incense on the altar of whole burnt offerings and on the altar of incense offerings, were for all the service of the Holy of Holies, and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God commanded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>And these were the sons of Aaron, Eleazar his son, Phineas his son, Abisu his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Bokki his son, Ozi his son, Saraia his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Mariel his son, Amaria his son, Achitob his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Sadok his son, Achimaas his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Now these were their dwelling places with their towns and their borders. To the sons of Aaron to their family as Kaathites, because the lot fell to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>therefore they gave them Chebron in the land of Juda with its suburbs round about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>But the fields belonging to the city and the villages thereof had been given to Chaleb son of Jephonne;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>to the sons of Aaron they gave these cities; of the refuge cities, Chebron and Lobna with its suburbs, and Salna with its suburbs, and Esthamo with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>and Jethar, with its suburbs, and Dabir with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>and Asan with its suburbs, and Baithsamus with its suburbs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>and from the tribe of Benjamin, Gabai with its suburbs, and Galemath with its suburbs, and Anathoth with its suburbs. All their cities were thirteen according to their families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>And to the rest of the Kaathites they gave by lot out of the tribe consisting of two communities, namely, out of Ephraim and the half of the tribe of Manasses, ten cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>And to the Gersonites according to their families, they gave out of the tribe of Issachar, out of the tribe of Aser, out of the tribe of Nephthaleim, and out of the tribe of Manasses in Basan, thirteen cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>And to the Merarites according to their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, out of the tribe of Gad, out of the tribe of Zabulon, twelve cities by lot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>Now when the Israelites gave the Levites the cities and their suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>and had given by lot out of the tribe of Juda and out of the tribe of Symeon and out of the tribe of Benjamin, the cities which are mentioned by name,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>then the families of the sons of Kaath got these cities also of their borders. Out of the tribe of Ephraim</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>they gave them of the cities of refuge, Sychem and its suburbs on mount Ephraim; and Gazer with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>and Jekman with its suburbs, and Baithoron with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>and Ailon with its suburbs, and Gethremmon with its suburbs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>and out of the half tribe of Manasses, Anar with its suburbs, and Jemblaan with its suburbs for the rest of the Kaathites according to their families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>And to the Gersonites they gave from the families of the half tribe of Manasses Golan of Basan with its suburbs. and Aseroth with its suburbs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>and out of the tribe of Issachar, Kedes with its suburbs, and Deberi with its suburbs, and Dabor with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="73">
      <content>and Ramoth with its suburbs, and Ainan with its suburbs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="74">
      <content>and out of the tribe of Aser, Maasal with its suburbs, and Abdou with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="75">
      <content>and Akak with its suburbs, and Rohob with its suburbs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="76">
      <content>And out of the tribe of Nephthaleim, Kedes in Galilee with its suburbs, and Chamoth with its suburbs, and Kariathaim with its suburbs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="77">
      <content>And to the Merarites, the remaining Levites, they gave out of the tribe of Zabulon, Remmon with its suburbs, and Thabor with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="78">
      <content>and on the western bank of the Jordan, Jericho; and out of the tribe of Reuben, Bosor in the wilderness with its suburbs, and Jasa with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="79">
      <content>and Kadmoth with its suburbs, and Maephla with its suburbs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="80">
      <content>and out of the tribe of Gad, Rammoth Galaad with its suburbs, and Manaim with its suburbs,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="81">
      <content>and Esebon with its suburbs, and Jazer with its suburbs.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The sons of Issachar were Thola and Phua and Jasub and Semeron, four.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the sons of Thola were Ozi, Raphaia and Jeriel and Jamai and Jemason and Samuel, chiefs of the houses of the families of Thola, mighty in power in their respective communities. Their number in the days of David was twenty two thousand six hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the sons of Ozi, Jezraia; and the sons of Jezraia, Michael, Abdiu and Joel and Jesia, five, all chiefs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And under them in their respective communities according to the houses of their families, the able bodied men fit for array in battle, were thirty six thousand; for they had many wives and children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And their brethren comprehending all the families of Issachar, the able bodied men fit for battle were eighty seven thousand. This was the number of them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The sons of Benjamin were Bale and Bachir and Jediel, three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the sons of Bale were Esebon and Ozi and Oziel and Jerimuth and Ouri, five, chiefs of houses of families mighty in power, and their number was twenty two thousand and thirty four.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the sons of Bachir were Zemira and Joas and Eliezar and Elithenan and Amaria and Jerimuth and Abiud and Anathoth and Eleemeth, all these were sons of Bachir,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and their number according to their several communities, they being chiefs of the houses of their patriarchal families mighty in power, were twenty thousand two hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the sons of Jediel were Balaan, and the sons of Balaan, Jaus and Benjamin and Aoth and Chanana and Zaithan and Tharsi and Achisaar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>All these sons of Jediel being chiefs of their families mighty in power, were seventeen thousand two hundred who went out in the army to war,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>including Sapphin and Apphin and the sons of Or, Asom, and his son Aor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the sons of Nephthaleim were Jasiel, Goni and Aser and Sellum his son and Balam his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the sons of Manasses were Esriel whom his concubine Syra bore to him. She bore to him also Machir the father of Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Machir took to wife a sister of Apphin and a sister of Sapphin. The sister of the one was named Moocha, and the sister of the other Sapphaad. And to him by Sapphaad daughters only were born;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>but Moocha the wife of Machir bore a son and called his name Phares, and his brother's name was Sourus. His sons were Oulam and Rokon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the sons of Oulam, Badam. These were of the house of Galaad son of Machir son of Manasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And his sister Malecheth bore Isud and Abiezer and Maela.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the sons of Semira were Aim and Sychem and Lakim and Anian.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the sons of Ephraim were Sothalath and Barad his son and Thaath his son, Elada his son, Saath his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and Zabad his son, Sothole his son; and Aser and Elead whom the men of Geth who were born in this land slew, because they went down to take their cattle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Whereupon Ephraim their father mourned many days. But when his brethren came to comfort him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>he went in unto his wife, and she conceived and bore him a son, and he called his name Beria, Because, said he, he was born during the calamities in my house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And his daughter was Saraa, who formed a family among them, who were left, and it built the upper and lower Baithoron. And the sons of Ozan were Seera</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and Raphe his son, Saraph and Thaleas his sons, Thaen his son</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and by his son Laadon, son Amiud, son Elisamai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>son Nun, son Jesue were his sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now their possession and their dwelling was Baithel and its villages, eastward Nearan, and westward Gazer and its villages, and Sychem with its villages even to Gaza,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and the villages thereof, and in the borders of the children of Manasses, Bethsan and its villages, Thanach and its villages, Mageddo and its villages, Dor and its villages. In this dwelt the children of Joseph son of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The sons of Aser were Jemna and Suia and Isai and Beria with Sore their sister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And the sons of Beria were Chaber and Melchiel who was the father of Berthaith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And Chaber begot Japhlet and Samer and Chothan and Sola their sister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the sons of Japhlet were Phasek and Bamael and Asith. These were sons of Japhlet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And the sons of Semmer were Achir and Rooga and Jaba and Aram and Baneelam. His brother's sons were Sopha and Imana and Selles and Amal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the sons of Elam his brother were Sopha and Imana and Selles and Amal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>The sons of Sopha were Sue and Arnaphar and Suda and Barin and Imram</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Basan and Oa and Sama and Salisa and Jethra and Beera.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And the sons of Jether were Jephina and Phaspha and Ara.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And the sons of Ola, Orech, Aniel and Rasia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>All these were sons of Aser, all chiefs of families, chosen men mighty in power, chief leaders. The number of them fit for the array of battle; their number was twenty six thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now Benjamin begot Bale his first born and Asbel his second son and Ara his third, Noa his fourth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and Rapha his, fifth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the sons of Bale were Adir and Gera and Abiud</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and Abessue and Noama and Achia</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and Gera and Sephupham and Ouram.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>These are sons of Aod; these are the heads of the families who dwelt in Gabae, and who removed to Machanathi,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>namely Nooma and Achia and Gera who is called Jeglaam and begot Aza and Jachicho.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And Saarin begot in the plain of Maob (after he had put away Osin and Baada his wife,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>he had by his wife Ada) Jolab and Sabia and Misa and Melchas</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and Jebus and Zabia and Marina. These were chiefs of families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now by Osin he had Abitol and Alphaal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the sons of Alphaal were Obed, Misaal, Semmer (who built Onan and Lod and the villages thereof)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and Beria and Sama. These were the chiefs of the families who inhabited Ailam after they had driven out the inhabitants of Geth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>namely his brother Sosek and Arimoth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and Zabodia and Ored and Eder</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Michael and Jespha and Joda sons of Beria;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and Zabadia and Mosollam and Azaki and Abar</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and Isamari and Jezlias and Jobab sons of Elphaal:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and Jakim and Zachri and Zabdi</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Elionai and Salathi</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and Eleeli and Adaia and Baraia and Samarath sons of Samath;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and Jesphan and Obed and Eleel</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and Abdon and Zechri and Anan</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Anania and Ambri and Ailam and Anathoth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and Jathin and Jephadias and Phanuel sons of Sosek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And Samsari and Saarias and Gotholia</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and Jarasia and Eria and Zechri son of Iroam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>These were chiefs of their respective families. These chiefs dwelt in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And in Gabaon dwelt father Gabaon, and his wife's name was Maacha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and her first born son was Abdon, and Sur and Kis and Baal and Nadab and Ner</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and Gedur and his brother and Zakckur and Makeloth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and Makeloth begot Samaa. These also dwelt over against their brethren in Jerusalem, with their brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And Ner begot Kis; and Kis begot Saul, and Saul begot Jonathan and Melchisue and Aminadab and Asabal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And Meribaal was a son of Jonathan, and Meribaal begot Micha;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and the sons of Micha, were Phithon and Melach and Tharach and Achaz.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And Achaz begot Jada, and Jada begot Salaimath and Asmoth and Zambri. And Zambri begot Maisa</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Maisa begot Baana. Raphaia was his son, Elasa his son, Esel his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And Esel had six sons, and these are their names, Ezrikam the first born, and Ismael and Saraia and Abdia and Anan and Asa. All these were sons of Esel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And the sons of Asel his brother were Ailam his first born, and Jas his second, and Eliphalet, his third.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And the sons of Ailam. mighty men for war; bending the bow, and abounding in sons and sons of sons, were a hundred and fifty. All these were of the sons of Benjamin.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>With respect to all Israel, this is a brief account of them. Now these are they who are enrolled in the book of the kings of Israel and Juda, with them who were carried away to Babylon, for their iniquities,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and who had formerly dwelt in their possessions in the cities of Israel, including the priests, the Levites and the persons given them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>(for in Jerusalem there dwelt some of the children of Juda, and some of the children of Benjamin, and some of the children of Ephraim, and Manasses;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Gnothi son of Samiud, son of Amri, son of Ambraim, son of Bouni, son of the children of Phares, son of Juda;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and of the Selonites, Asaia the first born and his sons;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and of the sons of Zara, Jeel and their brethren, six hundred and ninety.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And of the sons of Benjamin, Salom son of Mosollam, son of Oduia, son of Asinu;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and Jemnaa, son of Jeroboam, and Elo, who were sons of Osi, son of Machir; and Mosollam, son of Saphatia, son of Raguel, son of Jemnai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>with their brethren, according to their respective families, nine hundred and fifty six. All these were heads of families, according to the houses of their families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And of the priests, Jodae and Joarim and Jachin</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Azaria son of Chelkias, son of Mosollam, son of Sadok, son of Maraioth, son of Achitob, ruler of the house of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and Adaia, son of Iraam, son of Phaschor, son of Melchia; and Maasia, son of Adiel, son of Ezira, son of Mosollam, son of Maselmoth, son of Emmer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and their brethren, chiefs of houses of their families, a thousand seven hundred and sixty, mighty in power for the work of the service of the house of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And of the Levites, Samaia son of Asob, son of Ezrikam, son of Asabia, of the sons of Merari;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and Bakbachar and Ares and Galaal and Matthanias, son of Micha, son of Zechri, son of Asaph;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Abdia, son of Samia, son of Galaal son of Idithun; and Barachia, son of Ossa, son of Elkana, who dwelt in the villages of Notephati;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the keepers of the gates, Salom, Akum, Telmon and Diman and their brethren, Salom being at this time, the chief</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>at the king's gate, namely the eastern gate, of the camp of the Levites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and Sellum son of Kore, son of Abiasaph, son of Kore. Now his brethren, for the house of his father, namely the Korites, were over the works of the service keeping the watches of the tabernacle, and their fathers were over the camp of the Lord guarding the entrance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Phineas son of Eleazar was the ruler over them, and these were his assistants;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Zacharias son of Mosollomi, keeper of the door of the tabernacle of the testimony,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>all the chosen keepers of the gates, were two hundred and twelve. With respect to the distribution of these in their respective courts, David and Samuel the seer appointed them to their office,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and they and their sons had the charge of the gates in the house of the Lord, and in the house of the tabernacle, to keep watch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The gates were according to the four winds, east, west, north, and south.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And their brethren in the villages were to relieve them, every seven days from time to time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Because the four chiefs had the charge of the gates, and the Levites who were over the store houses, and over the treasures of the house of God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>encamp near; because the watch rested on them, therefore they had the charge of the keys to open every morning, the doors of the sanctuary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now some of the Levites were over the implements of the service, for they were to be brought in and carried out by tale.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So some were over the implements, and over all the holy vessels, and over the fine flour, the wine and the oil, the frankincense and the spices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And of the sons of the priests, some were confectioners and prepared the spices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And of the Levites, Matthathias, who was the first born of Salom the Korite, he had the charge of the works of the sacrifice prepared in the pan of the high priest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and Banaias the Kaathite, who was of their brethren, was over the shew bread, to set it in order every sabbath;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and the singers, the chiefs of those families of the Levites, who were distributed into daily classes; because the chiefs of these families of the Levites were employed in this service day and night,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>therefore they dwelt in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now at Gabaon dwelt father Gabaon, Jeel, whose wife's name was Mocha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and his son, the first born, Abdon; and Sour and Kis and Baal and Ner and Nadab</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Gedour and a brother, and Zakchur and Makeloth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and Makeloth begot Samaa. And these among their brethren dwelt at Jerusalem, among their brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And Ner begot Kis, and Kis begot Saul, and Saul begot Jonathan, and Melchisue and Aminadab and Asabal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and the son of Jonathan, was Meribaal and Meribaal begot Micha,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>and the sons of Micha, Phithon and Malach and Tharach:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and Achaz begot Jada, and Jada begot Galemith and Gazmoth and Zambri, and Zambri begot Massa,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>and Massa begot Baana, and Raphaia was his son, and Elasa his son, and as for Esel his son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Esel had six sons, and their names were Ezrikam, his first born, and Ismael and Saraia and Abdia, and Anan and Asa. These were sons of Esel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When the Philistines fought against Israel and the Israelites fled before them, and fell down slain on mount Gelbue,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the Philistines pursued close after Saul and after his sons; and when they had slain Jonathan and Aminadab and Melchisue, the sons of Saul, the weight of the battle was directed against Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the archers assailed him with bows, and darts, and wounded him with arrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon Saul said to his armour bearer, Draw thy sword and run me through with it, lest the uncircumcised come and insult me. But his armour bearer would not; for he was greatly terrified. Thereupon Saul took the sword and fell on it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when his armour bearer saw that he was dead, he also fell on his sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thus Saul died with his three sons that day. And all his house died together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when the Israelites who dwelt in the plain, saw that Israel had fled and that Saul and his sons were dead they left their cities and fled, and the Philistines came and dwelt therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now on the next day when the Philistines came to strip the dead, they found Saul and his sons fallen, on mount Gelbue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when they had stripped him, they took his head and his armour, and sent them to the land of the Philistines round about, to proclaim the good news to their idols, and to the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And having deposited his armour in the house of their god, they fixed up his head, in the house of Dagon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But when all the inhabitants of Galaad heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul and Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>all the valiant men of Galaad arose and took the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons, and carried them to Jabis and buried their bones under the oak at Jabis, and fasted seven days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thus died Saul, for his transgressions, which he had committed against God, according to the word of the Lord. Because he did not keep watch; because Saul sought to consult by a belly speaker, therefore Samuel the prophet answered him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>though he sought not the Lord, and the Lord slew him, and transferred the kingdom to David, son of Jessai.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then all Israel came to David to Chebron, and said, Behold we are thy bones and thy flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Even in time past when Saul was king, it was thou who didst lead out and bring in Israel, and the Lord said to thee, Thou shalt feed my people Israel, and thou shalt be ruler over Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So when all the elders were come to the king at Chebron, king David made a covenant with them at Chebron before the Lord, and they anointed him to be king over Israel, according to the word of the Lord by the ministry of Samuel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When the king and his men went to Jerusalem, which is Jebus, the inhabitants of the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the Jebusites who were there said to David, Thou shalt not come here, yet he took the fortress Sion which is now the city of David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He indeed said, Whoever first smiteth the Jebusites, he shall be made chief and general of the army. Upon which Joab son of Saruia went up first and was made chief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And David made his abode in the fortress, for which cause he called it the city of David,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and built the city around it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And David proceeded on advancing in greatness, for the Lord Almighty was with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now these are the chiefs of the mighty men who were with David, who with him prevailed with all Israel during his reign, that he should be, according to the word of the Lord, king over Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And this is the number of David's worthies. Jesebada son of Achaman, the first of thirty. He drew his sword once against three hundred men who were slain at one time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And after him Eleazar son of Dodai the Achochite, who was one of the three worthies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He was with David at Phasodamin when the Philistines were assembled there for battle. And there was a portion of a field full of barley. And when the people fled before the Philistines,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>he stood in the midst of the piece of ground and maintained it and smote the Philistines, and the Lord gave a great victory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>When three of the thirty chiefs went down to the rock to David, to the cave Odollam, at the time when the Philistines were encamped in the giant's vale,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and David was in the fortress and there was a garrison of the Philistines at Bethlehem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>David longed and said, O that some one would give me some water to drink out of the well of Bethlehem which is by the gate!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Upon this the three broke through the camp of the Philistines, and having drawn some water out of the well of Bethlehem by the gate, they took it and came to David. But David would not drink it, but poured it out as a libation to the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and said, God forbid that I should do such a thing! Shall I drink the blood of these men who have jeoparded their lives? Because they had brought it at the hazard of their lives he would not drink it. These things were done by these three worthies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Abisa brother of Joab, who was chief of the three; he drew his sword against three hundred who were slain at one time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He was renowned among the three. Of the three he was higher in rank than two and was their chief, but did not come up to the three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And Banaias son of Jodae, son of a worthy, whose works for Kabasael were many; he smote the two Ariels of Moab. He went down also and smote a lion in the pit in a snowy day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He smote also the Egyptian, a noted man of five cubits high. Though the Egyptian had in his hand a spear like a weaver's beam, Banaias went against him with a staff, and wresting the spear out of the hand of the Egyptian, he slew him with his own spear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>These things Banaias son of Jodae did, and had a name among the three worthies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He was higher in rank than the thirty but did not come up to the three, and David set him over his family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the commanders of the armies were Asael a brother of Joab, Eleanan son of Dodoe of Bethlehem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Samaoth the Arorite; Chelles the Phelonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Or, a son of Ekkis the Thekoite; Abiezer the Anathothite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Sobochai the Ousathite; Eli the Achonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Marai the Netophathite: Chthaod son of Nooza the Netophathite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Airi son of Rebie of Mount Benjamin; Banaias the Phrathonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Ouri of Nachaligaas; Abiel the Garabaithite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Azbon the Baromite; Eliaba the Salabonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Son Asam the Gisonite; Jonathan son of Sola the Ararite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Achim son of Achar the Ararite; Elphat son of Thurophar the Mechorathrite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Achia the Phelonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Esere the Charmadite; Naarai son of Azobai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Joel son of Nathan; Mebaal son of Agari;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Sele the Ammonite; Nachor the Berothite the armour bearer of the son of Saruia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Ira the Jethrite; Gareb the Jethrite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Uria the Chettite; Zabet son of Achaia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Adina son of Saiza the chief of Reuben, yet there were thirty above him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Anan son of Moocha and Josaphat the Matthanite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Ozia the Astarothite; Samatha and Jeiel sons of Chotham the Ararite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Jediel son of Semeri, and Josae his brother the Thosite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Eliel the Maoite; Jaribi and Josia his son; Ellaam and Jethama the Moabite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Daliel and Obeth, and Jessiel the Messobiate.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these were they who came to David to Sekelag, while he kept himself close because of Saul son of Kis; and these among the worthies assisted in battle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and used the bow, slung stones and hurled darts with both hands. Of the brethren of Saul; of Benjamin</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>the chief Achiezer and Joas son of Asma the Gabathite, and Joel and Jophalet sons of Asmoth and Berchia and Jeul the Anathothite,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and Samaias the Gabaonite, a commander among the thirty and over the thirty; Jeremia and Jeziel and Joanan and Joazabath the Gadarathiite</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Azai and Arimuth and Baalia and Samaraia and Saphatias the Charaiphielite,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Elkana and Jesuni and Ozriel and Jozara and Sobokam, who were Korites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and Jelia and Zabadia sons of Iroam and who were Gedorites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And from the Gadites there withdrew to David from the wilderness, valiant men fit to command an army in battle array, wielding shields and spears. Their faces were the face of a lion, and they were swift as roes on the mountains;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Asa the chief, Abdia the second, Eliab the third,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Masmana the fourth, Jeremias the fifth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Jethi the sixth, Eliab the seventh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Joanan the eighth, Eliazer the ninth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Jeremia the tenth, Melchabania the eleventh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>These from among the sons of Gad were officers of the army, the least of them commanded a hundred, and the greatest a thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>These were they who crossed the Jordan in the first month, when it overflowed all its banks, and put to flight all the inhabitants of the plains, from east to west.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>There came also some from Benjamin and Juda to the assistance of David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And David went out to meet them, and said to them, If you are come to me with good intent, let my heart as it is disposed be knit to you: but if to betray me to my enemies, and not with sincerity, may the God of our fathers see and rebuke.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whereupon Amasai, a chief of the thirty, became inspired, and said, Advance, David son of Jessai! for they are thy people; Peace! peace to thee! and peace to them who assist thee, because thy God hath helped thee. So David received them, and made them officers of the armies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>There withdrew also to David some from Manasses, when the Philistines came against Saul to battle. He indeed did not assist them, for in a council of war held by the generals of the Philistines, they said, With the heads of these men he will return to his master Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>As David was returning to Sekelag there came to him from Manasses, Edna and Josabath and Rodiel and Michael and Josabaith and Elimuth and Semathi. They were the leaders of the thousands of Manasses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and they assisted David in the battle against the roving horde; for they were all men of valour, and for their valour commanders in the army.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For there came men daily to David to form a great army like the host of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now these were the rolls of the chiefs of the army who came to David to Chebron, to transfer the kingdom of Saul to him, according to the word of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The children of Juda armed with shields and spears, six thousand eight hundred, fit for the array of battle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>of the Symeonites fit for the array of battle, seven thousand one hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>of the Levites, four thousand six hundred,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and Joadas the leader of the house of Aaron, and with him three thousand seven hundred,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>with Sadok a young man of valour, and of his patriarchal family twenty two chiefs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and of the Benjaminites, Saul's brethren, three thousand; but still the greater part of them kept the watch of Saul's house;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>of the Ephraimites, twenty thousand eight hundred valiant men, the most renowned in the houses of their respective families;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and of the half of the tribe of Manasses, eighteen thousand, who were enrolled for the express purpose of making David king</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and of the children of Issachar, men who had knowledge suitable for the times, who knew what Israel should do, two hundred chiefs, and all their brethren with them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and from Zabulon there came ready for battle, with all the implements of war with them, fifty thousand, to assist David effectually;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and from Nephthaleim, a thousand chiefs, and with them thirty seven thousand, armed with shields and spears;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and from the Danites, twenty eight thousand eight hundred, marshalled for battle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and from Aser they who go forth for battle, forty thousand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and from beyond the Jordan; from Reuben and Gad, and from the half of the tribe of Manasses, with all the implements of war, a hundred and twenty thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>All these warriors were arrayed for battle, with a peaceable intention. They came to Chebron to make David king over all Israel. And all the rest of Israel were of one mind that David should be king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And they were three days eating and drinking. For their brethren made provision for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And they who were nearest, as far as Zabulon and Issachar and Nephthaleim brought provisions for them on camels and asses and mules and oxen, namely, flour, fig cakes, dried grapes, wine and oil, with cattle and sheep in abundance; for there was joy in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When David had consulted with the captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, under every leader,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he said to the whole congregation of Israel, If it seemeth good and be countenanced by the Lord our God, let us send to the rest of our brethren who are left in all the land of Israel, and with them let the priests, the Levites in the cities of their possession be assembled with us;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and let us bring the ark of our God to us. For they had not sought it from the days of Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon the whole congregation gave orders to do so; for the proposal was right in the eyes of all the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Accordingly, David assembled all Israel from the border of Egypt to the bay of Emath, to bring the ark of God from the city Iarim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and David brought it up. Now when all Israel came to the city Iarim which belonged to Juda, to bring up thence the ark of God the Lord, enthroned on cherubim whose name was invoked,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>they put the ark of God on a new cart. And from the house of Aminadab, Oza and his brothers guided the cart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>while David and all Israel were playing with all their might before God, on psalteries and kinyras and nablas and tympanums and cymbals and trumpets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But when they came to the threshing floor, Oza stretched forth his hand to take hold of the ark, because the bullock caused it to lean:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>whereupon the anger of the Lord was kindled against Oza, and he smote him there, because he stretched forth his hand upon the ark, and he died there before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And David was disheartened because the Lord had made a breach on Oza, and called that place, Breach of Oza, which is still its name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And David was that day afraid of God and said, How can I bring the ark of God home to me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So David did not bring the ark of God home to himself, to the city of David, but caused it to turn aside to the house of Abeddara, the Gethite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the ark of God abode in the house of Abeddara three months, and God blessed Abeddara and all that belonged to him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Chiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, with cedar timber, and masons and carpenters to build him a house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and David knew that the Lord had prepared him to be king over Israel; for his kingdom was highly exalted for the sake of his people Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>David took still more wives in Jerusalem, and more sons and daughters were born to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now these are the names of those who were born to him in Jerusalem, Samaa, Sobab, Nathan and Solomon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and Baar and Elisa, and Eliphaleth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Nageth, and Naphath and Japhie,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and Elisamae and Eliade, and Eliphala.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, they all came up to seek David. And when David heard it he went out to meet them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now the Philistines had come and spread themselves in the giant's vale.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And David inquired of God, saying, If I go up against the Philistines, wilt thou deliver them into my hands? And the Lord said to him, Go up and I will deliver them into thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So he went up to Baal Pharasin. And when he had smitten them there David said, God broke through, my enemies by my hand, like the breaking out of water, therefore he called the name of that place, Breach of Pharasin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the Philistines having left their gods there, David ordered them to be burned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Again the Philistines came up and spread themselves again in the giant's vale.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when David again inquired of God, God said to him, Thou shalt not go up after them. Turn from them and come upon them near the pear trees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when thou shalt hear a sound of rustling in the tops of the pear trees, then thou shalt come to battle, for God is gone out before thee to smite the camp of the Philistines.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Accordingly he did as the Lord commanded him, and he smote the camp of the Philistines from Gabaon to Gazera.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the fame of David spread through all the land, and the Lord brought the dread of him on all the nations.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When David had built houses for himself in the city of David, and prepared the place for the ark of God, and made for it a tabernacle:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>then David said, None but the Levites ought to carry the ark of God; for the Lord hath chosen them to carry the ark of the Lord and to minister to him forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So when David assembled all Israel at Jerusalem, to bring the ark of the Lord to the place which he had prepared for it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>he assembled the sons of Aaron, the Levites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>of the Kaathites, Uriel the chief and his brethren, a hundred and twenty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>of the Merarites, Asaia the chief and his brethren, two hundred and twenty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>of the Gersonites, Joel the chief and his brethren, a hundred and thirty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>of the sons of Elisaphat, Semei, the chief and his brethren, two hundred;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>of the sons of Chebron, Eliel the chief and his brethren, eighty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>of the sons of Oziel, Aminadab the chief and his brethren, a hundred and twelve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And David sent for Sadok, and Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, Uriel, Asaia and Joel, and Semaia and Eliel, and Aminadab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and said to them, You chiefs of the families of the Levites, purify yourselves, both you and your brethren, that you may carry up the ark of the God of Israel to the place which I have prepared for it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for because you did not do this on the former occasion, our God made a breach among us, because we did not seek him with judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So when the priests and the Levites had purified themselves to carry the ark of the God of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the Levites took up the ark of God, as Moses had by the word of the Lord ordered in writing, with the staves on their shoulders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now David had said to the chiefs of the Levites, Appoint your brethren, such as play on musical instruments, on nablas and kinyras, and cymbals, that they may make a loud sound with the voice of joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the Levites had appointed Aiman son of Joel and of his brethren, Asaph son of Barachia, and of the sons of Merari his brethren, Aithan the son of Kisias</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and with them their brethren of the second rank, Zacharias and Oziel, and Semiramoth and Jeiel, and Elioel and Eliab, and Banaia and Maasaia, and Matthathia and Eliphena, and Makellia and Abdedom, and Jeiel and Ozias, the keepers of the gates;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the musicians Aiman, Asaph and Aithan, sung and played on brass cymbals in the highest key;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and Zacharias and Oziel, Semiramoth, Jeiel; Oni, Eliab, Maasias, Banias, on nablas in alaimoth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and Mattathias and Eliphalu, and Makenia and Abdedom, and Jeiel and Ozias, on kinyras in Amasenith to give a strong sound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And Chononias, a chief of the Levites, was master of the odes, for he was skilled therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And Barachia and Elkana were door keepers of the ark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Somnia and Josaphat, and Nathaniel and Amasai, and Zacharia and Banaia, and Eliezer the priests, sounded the trumpets before the ark of God. And Abdedom and Jeia were door keepers of the ark of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And David with the elders of Israel and the captains of thousands, marched before when they were bringing up the ark of the covenant from the house of Abdedom with joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And because God strengthened the Levites who carried the ark of the covenant of the Lord, therefore they sacrificed each seven bulls and seven rams.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now David was girded in a cotton stole, as were all the Levites who carried the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and the musicians and Chonenias the chief of the singers. And when David in his cotton stole,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and all Israel were bringing up the ark of the covenant of the Lord with shouting and the sound of clarions and trumpets, answered by nablas and kinyras,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>it happened that when the ark of the covenant of the Lord came to the city of David, Melchol the daughter of Saul looking out at a window saw king David dancing and playing, and she despised him in her heart.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when they had brought in the ark of God and set it in the midst of the tabernacle, which David had erected for it, they offered whole burnt offerings and offerings of thanks giving before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when David had finished offering the whole burnt offerings and the offerings of thanksgiving, he blessed the people in the name of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and distributed to all Israel both men and women, to every one a loaf of baker's bread, and a cake made with honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then he appointed some of the Levites to minister before the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and in responsive strains to thank and praise the Lord the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Asaph was the leader, and to him responded Zacharias, Jeiel, Semiramoth and Jeiel, Matthathias, Eliab and Banaias, Abdedom and Jeiel, with musical instruments, nablas and kinyras; but Asaph used the cymbal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Banaias and Oziel the priests, with trumpets, were to be continually before the ark of the covenant of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>On that day David gave orders for beginning the praises of the Lord by the ministry of Asaph and his brethren, with this Ode:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>O give thanks to the Lord, Invoke him by his name; Among peoples make known his designs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Sing to him. Sing praises to him. Proclaim to all the wonders which the Lord hath done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Sing praises to his holy name. Let the heart which seeketh his favour be glad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Seek the Lord and persevere; Seek his face continually.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Remember the wonders which he hath done; The miracles and judgments of his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The seed of Israel are his servants; The sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He is the Lord our God; In all this land are his judgments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Let us ever remember his covenant; His word which he enjoined for a thousand generations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The covenant which he made with Abraham; And the oath which he sware to Isaak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This he confirmed for a law to Jacob; To Israel as an everlasting covenant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Saying, To thee I will give the land of Chanaan, To be the portion of your inheritance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When they were very few in number; Of little account, and sojourned therein;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When they were passing from nation to nation; And from one kingdom to another people;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He suffered no man to oppress them; He rebuked kings for their sake</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Touch not these my anointed ones, And to these my prophets do no harm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Sing to the Lord, all ye of this land, From day to day proclaim his salvation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Declare his glory among the nations; Among all peoples his marvellous works;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>That the Lord is great and greatly to be praised; Above all the gods he is awful</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>That all the gods of the nations are idols; But our God hath made the heavens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Glory and honour are before him; Majesty and gladness in his abode.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Ascribe to the Lord, ye families of nations, Ascribe to the Lord glory and majesty</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Ascribe to the Lord, glory to his name. Take gifts and bring them before him, And worship the Lord in his holy courts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Let all the earth be awed at his presence, Let the earth be renovated and not dismayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Let heaven rejoice, and the earth exult with joy, Let them say among the nations, The Lord is king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Let the sea roar and the fulness thereof; And the trees of the field and all therein;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Let the trees of the forest also rejoice at the presence of the Lord; Because he is come to judge the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>praise the Lord; for it is good, For to everlasting his mercy endureth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And say, Save us, God of our salvation! Gather us and deliver us from our enemies; That we may praise thy holy name, And in thy praises make our boast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Blessed be the Lord, the God of Israel, From everlasting to everlasting, And let all the people say, Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And when they had praised the Lord, they left there, before the ark of the covenant of the Lord, Asaph and his brethren, that they might minister before the ark continually as each day's service required.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And with regard to Abdedom and his brethren who were sixty eight, Abdedom son of Idithun and Osa were to be door keepers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And they left Sadok the priest, and his brethren the priests, before the tabernacle of the Lord at the high place at Gabaon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>that they might offer whole burnt offerings to the Lord, on the altar of whole burnt offerings continually every morning and evening, according to all that is written in the law of the Lord, which he enjoined on the children of Israel by the ministry of Moses the servant of God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>and with him were Aiman and Idithun, and the rest who were chosen by name to praise the Lord, because his mercy endureth forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And they had with them trumpets and high sounding cymbals, and musical instruments, for the songs of God. And the sons of Idithun were to be keepers of the gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then all the people returned every one to his home, and David returned to bless his household.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When David was settled in his house, he said to Nathan the prophet, Behold I dwell in a house of cedar, but the ark of the covenant of the Lord is beneath curtains of skin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thereupon Nathan said to David, Do whatever is in thy heart; for God is with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But that very night there came to Nathan a word of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Go, and say to David my servant, Thus saith the Lord, Thou shalt not build me a house to dwell in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Because I have not dwelt in a house from the day I brought up Israel even to this day, but have been in a tent and under a curtain</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>in all the places, through which I passed among Israel, did I ever speak to any tribe of Israel, whom I commanded to feed my people, and say, Why have you not built for me a house of cedar?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But now, Thus shalt thou say to my servant David, Thus saith the Lord Almighty, I took thee from the fold; from following the flocks, to be ruler over my people Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and have been with thee wherever thou hast gone, and have cut off all thy enemies from before thee, and made thee a name like the name of the great men on the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and I will fix a place for my people Israel, and plant them, and they shall dwell by themselves and no more be in trouble, nor shall a son of iniquity any more humble them as at the first,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>even from the time I appointed judges over my people Israel. I have indeed subdued all thy enemies, and I will increase thee and the Lord will build thee a house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when thy days are fulfilled and thou shalt go to rest with thy fathers, I will raise up thy seed after thee who shall proceed from thy loins, and I will prepare his kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>He shall build a house for me, and I will establish his throne forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I will be to him a father and he shall be to me a son; and I will not withdraw my mercy from him as I withdrew it from them who were before him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but will confirm him in my house and in his kingdom, and his throne shall be established forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>According to all these words and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak to David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Whereupon king David went and sat down before the Lord, and said, Who am I, Lord my God, and what is my house that thou shouldst love me forever!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Though these were very small before thee, my God, yet thou hast spoken of thy servant's house for a great while to come, and hast looked upon me as with the eyes of a man, and exalted me. Lord my God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>what more can David address to thee to express thy praise? Thou knowest thy servant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and according to thy own heart thou hast made all this greatness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>O Lord! there is none like thee, nor is there a god besides thee according to all that we have heard with our ears;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>nor is there another nation on the earth like thy people Israel. How hath God led them to redeem a people for himself, to make himself a name great and glorious, by driving out nations from before thy people whom thou didst redeem out of Egypt!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>As thou hast made thy people Israel a people for thyself forever, and thou the Lord art become their God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>now therefore, Lord, let the word which thou hast spoken to thy servant, and touching his house be established forever, and do as thou hast spoken;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and let thy name be established and magnified forever by men, saying, Lord, Lord Almighty, thou art the God of Israel, and the house of thy servant David is established before thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Because thou, Lord my God, hast revealed to the ear of thy servant, that thou wilt build him a house; therefore thy servant hath found freedom to make supplication before thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And now, Lord, thou art God. As thou hast spoken these good things, respecting thy servant;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>now therefore begin to bless the house of thy servant that it may be before thee forever. Because thou hast blessed, therefore bless it forever.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now after these things, David smote the Philistines and subdued them, and took out of their hands Geth and the villages thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He smote Moab also, and they became vassals to David and brought him gifts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>David also smote Adraazar king of Suba Emath. As he was going to establish his dominion over the river Euphrates;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>David intercepted a thousand of his chariots and seven thousand cavalry, and twenty thousand infantry. And David destroyed all the chariots, reserving only a hundred of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when the Syrians of Damascus came to assist Adraazar king of Suba, David smote of the Syrians twenty two thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And David garrisoned that part of Syria which belonged to Damascus, and the inhabitants became David's vassals, and brought him gifts. And the Lord preserved David wherever he went.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And David took the chains of gold which were on the servants of Adraazar, and brought them to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And from Matabeth and from the chief cities which belonged to Adraazar, David took brass in great abundance, of which Solomon made the brasen sea and the pillars and the vessels of brass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now when Thoa king of Emath, heard that David had smitten all the army of Adraazar king of Suba,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>he sent his son Aduram to king David, to sue for peace with him, and to congratulate him because he had fought Adraazar and defeated him; for Thoa was at war with Adraazar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And all the vessels of gold and silver and brass, which he brought, these king David dedicated to the Lord, together with the silver and the gold which he took from all the nations from Idumea and Moab, and from the Ammonites and the Philistines and from Amelek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When Abessa son of Saruia had smitten of the Idumeans in the valley of salt, eighteen thousand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>he put garrisons in the vale; and the Idumeans became David's vassals, and the Lord preserved David wherever he went.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And David reigned over all Israel, and continued to execute judgment and justice among all the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Joab son of Saruia was over the army; and Josaphat son of Achilud was recorder;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Sadok son of Achitob and Achimelech son of Abiathar, were the priests; and Sousa was secretary;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and Banaias son of Jodae was over the Cherethites and the Phelethites, and David's sons were next in rank to the king.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now after these things, when Naas king of the Ammonites died and his son Anan reigned in his stead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>David said, I will shew kindness to Anan son of Naas as his father shewed kindness to me. So David sent messengers to comfort him for his father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But when David's servants came to the country of the Ammonites to Anan to comfort him, the chiefs of the Ammonites said to Anan, Is it to honour thy father in thy presence that David hath sent comforters to thee? Is it not that they may examine the city and spy the country that his servants are come to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon Anan took David's servants and shaved them, and having cut off the half of their military robe even to the under garment, he dismissed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when messengers came to inform David respecting his servants, David sent to meet them, because they had been greatly dishonoured; and the king said to them, Abide at Jericho till your beards grow and then return.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now when the Ammonites saw that David's people were dishonoured, Anan and the children of Ammon sent a thousand talents of silver to hire for themselves chariots and cavalry from Syrian Mesopotamia, and from Syrian Maacha and from Sobal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And they hired thirty two thousand of the chariot army, and the king of Maacha and his people. And when they arrived they encamped over against Medaba, and the Ammonites were drawn together out of their cities, and came to commence war.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When David heard this he sent Joab with all the army of the worthies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the Ammonites came out and drew up in array for battle before the gate of the city; but the kings who had come, encamped by themselves in the plain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When Joab saw that they were arrayed for battle against him both in front and rear, he made a draught out of all the youth of Israel and drew them up in array against the Syrians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the rest of the people he put under the command of Abesai his brother, and they were drawn up in array against the Ammonites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Joab said, If the Syrians be too strong for me, thou must come to my assistance; and if the children of Ammon prove too strong for thee I will support thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Be of good courage and let us act valiantly for our people and for the cities of our God, and the Lord will do what is good in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when Joab and the people with him drew up in array for battle over against the Syrians they fled from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And soon as the Ammonites saw that the Syrians fled they also fled before Abesai and before Joab his brother, and entered the city. Upon which Joab returned to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When the Syrian saw that Israel had defeated him, he despatched messengers and drew out the Syrians from beyond the river. And Sophath the general of Adraazar's army was at their head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This being told David, he assembled all Israel and crossed the Jordan and came upon them, and drew up for battle against them. And while David was marshalling his army for battle against the Syrians, they attacked him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>but the Syrians fled before Israel, and David slew of the Syrians seven thousand of the chariot army, and forty thousand infantry. He slew also Sophath the general of the army.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when the servants of Adraazar saw that they were defeated before Israel, they made peace with David and served him. And the Syrians would not help the Ammonites any more.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And at the return of the year when kings take the field, Joab led out all the strength of the army, and having laid waste all the country of the Ammonites, he went and besieged Rabba while David abode at Jerusalem. And when Joab had smitten Rabba and demolished it</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>David took the crown of Molchom their king from his head, and the weight of it was found to be a talent of gold, and in it was a precious stone and it was on the head of David. And having brought out the spoils of the city which were very great,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>he brought out the people who were in it, and put them to saws and iron mattocks and among quarry men. And when David had done in this manner to all the Ammonites, he and all the people returned to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And after these things there was another battle at Gazer with the Philistines, in which Sobochai-Sosathai smote Saphut a descendant of the giants and subdued him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>There was also another battle with the Philistines, when Eleanan son of Jair smote Lachmai a brother of Goliath the Gethite, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver's beam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>There was also another battle at Geth, and there was a man of great stature there, who had six fingers on each hand and six toes on each foot, in all twenty four, and he also was a descendant of the giants,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and he defied Israel; but Jonathan son of Samaa, a brother of David, smote him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>These were the descendants of Rapha at Geth. They were all four giants, and they fell by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when an adversary stood up in Israel and persuaded David to number Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and king David said to Joab and the chiefs of the army, Go, number Israel from Dan to Bersabee, and let me know the number of them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Joab replied, The Lord add to his people a hundred times as many as there are. and may the eyes of my lord the king see it. They are all servants to my lord. Why doth my lord seek this? May it not be a cause of trespass to Israel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But the king's determination prevailed against Joab, so he went forth, and having passed through all Israel, and come to Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>he gave David an account of the review of the people, and the whole number of the men of Israel who drew a sword, was eleven hundred thousand, and the children of Juda were four hundred and seventy thousand men who drew a sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But he did not number Levi and Benjamin among them. Because the king's word prevailed over Joab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the thing was evil in the sight of God, therefore he smote Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When David said to God, I have sinned greatly in doing this, now therefore take away, I beseech thee, this wickedness of thy servant, for I have acted very foolishly</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the Lord spoke to Gad, the seer, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Go, and speak to David, and say, Thus saith the Lord, I offer thee three things, chuse for thyself one of them that I may do it to thee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So Gad went to David and said to him, Thus saith the Lord, Chuse for thyself</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>either three years of famine; or three months to flee before thy enemies while the sword of thy enemies is destroying thee; or the sword of the Lord and pestilence for three days throughout the land, while an angel of the Lord is making havock in all the inheritance of Israel. Now therefore consider What answer shall I make to him who sent me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thereupon David said to Gad, Very hard indeed to me are all the three. Let me however fall into the hands of the Lord, for his tender mercies are exceeding great. But let me not fall into the hands of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So the Lord sent a pestilence through Israel, and there fell of the Israelites seventy thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when God sent an angel to Jerusalem to destroy it, and he was making havock, the Lord looked and relented at the calamity, and said to the destroying angel, Let this suffice thee. Stay thy hand. Now the angel of the Lord was standing at the threshing floor of Orna, the Jebusite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when David raised his eyes and saw the angel of the Lord standing between the earth and heaven, with a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem, he and all the elders being clad in sackcloth, fell on their faces,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and David said to God, Was it not I who ordered the numbering of the people? I indeed am the sinner. It is I who committed the sin. But as for this flock, what have they done? Lord my God, Let thy hand be upon me, and on my father's house, and not on this thy people, O Lord, to destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thereupon the angel of the Lord ordered Gad to tell David to go up and erect an altar to the Lord on the threshing floor of Orna the Jebusite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So David went up according to the word which Gad spoke in the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when Orna turned and saw the king and his four sons with him, with attendants (now Orna was threshing wheat)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>upon David's approach to Orna, Orna came out of his threshing floor and made obeisance to David with his face to the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And David said to Orna, Grant me the place of this threshing floor of thine, that I may build thereon an altar to the Lord; grant it to me for its worth in money, that the plague may be stayed from the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And Orna said to David, Take it for thyself; and let my Lord the king do what is good in his sight. Behold I have given these young bulls for a whole burnt offering, and that plough for wood, and this corn for a sacrifice. Of all these things I make a gift.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And David said to Orna, By no means: for I must buy them for their worth in money. For I cannot take what are thine for the Lord, to offer a whole burnt offering to the Lord at free cost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So David gave Orna for the place six hundred shekels of gold by weight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And having built there an altar to the Lord, he offered up the offerings of homage and thanksgiving, and cried to the Lord, and the Lord hearkened to him by fire from heaven upon the altar of the whole burnt offering, which consumed the whole burnt offering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then the Lord spoke to the angel and he sheathed his sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When David saw that the Lord hearkened to him at the threshing floor of Orna the Jebusite, and that he had sacrificed there</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>at that time, though the tabernacle of the Lord which Moses had made in the wilderness, and the altar for whole burnt offerings were at that time at the high place of Gabaon</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>now he could not go before it to inquire of God, for that would not have been answerable to the haste in which he was, on account of the sword of the angel of the Lord</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>David said, This is the house of the Lord God, and this is the altar for whole burnt offerings for Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then David ordered the strangers in the land of Israel to be assembled, and appointed stone cutters to cut hewn stones to build the house for God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He provided also iron in abundance for nails, for the doors and gates, and for hinges; and brass in abundance, without weight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and cedar beams innumerable; for the Sidonians and Tyrians, brought for David, cedar timber in abundance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And David said, My son Solomon is young and tender, and the house to be built for the Lord is for extraordinary grandeur, for renown and glory, through every land, I will make provision for it. So David provided materials in abundance before his death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And he called Solomon his son, and gave him a charge, to build the house for the Lord God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And David said to Solomon, My son, it was in my mind to build a house for the name of the Lord God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>when there came to me a word from the Lord saying, Thou hast shed much blood, and fought many battles, thou shalt not build a house for my name, because thou hast shed much blood on the earth before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Behold a son shall be born to thee. He shall be a man of rest. I will give him rest from all his enemies round about. For his name shall be Solomon; and I will give Israel peace and rest in his days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He shall build a house for my name. And he shall be to me a son; and I will be to him a father. And I will establish the throne of his kingdom in Israel forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now therefore, my son, the Lord will be with thee, and will prosper thee, and thou shalt build a house for the Lord thy God, as he hath spoken concerning thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let but the Lord grant thee wisdom and understanding, and strengthen thee over Israel, that thou mayst keep and perform the law of the Lord thy God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>then will he prosper thee, if thou be watchful to execute the statutes, and judgments, which the Lord enjoined on Israel by Moses. Quit thyself like a man, and be strong. Fear not nor be dismayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now behold according to my poor ability I have provided for the house of the Lord a hundred talents of gold, and ten hundred talents of silver, and brass and iron without weight, because of their abundance. I have also provided timber and stones, but thou must add thereto.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And thou must add to the number of workmen of whom there are with thee artists, and masons and carpenters and men skilled in every kind of work,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>of gold and silver and brass and iron, an innumerable number. Up therefore; and fall to work. And the Lord be with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>David also gave a charge to all the chiefs of Israel to assist his son Solomon, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Hath not the Lord been with you, and given you rest all around? For he hath delivered into your hands the inhabitants of this land, and the land is subdued before the Lord, and before his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now therefore apply your hearts, and your souls to seek the Lord your God and arise and build a sanctuary for your God, that you may carry the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and the holy vessels of God, into the house to be built for the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When David was old and full of days, and had made Solomon his son king over Israel in his stead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>then he assembled all the chiefs of Israel, and the priests and the Levites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the Levites were numbered, from thirty years old and upwards; and the number of them by their poll, amounted to thirty eight thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Of these, twenty four thousand were for the works for the house of the Lord; and six thousand were scribes and judges;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and four thousand were guards of the gates, and four thousand were to praise the Lord with musical instruments, which he had made for praising the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And David distributed them into daily classes, under the heads of Gerson, Kaath and Merari, the sons of Levi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now to Gerson belonged Edan and Semei;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the sons of Edan, were chief Jeiel, and Zethan and Joel, three:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the sons of Semei, were Salomith, Jeiel and Dan, three. Those were the chiefs of the families of the Edantes;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but the Semeites, had also Jeth and Ziza, and Joas and Beria; these four were sons of Semei,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Jeth was the chief and Ziza the second, and Joas and Beria not having many children were comprehended in one muster, for a house of a family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the sons of Kaath were Ambram, Issaar, Chebron, Oziel; four.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The sons of Ambram were Aaron and Moses. Now Aaron was set apart for the sanctification of the most holy things, he and his sons, to burn incense before the Lord, to minister in the priest's office, and to bless in his name forever</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But as for Moses the man of God, his sons were classed in the tribe of Levi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The sons of Moses, were Gersam and Eliezer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Of the Gersamites, Subael was chief,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and of the Eliezerites, Rabia was chief. Now Eliezer had no other sons; but the sons of Rabia were increased to a multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The sons of Issaar, were Salomith the chief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The sons of Chebron, were Jeria the chief, Amaria the second, Jeziel the third, Jekemias the fourth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The sons of Oziel, were Micha the chief and Isia the second.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The sons of Merari were Mooli and Mousi. The sons of Mooli were Eleazar and Kis.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now Eleazar died, and left no sons, but only daughters. So the sons of Kis, their brethren, took them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The sons of Mousi were Mouli and Eder and Jerimoth, three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>These are the sons of Levi, according to the houses of their patriarchal families. The chiefs of these families, according to the review of them, according to the number of their names were polled to perform the works of the service of the house of the Lord, from twenty years old and upwards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For David said, The Lord God of Israel hath given his people rest and fixed his abode in Jerusalem forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So the Levites not having to carry the tabernacle and all the utensils thereof for its service;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for this cause by these last orders of David, the Levites are numbered from twenty years old and upwards,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>for he set them under the superintendance of Aaron to serve in the house of the Lord, over the courts and over the store houses and over the purification of all the holy things, and over the work of the service of the house of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and for the shew bread, and for the fine flour of the sacrifice and for the unleavened cakes, and for the frying pan, and the mixed sacrifice, and for all kinds of measuring,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and to stand every morning to sing praises, and give thanks to the Lord, and the same every evening:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and to have charge of all the offerings of homage made to the Lord, on the sabbaths and at the new moons, and at the festivals according to the number, and according to the rule prescribed for them, continually for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And they are to keep the watch of the tabernacle of the testimony, and to guard the sanctuary, and to guard the sons of Aaron, their brethren, that they may minister as priests, in the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now with regard to the sons of Aaron in the line of Nadab and of Abiud, and of Eleazar and of Ithamar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As Nadab and Abiud died in the presence of their father and had no sons; and Eleazar and Ithamar had officiated as priests;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>David classed Sadok at the head of the sons of Eleazar, and Achimelech at the head of the sons of Ithamar, according to the review of them according to their service, according to the houses of their families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And as the Eleazarites were found to be more numerous for chiefs of mighty men than the sons of Ithamar, therefore he distributed them; for the sons of Eleazar sixteen chiefs for houses of families, and for the sons of Ithamar chiefs for eight houses of families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>These he distributed by lot, one with the other. Because there were chiefs of the holies, and chiefs of the Lord, among the sons of Eleazar and among the sons of Ithamar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore in the presence of the king and the chiefs, Samaias son of Nathaniel, the muster master of the Levites, wrote down Sadok the priest and Achimelech son of Abiathar, and the chiefs of the families of the priests and the Levites, a chief of a house of families alternately, one for Eleazar and one for Ithamar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the first lot came out for Joarim; the second for Jedia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the third for Charib; the fourth for Seorim;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the fifth for Melchias; the sixth for Meiamin;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the seventh for Ros; the eighth for Abia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>the ninth for Jesus; the tenth for Sechenias;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the eleventh for Eliabi; the twelfth for Jakim;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>the thirteenth for Oppha; the fourteenth for Jesbaal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>the fifteenth for Belga; the sixteenth for Emmer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the seventeenth for Chesin; the eighteenth for Aphese;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the nineteenth for Phetaia; the twentieth for Ezekel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the twenty first for Achim; the twenty second for Gamul;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>the twenty third for Adallai; the twenty fourth for Maasai.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>This was the review of them according to their service, to go into the house of the Lord according to the rule prescribed for them, under the inspection of Aaron their father, as the Lord God of Israel commanded Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And for the rest of the Levites; for the Ambramites, Sobael; for the sons of Sobael, Jedia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>for the Rabiates, the chief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For the Isaarites Salomoth, for the sons of Salomoth, Jath;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>the sons of Ekdiu; Amadia the second; Jaziel the third; Jekmoam the fourth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For the Ozielites, Micha; for the sons of Micha, Samer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>the brother of Micha, Isia; the sons of Isia, Sacharia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>the Merarites Mooli and Mousi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>the sons of Ozia, to whom belonged the title Merarite; his sons Isoam; and Sakckur, and Abai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>for Mooli, Eleazar and Ithamar, now Eleazar died and had no sons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>for him Kis; the sons of Kis, Jerameel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>the sons of Mousi, Mooli and Eder and Jerimoth, these sons of the Levites according to the houses of their families;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>they also drew lots as their brethren the sons of Aaron did, in the presence of the king and of Sadok and Achimelech, the senior chiefs of the families both of the priests and the Levites submitting to the lot equally with their younger brethren.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then David the king with the chiefs of this host, appointed to their services the sons of Asaph and Aiman and Idithun, who chanted with kinyras and with nablas and with cymbals, and an account was taken by poll of those employed in these services.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The sons of Asaph were Zakchur and Joseph, and Nathanias and Erael. The sons of Asaph were near the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>With Idithun were the sons of Idithun, Godolias and Suri, and Iseas and Asabias, and Matthathias, six after their father Idithim, chanting on kinyras thanksgiving and praise to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>With Aiman were the sons of Aiman, Bukias and Matthanias, and Oziel and Subael, and Jerimoth and Ananias, and Anan and Eliatha, and Godollathi and Rometthiezer, and Jesbasaka and Melithi, and Otheri and Meazoth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>All these sons Aiman had with him when he commenced a psalm for the king in the words of God. To exalt the horn God indeed had given Aiman fourteen sons and three daughters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>All these with their father, sung in the house of God to cymbals and nablas and kinyras, for the service of the house of God near the king, with Asaph and Idithun and Aiman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the number of them, including younger brethren, who were instructed to sing to the Lord, even all who were skilled, was two hundred and eighty eight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And they cast lots for their daily courses, as well the younger as the senior, both teachers and scholars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the lot which came out the first of his sons and his brethren for Asaph was that of Joseph, namely Godolias; the second Henia, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the third Zakchur his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>the fourth Jesri, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the fifth, Nathan, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>the sixth Bukias, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>the seventh Iseriel, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the eighth Josia, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the ninth Matthanias, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the tenth Semeia, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>the eleventh Asriel, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>the twelfth Asabia, his sons and brethren, twelve; the</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>thirteenth Subael, his sons and brethren twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>the fourteenth Matthathias his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>the fifteenth Jerimoth. his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>the sixteenth Anania, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the seventeenth Jesbasaka, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>the eighteenth Ananias, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>the nineteenth Mellithi, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>the twentieth Eliatha, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>the twenty first Otheri, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>the twenty second Godollathi, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>the twenty third Meazoth, his sons and brethren, twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>the twenty fourth Rometthiezer, his sons and brethren, twelve.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And for the guards of the gates were the Korites, Mosellamia, of the sons of Asaph;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and for Mosellamia were Son Zacharias the first born, Jadiel the second, Zabadia the third, Jenuel the fourth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Jolam the fifth, Jonathan the sixth, Elionai the seventh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Abdedom the eighth; and the sons of Abdedom were, Samaias the first born, Jozabath the second, Joath the third, Sachar the fourth, Nathaniel the fifth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Amiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Philathi the eighth; because God had blessed him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore for Samia his son, there were born, sons of his first born, Rosai, to make his a patriarchal house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>because the Samaites had heads of families, namely Othni and Raphael, and Obed and Elzabeth, and Achiud, mighty sons, Eliu and Sabachia, and Isbakom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>all descendants of the sons of Abdedom, they and their sons and their brethren, acting as heads of families in the service. All the sons of Abdedom were sixty two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the sons of Mosellamia with their brethren, were eighteen heads of families.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Osa, also of the children of Merari, had sons who kept up his chieftancy. Because he was not first born, therefore his father made him chief of the second branch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Chelkias was the second, Tablai the third, Zacharias the fourth. All the sons and brethren of Osa were thirteen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Among these the gates were distributed, the heads of families having daily courses like their brethren, to do service in the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they cast lots, the junior as well as the senior, according to the houses of their families for their respective gates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the lot for the eastern gate fell to Selemia and Zacharias. The sons of Joaz having cast lots, the north gate fell to Melchia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and to Abdedom the south gate over against the house of Esephim;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>to Osa that to the west, behind the gate of the chamber of ascent, guard being over against guard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Eastward there were six a day, northward four a day, southward four a day, and two for Esephim to relieve each other;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and for Osa westward behind the gate of the chamber, three, a watch over against the watch of the ascent. On the east six a day, and on the north four, and on the south four, and at Esephim two to relieve each other,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and at the west four, and for the causeway two to relieve each other. These distributions of the guards of the gates were among the Korites and the Merarites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And with regard to the Levites their brethren, who were over the treasures of the house of the Lord and over the treasures of dedicated things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>these were Ladanites, the sons of Ladan the Gersonite; the heads of families belonging to Ladan. To Ladan the Gersonite belonged Jeiel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>the sons of Jeiel; Zethom and Joel. These brethren were over the treasures of the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>With respect to the Ambramites and Isaarites. Chebronites and Ozielites;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Subael son of Gersam, son of Moses, was over the treasures.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And to his brother Eliezer belonged Rabias a son, and Josias and Joram, and Zechri and Salomoth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>This Salomoth and his brethren were over the treasures of the dedicated things, which were dedicated by David the king and by the chiefs of families, the captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, and generals of the army,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>which they had taken from the cities and from the spoils won in battle, and of which they had dedicated a part, that the building of the house of God might not be delayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>They had the charge also of all the dedications made to God by Samuel the prophet, and by Saul son of Kis, and by Abenner son of Ner, and by Joab son of Saruia. All that they dedicated was under the care of Salomoth and his brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Of the Issaarites, Chonenia and sons had the charge of the business abroad over Israel, to act as scribes and judges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And of the Chebronites, Asabias and his brethren, heads of subordinate families, amounting to seventeen hundred, had the oversight of Israel on the western bank of the Jordan, for every service of the Lord and every work of the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>With regard to the Ozielites, Ourias was the chief of the Ozielites, according to their genealogies by families. In the fortieth year of the king's reign they were reviewed, and the head man among them was found at Jazer of Galaaditis.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And his brethren, the heads of subordinate families, were two thousand seven hundred. And king David set them over the Reubenites and the Gadites, and the half of the tribe of Manasses, for every ordinance of the Lord and every affair of the king.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>With regard to the sons of Israel according to their number, the chiefs of the families, the captains of thousands and the captains of hundreds, and the muster masters; these attended the king, and were ready at every call of the king in divisions, coming in and going out, month after month, each division consisting of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And over the first division for the first month was Isboaz son of Zabdiel; over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He being chief of the sons of Phares, was the chief of all the chiefs of the army of the first month.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And over the division of the second month was Dodia the Elchochite, and over this division of his was also Makelloth the leader of this division of his, which consisted of twenty four thousand; they were chiefs of the army.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The third for the third month was Banaias son of Jodae, who, though a priest, was the chief over this division of his which consisted of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This Banaias was higher in rank than the thirty, and over the thirty. And over this division of his was Zabad his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The fourth for the fourth month was Asael the brother of Joab. And Zabadias his son, and his brothers, were over this division of his which consisted of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The fifth for the fifth month was the leader Samaoth the Jesraite, he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The sixth for the sixth month was Oduias of Ekkes the Thekoite, he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The seventh for the seventh month was Chelles of Phallus, of the sons of Ephraim, he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The eighth for the eighth month was Sobochai the Ousathite, a house of the Zaraites; he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The ninth for the ninth month was Abiezer of Anathoth, of the land of Benjamin, he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The tenth for the tenth month was Meera the Netophathite, a house of the Zaraites; he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The eleventh for the eleventh month was Banaias the Pharathonite, of the sons of Ephraim; he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The twelfth for the twelfth month was Choldia the Netophathite, a house belonging to Gothoniel; he was over his division of twenty four thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And over the tribes of Israel; Over Reuben, Eliezer the son of Zechri was ruler; over Symeon, Saphatias the son of Maachi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>over Levi, Asabias the son of Kamuel; over the Aaronites, Sadok;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>over Juda, Eliab, David's eldest brother; over Issachar, Ambri the son of Michael;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>over Zabulon, Samaias the son of Abdiu; over Nephthaleim, Jerimoth the son of Oziel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>over Ephraim, Ose the son of Oziu; over the half of the tribe of Manasses, Joel the son of Phadaia;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>over the half of the tribe of Manasses in the land of Galaad, Jadai the son of Zadaiu; over the Benjaminites, Jasiel the son of Abenner;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>over Dan, Azariel the son of Iroab. These were the rulers of the tribes of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But David did not take the number of them from twenty years old and under, because the Lord said, he would multiply Israel like the stars of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When Joab the son of Saruia, began to number the people, though he did not finish it, there was wrath for it on Israel, so that the number was not set down in the journal of king David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And over the treasures of the king was Asmoth the son of Odiel. And over his stores in the country, and in the towns, and in the villages, and in the castles, was Jonathan the son of Oziu;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and over the husbandmen who tilled the ground was Esdri the son of Chelub;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and over the fields, Semei the Raelite; and over the stores of wine in the vineyards Sabdi the son of Sephni;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and over the olive yards and sycamine orchards in the plains, Ballanan the Gedorite: and over the stores of oil, Joas;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and over the herds which pastured at Sharon, Satrai the Saronite; and over the cattle in the vales, Sophat the son of Adli;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and over the camels, Abias the Ismaelite; and over the asses, Jadias the Merathonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and over the flocks, Jaziz the Agarite. All these were overseers of David's substance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And Jonathan David's uncle was a counsellor, a wise man, and Jeel and the son of Achami were with the king's sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Achitophel was a counsellor of the king. Now Chusi the king's friend was the first,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and after him Achitophel, next Jodae the son of Banaias, then Abiathar and Joab the king's captain general.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When David had assembled all the chiefs of Israel, the chiefs of the judges, and all the chiefs of the divisions which attended the king's person in courses, and the chiefs over the thousands, and the chiefs over the hundreds, and the treasurers, and them who were entrusted with the care of the king's substance, and of all his possessions, and of his children, with the chamberlains and the worthies and the soldiers of the army at Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he stood up in the midst of the assembly and said, Hear me, my brethren and my people, I had it on my mind to build a house of rest for the ark of the covenant of the Lord, and a place for the feet of our Lord, and had provided what were suitable for the building;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>but God said, Thou shalt not build a house for me, to be called by my name; for thou art a warrior and hast shed much blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now the Lord God of Israel chose me in preference to all my father's house to be king over Israel forever, As he chose the royalty in Juda, and my father's house out of the house of Juda and among the sons of my father, it was his pleasure that I should be king over all Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>so in preference to all my sons, for the Lord hath given me many sons, he hath made choice of my son Solomon, to set him on the throne of the Lord's kingdom, over Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And God hath said to me, Thy son Solomon shall build my house, and my court; for I have chosen him to be my son; and I will be to him a father;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and I will establish his kingdom forever, provided he exert his power to keep my commandments and my judgments as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now therefore, in the presence of all the congregation of the Lord, and in the audience of our God, I adjure you to keep and to seek all the commandments of the Lord our God, that you may possess this good land and leave it for an inheritance for your children after you forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And now, Solomon, my son, know thou the God of thy fathers, and serve him with a perfect heart and a willing mind; for the Lord searcheth all hearts and knoweth every thought. If thou seek him, he will be found by thee; but if thou forsake him, he will at last forsake thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Observe now, since the Lord hath chosen thee to build a house for him for a sanctuary, be strong and do it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then David gave his son Solomon the model of the temple, and its houses and its treasuries, and of the upper chambers and the inner depositories, and of the house for the propitiation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and the plan which he had in his mind of the courts of the house of the Lord, and of all the chambers round about; those for store houses for the house of the Lord; and of the depositories for the holy things, and the lodging rooms;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and of the daily courses of the priests and the Levites, for all the work of the service of the house of the Lord; and of the depositories for the vessels used in the service of the house of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and the exact weight of these vessels, whether made of gold or of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He gave him the weight of the candle sticks and of the lamps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He gave him likewise the weight of the tables for the shew bread; of every table made of gold, and likewise of those to be made of silver;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and of the flesh forks and the libation cups, and of the cups of gold; the weight both of those to be made of gold and of those to be made of silver; and of the censers, of each its several weight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and pointed out to him the weight of the utensils of the altar of incense, which was to be of pure gold; and the model of the chariot of the cherubims with expanded wings, which over shadow the ark of the covenant of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>All these David gave to Solomon in a drawing of the hand of the Lord, according to the knowledge given him of the workmanship of the model.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then David said to his son Solomon, Be strong and of good courage and do the work. Fear not nor be dismayed; for the Lord my God is with thee. He will not leave thee nor forsake thee, till thou hast finished all the work for the service of the house of the Lord. And behold this is the model of the temple, and of his house and his treasury, and the upper rooms and the inner depositories, and the house of the propitiation; even the model of the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And these are the courses of the priests and the Levites, for all the service of the house of the Lord. And there will be with thee for the work, every artist skilled in every art, and all the chiefs and all the people to execute all thy commands.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then king David said to all the congregation, My son Solomon whom the Lord hath chosen, is young and tender, and the work is great; for it is not for man but for the Lord God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>According to my utmost ability I have provided for the house of my God, gold, silver, brass, iron, wood, stones of Soam, and stones to be set, precious and variegated, every kind of precious stones, and Parian marble in abundance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Moreover, because I have set my affection on the house of my God, the gold and silver which I kept for myself, behold this I have given for the house of my God, over and above what I provided for the house of the Holies;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>three thousand talents of the gold of Souphir, and seven thousand talents of pure silver, for overlaying therewith the walls of the sanctuary,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the gold for that to be done with gold, and the silver for that to be done with silver, and for every work to be made by the hand of artists. Now let every one who is so inclined fill his hands this day for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thereupon the chiefs of families, and the chiefs of the sons of Israel, and the captains of thousands, and the captains of hundreds, and the overseers of the king's works and his builders, were liberally disposed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and gave for the works of the house of the Lord five thousand talents and ten thousand pieces of gold, and ten thousand talents of silver, and eighteen thousand talents of brass, and a hundred thousand talents of iron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And they who had precious stones gave them for the treasures of the house of the Lord which were under the care of Jeiel the Gersonite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the people were rejoiced at this readiness, for with a per feet heart they gave liberally to the Lord. And David the king was exceedingly rejoiced,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and blessed the Lord in the presence of the assembly, saying, Blessed art thou Lord God of Israel, our Father, from everlasting to everlasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>To thee, Lord, be ascribed greatness, and power, and exultation, and victory, and majesty; for thou hast dominion over all things in heaven and on earth. At thy presence every king and nation is struck with awe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>From thee come riches and glory; Thou, Lord, rulest over all. Thou art the head of all dominion, and in thy hand is majesty and power. And by thy hand, Almighty Sovereign, all things are made great and strong.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now therefore, Lord, to thee we render thanks; and we praise thy glorious name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But who am I, and what is my people, that we should be enabled to shew such liberality to thee. For all things are thine and of thine own we have given thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For we before thee are strangers and sojourners as all our fathers were. Our days on earth are like a shadow and there is no fixed abiding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Lord our God, all this store which I have provided for building a house to thy holy name is from thy bounty, and belongeth all to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>As I know, O Lord, that thou triest hearts and lovest righteousness, I have with singleness of heart freely offered all these things, and have now seen with joy all thy people who are here present freely offering to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Lord, the God of Abraham and Isaak and Israel our fathers, keep these things forever in the thoughts of the hearts of thy people and direct their hearts to thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and give to my son Solomon a good heart to execute all thy commandments, and thy testimonies, and thy statutes, and that he may finish completely the structure of thy house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then David said to all the congregation, Bless ye the Lord our God. And all the congregation blessed the Lord the God of their fathers, and with bended knees made a reverence to the Lord and to the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And on the morrow of the first day, when David had offered up whole burnt offerings to God, he sacrificed as thank offerings to the Lord a thousand young bulls, a thousand rams, a thousand lambs with their libations, and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And having eaten and drunk that day with gladness before the Lord, they proclaimed Solomon son of David king a second time, and anointed him to be king for the Lord, and Sadok to be priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So Solomon sat on the throne of his father David and prospered, and all Israel obeyed him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The chiefs, and the men in authority, and all the sons of king David his father were subject to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and the Lord magnified Solomon over all Israel, and gave him royal glory, such as no king had before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>When David son of Jessai had reigned over Israel forty years;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>seven years at Chebron and thirty three at Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>he died at a good old age, full of days, riches and glory. And Solomon his son reigned in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now the rest of the acts of David, the first and the last, are written among the words of Samuel the seer, and in the words of Nathan the prophet, and in the words of Gad the seer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>touching all his reign, and his mighty power, and the times which happened to him, and to Israel, and to all the kingdoms of the land.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>