<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The words of Nehemias, son of Chelkia. In the month Chaseleu of the twentieth year, when I was at Susanabira,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Anani, one of my brethren, came with certain men of Juda, and I inquired of them concerning the remnant who were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and they informed me that the remnant of the captivity who were left, were in that country in great affliction and reproach, and that the walls of Jerusalem continued demolished, and that the gates thereof were burned with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Upon hearing this report, I sat down and wept and mourned some days, fasting and praying before the God of heaven,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and I said, I beseech thee, Lord, God of heaven, the Mighty, the Great and the Awful, who keepest thy covenant and thy mercy with them who love thee and keep thy commandments,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>let thine ear, I beseech thee, be attentive, and thine eyes open, that thou mayst hear the prayer of thy servant which I now make before thee day and night, for the children of Israel thy servants, and plead for their sins which we have committed against thee. Both I and my father's house have sinned against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>We have broken covenant with thee, and have not kept the commandments, and the statutes, and the judgments, which thou gavest in charge to thy servant Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Remember, I beseech thee, the word which thou didst give in charge to Moses thy servant, saying, When you break covenant with me, and I scatter you among the nations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>if you then return to me and keep my commandments and do them, though your dispersion may be to the farthest part of heaven, thence I will gather them and bring them to the place which I have chosen for my name to dwell there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now they are thy servants and thy people, whom thou hast redeemed with thy great power, and with thy strong hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Turn not away, I beseech thee, Lord. But let thine ear be attentive to the prayer of thy servant, and to the prayer of thy children, who desire to fear thy name: and prosper, I beseech thee, thy servant this day, and grant him favour in the sight of this man. Now I was the king's butler,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and in the month Nisan of the twentieth year of king Arthasastha, the wine being before me, I took the wine, and when I had given it to the king (now there was none besides me in waiting)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the king said to me, Why is thy countenance sad, and thou not at thine ease? this is nothing but grief of heart. At this I was greatly terrified</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and said to the king, Let the king live forever! Why should not my countenance be sad, seeing the city, the house of my father's sepulchre, is in a state of desolation, and the gates thereof burned with fire?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon the king said to me, For what dost thou make request? And when I had prayed to the God of heaven,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I said to the king, If it seemeth good to the king, and if thy servant shall find favour in thy sight, that thou wouldst send me to Juda to the city of the sepulchres of my fathers, and let me rebuild it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon this the king said to me (now his concubine was sitting by him) For how long shall thy journey be, and when wilt thou return? So the king being pleased to send me, I set him a time</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and said to the king, If it seemeth good to the king, let him give me letters to the governors beyond the river, that they may conduct me on in my journey till I come to Juda;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and a letter to Asaph, the keeper of the king's forest, that he may supply me with timber to cover the gates and for the wall of the city, and for a house to which I may go. So the king gave me, as the hand of God was favourable,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and I came to the governors beyond the river, and delivered them the king's letters. Now the king sent with me captains of the army and horsemen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But when Sanaballat the Aronite and Tobia the servant, the Ammonite, heard this, it grieved them that a man was come to promote the welfare of the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now when I came to Jerusalem and had been there three days,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I arose by night, I and a few men with me, but I did not tell a man what God had put into my heart to do for Jerusalem; and there was not a beast with me but that on which I rode;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and I went out at the gate Golela on to the mouth of the well of fig trees, and on to the dung gate, tracing the wall of Jerusalem which had been demolished, and the gates of which were burned with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then I passed on to the gate of Ain and to the king's pool. But there being no place for the beast under me to pass,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I continued going up by night along the wall of the valley. And having hastily traced the wall, and come to the valley gate, I returned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now the watchmen did not know why I went nor what I was doing; for I had not yet told the Jews, nor the priests, nor the nobles, nor the officers of the army, nor the rest who were to do the work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then I said to them, You see the distress in which we are! How Jerusalem is a waste, and the gates thereof have been given to the flames. Come, let us build up the wall of Jerusalem that we may no longer be a reproach.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when I told them of the good hand of God which was upon me, and the words which the king spoke to me, and said, Let us arise and build; their hands were strengthened for this good work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But when Sanaballat the Aronite, and Tobia the servant the Ammonite and Gesem the Arab heard, they laughed at us, and came to us and said, What is this which you are doing? Are you going to rebel against the king?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In reply to which I said, The God of heaven will prosper us, as we his servants are pure and will go on with the building; but you have no portion, nor right, nor memorial in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So Eliasub the high priest arose with his brethren the priests, and having built the sheep gate, they consecrated it and set up the gates thereof. They consecrated as far as the tower of the hundred, and to the tower of Anameel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>even to the work performed by the chiefs of the children of Jericho and to the work performed by the children of Zakchur son of Amari.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the fish gate was built by the sons of Asana. Having covered it, they covered also the doors thereof and the locks and bars thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And next to them the chief of the children of Ramoth son of Ouria, son of Akkos, continued on the work. And next to them Mosollam son of Barachias, son of Mazebel continued it on.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And next to them it was continued on by Sadok son of Baana. And next to them the Thekoites continued it, but their nobles did not put their neck to their work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And Joida son of Phasek and Mesulam son of Basodia repaired the gate Jasanai. They covered it and set up the doors thereof, and the locks and the bars thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And next to them Maltias the Gabaonite and Evaron the Meronothite, the chiefs of Gabaon and Maspha continued the repairs to the throne of the governor on this side the river.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And next to him Oziel son of Arachias with the gold smiths continued the repairs, and next to them Ananias a chief of the apothecaries fortified, and they left Jerusalem behind them to the broad wall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And next to them the fortifications were carried on by Raphaia son of Sur, the chief of one half of the environs of Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And next to them Jedaia son of Eromaph fortified over against his house And Attuth son of Asabania fortified next to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the next who fortified was Melchias son of Eram, then Asub son of Phaath-moab; and they continued on to the tower of Thanurim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And next to him the fortifications were continued by Sallum son of Alloes, the chief of the half of the environs of Jerusalem; by him and his daughters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The gate of the valley was secured by Anun and the inhabitants of Zano. They built it and set up the doors thereof, and the locks and the bars thereof, and built a thousand cubits of the wall even to the dung gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the dung gate was secured by Melchia son of Rechab, chief of the Bethakcharim ward; by him and his sons. They covered it and set up the doors thereof, and the gates and the bars thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the gate of the fountain was secured by Solomon son of Choleze, a chief of a part of Maspha. He rebuilded and covered it, and set up the doors and the bars thereof, and built the wall of the pool of poppies by the king's garden, continuing it on to the stairs coming down from the city of David,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And after him Nehemias son of Azabuch, chief of the half of Bethsur ward, continued the fortifications to the garden of David's sepulchre and to the artificial pool and to Bethaggarim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And after him the fortifications were continued by the Levites, by Raum son of Bani, and next to</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>him by Asabia chief of the half of Keila ward, in his ward; and after him by their brethren, Benei son of Enadad, chief of the half of Keila ward;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and next to him Azur son of Jesus, the chief of Masphai repaired one curtain of the tower of Ascent which united them at the corner;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and after him Barach son of Zabu, repaired the other curtain from the corner to the door of Betheliasub which belonged to the chief priest;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and after him Meramoth son of Ouria son of Akkos, another piece from the door of Betheliasub to the termination of that house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And after him the priests, the men of Ekkechar continued the repairs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>After him Benjamin repaired, and Asub over against their house; And after him Azarias son of Maasias son of Anania, repaired adjoining to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>After him Bani son of Adad, repaired the next curtain from Bethazaria to the corner;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but as far as the curve over against the corner, including the tower projecting from the king's house above the court of the guard house, was the work of Phalach son of Euzai; and after him was Phadaia son of Phoros,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and the Nathanims who dwelt at Ophal, even to the garden of the water gate eastward, and they had also the tower which projecteth outwards;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and after him the Thekoites had the curtain over against the great projecting tower and onward to the wall of Ophla.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Above the horse gate the priests repaired every man over against his house:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and after them Sadduk son of Emmer repaired over against his house; and after him repaired Samaia, son of Sechenia, the keeper of the eastern gate;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and after him Anania, son of Selemia, and Anom the sixth son of Seleph had the next curtain; and after Lim Mesulam, son of Barachia had over against his treasury office;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and after him Melchia son of Sarephi had as far as Bethan-nathanim; and the haberdashers were over against the Maphekad and as far as the ascent of the curve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and the brasiers and the haberdashers had between that and the sheep gate.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when Sanaballat heard that we were building the wall it appeared evil to him and he was much incensed, and railed against the Jews,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and said before his brethren, Is the army of Somoron reduced to this, that these Jews are building their city? They are indeed offering sacrifice; but can they prevail? Can they heal the stones after being burned to a heap of dust?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thereupon Tobias the Ammonite came near him and said to them, Can they either sacrifice or eat in that place of theirs? Cannot a fox go up and demolish their stone walls?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hear, our God, how we are made a laughing stock, and turn their reproach back on their own head, and make them an object of derision in a land of captivity,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and cover not their iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But when Sanaballat and Tobias, and the Arabs and the Ammonites, heard that the walls of Jerusalem advanced in height, and that the breaches began to be stopped, it appeared to them very vexatious,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and they all assembled together to come and attack Jerusalem, and lay it waste.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Upon this we prayed to our God, and posted our guards against them day and night for fear of them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>though Juda said, Were the power of these enemies broken, there is so much rubbish that we cannot build the wall;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and they who afflicted us said, They shall not know nor see till we are in the midst of them, and slay them, and cause the work to cease.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when the Jews who dwelt near them came and told us, They are coming against us from all quarters,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I then posted, for the lowest parts of the place in the fortified posts behind the wall, the spear men and bow men; and stationed the people with their swords by communities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and having taken a view, I arose and said to the nobles, and to the officers, and to the rest of the people, Be not afraid of them. Remember our God who is great and terrible; and fight for your brethren, your sons, your daughters, your wives and your houses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when our enemies heard that we had got intelligence; and God had frustrated their designs, we all returned to the wall, every man to his work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And from that day one half of them who had been drawn off carried on the work, and the other half was kept ready with spears and shields, and bows and breast plates; and the chiefs were behind all the house of Juda</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>who were building the wall. And they who were employed in carrying burdens were armed. With one hand they did their work, and with the other grasped a javelin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the builders had every man his sword girded on his loins while they were building. And near every chief was a trumpeter with a horn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I said to the nobles and to the chiefs, and to the rest of the people, The work is extensive and large, and we are scattered on the wall, one chief far from another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In what place soever you hear the sound of the trumpet, thither you must assemble to us, and our God will fight for us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So while we were carrying on the work, one half of them held their spears from break of day till the stars appeared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And at that time I said to the people, let every man with his youths, lodge in Jerusalem, and let the night be devoted to watching and the day to work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now I myself mounted guard, and the men on duty attended me, and not a man of us put off our clothes.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now there was a great cry of the people and their wives, against their brethren the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>There were some who said, We with our sons and our daughters are many, therefore we will take corn that we may eat and live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>There were others who said, As for our fields and our vineyards and our houses, let us mortgage them that we may get corn and eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>There were others who said, We have borrowed money to pay the king's tribute, and pledged our fields and our vineyards and our houses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and now our flesh is the same as that of our brethren, our sons the same as theirs, yet behold we are subjecting our sons and our daughters to be slaves, nay, some of our daughters are already subjected to bondage, and we have no means to redeem them, for our nobles have got our fields and our vineyards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon hearing their cry and these speeches, I was exceedingly grieved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And having consulted in my own mind, I chid the nobles and the chiefs, and said to them, would any man exact of his brother what you exact? Then having assembled a great meeting against them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I said to them, We with our free will offerings have purchased' our brethren the Jews who were sold to the nations; and are you going to sell your brethren that they may be sold to us? And when they held their peace and found no answer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I said, This thing which you do is not good. It is not in this manner that you are in the fear of our God to avoid the reproach of the nations, our enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>My brethren and my acquaintances, and I myself, have lent them money and provisions. Let us I pray you relinquish our demands for this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Restore to them, I beseech you, this very day their fields, and their vineyards, and their olive yards, and their houses; and abate the price at which you have sold to each other corn and wine and oil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thereupon they said, We will restore, and require nothing of them. We will do as thou sayest. Then I called the priests and having caused them to swear that they would do according to this decree,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I shook my lap and said, So may God shake every man who will not perform this promise, out of his house and from his labour, and let them be shaken out and emptied. And all the congregation said, Amen; and praised the Lord, and the people executed the decree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>From the day I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Juda; from the twentieth to the thirty second year of Arthasastha; for twelve years, I and my brethren did not eat the daily allowance which was their due;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>those daily allowances with which they who were before me had loaded them, and which they had exacted from them in bread and wine, to the amount at least of forty didrachms of silver. They indeed who had been displaced, tyrannised over the people; but as for me I did not do so; because I feared God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Even in the work of the wall, I did not domineer over them; nor did I purchase a field: and all who were employed with me there in the work,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>even a hundred and fifty chief men of the Jews, besides those who came to us, from the nations around us, were at my table.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the daily provisions for my table, was one ox, six choice sheep, and a kid for myself; and every ten days wine in plenty for all. Yet for all this I did not demand the daily allowance of bread, because the bondage was heavy upon the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Remember me, my God, for good, for all I have done for this people.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when Sanaballat and Tobias and Gesam the Arab, and the rest of our enemies heard that I had built the wall, and that there was no opening left therein; (at that time I had not fixed up the doors in the gates,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Sanaballat and Gesam sent to me saying, Come let us have a meeting at the villages in the plain of Ono, intending to do me some mischief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Upon which I sent messengers to them saying, I am engaged in a great work, and cannot go down, lest the work should stop. Soon as I have completed it, I will go down to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Again they sent to me to the same effect, and I returned them the same answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Sanaballat sent his servant to me with an open letter in his hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>in which was written, It is reported among the nations that thou and the Jews intend to rebel; that for this purpose thou art rebuilding the wall; and that thou art to be their king:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and besides this that thou hast set up prophets for thyself that thou mayst make thyself king in Jerusalem over Juda. Now these reports will be told to the king, now therefore come and let us consult together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>In reply to which I sent to him saying, There is no foundation for the reports as thou mentionest them, for thou thyself feignest them out of thine own heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Because all were trying to terrify us saying, Their hands must be weakened from this work, so that it may not be accomplished, therefore on this occasion I strengthened my hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So when I went to the house of Semei, son of Dalaia, son of Metabaal, he became enrapt and said, Let us repair to the house of God; into the midst thereof; and shut the doors thereof; for they are coming by night to kill us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But I said, What sort of a man must he be who would go into the house of God to save his life!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And upon inquiry I found that God had not sent him, and that his prophecy was a contrivance against me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and that Tobias and Sanaballat had hired a multitude against me, that I might be frightened, and act in this manner, and take a wrong step, and fall into disrepute, that they might reproach me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Remember, God, Tobias and Sanaballat, according to these doings of theirs; and Noadias the prophet, and the rest of the prophets, who tried to terrify me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now the wall was finished on. the five and twentieth day of the month Elul, in fifty two days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when all our enemies heard; all the nations around us were terrified, and great fear fell upon them; for they saw plainly that the perfecting of this work was of our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>In those days many of the nobles of Juda sent letters to Tobias, and received letters from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For many in Juda were affined to him, for he was the son in law of Sechenias, son of Erae, and his son Jonan had married a daughter of Mesulam, son of Barachias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and they kept on, telling me what he said and conveying to him what I said. And Tobias sent letters to frighten me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the keepers were reviewed and the musicians and the Levites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I gave a charge to my brother Ananias, and to Ananias chief of Bira in Jerusalem; for he was a man of truth, and feared God above many;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and I said to them, The gates of Jerusalem must not be opened till sunrise. And when the watch is set, let the doors be shut and well bolted, and appoint guards of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every man in his ward, and every man over against his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>As the city was of large extent, and the people therein few, and the houses were not rebuilt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>God put it into my heart, and I had collected the nobles and the chiefs, and the people into classes, having found a book of the enrollment of those who first came up, in which I found written:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now these are the children of the province who came up from the captivity; from the distant abode to which Nabuchodonosar the king of Babylon had sent them, and who returned, every man to his city,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>with Zorobabel and Jesus, and Nehemias, Azarias and Reelma, Naemani, Mordecai, Balsan, Maspharath, Esdra, Baguia, Inaum, Baana, Masphar, head men of the people of Israel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The children of Pharos, two thousand a hundred and seventy two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The children of Saphatia, three hundred and seventy two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The children of Era, six hundred and fifty two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The children of Phaath-moab, descendants of Jesu and Joab, two thousand six hundred and eighteen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The children of Ailam, a thousand two hundred and fifty four;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The children of Zathuia, eight hundred and forty five;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The children of Zakchu, seven hundred and sixty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The children of Banui, six hundred and forty eight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The children of Bebi, six hundred and twenty eight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The children of Esgad, two thousand three hundred and twenty two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The children of Adonikam, six hundred and sixty seven;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The children of Bagoi, two thousand and sixty seven;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The children of Edin, six hundred and fifty five;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The children of Ater, descendants of Ezekias, ninety eight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The children of Esam, three hundred and twenty eight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The children of Besei, three hundred and twenty four;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The children of Ariph, a hundred and twelve; The children of Asen, two hundred and twenty three;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The children of Gabaon, ninety five;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The children of Baithalem, a hundred and twenty three; The children of Atopha, fifty six;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The children of Anathoth, a hundred and twenty eight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The men of Bethasmoth, forty two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The men of Kariathiarim, Kaphira and Beroth, seven hundred and forty three;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The men of Arama and Gabaa, six hundred and twenty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The men of Machemas, a hundred and twenty two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The men of Baithel and Ai, a hundred and twenty three;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>The men of Nabia, a hundred and fifty two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>The men of Elamaar, a thousand two hundred and fifty two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The children of Eram, three hundred and twenty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>The children of Jericho, three hundred and forty five;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>The children of Lodadid and Ono, seven hundred and twenty one:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>The children of Sanana, three thousand nine hundred and thirty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>The Priests. The children of Jodae, for the house of Jesus, nine hundred and seventy three;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>The children of Emmer, a thousand and fifty two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The children of Phaseur, a thousand two hundred and forty seven;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>The children of Eram, a thousand and seventeen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>The Levites. The children of Jesus and Kadmiel, descendants of Ouduia, seventy four.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>The musicians, the children of Asaph, a hundred and eighty eight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>The keepers of the gates, the Salumites, the Aterites, the Telmonites, the Akubites, the Atites, the Sabites, a hundred and thirty eight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>The Nathinims, The Seas', the Asphas, the Tabaoths',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>the Kiras, the Asuias, the Phadons',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>the Labanas, the Agabas, the Selmeis',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>the Anans, the Gadels, the Gaars',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>the Raaias, the Rassons, the Nekodas',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>the Gersams', the Ozis', the Pheses',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>the Besis', the Meinons', the Nephosasis',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>the Bakbuks', the Achiphas', the Aroers',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>the Basaloths', the Midas', the Adasons',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>the Barkoues', the Sisaraths', the Themas',</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>the Nisias, the Atiphas'.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>The children of Solomon's servants, the Suteis, the Sapharats, the Pheridas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>the Jelels, the Dorkons, the Gadaels,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>the Saphatias', the Ettels, the Phakaraths, the Sabaims, the Emins,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>all these Nathinims and the children of Solomon's servants, three hundred and ninety two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>These also came up from Thelmeleth, Thelaresa, Charub, Eron, Jemer, but could not shew the houses of their families, nor their seed, whether they are of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>namely, the children of Dalaia, the children of Tobia, the children of Nekoda, six hundred and forty two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>And of the priests: the children of Ebia, the children of Akos, the children of Berzelli, (for they had married some of the daughters of Berzelli, the Galaadite, and were called by their names);</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>these sought the register of their genealogy, but it could not be found. Though they were related to the priesthood,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>yet the Athersastha ordered, that they should not eat of the most holy meats, until a priest should arise with the Manifestation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>The whole congregation was about forty two thousand three hundred and sixty,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>exclusive of their men servants and maid servants, the number of whom was seven thousand three hundred and thirty seven, and the choristers of both sexes, two hundred and forty five.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>Their asses were two thousand seven hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>As some of the heads of the families had given for the work; to Nehemias, for the treasury, a thousand pieces of gold, fifty cups, and thirty vestures for the priests;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>the other heads of the families gave for the treasures of the work, twenty thousand pieces of gold, and two thousand three hundred mnas of silver;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>and the rest of the people gave twenty thousand pieces of gold, and two thousand two hundred mnas of silver, and sixty seven vestures for the priests.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="73">
      <content>Now the priests and the Levites, and the keepers of the gates and the musicians, and some of the people, and the Nathinims, and all Israel, had taken up their abode in their cities;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>but when the seventh month was come, the sons of Israel who were in their cities, and all the people, assembled like one man, in the street which is before the water gate, and spoke to Esdras the scribe to bring out the book of the law of Moses, which the Lord had enjoined on Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So Esdras the priest, brought out the law before the congregation, consisting of men and women, even all who had understanding, to hear it, on the first day of the seventh month,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and read therein from sun rising to mid day, before the men and the women, even all who were capable of understanding. And the ears of all the people were attentive to the book of the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now Esdras the scribe stood on a wooden scaffold, and there stood near him Matthathias and Samaias and Ananias and Ourias and Chelkia and Maasia on his right; and on his left, Phadaias and Misael and Melchias and Asom and Asabadma, and Zacharias and Mesollom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And Esdras opened the book in the presence of all the people, for he was above them. And when he opened it all the prophets stood up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then Esdras blessed the Lord the great God. And all the people answered and said, Amen, with uplifted hands. Then they bowed down and worshipped the Lord with their faces to the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And Jesus and Banaias and Sarabias proceeded to instruct the people in the law, and the people kept their station.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when they had read in the book of the law of God, Esdras taught and enforced it with a knowledge of the Lord, so that the people gained understanding by the reading.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then spake Nehemias; when Esdras the priest and scribe and the Levites and they who instructed the people, had said to all the people, This day is holy to the Lord our God, mourn not nor weep (for all the people wept when they heard the words of the law)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>then he said to them, Go, eat dainty meats, and drink sweet wine and send portions to them who have none, for this day is holy to the Lord; and do not despond; for the Lord is our strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the Levites stilled all the people, saying, Hold your peace for this is a holy day and do not despond.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So all the people went away to eat and drink, and send portions and make great joy, because they had gained knowledge by the words which were explained to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And on the second day, when the heads of the families with all the people and the priests and the Levites, were assembled before Esdras the scribe, to attend to all the words of the law,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>they found it written in the law which the Lord had given in charge to Moses, That the Israelites should dwell in booths at the festival in the seventh month,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and that they should sound trumpets in all their cities and in Jerusalem. Whereupon Esdras said, Go out to the mountains and bring in olive branches, and branches of cypress trees and myrtle branches and palm branches, and the branches of every bushy tree to make booths according to what is written.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Accordingly the people went out and brought them, and made for themselves booths, every man on his house top, and in their court yards, and in the courts of the house of God, and in the streets of the city, even to the gate of Ephraim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when all the congregation; all who had returned from captivity, had made themselves booths and sat therein, because the Israelites had not done so from the days of Joshua son of Nave even to that day, the joy was great.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>So he read in the book of the law of God, day by day, from the first day to the last. And when they had kept the festival for seven days, on the eighth day they kept the exod according to custom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And on the twenty fourth day of the same month, the children of Israel were assembled, fasting, and in sackcloth, and with earth on their heads,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and having separated themselves from every stranger, they stood and confessed their sins and the iniquities of their fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When they had stood in their place and had the book of the law of the Lord their God read to them, and had made confession to the Lord and worshipped the Lord their God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>then Jesus stood on the step of the Levites with the sons of Kadmiel, Sechenia son of Sarabia, the sons of Choneni: and when they had cried with a loud voice to the Lord their God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and the Levites, Jesus and Kadmiel said, Arise, bless ye the Lord our God; from everlasting to everlasting let them bless thy glorious name, and exalt it with all blessing and praise, then Esdras said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thou art thyself the only Lord. Thou hast made the heaven and the heaven of heaven with all their host, the earth and all the things therein, the seas and all which are in them; and thou quickenest them all; and the armies of heaven worship thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thou art the Lord God. Having made choice of Abram, thou didst lead him out from the country of the Chaldees and give him the name of Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And finding his heart faithful before thee, thou madest a covenant with him, to give him the land of the Chananites and the Chettites and the Amorites and the Pherezites and the Jebusites and the Gergasites, even to his seed, and hast performed thy words, for thou art righteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou didst see the affliction of our fathers in Egypt and didst hear their cry at the Red Sea:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and having shewn signs and wonders in Egypt on Pharao and on all his servants and on all his people, because thou knewest that they had behaved proudly against them, and made thyself a name as at this day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>thou didst cleave the sea before them, and they passed through the midst of the sea on dry ground, but those who were pursuing thou didst cast into the deep like a stone in boisterous water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>With a pillar of cloud thou didst guide them by day; and by night with a pillar of fire, to illumine the way for them in which they should go:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>thou camest down also on mount Sina and didst speak to them from heaven, and give them right judgments and laws of truth and statutes and good commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou madest known to them thy holy sabbaths and didst prescribe for them commandments and statutes and a law by the ministry of thy servant Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thou gavest them also bread from heaven for their food, and didst bring water for them out of a rock for their thirst, ordering them to go in and take possession of the land which thou hadst stretched forth thy hand to give them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But they, even our fathers, behaved proudly and hardened their neck, and hearkened not to thy commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Though they refused to go in, and were unmindful of thy wonders which thou hadst done among them; though they hardened their neck, and set up a head to return to their bondage in Egypt, yet thou who art a God merciful and gracious, long suffering and of great kindness, didst not forsake them utterly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Even before this, though they made themselves a molten calf and said, These are the gods which brought us up out of Egypt, and committed great provocations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>yet thou through thy manifold mercies didst not leave them in the wilderness. Thou didst not withdraw from them by day the pillar of a cloud which was to guide them in the way, nor the pillar of fire, at night, which was to illumine the way for them in which they should go;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but gavest thy good spirit to instruct them; and not withholding thy manna from their mouth, thou gavest them water when they were athirst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thus didst thou sustain them forty years in the wilderness, not suffering them to want any thing. Their clothes did not wear out, nor were their feet galled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then thou gavest them kingdoms, and didst divide peoples among them; so they took possession of the land of Seon king of Esebon, and of the land of Og king of Basan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And having multiplied their children as the stars of heaven, thou broughtest them into the land which thou hadst promised their fathers; and they took possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But when thou hadst subdued before them the inhabitants of the land of the Chananites, and delivered them into their hands; both the kings and the people of the land, to do with them as they thought fit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and they had taken lofty cities, and got possession of houses filled with all good things, of cisterns ready hewn out of stone, of vineyards and olive yards, and all sorts of fruit trees in abundance, and had eaten and were filled, and became fat, they rioted on thy great bounty,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and turned and apostatised from thee, and cast thy law behind their backs: Nay, they slew thy prophets who testified against them to turn them to thee; and committed great provocations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Therefore thou didst deliver them into the hand of their enemies, who afflicted them. But when, in the time of their distress they cried to thee, thou from heaven didst hear, and in thy tender mercies which are great, thou didst send them deliverers, and save them out of the hand of them who were afflicting them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Yet soon as they had rest, they returned to do evil in thy sight, therefore thou didst leave them in the hand of their enemies, who exercised dominion over them. But again when they cried to thee, thou from heaven didst hearken, and in the multitude of thy tender mercies didst deliver them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and admonish them to return to thy law. When they hearkened not, but transgressed thy commandments and thy judgments, (which if a man practise he shall live thereby) and turned back rebelliously, and hardened their neck, and would not hear,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and thou hadst borne with them many years, and testified against them by thy Spirit; by the ministry of thy prophets; and they did not give ear, though thou didst deliver them into the hands of the people of the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>yet in the multitude of thy tender mercies thou didst not give them up to utter destruction, nor quite forsake them. Seeing thou art mighty and merciful, and tenderly compassionate;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>now therefore, our God, the Mighty, the Great, the Powerful and the Awful, who keepest thy covenant and thy mercy, let not all the trouble be accounted light in thy sight, which hath come upon us, and our kings, and our chiefs, and our priests, and our prophets, and our fathers, and on all thy people from the days of the kings of Assur even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Thou indeed art righteous in all that have come upon us. For thou hast acted with truth; but we have sinned greatly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Our kings, and our chiefs, and our priests, and our fathers, have not kept thy law, nor hearkened to thy commandments and thy testimonies which thou hast testified against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Even in thine own kingdom, and during that abundant bounty of thine which thou didst bestow on them, and in this extensive and rich country which thou gavest before them, they have not served thee, nor turned away from their wicked devices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Behold we are now slaves, and as for this land which thou gavest to our fathers to eat the fruits thereof, and the good things thereof, behold we are slaves in it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and its abundant fruits belong to those kings whom for our sins thou hast set over us, and who have dominion over our bodies, and who can do with our cattle what they please, so that we are in great affliction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>In a due sense, therefore, of all these things we pledge our faith, we by writing, and our chiefs, our Levites, and our priests by sealing;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>(note they who sealed were Nehemias the Artasastha, son of Achelia, and Sedekias son of Araia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and Azaria and Jeremia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Phasur, Amaria, Melchia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Attics, Sebani, Maluch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Iram, Meramoth, Abdia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Daniel, Gannathon, Baruch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Mosulam, Abia, Miamin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Maasia, Belgai, Samaia: And these priests</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and Levites, Jesus son of Azania, Banaiu, of the sons of Enadad, Kadmiel</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and his brethren, Sabania, Oduia, Kalitan, Phelia, Anan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Micha, Rohob, Asebias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Zakchur, Sarabia, Sebania,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Odum, sons of Banuai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>the chiefs of the people, Phoros, Phaath Moab, Elam, Zatthuia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>sons of Bani, Asgad, Bebai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Adania, Bargoi, Edin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Ater, Ezelda, Azur,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Oduia, Esam, Besi,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Ariph, Anathoth, Nobai,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Megaphes, Mesullam, Ezir,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Mesozebel, Saduk, Jeddua,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Phaltia, Anan, Anaia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Osee, Anania, Asub,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Aloes, Phalai, Sobek,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Reum, Essabana, Maasia</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and Aia, Ainan, Eram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Maluch, Eram, Baana:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and the rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the keepers of the gates, the musicians, the Nathinims, and every one who came from among the people of the land to the law of God, their wives, their sons, their daughters, every one who had knowledge and understanding,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>were urgent with their brethren, and bound themselves with an oath, entering into a curse and an oath;) that we will walk in the law of God, which was given by the ministry of Moses the servant of God, to keep and to do all the commandments of the Lord and his judgments and his statutes;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and that we will not give our daughters to the people of the land; nor will we take their daughters for our sons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and that with regard to the people of the country who bring wares or any thing to sell on the sabbath day, we will not buy of them on the sabbath, or on a holy day: and that every seventh year we will remit every demand of what kind soever:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and that we will confirm the commands upon us to give every year a third of a didrachm for the service of the house of our God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>for the presence loaves and the sacrifice of the daily oblation and for the whole burnt offering of every day, of the sabbaths, of the new moons, for the festivals and for the holy things, namely, the sin offerings to make atonement for Israel, and for the works of the house of our God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and that we the priests and the Levites and the people who have cast lots touching the bringing of wood, will bring it for the house of our God, for the house of our families, at the set times and seasons yearly, to be burned on the altar of the Lord our God, as it is written in the law:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and that we will bring the first fruits of our land, and the first fruits of every fruit tree yearly to the house of the Lord, and do,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>with regard to the first born of our sons and our cattle, as it is written in the law; that we will bring the firstlings of our herds and our flocks to the house of our God for the priests, who minister in the house of our God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and that we will bring the dedications of our corn including the fruit of trees, and of wine and oil to the stores of the house of God for the priests; and the tythe of our land for the Levites. But the Levites themselves shall receive the tythes in all the cities of our bondage;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and the priest, the son of Aaron, shall share with the Levite in the Levite's tythe; and the Levites shall carry the tythe of their tythe to the house of our God; to the store houses for the house of our God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>because the children of Israel including the children of Levi are to carry the dedications of their corn, their wine and their oil to these treasuries, and the holy vessels and the priests and the ministering servants and the keepers of the gates and the musicians are to be there, therefore we will not forsake the house of our God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the chiefs of the people dwelt at Jerusalem, and the rest of the people cast lots to bring one of every ten to dwell in Jerusalem, the holy city, and nine parts in their cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the people blessed all those men who were of their own accord willing to dwell in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now these are chiefs of the country who dwelt in Jerusalem and the cities of Juda. There dwelt every man in his possession in their cities, Israel, the priest and the Levites and the Nathinims and the children of Solomon's servants:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and there dwelt in Jerusalem some of the sons of Juda and some of the sons of Benjamin; of the sons of Juda, Athaia, son Azia, son Zacharia, son Samaria, son Saphatia, son Maleleel; and of the sons of Phares</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>also, Maasia, son Baruch, son Chalaza, son Ozia, son Adaia, son Joarib, the son of Zacharias, the son of the Selonite;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>all these sons of Phares who dwelt in Jerusalem were four hundred and sixty eight men of array.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And these were the sons of Benjamin, Selo, son Mesulom, son Joad, son Phadaia, son Choleia, son Maasias, son Ethiel, son Jesia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and after him, Gebe, Sele, nine hundred and twenty eight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and Joel son of Zechri was overseer over them, and Juda son of Asana for the city was second.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Of the priests, Jadia son of Joarid, Jachin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Saraia, son Alchia, son Mesulam, son Sadduk, son Marioth, son Aitoth were over against the house of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and their brethren who did the work of the house were eight hundred and twenty two; and Adaia a son of Jeroam who was the son of Phalatia son of Amasi, son Zacharias, son Phasur, son Melchia</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and his brethren, heads of families, two hundred and forty two; and Amasia son of Esdriel who was the son of Mesarimith, son of Emmer</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and his brethren fit to be mustered, a hundred and twenty eight, and their overseer was Badiel one of the nobles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And of the Levites, Samaia son of Esrikam,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Matthanias son of Micha and Jobed, son of Samue,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>two hundred and eighty four.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the keeper of the gates, Akub, Telamin and their brethren, a hundred and seventy two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And the overseer of the Levites son Bani, son Ozi, son Asabia, son Micha of the sons of Asaph the musicians attended over against the work of the house of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>for it was the king's command to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Phathaia son of Baseza was the king's minister for all matters with the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And for their villages in the fields some of the sons of Juda dwelt at Kariatharbok</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and at Jesou</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and at Bersabee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And their villages were Lachis and its fields, and they encamped at Bersabee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And the sons of Benjamin were from Gabaa to Machmas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and of the Levites, some were with Juda and some with Benjamin.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the priests and the Levites who came up with Zorobabel son of Salathiel and Jesus, Saraia, Jeremia, Esdra,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Amaria, Maluch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Sechenia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>these were the chiefs of the priests; and their brethren in the days of Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>namely the Levites, were Jesu, Banui, Kadmiel, Sarabaia, Jodae, Matthania. He was superintendant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and their brethren were for the courses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Jesus begot Joakim and Joakim begot Eliasib and Eliasib begot Jodae,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Jodae begot Jonathan, and Jonathan begot Jadu.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And in the days of Joakim his brethren the priests, the chiefs of the families were for Saraia, Amaria; for Jeremia, Anania;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for Esdra, Mesulam; for Amaria, Joanan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>for Amaluch, Jonathan; for Sechenia, Joseph;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>for Are, Mannas; for Marioth, Elkai;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>for Adadai, Zacharia; for Ganathoth, Mesolam;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>for Abia, Zechri; for Miamin, Maadai; for Pheleti;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for Balgas, Samue; for Semia, Jonathan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>for Joarib, Matthanai; for Edio, Ozi;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for Salai, Kallai; for Amek, Abed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>for Elkia, Asabias; for Jediu, Nathaniel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And in the days of Eliasib, these Levites, Joada and Joa, and Joanan and Idua were enrolled chiefs of the families, and they were the priests in the reign of Darius the Persian.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now the Levites enrolled as heads of the families in the book of Chronicles, continued till the days of Joanan son of Elisue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And these were the chiefs of the Levites, Asabia and Sarabia and Jesu, and the sons of Kadmiel and their brethren, were over against them for the hymn, to sing praises according to the command of David the man of God course for course.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When I had collected the keepers of the gates</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>in the days of Joakim, son of Jesus, son of Josedek, even in the days of Nehemias, when Esdras was the priest and scribe,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>at the dedication of the wall of Jerusalem, they sought the Levites in all their places to bring them to Jerusalem, to make the dedication with joyful thanksgivings and with songs, accompanied with cymbals and psalteries and kinyras;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and the sons of the musicians were assembled at Jerusalem from the neighbourhood around,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>both from the villages and the fields. For the musicians at Jerusalem had built villages for themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And the priests and the Levites having purified themselves, purified also the people, and the keepers of the gates and the wall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then they brought up the chiefs of Juda upon the wall, and having appointed two great companies for the songs of praise, they proceeded on from the right upon the wall of the dung gate;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and after them went Osaia and half of the chiefs of Juda,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Namely, Azarias and Esdras, and Mesolam</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and Juda, and Benjamin and Samaias, and Jeremia</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and some of the sons of the priests, with trumpets, Zacharias, son Jonathan, son Samaia, son Matthania, son Michaia, son Zakchur, son Asaph</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and his brethren, Samaia and Oziel, Gelol, Jama, Aia, Nathaniel and Juda, Anani, to sing praises in the songs of David, the man of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Esdras the scribe was before those at the gate, to sing praises over against these. And they went up the stairs of the city of David, by the ascent of the wall above the house of David, and on to the water gate</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>of Ephraim, and over the fish gate, and by the tower of Anameel, and on to the sheep gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And the musicians were heard though they were hid from view.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And on that day they offered great sacrifices, and rejoiced. Because God had given them great joy, therefore their wives and their children rejoiced, and the joy of Jerusalem was heard at a great distance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And on that day they appointed chief men over the store houses for the treasures, the dedications, and the tythes, and what were collected therein for the chiefs of the cities, and assigned portions for the priests and the Levites. For Juda rejoiced at the attendance of the priests and the Levites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>as they kept the watches of their God and the watches of purification; and at the attendance of the musicians and the keepers of the gates, as they were instituted by the command of David and his son Solomon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Because in the days of David at the institution, Asaph was the first of them who sung hymns and praises to God, therefore in the days of Zorobabel and in the days of Nehemias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>all Israel continued the giving daily portions to the musicians and to the keepers of the gates, dedicating them to the Levites, and the Levites dedicating them to the sons of Aaron.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>On reading that day in the book of Moses in the audience of the people, it was found written therein, that the Ammonites and the Moabites should not enter into the congregation of God forever;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>because they did not meet the Israelites with bread and water; but hired Balaam against them to curse them; but our God turned the curse into a blessing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when they heard the law, they separated from Israel all the mixed multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now before this, Eliasib the priest, made his dwelling in a store house of the house of our God. Having an affinity with Tobias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>he had fitted up for himself a large store house in which they formerly stored up the sacrifice and the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tythe of the corn, and the wine and the oil, the allotment of the Levites and the musicians, and the keepers of the gates, and the oblations which belonged to the priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But during all that time I was not at Jerusalem. For in the thirty second year of Arthasastha king of Babylon, I went to the king. And at the end of the year, having obtained the king's leave,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>I came to Jerusalem. When I was informed of the wickedness which Eliasib had committed for the sake of Tobias, in fitting up for him a treasure house in the court of the house of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>it grieved me exceedingly; therefore I threw all the furniture of Tobias out of the treasure house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when by my orders they had purified the rooms, I caused to be brought there again the utensils of the house of God, and the sacrifice and the incense.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when I understood that the portions of the Levites had not been given them; and that the Levites and the musicians who were employed in the service had fled, every man to his field,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I quarrelled with the officers and said, Why is the house of God forsaken?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then I brought them together and set them in their station; and all Juda brought in the tythe of the corn, and the wine, and the oil into the treasuries,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>under the charge of Selemia the priest, and Sadok the scribe, and Phadaia, one of the Levites, who had for assistants Anan, son Zakchur, son Mathanias, because they were accounted faithful. And it was their business to make distribution among their brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Remember me, God, for this; and let not the observance I have paid to the house of the Lord God be blotted out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In those days I saw in Juda some treading wine presses on the sabbath day, and some carrying sheaves, and loading their asses with wine and grapes and figs, and all kinds of burdens, and bringing them to Jerusalem on the sabbath day. Whereupon I testified against them, touching the day of their selling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Some also dwelt there who brought fish, and sold all sorts of wares on the sabbath, to the children of Juda, even in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Upon this I chided the freemen of Juda, and said to them, What evil is this which you do in profaning the sabbath?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Did not your fathers do so, and did not our God bring upon them and upon us, and upon this city, all these evils? And are you bringing more wrath upon Israel by profaning the sabbath?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when the gates of Jerusalem were set up, I ordered them to be shut before the sabbath, and gave a charge that they should not be opened till after the sabbath; and I stationed some of my servants at the gates that no burdens might be brought in on the sabbath day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Upon this they all lodged and carried on their traffick without Jerusalem once or twice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then I testified against them and. said to them, Why do you lodge before the walls? If you do so any more I will lay hands on you. From that time they did not come on the sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then I ordered the Levites who were sanctified and come to guard the gates, to keep holy the sabbath day. For these things remember me, my God, and have compassion on me according to thy abundant mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>In those days also I saw the Jews who had married wives of Azotus, of Ammon, and of Moab,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and their children spoke half in the dialect of Azotus, and did not know how to speak the Jewish language;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and I quarrelled with them, and reproached them, and smote some men among them, and caused some of them to be shaved, and adjured them by God, saying, You shall not give your daughters to their sons, nor take any of their daughters for your sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Did not Solomon king of Israel sin by doing so? Though among many nations there was not a king like him? Though he was beloved by God, and God had made him king over all Israel, yet strange women led him astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Let us not therefore hear of your committing all this iniquity, breaking covenant with our God, and marrying strange women.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And one of the sons of Joada the son of Elisub the high priest, being the son in law of Sanaballat the Ouranite, I drove him from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Put them in mind, God, of their near relation to the priesthood, and of the covenant of the priesthood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>As for the Levites I purified them from all connexion with strangers, and appointed the courses of the priests and the Levites, every man according to his business,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and the offering of the wood carriers at stated periods, and at the festivals. Remember me God, for good.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>