<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>There was a man in the country of Ausitis whose name was Job. He was a man of truth and integrity, just, pious, and who abstained from every thing that was evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He had seven sons and three daughters; and his cattle were seven thousand sheep, three thousand camels, five hundred yoke of oxen, five hundred breeding asses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>His attendants were numerous, and his works great in the country. He was also a man of illustrious birth, among the people of the east.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now his sons had a custom of meeting at each others houses, and making an entertainment, each on his day, taking along with them their three sisters to eat and drink with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And soon as the days of the entertainment were over, Job sent for, and purified them early the next morning, and offered sacrifices for them according to their numbers; a young bull for a sin offering for each of them; for Job said, Perhaps my children have in their mind conceived evil before God. In this manner therefore Job acted after every of those days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And it came to pass that on the same day, when lo! the angels of God came to present themselves before the Lord, Satan also came with them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the Lord said to Satan, Whence comest thou? And Satan in reply said to the Lord, Having gone round the earth, and roved the whole of it under heaven, I am come here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the Lord said to him, Hast thou harboured in thy mind any thing against my servant Job? For there is not like him on the earth, a man unblameable, true, pious, abstaining from every thing evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And Satan in reply said before the Lord, Doth Job worship the Lord for nothing?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hast thou not made a hedge about all that he hath, abroad and at home, and about all that belong to him round about, and blessed the works of his hands, and multiplied his cattle on the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But put forth thine hand and touch all that he hath, he will indeed openly renounce thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Satan, Behold all that he hath I deliver into thine hand; but himself thou must not touch. So Satan went out from the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and after that, on the same day, when the sons and daughters of Job were drinking wine at their elder brother's house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>lo! a messenger came to Job, and said to him, The oxen were ploughing and the asses feeding near them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and the plunderers came and carried them off. Thy servants also they slew with the sword, and I alone having escaped, am come to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>While he was yet speaking, another messenger came, and said to Job; Fire hath fallen from heaven and burned up the sheep, and devoured the shepherds likewise; and I, alone having escaped, am come to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>While this one was still speaking, another messenger came and said to Job, The horsemen, having formed three bands against us, surrounded the camels and have carried them off, and slain thy servants with the sword; and I, alone having escaped, am come to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>While he was still speaking, another messenger came, and said to Job, While thy sons and thy daughters were eating and drinking at their eldest brother's,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>a great blast of wind came up suddenly from the wilderness, and took the four corners of the house, so that the house fell upon thy children, and they are dead, and I, alone having escaped, am come to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Upon this Job rising up rent his clothes, and shaved his head, and falling on the ground he worshipped</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and said, Naked I came from my mother's womb, and naked I shall depart hence. The Lord gave and the Lord hath taken away. As it pleased the Lord so hath it come to pass. Blessed be the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In all these things which befel him, Job transgressed not against the Lord, nor imputed indiscretion to his God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again on the day when the angels of God came to present themselves before the Lord, Satan also came among them to present himself before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the Lord said to Satan, Whence comest thou? And Satan said before the Lord, Having traversed that under heaven, and roved through the whole of it, I am come here</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the Lord said to Satan, Thou hast therefore attended to my servant Job; that there is not of those on the earth a man like him, guiltless, true, unblameable, abstaining from all evil. Still he retaineth his innocence; so that thou hast ordered the destruction of his property, without accomplishing thy purpose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>In reply to which Satan said to the Lord, Skin for skin. All that a man hath he will give for his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Only put forth thy hand, and touch his bones and his flesh, he will indeed openly renounce thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then the Lord said to Satan, Behold I deliver him up to thee, only preserve his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thereupon Satan withdrew from the presence of the Lord, and smote Job with foul ulcers from head to foot,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>so that he took a shell to scrape away the ichor, and sat down in an unclean place without the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And much time having elapsed, his wife said to him, How long wilt thou persist saying, Behold I will wait yet a little longer, in hope and expectation of my deliverance? For behold the memorial of thee; those sons and daughters, whom I brought forth with pangs and sorrow, and for whom I toiled in vain, are vanished from the earth; and thou thyself sittest among the putrefaction of worms, all night long in the open air, while I am wandering about, or working for wages, from place to place and from house to house, wishing for the setting of the sun, that I may rest from the labours and sorrows I endure. Do but say something for the Lord and die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Whereupon he looking stedfastly at her said, Like one of the women without understanding hast thou spoken? If we have received good things at the hand of the Lord, shall we not bear up under afflictions? In all these things which befel him, Job transgressed not with his lips against God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now when his three friends heard of all the calamities which were come upon him, they came to him each from his own country, namely, Eliphaz the king of the Thaimanites, Baldad the sovereign of the Saucheans, and Sophar the king of the Minaians. Having made an appointment they came to him to comfort and take care of him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>but seeing him at a distance they did not know him. Then raising their voices they wept aloud, and having rent each his robe and sprinkled themselves with dust,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>they sat down by him seven days and seven nights. And none of them spoke. For they saw that the stroke was grievous and very great.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this Job opened his mouth and cursed his day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Perish the day in which I was born; and the night in which they said, It is a male!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let that night be darkness: let not the Lord from above regard it, nor splendour come upon it:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but let darkness and the shadow of death cover it: upon it let there come a thick darkness. May the day be execrated!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And as for that night, may a pitchy darkness sweep it away! May that never come into the days of the year; nor be numbered among the days of months.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But as for that night, may it be sorrow, and may there never come upon it gladness or mirth!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But let him curse it who curseth the day; him who is to attack the great sea monster.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>May the stars of that night be obscured in darkness: may it long for light but never reach it; nor see the rising of the morning star:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>because it shut not up the door of my mother's womb: for that would have removed sorrow from mine eyes:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>for why did I not end my days in the womb? Or when I came forth from the belly why did I not instantly perish?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Why was I dandled upon the knees? And why have I sucked the breasts?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I might now have lain still and been quiet; I might have gone to sleep and been at rest;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>with despots of the earth who gloried in their swords:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>or with chiefs who abounded in gold; who filled their houses with silver;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>or like an untimely birth sent forth from its mother's womb: or like infants which never saw the light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>There the wicked have ceased to be a terror: there the weary have got rest for their body:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and they of old who are assembled there together; have never heard the exactor's voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Small and great are there on a level; the servant, with his dreaded lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For why is light given to them in misery; or life to souls distressed with sorrow,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>who long for death but find it not; though they dig for it as for treasures;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and would rejoice exceedingly if they should chance to find it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For God hath shut up death from a man; to whom it would have been a repose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For my groaning cometh before my meat; and I pour forth tears, begirt with sorrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For the terror, which I dreaded, is come upon me; and that, of which I was afraid, hath befallen me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Did I not cultivate peace? was I not quiet? was I not at rest? Yet wrath is come upon me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Here Eliphaz the Thaimianite interrupting him, said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Should frequent replies be made to thee in distress? But o who can bear the vehemence of thy words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For if thou hast instructed many; and strengthened hands which were weak; and raised up with words them who were fainting;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and given courage to knees which were strengthless:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but now, when trouble hath come upon thee and touched thee, thou art impatient:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>is not either thy fear grounded on folly; or thy hope? And this calamity the effect of thy conduct?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Recollect therefore. Who ever perished, being innocent? Or when were the righteous utterly destroyed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>As I have seen men ploughing improper grounds: they who sow such places shall reap sorrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>By the decree of the Lord they shall perish; and by the blast of his ire be utterly consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The strength of a lion and the roaring of a lioness and the boastful pride of dragons have been extinguished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The myrmekoleon hath perished for want of food: and young lions have forsaken each other.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But had there been any truth in thy words; none of these evils would have happened to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Should not my ear receive unusual things coming from him? At a dreadful sound by night, when terror appalleth men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I was seized with a horror and trembling, which gave a violent shog to my bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>A wind indeed blew full in my face, and my hair stood erect and my flesh quivered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I started up, but could perceive nothing: I looked, but there was no form before my eyes. I only heard a sound and a voice, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>What! can a mortal be pure before the Lord, or a man by his works be blameless?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If in his servants he placeth not confidence, and in his angels perceiveth some blemish:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>how should he treat them who dwell in houses of clay, (of which clay we indeed are) but as worms?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but from morning till noon: and they are no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Because they could not help themselves they were destroyed. For he blowed on them and they withered: they perished because they had not wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Appeal now, will any one answer. Or shalt thou see any of the holy angels?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Passion indeed transporteth the foolish, and envy killeth the wanderer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now I have seen the foolish taking root, but their sustenance was quickly consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let their children be but far from safety, and insulted at the gates of minors, there will then be none to deliver them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For what they have collected the righteous shall eat. Nor will they themselves be exempt from wrongs, should their power be exhausted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For trouble cannot come forth out of the earth; nor will affliction spring up from mountains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But man is born for trouble, as the young of the vulture soar aloft,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>No, indeed; but notwithstanding this, let me supplicate the Lord. And call upon the Lord, the master of all,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>who doth great and unsearchable things; things glorious and wonderful, not to be numbered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Who giveth rain on the earth and sendeth water on all under heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Who setteth on high them who are low, and raiseth up them who have been ruined.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Who changeth the counsels of the crafty, so that their hands can perform no enterprise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Who entangleth the wise in their wisdom, and defeateth the counsel of the artful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>In the day time, darkness shall meet them, that they may grope at noon day as at night,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and that they may perish in battle, and the weak escape from the hand of the mighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And that the feeble may have hope, and the mouth of the wicked be stopped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But happy the man whom the Lord correcteth. Therefore despise not thou the correction of the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For He causeth pain and again removeth it: and him whom he smote, his hands have healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>From six distresses he will deliver thee, and in the seventh evil shall not touch thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In famine he will deliver thee from death, and in battle save thee from the edge of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He will hide thee from the scourge of the tongue: and thou need'st not be afraid of impending ills.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>At the wicked and unrighteous thou shalt laugh;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and of savage beasts need'st not be afraid; for the beasts of the field shall be at peace with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Thou shalt know that thy family is at peace, An objection. The answer. and that the provision for thy household shall not fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thou shalt know also that thy seed shall be great: thy children shall be like the grass of the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And thou shalt come to the grave like ripe grain cut in due season; or like a heap from a threshing floor, carried home in time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Behold these are the things which, by investigation, we have found to be so. These are things which we have heard: apply them to thyself, if thou hast done any thing.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To this, Job in reply said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>that some person would weigh my passion: and poise in a balance against it, my calamities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But these would outweigh the sand of the sea, though you seem to think my words too vehement:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>for the arrows of the Lord are in my body, the fury of which drinketh up my blood: when I attempt to speak they pierce me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>What! will a wild ass bray without cause? Will it do so, except when in search of food? Or will an ox low having fodder in his stall?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Can bread be eaten without salt, or is there any relish in vain words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For my temper cannot be calm, while my meat is horrible as the smell of a lion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>O that he would grant! that my request might be complied with! that the Lord would grant me what I long for!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let the Lord, having begun, wound me, but not utterly destroy me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Let but the grave be my city, having got on its walls I will not be slack to enter, for I have not disputed the holy commands of my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For what is my strength that I should bear up! what my time that my life is prolonged?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Is my strength the strength of stones, or is this flesh of mine made of brass?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Or have I not confided in him? But help is far from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Mercy hath bidden me adieu. When the superintending care of the Lord overlooked me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>my nearest friends did not regard me: like a failing brook, or like a wave of the sea, they passed me by.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They who had assiduously paid me court, now made me a slight visit, like snow or hoar frost,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>which melting at the approach of heat, the place where it was is not known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thus was I forsaken by all, and being undone, I became an outcast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Take a view of the ways of the Thaimanites, ye who mark out the Sabean tracks!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and they who trust in cities and wealth must blush. But now when you have come to me, it is without compassion;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>just to see my wound and be terrified. But why?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Have I asked anything of you, or do I crave any help from you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>to save me from mine enemies; or deliver me out of the hand of the mighty?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Teach me and I will hold my tongue. If I have erred, tell me plainly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But my words, it seems, are devoid of truth, because I do not beg assistance from you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Your reproof can neither stop my speaking, nor can I bear the tone of your oration:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>because, you not only fall upon the orphan, but also insult your friend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But now having looked you in the face I will not lie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Sit down I pray you, and let there be no more reproaches. Indeed you again meet a righteous man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For there are no reproaches on my tongue, and as for my palate, doth it not relish wisdom?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Is not the life of man on the earth a state of trial, and his days like the days of a hireling?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Is he not like a servant, who in a shade is afraid of his lord? Or like a hireling waiting for his hire?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Just so have I waited months in vain, and wearisome nights have been doled out to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When I lay me down to rest, I say, When will it be day? And soon as I rise; I again say, When will it be evening? I am full of pains from evening till morning;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and my body swarms with the putrefaction of worms: and I moisten the clods of earth with the ichor of ulcers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Though my life is swifter than a word; yet it is destroyed with vain hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Remember therefore that my life is but a breath; and that mine eyes shall never return again to see good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The eye of him who seeth me now shall not see me again. Thine eyes are upon me and I am gone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I am like a cloud swept clean away from the sky. For when a man goeth down to the mansion of the dead;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>he can never reascend again; he can never return again to his own house; nor shall his place know him any more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For this cause then I will not refrain my mouth: I will speak though I am in anguish: though distressed, I will unfold the bitterness of my soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Am I a sea or a dragon, that thou hast set a guard over me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Did I say my bed will comfort me; I will converse with myself privately on my bed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou terrifiest me with dreams and affrightest me with visions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Wilt thou drive away my life from my spirit; and yet keep my bones from death?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For I am not to live forever, that I should bear patiently. Withdraw from me; for my life is vanity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For what is man, that thou hast magnified him; or that thou payest attention to him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Wilt thou keep a watch upon him till the morning. And judge him to the time of going to rest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>How long wilt thou not let me alone: nor let me go, that I may swallow my spittle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>If I have sinned what can I do? thou who knowest the hearts of men; why hast thou set me up as thy mark to shoot at? Am I indeed a burden to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Why hast thou not made an oblivion of my transgression; or a purification for my sin? Now therefore let me depart into the earth: and when thou risest in the morning, I am no more.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Here Baldad the Sauchean interposing said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>How long wilt thou speak such things? The breath of thy mouth is profuse of words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Will the Lord in judging pass an unrighteous judgment? Or will he who made all things pervert justice?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>If thy children have sinned in his sight, he hath dismissed them for their transgression:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But rise thou betimes and supplicate the Lord Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If thou art pure and upright, he will hear thy prayer; and render to thee the reward of righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Let thy beginning therefore be ever so small, thy end will be unspeakably great.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For inquire of the former generation; and search diligently among the race of fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>(for we are but of yesterday and know nothing; for our life on the earth is but a shadow)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>will not they teach thee, and declare; and from the heart utter these maxims:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Can the papyrus grow without water?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Or can grass grow rank without drink? While grass is low it should not be mown. Before drinking doth not every herb wither?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Such therefore shall be the end of all who forget the Lord: for the hope of the ungodly shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For his house shall be uninhabited: and his tent shall fly away like a spider's web.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Though he prop up his house, it cannot stand: Though he take hold of it, it will not abide,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>for is he somewhat green underneath the sun? Though a tender branch may start up from his rottenness; his bed is on a heap of stones:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and can he live among flint stones?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Should he wish to drink, the place will disappoint him. Hast thou not seen such things; that such is the catastrophe of the wicked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But out of the ground he will cause another to spring up:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for the Lord will not cast off the innocent, nor from the ungodly accept a gift:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but he will fill the mouth of the upright with, laughter, and their lips with songs of thanksgiving:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and their enemies shall be clothed with shame; and the dwellings of the wicked shall come to naught.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To this Job replied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Of a truth I know that it is so. For how can a mortal be righteous with the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For were it his pleasure to come to trial with him; he could not join issue to answer one charge of his in a thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For he is wise in heart and strong and great. Who is hardy enough to stand up against him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>who maketh mountains old insensibly; who overturneth them in his anger;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>who shaketh the earth to its foundations, so that the pillars thereof totter;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>who commandeth the sun and it riseth not; and who sealeth up against the stars;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>who alone hath outspread the heaven; and who walketh on the sea as on a pavement;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>who is the maker of the Pleiads and Hesperus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and of Arcturus and the chambers of Notus; who doth things great and unsearchable; things glorious and wonderful not to be numbered?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When he passed over me I did not see him. When he passed by me, I did not know how.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If he dismiss who shall bring back? Or who shall say to him, What hast thou done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For he himself slighted anger; by him the monsters under heaven were bowed down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But if he will come to a trial with me, or will take cognisance of my affairs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>(for if I be righteous will he not hearken to me; shall I not supplicate his decision?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And if I call and he will not answer, I do not believe that he hath hearkened to my voice?)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Let him not break me with a tempest. But he hath multiplied my wounds without cause.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For he suffereth me not to take breath, and hath filled me with bitterness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For because he is strong, he prevaileth. Who then can withstand his decrees?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For if I am righteous shall my mouth be wicked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And if I am blameless, shall I go away crouching? For if I have acted wickedly, I am not conscious to myself: Nevertheless my life is taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Say then, wrath destroyeth the great and powerful:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>that the wicked fall by an untimely death. But the righteous are laughed to scorn:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>for they have been delivered into the hands of the wicked. He covereth the faces of the judges of that wrath. If it is not he, who is it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now my days are swifter than a courier. They are gone without being perceived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Is there any track left by ships in their passage? Or of an eagle flying in pursuit of its prey?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now if I say, Let me forget speaking, let me bow down my face and groan:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>I shudder in all my limbs; for I know that thou wilt not let me alone though innocent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now since I am wicked, why have I not died?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For though I have washed myself with snow, and purified myself with clean hands:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>thou hast so thoroughly plunged me in filth that my very robes abhor me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For thou art not a man as I am, with whom I can contend; that we may come together to a trial.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>O that there were a mediator betwixt us; one to determine between and hear us both.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Let him remove his rod from me; and let not the dread of him terrify me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Let me not be terrified, but speak, (for in that case I am not master of myself)</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Weary of my life I would pour forth with groans my words before him: oppressed as I am I would speak in the bitterness of my soul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and say to the Lord, Teach me not to be impious. Now, for what cause hast thou thus condemned me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Is it agreeable to thee that I should commit iniquity; seeing thou hast rejected the works of thy hands; and favoured the counsel of the wicked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>As a mortal looketh dost thou look down? Or as a man looketh wilt thou behold?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Are thy days as the days of a mortal; or thy years, the years of a man;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>that thou hast sought out mine iniquity, and diligently traced my sins?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For thou knowest that I am not impious: but who can deliver out of thy hands?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thy hands have fashioned me and made me. After that thou hast changed thy mind and smitten me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Remember that thou hast made me of clay, and art turning me again into mould.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hast thou not churned me as milk, and curdled me as cheese;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and clothed me with skin and flesh; and fenced me with bones and sinews,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and granted me life and favour, and by thy visitation preserved my spirit?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>As thou hast these things in thyself; I know that thou canst do all things, and that with thee nothing is impossible.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If I indeed have sinned inadvertently, thou hast me in custody, and hast not acquitted me of transgression.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If I indeed am impious, Woe is me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And if I be righteous, I cannot hold up my head, for I am full of ignominy. For I am hunted as a lion for slaughter. For turning again furiously thou destroyest me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Renewing the examination against me, thou hast exercised against me great wrath; and hast brought against me tortures.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Why then didst thou bring me forth from the womb? And why did I not die without an eye seeing me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and become as if I never had existed? Why was I not carried from the womb to the grave?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Is not the term of my life of short duration? permit me to enjoy a little repose:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>before I go, whence I shall not return;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>to a land dark and gloomy; to a land of everlasting darkness; where there is no light; no seeing the life of mortals.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Here Sophar and Minaian answering said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He who speaketh much should be answered: else the fine speaker thinketh himself just; and the short lived offspring of woman is blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Be not profuse of words, because there is none to answer thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>nor say I am pure in works and irreprehensible before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But how would the Lord speak to thee; were he to open his lips against thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Indeed were he to unfold to thee the power of wisdom; because it must needs be double to what are with thee: then thou wouldst know that what have come upon thee from the Lord are answerable to the sins which thou hast committed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Canst thou trace the footsteps of the Lord? Or hast thou reached the extent of what the Almighty hath done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The heaven is high, what then canst thou do? And there are things deeper than the mansion of the dead; what dost thou know?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Of greater extent than the measure of the earth or the breadth of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now were he to overturn all these, who could say to him what hast thou done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For he knoweth the works of the wicked, and on seeing wickedness will not overlook it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But man vainly floateth about in words; but a mortal born of woman is like a wild ass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For if thou hast made thy heart pure, and lift thy hands to him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>if there be any iniquity in thy hand, put it far from thee; and let not injustice lodge in thy dwelling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For thus will thy countenance brighten like pure water: thou wilt disrobe thyself of filth, and no more be terrified:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>thou shalt forget thy trouble like a wave that is past and not be afraid; and thy wish will spring up like the morning star;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and life will arise for thee from noon day:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and thou shalt be in a state of security because thou hast hope. And out of sorrow and care, peace will shine upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For thou shalt rest at ease, and none shall be at war with thee: and many, changing their conduct, will intreat thy favour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But safety shall forsake them: for their hope shall be their destruction; and the eyes of the wicked shall melt away.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To this Job replied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You, forsooth, are men, and wisdom will die with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But I indeed have understanding as well as you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For a just man and one irreprehensible hath been made a mocking stock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For it hath been ordered that for a time he shall fall beneath others: and that his houses shall be wasted by transgressors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Nevertheless let no wicked man indulge a confidence that he shall escape condemnation. Whoever provoke the Lord to anger shall not they also undergo a trial?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But ask, I pray thee, the beasts of the field, if they could speak to thee; and the birds of the air, if they could tell thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>speak to the earth, if it could converse with thee; even the fishes of the sea can tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Who then among all these doth not know that the hand of the Lord hath done these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Is not the life of all living beings in his hand; and the breath of every man?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The ear indeed discerneth words and the palate tasteth meats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>By length of time wisdom is acquired, and by long life, experience.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>With him is wisdom and power; with him counsel and understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If he demolish who can rebuild? If he shut against men, who can open?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If he withhold water he drieth the earth. And when he let it loose, he overthrew and destroyed it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>With him is strength and power; with him knowledge and understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He hath led counsellors away captive. And confounded the judges of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>It is he who settleth kings on thrones and girded their loins with a girdle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>who sendeth priests into captivity and overthrew the sovereigns of the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>who changeth the lips of liege men and knoweth the wisdom of elders;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>who poureth contempt on princes and hath healed them who were low;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>who revealeth deep things from darkness; and hath brought to light the shades of death;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>who leadeth nations into error and destroyeth them; who prostrateth nations and conducteth them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>who changeth the hearts of the rulers of a land and hath caused them to wander in a way which they knew not:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>That they might grope in darkness without light; and that they might stagger like a drunken man.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Behold these things mine eye hath seen and mine ear heard:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for I know all that you know and am not inferior to you in knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Nevertheless I would speak to the Lord; and argue before him, were it his pleasure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now you are all bad physicians and curers of maladies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Could you hold your peace, it would be your wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Hear now the argument of my mouth and the pleading of my lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Are you not speaking in the presence of the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And do you in his presence utter deceit in a solemn manner? Or will you keep back any thing? Judge for yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For will it be well for you, if he mark your steps? For though feigning all these things you apply them for him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>he will, notwithstanding this, reprove you. And if you secretly respect persons;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>will not his awful majesty confound you; and the terror of him fall upon you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And your boasting be dissipated like ashes; and your bodies be reduced to clay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Keep silence that I may speak, and have some respite from wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Taking my flesh in my teeth I will put my life in my hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Though the Almighty, as he hath begun, may subdue me: yet I will speak and plead before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And this will contribute to my deliverance: for no deceit shall come before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Hear, hear my words: for I will proclaim them in your hearing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold I am near my trial. I know that I shall appear just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For who is there who will emplead me? For now I will be silent and expire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now two things thou art to grant me: then I will not hide myself from thy presence;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>withdraw thy hand from me: and let not the dread of thee overwhelm me with terror.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then call and I will answer thee: or speak and I will make thee a reply.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>How many are my sins and mine iniquities? Teach me what they are.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Why dost thou hide thyself from me and hast accounted me thine adversary?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Canst thou be afraid of one who is like a leaf moved with a breath of wind? Or as against dried grass carried away with a blast, dost thou set thyself against me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For thou hast written evil things against me; and laid to my charge the inadvertencies of youth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and put my feet in a clog and watched all my doings; and hast tracked the soles of my feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>He who is born of a woman waxeth old like a leathern bag: or like a garment which is moth eaten;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>for he is mortal, short lived and full of disquiet:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>or like a flower which fell when in bloom. He glideth away indeed like a shadow and can make no stay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And is it not such a one thou hast called to account; and caused such a one to come to trial before thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For who can be free from stain? Surely none.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Whether the course of his life on earth be one day; or months be numbered out for him, he cometh to the term thou hast set, but cannot pass it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Turn away from him, that he may take rest, and comfort his life like a hireling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For there is hope for a tree; for if lopped, it may sprout again, and the tender branch may not fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And if its root become old in the earth, or die on a rock:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>its stem by the scent of water may blossom; and produce a crop like a tree lately planted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But when a man dieth he is gone: when a mortal falleth, he is no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For in a course of time a sea is spent; and a river when unsupplied is dried up:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and man when composed in the grave cannot rise again; until the heaven be folded up; they shall not be awakened from their sleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>O! that thou hadst kept me in the mansion of the dead; and hid me till thine indignation should cease: and that thou wouldst set me a time when thou wouldst remember me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>(for though a man die he may be revived, after finishing the days of this life of his,) I would wait patiently, until I come again into existence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then call and I will answer. But reject not the works of thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now thou hast numbered up my devices, and not one of my inadvertencies could escape thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou hast sealed up mine iniquities in a bag; and set a mark on every transgression, which I inadvertently committed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But not to mention that a falling mountain will continue its fall; even a rock may by force be removed from its place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Waters have worn stones smooth; and waters have washed away mounds of earth; and thou hast destroyed the patience of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou hast brought him to an end, and he is gone: thou hast set thy face against him and dismissed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And though his children be multiplied, he knoweth it not: and if they become few in number, he doth not perceive it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>His flesh hath been for nothing but to suffer pain; and his soul only to suffer grief.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Here Eliphaz the Thaimanite taking up the argument said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Will a wise man give the wind of knowledge for an answer; though he hath therewith filled his labouring belly?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Or in pleading use arguments which he ought not; and words in which there is no profit?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hast thou not cast off fear, and used such arguments before the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>By the arguments of thine own mouth thou art guilty; and hast not discerned the arguments of the mighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let thine own mouth and not me convict thee: thine own lips indeed will testify against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>What! wast thou born before men? Or wast thou brought into being before the hills?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Or hast thou heard the established system of the Lord? Or hath God used thee as his counsellor? Or hath wisdom made application to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For what knowest thou, which we do not know? Or what dost thou understand which we do not?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Among us indeed are elders and aged men, more venerable for years than thy father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thou hast been chastised less than thy sins deserve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thou hast spoken with excessive haughtiness. To what a pitch of boldness is thy heart raised; or at what have thine eyes taken aim;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>that thou shouldst vent wrath before the Lord, and utter such words from thy mouth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For who being mortal can be irreprehensible? Or can the offspring of woman be righteous?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If in his holy ones he placeth not confidence; and the heaven is not pure in his sight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>how abominable and filthy must man be; who drinketh iniquity in, like water!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But let me tell thee; hear what I have seen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>let me tell thee what the wise say, and their fathers have not concealed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>They, to whom alone the earth was given; and no stranger came among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The whole life of the wicked is spent in anxiety. Though a certain number of years is given to the oppressor:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>yet the sound of terror is in his ears. When he seemeth to be at peace his destruction shall come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Let him not hope to return out of darkness; for he is already doomed to the edge of the sword;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and destined to be food for vultures. He knoweth within himself that he waiteth for a fall; and a dark day will torture him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Distress and anguish will overwhelm him; like a general at the head of troops falling upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Because he lifted up his hands against the Lord, and hardened his neck against the Lord Almighty:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>therefore he ran upon him contemptuously, with the thick boss of his buckler.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Because he covered his face with fatness; and made collops of fat upon his thighs:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>let him therefore lodge in deserted cities; and go into uninhabited houses: and what they had got ready, let others carry off.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Let him neither be enriched, nor what he hath continue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Let him never cast a shadow on the ground, nor escape out of darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Let the wind blast his bud, and his blossom fall prematurely. Let him not hope to continue, for vanity shall be his portion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Let his branch lopped unseasonably, die; and let not his young shoot flourish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Let him be gathered like unripe grapes before his time, and fall like the olive blossom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For death is the testimonial of a wicked man: and a fire shall consume the tents of bribery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>He shall conceive sorrows and bring forth vanity, and his belly shall produce an illusion.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To this Job replied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I have heard many such things, ye miserable comforters all!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>what! Have words of wind a regular succession? Or can they give thee offence, considering thine answer?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I indeed could speak as you do. But were your soul in my soul's stead, would I insult you with words and shake my head at you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And should there be strength in my mouth; would I not spare moving my lips?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For if I speak shall I not bemoan the wound? And if I hold my peace, shall I be any the less wounded?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But now when he hath made me a poor rotten fool;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>thou indeed hast fallen upon me. My lie is become a witness, and hath risen up against me; it hath answered me to my face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When in his wrath he threw me down and gnashed his teeth at me; the darts of his executioners fell upon me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When with the darts of his eyes he had transfixed me; with his spear had brought me on my knees: they with one consent rushed upon me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The Lord hath indeed delivered me up to the unrighteous; and turned me over to the ungodly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When I was at peace he broke me up; taking me by the hair he shook me; he set me up as a mark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They surrounded me with javelins, darting them into my reins; without mercy they poured my gall on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>They shot me, one deadly wound on another; they ran against me with all their might.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>They sewed sackcloth on my skin: and my strength was extinguished in the dust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>My belly was burned up with wailing; and on mine eyelids were the shades of death:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>yet there was no iniquity in my hands. And my prayer was pure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>O earth, cover not the blood of my flesh, nor let there be a place for this cry of mine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Even now, behold my witness is in heaven; and he who hath a perfect knowledge of me is on high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>O that my suit could come before the Lord, and that before him mine eye could drop a tear!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>That a man could plead before the Lord, as a son of man may with his neighbour!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But my numbered days are come, and I must go the way, by which I cannot return.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I am dying with a tortured spirit, and wishing for a burial, but do not obtain it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I am supplicating in distress, yet what have I done? Strangers have stolen my substance; who is the man?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Let him be brought to trial with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because thou hast hid their heart from understanding, thou shouldst not for this cause exalt them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Shall he reckon misfortunes for his portion; and were his eyes melted for his children?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But thou hast made me a by-word among nations, and I am become a subject of laughter for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For mine eyes are dim with sorrow, and I am closely besieged by all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>At this the upright are astonished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now the righteous should prevail over the wicked: and he who is faithful should hold on his way: and he who hath clean hands should take courage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>On these maxims you all rely. But come now; for I do not find truth among you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>my days have passed in groans, and my very heart strings are broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I have put night for day. Is light near on account of darkness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For though I have waited patiently, the mansion of the dead is to be my house, and my bed is made in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have called on death to be my father; and on corruption to be my sister and mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Where then have I any ground of hope? Or shall I see those good things of mine?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Shall they go down with me to the mansion of the dead? Or shall we go together beneath the mound?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Here Baldad the Sauchean interrupting him said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>How long will it be ere thou wilt stop? Forbear that we may speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Why should we like beasts be silent before thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Passion hath taken possession of thee. What! If thou die, shall the earth be uninhabited? Or the mountains overturned from their foundations?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The light of the wicked shall indeed be extinguished; and from them a spark shall not ascend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The light in his dwelling shall be darkness, and the lamp for him shall be extinguished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Let the weakest plunder his substance, and his own counsel subvert him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>His foot is caught in a trap;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>in a net let him be entangled, and let snares come upon him. He will strengthen the thirsty against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>A gin is hid for him in the ground, and the trap for him by the way side.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>May surrounding sorrows destroy him, and many come round his foot in sore famine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For him indeed a direful destruction is prepared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>May the toes of his feet be eaten up, and death devour his comeliness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>May health be expelled from his dwelling, and distress lay hold on him with the authority of a king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>It will make its abode in his tent; in his night all his finery will be strewed with sulphur.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Underneath his roots will be dried up; and above, his product will fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>May the memorial of him be destroyed from the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When his name shall be published abroad, may they drive him from light to darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He will not be acknowledged among his people, nor will his household be safe under the cope of heaven. But in his possessions others shall live secure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>They who came after groaned for him, but horror seized them who were before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Such are the houses of the unrighteous, and such the place of them who know not the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To this Job replied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>How long will you make my soul sorrowful? You are indeed destroying me with words. Know at least; because the Lord hath dealt thus with me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>you speak against me; without shame you fall upon me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Take it for granted that I have erred (though my error remaineth with myself) in speaking words which I ought not: and that my words are erroneous and unseasonable: but granted also,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>That you magnify yourselves against me, and insult me with reproach.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Know then, That it is the Lord who hath terrified me, and raised his bulwark against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold I laugh at reproach; I will not speak; I will cry aloud, There is no judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I am fenced about and cannot get out. Before me he hath placed darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He hath stripped me of my glory, and hath taken the crown from my head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He broke me on every side and I fled: and he hath cut down my hope like a tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When he exercised great wrath against me, and counted me as an enemy:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>With one consent his troops fell upon me; they who were in ambush beset my ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>My brethren stood aloof from me, they acknowledged strangers rather than me; and my friends were not compassionate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>My nearest relations paid me no attention: and they who knew my name forgot me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>As for my domesticks and maid servants, in their view I was a stranger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When I called my servant, he did not answer me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When with my mouth I entreated and supplicated my wife, and called affectionately the children of my concubines:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>they renounced me forever. When I insist, they speak against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>They who saw me, abhorred me; and they whom I loved rose up against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The flesh next my skin became rotten, and my bones begin to be corroded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Pity me, pity me, O my friends, for the hand of the Lord hath touched me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Why do you persecute me as the Lord doth, and are not satisfied with my flesh?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>O that my words were written and recorded in a book forever!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>That they were engraven with a graver of iron on lead, or on rocks!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For I know that he is eternal,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>who is about to dissolve me on earth, to raise again this skin of mine which draweth up these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For from the Lord those things have been done to me, of which I alone am conscious; which mine eyes have seen, and no other; and which have all been done to me in my bosom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now if you will say, What shall we say against him? And what ground of accusation shall we find in him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Stand in awe, I beseech you, of the developing scene; for wrath will come upon the unrighteous, and it shall then be known, where their filthiness is.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then answered Sophar the Minaian and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I did not suppose that thou wouldst return such an answer, but do not you feel it more than I?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Am I to hear my modesty corrected? And is a spirit from its consciousness to answer me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thou hast never known such things heretofore, from the time man was placed on the earth!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But the mirth of the wicked is sudden ruin, and the joy of transgressors, destruction,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>though his gifts mount up to heaven, and his sacrifice reach the clouds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For when he thinketh that he is now firmly established, then shall he be utterly destroyed; and they who have seen him will say, Where is he?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Like a dream which is gone, he cannot be found. He is vanished, like a spectre in the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The eye which saw him, shall see him no more; and his place shall no more observe him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Let minors destroy his children, and his own hands light up the signals of distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>His bones were full of his youth, but with him it shall go to rest beneath the mound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If wickedness be sweet in his mouth, he will hide it under his tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He will not be sparing of it, nor forsake it, but will gather it together in his mouth; therefore let him not be able to help himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The poison of an asp is in his belly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Riches collected unrighteously shall be vomited up. Out of his house let an angel drag him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>May he suck the venom of dragons! and may the tongue of the viper slay him!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>may he never see the milking of his kine, nor the distribution of his honey and butter!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He hath wearied himself for emptiness and vanity; for riches, of which he shall not have a taste, which are like a bur, neither to be chewed nor drunk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because he broke up the families of princes; and plundered dwellings and suffered them not to stand</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>There is no security for his possessions; nor shall he be saved by what he valueth highly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Not a scrap of his provisions is left. His good things shall not, on this account, be renewed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In the fullness of his sufficiency he shall be afflicted, and all manner of distress shall come upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If by any means he be permitted to fill his belly; may he send against him fiery indignation, and pour upon him sorrows!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Let him not escape from the edge of the sword!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>May the brasen bow wound him, and the dart pass through his body, and stars light on his dwellings!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>May terrors stalk around him and total darkness await him! An unkindled fire devoureth him. May his guest also afflict his family!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>may the heaven disclose his iniquities, and the earth rise up against him!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>May destruction bring his house to an end! Upon him may there come a day of wrath!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>This is the portion of a wicked man from the Lord, and this his possession, from the superintending Being.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To this Job replied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>hear, hear my words. Can I not have this consolation from you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Bear with me, and when I speak do not deride me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>What! is my pleading with man? Or, why shall I not be inflamed with indignation?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Look on me and be amazed, having laid your hand on your cheek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For at the bare recollection I shudder: and tortures rack my flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Why do the wicked live and grow old, abounding in wealth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Their crops are to their wish, and their children before their eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Their houses flourish and they have no dread; and a scourge from the Lord is not upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Their kine bring not forth untimely births, but go their time safely, and cast not their calves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>They abide continually like a flock, and their little ones frolick about them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>They take up the psaltery and kithara, and are charmed with the sound of the song;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and having spent their life in festivity, they are composed to rest in the peaceful grave.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Yet he saith to the Lord, Depart from me, I desire not to know thy ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>What is the Almighty, that we should serve him: and what the advantage, that we should wait on him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For their prosperity was by their own hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now doth not he observe the works of the wicked? and should not the lamp, at least of wicked men, be extinguished, and destruction come upon them? And pangs seize them, on account of anger:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and they be like chaff driven by the wind, or like dust swept away by a whirlwind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>His substance should fail from among his children. He should retribute to him. And he should know it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>His eyes should see his own destruction: and he should not escape from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Because his desire is in his family with him; therefore the number of their months should be cut short.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Is it not the Lord who teacheth wisdom and understanding, and doth he discriminate murderers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>One is to die in his full strength, all his life being successful and prosperous;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>his entrails are cloathed with fat, and his bones abound with marrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Another dieth with bitterness of soul, having never tasted any thing good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But they are both composed alike under ground, and putrefaction hath covered them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>I know you charge me with presumption,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>that you will say, Where is the house of the chief, and where is the covering of the tents of the wicked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Ask them who travel the high ways, or their monuments, you cannot miss them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Because the wicked is reserved for a day of destruction: let them be carried to prison for the day of his indignation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Who shall tell him his way to his face, and who shall retribute to him what he hath done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Even when he should be carried to the burying place, he had caused a watch to be kept over his tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>The flints of the torrent have been sweetened for him, and every man shall go after him, as innumerable have gone before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>How then do ye comfort me with vanity? There is nothing from you to give me consolation.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Upon this, Eliphaz the Thaimanite answered, and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Is it not the Lord who teacheth wisdom and understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>What! Is it any advantage to the Lord, if thou, in works, art irreprehensible? or any profit, that thou shouldst keep a straight course?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Or will he, instituting a suit against thee, argue and come to a trial with thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Is not thy wickedness great, and thy sins innumerable?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thou hast taken pledges of thy brethren for nought, and hast stripped the naked of their cloathing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thou hast not given drink to the thirsty: but hast robbed the hungry of their morsel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thou hast respected the persons of some and settled them in the land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>but hast sent widows away empty, and done injustice to orphans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore snares have beset thee, and an unexpected war hath made thee shudder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The light hath become darkness to thee, and water hath overwhelmed thee when asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Doth not he who dwelleth on high, observe; but hath he humbled the haughty?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Yes, thou hast said, How can the Almighty know? Can he judge in darkness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>A cloud is his covering, so that he cannot be seen, though he traverse the circuit of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thou wilt not keep the ancient way, which righteous men trod,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>who were borne aloft, and whose foundations were the surgy stream. As for them</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>who said, What can the Lord do to us, or what can the Almighty bring upon us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>(He, who had indeed filled their houses with good things, though the counsel of the wicked is far from him.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When the righteous saw them, they smiled, and he who was blameless laughed them to scorn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Had not the whole of them disappeared, a fire would have consumed the residue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Become hardened now, if thou remainest; and shalt thou be rewarded with good things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Receive, I pray thee, from his mouth, the terms of deliverance, and lay up his words in thy heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If thou wilt return and humble thyself before the Lord, having removed iniquity far from thy dwelling,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>thou shalt be placed on a mount, founded on a rock, and be like the rock of the torrent Sophir.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then will the Almighty be thy defence from enemies; and he will make thee pure as silver tried by fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then indeed thou shalt have confidence before the Lord; and mayst look up to heaven with cheerfulness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when thou prayest to him, he will hearken to thee, and will enable thee to pay thy vows;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and he will assign thee an habitation of righteousness, and light shall shine upon thy ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Because thou hast humbled thyself, thou wilt say, Such a one was insolent; but he will save him whose eyes are lowly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He indeed will save the innocent. Save thyself therefore, with clean hands.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In reply to this, Job said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I know very well, this trial is not in my disposal. And that his hand is made heavy by my groaning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But O that some person would let me know, that I might find him, and come to an issue;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that I might order the trial of myself, and that he would stop my mouth with arguments</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>That I might know what remedies he will prescribe for me, and understand what he will announce to me!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Though he may come against me with great majesty, he will not employ it in threatening me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For truth and argument proceed from him; and he would bring my cause to an issue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For if I am to go first and am no more, how do I know what will be at the last?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When he wrought on my left, I comprehended not; he may encompass my right and I not see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For he already knoweth my way and hath tried me like gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And I will come out at his commands; for I have kept his ways, and will not turn aside from his commands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>nor transgress in my bosom: indeed I have hid his words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But if he hath judged thus, who can gainsay him? For he hath done what was his pleasure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For this cause my shuddering is at him; and on being chastened, I thought of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For this cause I am to be awed at his presence; I am to meditate on and be in dread of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>It is the Lord indeed who hath softened my heart. It is the Almighty who hath made me shudder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For I had no knowledge of darkness coming upon me; and he had hid from my view thick darkness before me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But why have set times escaped the notice of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and the wicked transgressed all bounds; and ravaged both the flock and the shepherd?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They have driven away the ass of the fatherless; and taken the widow's cow for a pledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They have turned the weak out of the right way; and with one consent the meek of the land are hidden</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and are gone away like asses in a field. They are sprung up above me in their own order. To one, bread is sweetened for his children;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>others have reaped before dawn a field not their own; exhausted of strength have Worked the vineyards of the wicked without wages and without food.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They have caused many to sleep naked without covering; they have stripped them of clothing necessary for life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>These are wet with the dew of the mountains: and having no shelter they cling to a rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They have torn the orphan from the breast: and him who had fallen they have pressed down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They have by injustice caused some to be naked; and robbed the hungry of their morsel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>They have entrapped some unjustly in straits, and the path of justice they did not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Some are expelled from the city and their own houses: and the soul of babes heave heavy groans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now why hath he not called these to account while on earth? Though they did not acknowledge; though they did not know the way of justice; did they not still go on in their courses?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And hath he who knew their works delivered them up to darkness? And will he be as a thief in the night?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>When the eye of the adulterer watched for darkness; saying, No eye shall discover me; when he having put a mask on his face</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>digged through houses in the dark: (during the day they had shut themselves up; they had no acquaintance with light)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>because the morning is to all these as the shadow of death; because the terror of the shadow of death should acknowledge them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>is it swift on the face of the water? The portion of these on the earth should be cursed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and their plants exposed dry on the ground: for they plundered the sheaf of orphans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now was such a one's sin brought to remembrance? Though he was dark as the darkness of night; retribution should be made for what he hath done: and every wicked man should be broken; like a tree which cannot be healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Because he did not treat the barren with tenderness, and had no compassion for a poor weak woman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But overthrew the helpless with wrath: therefore when he riseth he should have no security for his own life:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>when sick, he should have no hopes of recovery: but should perish by his disorder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>As his exaltation afflicted many: he should wither like mallows by heat: or like an ear of corn which fell of itself from the stalk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now if this is not the case; who can say I have spoken falsehoods: and set my words at naught?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hereupon Baldad the Sauchean answered and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>What! Is there any apology, or fear with him; who made the universe and is supreme?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For let none suppose, because robbers have a respite; that snares shall not come from him on any.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For how can a mortal be just before the Lord or any offspring of woman make himself clean?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>If he setteth the moon beside him, it shineth not: and the stars are not pure in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Grant then that man is rottenness and that the son of man is a worm.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To this Job replied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whom dost thou assist, or whom art thou going to help? Is it not him, who hath mighty power and whose arm is strong?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For whom hast thou been acting as counsellor? Is it not for him who hath all wisdom? Whom art thou about to follow? Is it not him, whose army is beyond compare?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For whom hast thou announced dictates? And whose breath is it which proceeded from thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Are giants going to rise up from beneath the water and the places in its neighbourhood?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The mansion of the dead is naked before him: and destruction hath no covering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He it is, who stretcheth out Boreas over empty space; who suspendeth the earth upon nothing;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>who bindeth up water in his clouds; and the cloud under it is not rent;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>who taketh possession of the front of his throne and over it spreadeth his cloud.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>His decree hath drawn a circle on the face of the water; at the confines of light and darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The pillars of heaven flutter and are struck with consternation at his rebuke.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>By his power he calmed the sea; and by his knowledge the monster was overthrown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The bars of heaven were terrified at him; and by a decree he doomed to death the apostate dragon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Behold these are parts of his ways. But let us hear the least breath of reason for him. As for the strength of his thunder; who knoweth when he shall employ it?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Furthermore Job proceeded and by way of preface said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As God liveth, who hath thus condemned me; even the Almighty who hath made my life bitter:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>while I have the power of breathing and the breath of God is in my nostrils;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>my lips shall not speak wickedness, nor shall my soul contrive mischief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Far be it from me to acknowledge you to be right; for till I die, I will not give up mine innocence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And for asserting my righteousness I make no apology; for I am not conscious to myself of having done amiss.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Should not mine enemies then be as the overthrow of the wicked? And they who rise up against me as the destruction of transgressors?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now whatever hope a wicked man hath, that he persisteth; shall he who hath trusted in the Lord be indeed safe?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Or will God hear his prayer? Or when trouble cometh upon him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>hath he any assurance before him? Or upon his calling, will he hearken to him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But now let me tell you what is by the hand of the Lord. What are from the Almighty I will not falsify.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Behold you all know that you heap vanity on vanities, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>This is the portion of a wicked man from the Lord: and the possession of oppressors, which shall come to them from the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If their children be many they shall be for slaughter; and if they grow up to men, they shall be beggars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Those who are about him shall die by pestilence: and their widows none shall compassionate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Though he heap up silver as dust; and store up gold as clay:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the righteous shall take charge of all these; and men of truth shall enjoy his wealth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>His house is gone like moths or like a cobweb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He shall lie down rich but shall not continue so. He hath opened his eyes, and all is gone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Sorrows flowed in upon him like water. In a night a tempest swept him away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>A burning wind shall take him up and go he must. It shall blow him away out of his place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He will dash upon him and will not spare. Should he by flight flee from his hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>he will cause them to clap their hands at him and will hiss him out of his place.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>There is indeed a place, from which silver is got; and a place from which gold is strained.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Iron indeed is made out of the earth, and brass is hewn from a quarry like stones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He hath assigned a station for darkness: but every boundary he assigned is diligently explored; stones, darkness and the shadow of death;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>the channels of brooks choked up with sand: where to such as know not the right way; strength is unavailing and they are removed from among men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>As for the earth out of which bread cometh; from underneath it something like fire hath been turned up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The stones thereof is the place of the sapphire. And the dust thereof supplieth man with gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>A path is explored which no bird knew; and which the vulture's eye hath not seen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>which the race of boasters have not travelled; and over which the lion hath not stalked</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>One hath stretched forth his hand with a pick and hath overturned mountains from the roots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Another hath broken through the whirlpools of rivers: and mine eye hath seen every precious thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Another hath laid bare the bottoms of rivers and given manifest proofs of his power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But where is wisdom to be found? And where is the place of understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>A mortal knoweth not the way thereof; nor hath it indeed been found out by men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The abyss said, It is not in me: and the sea said, It is not in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>would not one give for it all he hath got?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But silver cannot be weighed as its price; nor can it be purchased with the gold of Sophir; with the precious onyx or the sapphire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Gold and chrystal cannot equal it in value; nor can jewels of gold be a barter for it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Things above need not be mentioned: but prize thou wisdom above all things below.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The topaz of Ethiopia cannot equal it in value: nor is it to be rated by pure gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But where can wisdom be found? And where is the place of understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>It hath escaped the knowledge of every man; and is hid from the birds of the air.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Destruction and death said, We have heard the fame of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>God is perfectly acquainted with its way and knoweth its place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For he surveyeth the whole world; and knoweth all on the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>all that he hath made; the weight of winds and the measures of water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>When he had made and seen and numbered them; and also a way for the pealing thunder:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>then did he see it and declare it: and having prepared and traced it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>he said to man, Behold the worshipping of God is wisdom: and to abstain from evil is understanding.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Job still further continued his speech, with this exordium:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>O that I were reinstated as in times past! As in the days of the months when God preserved me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>when his lamp shined over my head; when by his light I walked through darkness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>when I was making my ways conspicuous; when God watched over my family;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>when I was thick set with branches, and my servants were around me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>when my ways abounded in butter, and my mountains flowed with milk;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>when I walked early through the city; and a seat was set for me in the streets!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The young when they saw me hid themselves; and all the aged stood up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The nobles forbore talking and put their finger on their mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And while they who heard me were blessing me, their tongue cleaved to the roof of their mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When the ear heard me it blessed me; and the eye when it saw me, turned aside:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>for I saved the poor from the hand of the mighty; and assisted the orphan who had no helper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The blessing of him who was perishing came upon me: and the mouth of the widow blessed me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I put on righteousness and cloathed myself with justice as with a mantle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I was eyes to the blind and feet to the lame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I was a father to those in distress; and the cause which I knew not I searched out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And I broke the jaws of the unrighteous; and plucked the prey from betwixt their teeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore I said, My youth shall advance to old age. Like the stock of a palm, I shall live long.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>My root is spread out by the water; and the dew will abide on my produce.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>This vain glory of mine shall attend me: my bow is directed by his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They who heard me paid close attention;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and at my counsel they were silent. To my decree they added nothing But were overjoyed when I spoke to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>As the thirsty earth receiveth rain, so did they my speech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If I smiled on them they could scarce believe it. And the light of my countenance was not lost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I chose their way and sat as chief, and dwelt as a king among warriors; as one who comforteth the afflicted.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But now the meanest have me in derision: now, those undertake to admonish me; whose fathers I held in contempt: whom I did not think worthy the dogs of my flocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>What in deed was the strength of their hands to me? Destruction would have been lost upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>By reason of want and famine it was useless. Already they were fleeing ineffectually from distress and misery:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>they were crouding round the samphire on the sounding shore; and feeding on sea weeds as their food; despicable and contemned and in want of every thing good, they through extreme want were chewing even the roots of trees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Against me thieves have risen up,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>whose habitations were the clefts of rocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Amidst this tuneful choir, are to be heard the brawls of them who lived under hedges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>A race of fools and despicable wretches, whose name and honour are extinguished from the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But now I am become their song: and they have me for their by-word:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and have abhorred me and stood at a distance: and have not spared to spit in my face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Because he opened his quiver and afflicted me: therefore they have cast off the restraint, which they were under at my presence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>At the right of their brood they have taken their stand: they have stretched out their foot; and vindicated against me their destructive ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>My ways are destroyed; for I am stript of my robe. With his darts he hath pierced me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>he hath used me at his pleasure. I am become loathsome by sorrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>My sorrows roll back upon me. My hope is gone like a breath, and like a cloud, my safety.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And now my soul is melting within me. Days of sorrow take hold of me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and at night my bones are melted and my sinews are quite dissolved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>With great force he took hold of my garment; and girded me about like the collar of my vest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou hast accounted me as dirt: and my portion is in dust and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Though I have cried to thee, thou hearest me not: but they stood up and observed me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and came upon me without mercy. Thou hast chastised me with a heavy hand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and placed me among sorrows; and cast me away far from safety.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For I know that death will destroy me: for earth is the house for every mortal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For! how I wish that I might lay violent hands on myself; or beseech another to do this for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>As for me I indeed wept for every one in trouble; and sighed, when I saw a man in distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But when I expected prosperity: behold days of affliction came upon me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>My bowels have boiled and could not rest: days of misery have prevented me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>I have gone mourning without restraint; and have stood in the congregation and cried.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>I have been made a brother to jackals, and a companion to ostriches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>My skin is become very black; and my bones are burning with heat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>My kithara is turned into mourning, and my song to wailing for myself.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I made a covenant with mine eyes, that I would not gaze on a virgin:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>yet what portion hath God dealt out from above?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And what, alas! the lasting portion on high? Destruction is for the wicked and banishment for transgressors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Why will he not behold my way and number all my steps?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Have I walked with scoffers or hath my foot hasted to deceit?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For I have been weighed in a just balance; and the Lord knoweth mine integrity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If my foot hath deviated from the way or my heart gone astray after mine eyes; or if with my hands I have touched bribes:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>may I sow and others eat; and let me have no root in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If my heart hath gone after another man's wife, or if I have lain in wait at her gates;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>let my wife gratify another, and mine infant children be dishonoured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the defiling of another man's wife exciteth a fury of wrath not to be restrained.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For it is a fire burning in all the limbs; which will not go out, till it hath utterly consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If I have slighted the cause of my man servant or maid servant when they had a controversy with me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>what shall I do when the Lord maketh inquest? And when he visiteth, what answer shall I make?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Was not I formed in the womb as they were? And were we not alike fashioned in the belly?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Far from depriving the poor of what they had, or causing the heart of a widow to fail;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>if I have eaten my morsel alone, and have not shared it with the orphan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>(for from my youth I as a father nourished them, and was their guide from my mother's womb)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>If I have seen the naked perishing and have not clothed them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and if the poor have not blessed me, and their shoulders been warmed with the fleece of my lambs;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>If I have raised a hand against the fatherless, because I had around me greater support:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>may my shoulder bone be dislocated, and my arm broken at the elbow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For the fear of the Lord restrained me, and the burden of that I could not endure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If I have made gold my measure, or placed my confidence in precious stones:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>or if I have exulted because my wealth was great, or laid my hand on what was not counted out to me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>or, (do we not see the refulgent sun sometimes eclipsed, and the moon continually changing? for it is not in them:)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>if then my heart hath been secretly enticed, and I have laid my hand on my mouth and kissed it</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>let this be reckoned to me as the greatest transgression, that I have lied in the presence of the Lord, the Most High.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>If I have rejoiced at the downfall of mine enemies, and my heart hath said, Aha!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Let mine ear hear myself cursed, and let me be a by-word among the people, when I am afflicted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>If my maid servants have often said, that we had some of his flesh meat to eat! while I was living luxuriously:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>(indeed the stranger lodged not in the street, and my door was open to every comer:)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>If when I sinned inadvertently, I concealed my sin;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>for I was not so awed by the multitude as not to mention it before them; (Now if I had suffered a poor man to go from my door with an empty lap,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>who could have heard me with patience?) And if I had not feared the hand of the Lord</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>I would have put on my shoulders the writing which I had against any one, and have acknowledged it as a crown:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>But if I did not tear it in pieces and give it up, without taking any thing from the debtor:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>if ever my ground hath cried out against me, and the furrows thereof joined in the complaint:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>if I have eaten alone the strength thereof without money, and by rapine caused the heart of the owner of the soil to grieve:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>let nettles spring up for me instead of wheat, and bramble bushes instead of barley.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="32">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Here Job closed his speech, and his three friends ceased from making further reply to him; for he was righteous in their sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Then was kindled the wrath of Elius the son of Barachiel the Buzite, of the family of Ram, of the country of Ausitis. His wrath was kindled against Job to a high degree, because he had declared himself just before the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And with the three friends he was very angry, because they were not able to answer Job's defence: though they had charged him with being wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now Elius had waited to answer Job, because they were older than he.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But when he saw that there was no answer in the mouth of the three men, he was fired with indignation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore Elius the son of Barachiel the Buzite taking up the argument, said, I indeed am young and you are old; therefore I kept silence and was afraid to give my opinion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For I said, Is it not age which speaketh? And by many years they have gained wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But there is a spirit in mortals; and it is the inspiration of the Almighty which teacheth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They who live longest are not the wisest, nor is the knowledge of judgment confined to the aged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Wherefore I said, Hear me, and I will tell you what I know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Listen attentive to my words, for I will speak in your hearing that you may examine them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Even now I could wish to attend to you: but behold there is none who convicteth Job; none of you who refuteth his arguments:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>that you might not say, We the Lord's advocates have found wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And you have left a man at liberty to use hereafter the same arguments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>They were daunted. They answered not again. They have antiquated their own speeches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I waited patiently: for I had not spoken. Because they stopped and made no reply,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore Elius interposing, saith, I will speak again,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for I am full of words; for I am pained with a spirit within me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>for I am like a vessel full of new wine, in fermentation, without vent; or like the labouring bellows of a smith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>I will speak that I may have ease, by opening my lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For I should not be awed by man: nor put to the blush because of a mortal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For I am not apt to admire persons. Will not Worms devour them as well as me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="33">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now therefore, Job, hear thou my words, and listen attentively to my speech;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for lo! I have opened my mouth, and my tongue hath begun to speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>My words shall proceed from a pure heart; and the sentiments of my lips shall be pure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>It is the divine spirit, which made me, even the inspiration of the Almighty, which teacheth me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>If thou art able, give me an answer; come to trial, and let us stand face to face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thou art formed out of clay, and so am I: we are both made of the same material.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>By the dread of me thou wilt not be terrified; nor will this hand of mine be heavy on thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now thou hast said in my hearing; I heard the sound of thy words: for thou saidst,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I am pure, I have not sinned; I am irreprehensible, for I have not transgressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But he hath invented an accusation against me, and hath accounted me as an enemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He hath put my foot in a clog, and watched all my ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For how, dost thou say, I am righteous, yet he hath not hearkened to me. For He, who is over mortals, is eternal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And dost thou say, Why in my trial, hath he not hearkened to me on every matter?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For the Lord may have spoken once, and again;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In a dream, for instance, or in a nightly vision: As when a dread horror falleth on men, during their slumbers on a bed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>then doth he open the understanding of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>With such appearances of terror he frighted them, to turn man away from iniquity. Again he hath saved his body from a fall,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and hath rescued his soul from death; and hath not suffered him to fall in battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Again he hath rebuked him with sickness on a bed, and benumbed all his bones;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>so that he cannot take any nourishment, (though his soul longeth for food)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>until his flesh become rotten, and he can show his bones bare.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When his soul hath come near to death, and his life near to the mansion of the dead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>though there may be a thousand messengers of death, not one of them can mortally wound him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If he determine in his heart to turn to the Lord, when he shall have shewn man his charge against him, and pointed out to him his folly, he will support him, that he may not fall to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and renew his body like the plaistering on a wall, and will fill his bones with marrow; and make his flesh soft like that of an infant, and restore him to full strength among men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when he hath prayed to the Lord, and shall enjoy acceptable things, he will come with a cheerful countenance and with thanks: and render justice to men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then will such a man blame himself, and say, What I have done! He hath not chastened me, as my sins deserve!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Save my soul, that it may not go to destruction, and let my life see light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Behold in these three ways the Almighty doth all these things with man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He hath indeed delivered my soul from death; that in light my life may praise him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Listen attentively, Job, and hear me: keep silence that I may speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>If thou hast any thing to say, answer me: speak; for I wish thee to be justified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>If not: hearken to me: keep silence and I will teach thee.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="34">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Elius proceeded and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hearken to me, ye wise men, and ye who have knowledge listen attentively.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the ear trieth words and the palate tasteth meats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let us take upon us the right of judging: Let us know among ourselves what is good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For Job hath said, I am righteous: the Lord hath removed from me the trial;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and hath disappointed me of my trial. My wound is grievous without transgression.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>What man is there like Job, who drinketh up scorning like water;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>who hath neither sinned, nor been guilty of impiety; nor associated with the workers of iniquity to walk with impious men?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For thou shouldst not say, There shall be no visitation of man. He shall indeed have a visitation from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore hearken to me, ye who are wise in heart. Far be it from me to be profane before the Lord; or before the Almighty to disturb the course of justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But he should render to every man according to each one's work; so that in his own paths every man may find him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But dost thou think that the Lord will do improper things? Or will the Almighty who made the earth, pervert judgment?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now who is this maker of the world and of all the things therein?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For were it his pleasure to confine, and keep to himself, the wind,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>all flesh would expire together; and every mortal would return to earth, of which they were formed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>See that thou be not chastened. Hear these things; listen attentively to the sound of words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Consider that he who hateth iniquity; and that he who destroyeth the wicked, being eternal, is just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He is irreverent, who saith to a king, Thou transgressest: to princes, you are acting impiously.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Who hath no respect for the person of an honourable man; nor knoweth how to honour nobles by respecting their persons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But it should be in vain for them to cry or to entreat a man, for they behaved wickedly in turning aside the weak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For he is the observer of men's actions, and nothing that they do can escape his notice:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>nor can there be a place, where the workers of iniquity can be concealed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>That he will not yet set himself against a man;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>is because the Lord superintendeth all in ways unsearchable; glorious and wonderful, not to be numbered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>As he knoweth their works: he should bring on night and they should be humbled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But hath he extinguished the wicked though they are visible before him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Because they turned aside from the law of God and did not acknowledge his judgments,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>when they cause the cry of the poor to ascend to him, he should hearken to the cry of the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>But when he giveth rest, who shall call him to account? When he hideth his face, who can see him? Both against a nation, and against a man at the same time,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>he maketh a hypocritick man king; because of the perverseness of a people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Because one saith to the Almighty, I have taken, I will not again take a pledge:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>I will look beyond myself; do thou shew me: If I have done iniquity, I will do so no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Will he for thee punish that iniquity? Because thou must deny; because thou must draw the conclusion, not I: therefore speak what thou knowest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For they who are wise in heart will say the same: and a wise man hath heard this word of mine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Job indeed hath not spoken with wisdom: his words are not with understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Therefore let Job learn and no more make reply like the foolish;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>that we may not add to our transgressions. For iniquity will be charged to our account; if we multiply speeches before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="35">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Elius proceeded and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>What thinkest thou of this in thy pleading? Who art thou that thou shouldst say, I am righteous before the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Or wilt thou say, What can I do if I sin?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I will answer thee and these three friends of thine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Look up to yonder heaven and see; and observe the clouds, how high above thee they are.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If thou hast sinned, what canst thou do? And if thou hast multiplied transgressions, what canst thou effect?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If thou art righteous, what canst thou give him? Or will he receive any thing at thy hands?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thy wickedness may affect a man like thyself: and thy righteousness, a son of man .</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>On the account of a multitude, they who are falsely accused will scream: They will call aloud because of the arm of many,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but none said, where is the God who made me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>who regulateth the watches of the night; who distinguisheth me from the beasts of the earth and from the birds of the air?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>There let them scream. He indeed may not hearken even at the abuse of bad men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Since it is not the Lord's desire to see improper things; since he, the Almighty,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>is the observer of them who do injustice; he should save me: but be judged before him. Canst thou praise him as things are?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because he doth not regard Job's anger; and hath not severely animadverted on some offence:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>therefore Job vainly openeth his mouth; he loadeth his speeches with folly.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="36">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Elius proceeded further and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Bear with me a little longer that I may teach thee: for I have still something further to say;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>taking my knowledge from abroad and from my own works,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I will speak righteous things with truth, without considering in an unjust manner things which are unjust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Know then that the Lord, who is mighty in power and wisdom;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>will not reject the innocent, nor save the wicked: and that he will administer justice to the oppressed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He will not withdraw his eyes from the righteous, but will seat them at last with kings on a throne and they shall be exalted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>When they shall be bound with fetters or held with cords of affliction,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>he will shew them their works and their transgressions, that they bear;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But he will hearken to what is just, and hath ordered them to turn from iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If they hearken and serve; they shall end their days in prosperity and their years in the enjoyment of things convenient.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But the impious he saveth not: because they would not know the Lord, and because, when they were admonished, they were disobedient,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>the hypocrites in heart shall incur wrath: they will not cry because he bound them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Let their soul therefore perish in youth and their life be wounded by angels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because they afflicted the weak and feeble, he will support the cause of the meek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Though the abyss from the mouth of an enemy;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the overflow of that from underneath hath deceived thee; and thy table which was full of fatness hath fallen: yet the cause of the righteous shall not fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But there shall be wrath against the ungodly, on account of the wicked bribes which they received for injustice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Let not the earnest entreaty of the weak in distress turn aside thee and all those in the exercise of authority.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Do not spin out the night that crowds may come to their assistance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But be careful not to do improper things: for by such a conduct thou wilt extricate thyself from distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Behold the Almighty will strengthen with his strength: for who is powerful as he? Or who can examine his works?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Or who can say, He hath done unjust things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Remember that his works are greater than what men have attempted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Every man hath seen by himself how many mortals are wounded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Behold the Almighty is multifarious in operations beyond our comprehension. The number of his years are indeed infinite</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and by him the particles of rain can be counted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When they are collected into a cloud for rain, the heavens will pour down. But when the clouds cast a shade over the dumb creation he impressed a care on beasts, and they know the order for going to bed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>At all these things is not thine understanding confounded? And is not thy heart starting from the body? Now though the outspread cloud be rushing together, to the whole extent of his pavilion,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>behold! with a clap of thunder he will expand it over him. He hath indeed covered the out branchings of the sea!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For with what he judgeth nations he can give food in abundance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>When with his hands he hath covered the light, and hath given provisional orders concerning food;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>the Lord will warn his friend that there is a portion also for injustice. Therefore</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="37">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>on the account of this my heart was troubled, and moved violently out of its place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear the report made by the fierce anger of the Lord! when a threat shall proceed from his mouth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>as his dominion extendeth over all under heaven, and his light over the wings of the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>after it he will thunder with a voice; he will thunder with the voice of his indignation. (And should it not make a change in those men when he shall cause his voice to be heard?)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>With his voice the Almighty will thunder to our astonishment; for he hath done great things which we cannot comprehend;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>issuing a command to snow, be thou on the earth; When the tempest and storms of rain, under his command</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>seal up against the hand of every man, that every man may know his own weakness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>when the beasts have entered their coverts, and have gone to rest on their beds;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>sorrows issue forth from their chambers, and cold from its lofty summits;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>which by the blast of the Almighty produce frost, and governeth the water as he pleaseth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But when a cloud covereth a man of his choice, his light can disperse the cloud:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and he at his sovereign pleasure, can cause the revolving agents to return to their works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>What things soever he giveth them in charge: these are ordered by him on the earth; and whether they be for correction, or for the benefit of the earth; or for mercy, he is to be found in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Hearken, Job, to these things and stand instructed with regard to the power of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>We know that God hath disposed his works; that he hath made light out of darkness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>That he knoweth the different purposes of clouds, and the miraculous fall of wicked men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now thy cloathing is warm and there is peace in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>With him are powerful cordials for inveterate disorders: what an appearance of an infusion!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore teach me what we shall say to him. And let us refrain from much speaking.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Have I had a book or a scribe by me, that by stopping the man I could be silent?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Though the light is not visible to all, there is a brightening in the heavens, like that which cometh in clouds from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>From the north the clouds brighten like fulgent gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For these things great is the glory and honour of the Almighty. As we cannot find another equal to him in majesty; dost thou not think that he who judgeth righteously will hear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Men therefore ought to fear him. They indeed who are wise in heart, will fear him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="38">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After Elius had finished his speech, the Lord from a whirlwind and clouds, said to Job,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Who is this who is concealing counsel from me, and who hiding words in his heart thinketh to hide them from me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Gird up thy loins like a man and I will question thee and answer thou me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Where wast thou, when I laid the foundations of the earth? And tell me, if thou hast understanding,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>who settled the measures of it? Dost thou know? Or who stretched the line upon it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>To what are the hooks of it fastened? And who laid the corner stone thereof?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When the stars were made, all my angels praised me with a loud voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>It was I who shut up the sea with gates, when it rushed eagerly from its mother's womb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>It was I who made a cloud its cloathing; and thick darkness its swaddling bands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>It was I who set bounds to it; surrounded it with bars and gates;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and said to it, Thus far thou shalt come and no farther: but in thyself thy waves shall be spent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Was it in concert with thee that I ordered the morning light; and that the day spring knew its appointed time</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>to tinge the wings of the earth; to scare the wicked from it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Didst thou take clay of the earth and form an animal and place on the earth a creature endowed with speech?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Hast thou withdrawn the light from the wicked, and broken in pieces the arms of the haughty?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Hast thou gone to the head spring of the sea; and walked in the footsteps of the abyss?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Are the gates of Hades opened to thee through fear, and are the porters of Hades struck with awe at seeing thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Hast thou informed thyself of the breadth of that under heaven? Tell me then what is the extent of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>In what country doth light make its abode, and of what sort is the place of darkness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>If thou wouldst lead me to their borders, and if thou knewest their paths;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I would know that thou wast then born, and that the number of thy years is great.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Hast thou gone to the treasuries of snow, or hast thou seen the treasuries of hail?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Are they stored up for thee, for a time of enemies; for a day of battles and combat?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>From what place doth hoar frost issue, or whence is the south wind scattered over the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Who hath prepared a course for the tempest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and a way for impetuous storms to water the ground, where there is not a man; the desert where no man dwelleth; to saturate an untrodden, uninhabited land</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and cause the bud of the tender herb to spring?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Who is the father of rain, and who hath begotten the drops of dew?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>From whose womb doth ice proceed, and who in the sky hath brought forth hail</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>which descendeth like a shower? Who hath struck with terror the face of the wicked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Dost thou know the band of Pleias, or hast thou opened the hedge of Orion?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Canst thou cause Mazouroth to come forth in his season, or drag out Hesperus by his hair?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Dost thou know the revolutions of heaven, or the things on earth corresponding to them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Canst thou summon a cloud with thy voice, and will it, with the trembling of a water spout, answer thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Canst thou despatch thunders, that they may go, and will they say to thee, Here we are?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Who hath given woman a skill in weaving, and a knowledge of the art of embroidering?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Who is it who numbereth the clouds with wisdom, and hath caused the heaven to incline to the earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>when the earth was poured out like dust, and when I have glued the very clod as for a stone?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Wilt thou hunt the prey for lions, or satisfy the appetites of dragons?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For they are trembling for fear in their dens, and lying in ambush in their coverts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Who hath provided food for the raven? For his young have cried to the Lord, wandering about in search of provisions.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="39">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hast thou known the time of the rock-goat's delivery, and watched the pangs of hinds in travail?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hast thou numbered the months they go with young, and hast thou dismissed their pangs?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Hast thou brought up their young, devoid of fear, and wilt thou dismiss their pangs also?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Shall they cast off their young, and be encreased with a new progeny, and shall they go forth and no more return to them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who hath sent forth the wild ass free, and who hath loosed his bands?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>As I made the desart his habitation, and the saltish soil his place of encampment;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>he scorneth the crowds of a city, and regardeth not the clamours of a driver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The range of mountains he will consider as his pasture, and he searcheth after every thing green.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Will the unicorn condescend to serve thee, or to go to rest at thy stall?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Canst thou bind his yoke with thongs, or will he draw thy furrows in the field?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Hast thou relied on him because his strength is great?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Wilt thou leave thy labours to him, and trust that he will carry out thy seed, and bring home thy threshed grain?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Why is the wing of the ostrich that of the sportive? For though it comprehendeth that of the stork and falcon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>yet she will commit her eggs to the ground, and hatch them in the dust;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>not remembering that the foot may crush, and wild beasts trample them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>She hardened herself against her young, as if not her's; she laboured in vain without fear;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>because God had silenced wisdom in her. But did he not impart to her some understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>At a suitable occasion she will rear herself aloft; she will laugh to scorn the horse and his rider.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Hast thou invested the horse with strength, and clothed his neck with terror?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When thou arrayedst him with armour didst thou inspire his dauntless breast with courage?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Pawing in the plain he swelleth with pride, and rusheth impetuous to the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Meeting a king he meeteth him with scorn, and turneth not back for fear of the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>On him the bow and the sword swell with pride; and his rage will cause the ground to vanish,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>nor will he believe till the trumpet sounds:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but at the sound of the trumpet he saith, Aha, and snuffeth the battle from afar, with a bound and neighing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Hath the hawk by thy wisdom poised herself aloft with wings expanded, unmoved, surveying the regions of the south?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>At thy command doth the eagle soar, and the vulture abide seated on its nest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>on the high crag of a rock, and in secret,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and continuing there seek its food? Its eyes take an extensive survey,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and its young are besmeared with blood. Wherever carcasses are, there are they suddenly found.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="40">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord God addressing Job, said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Doth he decline a trial with the Almighty? Surely he who commenceth a suit against God, should support it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon Job, in reply, said to the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Why should I continue the debate any further? I stand corrected for commencing a suit against the Lord. On hearing such things, what answer can I, who am nothing, make to Thee? I will lay my hand on my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Once I have spoken, but I will not proceed a second time. I heard of Thee before, with the hearing of the ear; but now mine eye hath seen Thee, therefore I abhor myself, and am ready to drop into dissolution, and account myself as dust and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon the Lord further said to Job from the cloud:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>No, but gird now up thy loins like a man, and let Me question thee; and do thou answer Me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Decline not the trial with Me. Dost thou think that I have spoken to thee for any other purpose, but that thou mayst appear justified?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Hast thou an arm to contend against the Lord, or dost thou thunder with a voice against Him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Assume then majesty and power, and array thyself with glory and excellence;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and send forth angels in wrath, and humble everyone who is insolent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Extinguish also the haughty, and turn the wicked into instant corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Hide them in the earth together, and cover their faces with dishonour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then will I confess that thine own right hand can save thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But behold now the wild beasts around thee, which feed upon grass like cattle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>behold that one in particular whose strength is in his loins, and whose power is in the navel of his belly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He hath raised his tail like a cypress, and his sinews are plaited together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>His ribs are ribs of brass, and his back bone is molten iron;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>he is a chief of the Lord's fashioning, made to be insulted by his angels only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When he went up to the craggy mountain, he gave joy to the four footed beasts in the vale.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They go to rest under trees of every sort, by the papyrus, the reed and the bulrush:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But by him large trees with branches, and the bushes of the field are overshadowed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Should there come a flood he would not regard it; he is confident the Jordan can roll into his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Can one look steadily at him, can one craftily bore his nose?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="41">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Canst thou draw out Dragon with a hook, or put a bandage round his nostrils?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Or canst thou fasten a ring in his snout, or bore his lip for a jewel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Will he speak to thee with entreaties; with soothing supplications?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Will he make a covenant with thee? And wilt thou take him for a perpetual servant?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Wilt thou play with him as with a bird, or bind him as a sparrow for a child?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Do the nations feed upon him, or the Phoenicians divide him among them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>With their whole fleet they could not carry the first skin of his tail, nor his head in their fishing barks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Wilt thou lay thine hand on him, recollecting the battle made by his mouth? Do not so again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Hast thou not seen him? Hast thou not been amazed at what is said of him? Hast thou not been afraid that he was prepared against me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But who is there, who hath risen up against me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>or who can rise up against me and stand to it? If the whole world is mine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I cannot be put to silence by him. On the account of his power one may pity his equal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Who can strip off his outer robe, or who can come within the folds of his breast plate?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Who can open the doors of his mouth? His teeth are encompassed with terror.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>His scales are shields of brass; and his ligature, like a smyrite stone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They are glued one to another, so that no air may pass through to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They are to adhere close to each other; they stick so close that they cannot be torn asunder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>At his sneezing lightnings flash: and his eyes have the lustre of the morning star.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Out of his mouth issue as it were burning lamps; and flaky flames, in appearance, are belched out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>From his nostrils issueth the smoke of a furnace,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>flaming with a fire of burning coals. His animal life is glowing coals; and a flame proceedeth out of his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In his neck, strength maketh its abode; and destruction runneth before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The flesh of his body is glued together; it is so abundant that he cannot be shaken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>His heart is hard as a stone, and firm as an immoveable anvil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When he turneth himself about, all the four footed beasts on the earth shrink with fear. Though spears oppose him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>they effect nothing; for with regard to the lance and the breast plate,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>he considereth iron as straw, and brass as rotten wood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The bow of steel cannot wound him; and stones from a sling he considereth as grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Battering rams are accounted as stubble; and he laugheth at the shock of eruptive fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>His bed is sharp pointed obelisks; and all the gold in the sea under him, is but as dirt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>He causeth the deep to boil like a cauldron; and considereth the sea as a pot of ointment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The deepest gulf of the sea he accounteth his captive; and reckoneth the abyss itself as his parade.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Upon the earth there is not his fellow; made to be insulted only by my angels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>He beholdeth every thing that is high; and he is king over all that are in the waters.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="42">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Job in reply, said to the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I know that thou canst do all things, and that with thee nothing is impossible.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Who indeed can conceal counsel from thee? Though he forbeareth to speak, can he think to hide it from thee? But who will tell me those things which I did not know; those great and wonderful things which I did not understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hear me, O Lord, that I may speak. And let me ask, and do thou teach me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I heard of thee before, with the hearing of the ear; but now mine eye hath seen thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore I abhor myself, and am ready to drop into dissolution, and account myself as dust and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now after the Lord had spoken all these things to Job, the Lord said to Eliphaz, the Thaimanite, Thou hast sinned and thy two friends. For you have not spoken any thing true before me, as my servant Job hath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now therefore take seven young bulls and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and he will make an offering for you; and my servant Job will pray for you. For him only I will accept; for were it not for his sake, I would destroy you, because you have not spoken what is true against my servant Job.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So Eliphaz the Thaimanite, and Baldad the Sauchean, and Sophar the Minaian, went and did as the Lord commanded them, and he forgave them their sin for Job's sake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the Lord increased Job. Upon his making supplication for his friends, the Lord forgave them their sins, and the Lord gave Job twice as much as he had before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When all his brethren and his sisters heard what had befallen him, they came to him, together with all those who were formerly acquainted with him, and having eaten and drank at his house, they comforted him, and expressed their amazement at all that the Lord had brought upon him. And every one presented him a lamb, and a quarter of a drachm of gold bullion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the Lord blessed the latter days of Job more than the former; so that his stock was fourteen thousand sheep, six thousand camels, a thousand yoke of oxen, a thousand breeding asses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And he had seven sons born to him, and three daughters, the eldest of whom he called Hemera, and the second Kasia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and the third Amalthaiakeres.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And in all the land there were no women found so fair as the daughters of Job. And their father gave them an inheritance among their brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And Job lived after this affliction a hundred and seventy years. So that all the years which he lived were two hundred and forty. And Job saw his children and his children's children, to the fourth generation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and died an old man and full of days. And it is written that he will rise again with them whom the Lord raiseth up. This is translated out of a book in the Syrian language: For he dwelt in the land of Ausitis, on the confines of Idumea and Arabia. His first name was Jobab, and having married an Arabian woman, he had by her a son whose name was Ennon. Now he himself was a son of father Zare, one of the sons of Esau, and his mother's name was Bosorra: so that he was the fifth in descent from Abraham. Now these were the kings who reigned in Edom, over which country he also bore rule. The first was Balak, the son of Beor, and the name of his city was Dannaba. And after Balak, Jobab, who is called Job; and after him, Asom who was general from the region of Thaimanitis; and after him, Adad, son of Barad, who smote Madiam in the plain of Moab; and the name of his city was Gethaim. And the friends who came to Job were Eliphaz, of the sons of Esau, the king of the Thaimanites; Baldad, the sovereign of the Saucheans, and Sophar, the king of the Minaians.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>