<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A vision which Esaias son of Amos saw, (which he saw respecting Judea and Jerusalem) in the reign of Ozias, and Joatham and Achaz and Hezekias, who reigned over Judea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hearken, heaven! and hear earth! what the Lord hath spoken. I have begotten children and brought them up; and they have rebelled against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The ox knoweth his owner, and the ass his master's crib; but Israel did not know me. And this people have not regarded me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Ah! sinful nation; people full of sins! vile race! iniquitous children! you have utterly forsaken the Lord; and provoked to wrath the Holy One of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>What! must you persisting in iniquity be smitten still more? The whole head is sick, and the whole heart faint:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>from the feet to the head, there is no soundness therein. Is it not, here a wound, there a bruise, there a putrefying sore? there is no applying poultice, nor oil, nor bandages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Your land is a desert: your cities are burnt with fire. As for your country, before your eyes strangers are devouring it; and it is laid waste, being subdued by foreign tribes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Must the daughter of Sion be left as a shed in a vineyard: and as a lodge in a garden of cucumbers; as a city taken by siege?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Had not the Lord of Hosts left us a seed, we should have been as Sodom and made like Gomorra.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hear a word of the Lord, chiefs of Sodom! Attend to the law of God, ye people of Gomorra!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>What is the multitude of your sacrifices to me? saith the Lord: I am cloyed with whole burnt offerings of rams: in the fat of lambs and the blood of bulls and goats I have no delight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>nor should you come to appear before me: for who hath required these at your hands? You shall no more be admitted to tread my court.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Though you bring fine flour; it is a vain incense: it is an abomination to me. Your new moons and sabbaths and great day I cannot endure:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>your fasting and cessation from labour; and your new moons and your festivals my soul hateth. You are become loathsome to me; I will no longer remit your sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>When you stretch forth your hands, I will turn mine eyes from you: and though you multiply prayer, I will not hearken to you: for your hands are full of blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Wash and become clean: remove iniquities from your souls; in my presence, cease from your evil deeds;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>learn to do good; seek judgment; deliver him who is injured; administer justice to the orphan, and plead the cause of the widow:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>then come: (let our controversy be brought to issue, saith the Lord) and though your sins be as a purple stain; I will make you white as snow; though they be as a stain of scarlet; I will make you white as wool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>If you indeed be willing and will hearken to me, you shall eat the good things of the land:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but if you refuse and hearken not to me, the sword shall devour you; for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken these words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>How is the faithful city become a harlot? Sion that was full of justice! In it righteousness made its abode; but now murderers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Your silver is not pure: thy vintners mix the wine with water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The chiefs are rebellious; associates of thieves: they love gifts; they seek rewards: to orphans they do not administer justice; and to the cause of widows they do not attend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the sovereign Lord of hosts. Alas for the rulers of Israel; for my wrath against these adversaries shall not abate. On these enemies of mine I will execute judgment:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and I will bring my hand over thee, and purify thee with fire. Them who are disobedient I will destroy; and I will take away from thee all transgressors,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and establish thy judges as at the first: and thy counsellors as at the beginning: and after these things thou shalt be called The city of Righteousness, the faithful metropolis, Sion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For in the exercise of judgment her captivity shall be saved: and in the exercise of mercy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>the lawless and sinful shall be crushed together; and they who have forsaken the Lord shall be utterly destroyed:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>for they shall be exposed to shame for the idols on which they doted; as they have been for the gardens which they desired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For they shall be like an ilex, which hath shed its leaves; and like a garden which hath no water:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and their strength shall be like tow; and their works like sparks of fire: and the lawless and sinful shall be burned up together; and there shall be no extinguisher.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came to Esaias, son of Amos concerning Judea and concerning Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Because in the last days, the mount of the Lord will be conspicuous; and the house of God will be on the top of mountains; and exalted above the hills: therefore all the nations will come to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Many nations indeed, will go saying, Come, let us go up to the mount of the Lord; and to the house of the God of Jacob. And he will teach us his way, and we will walk therein. For from Sion shall go forth a law; and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And he will judge among the nations; and work conviction in many a people: and they shall beat their swords into plough shares; and their spears into pruning hooks: and nation shall not lift up a sword against nation; nor shall they learn war any more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now therefore, O house of Jacob; come, let us walk in the light of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For he hath forgiven his people, the house of Israel Because their land was filled as at first with divinations; like that of the Philistines and many strange children were born to them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for their country was filled with silver and gold, and there was no counting their treasures; and their land was filled with horses, and there was no end to their chariots;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the land was filled with abominations, the workmanship of their own hands; and they worshipped the things which their fingers had made,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and the commoner bowed down and the noble humbled himself; therefore I will not forgive them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now therefore go into the rocks and hide yourselves in the earth, from the tremendous presence of the Lord; and from the glory of his majesty, when he shall arise, to crush the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the eyes of the Lord are lofty; but man is low; and the loftiness of these men shall be humbled; and the Lord alone shall be exalted in that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For the day of the Lord of hosts is against every scorner and haughty man; and against every one high and lofty, and they shall be humbled:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>even against every of those high towering cedars of Lebanon; and against every oak of Basan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and against every lofty mountain; and against every hill that is high;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and against every stately tower; and against every high raised wall;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and against every ship of the sea; and against every ensign of beauteous ships:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and every man shall be humbled; and the haughtiness of these men shall fall; and the Lord (Jehovah) alone shall be exalted in that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then will they hide all these handiworks,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>carrying them into caverns and clefts of the rocks, and into the caves of the earth, from the tremendous presence of the Lord, and from the glory of his majesty, when he shall arise to crush the lands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For on that day men will cast to the bats their abominations both of silver and gold, which they made to worship vanities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>that they may go into holes of the flinty rock: nay into the very clefts of the rock, from the tremendous presence of the Lord, and from the glory of his majesty, when he shall arise to crush the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Behold now the Sovereign Lord of hosts will remove, from Jerusalem and from Judea, all stay and support of every kind; the stay of bread and the stay of water;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the giant and mighty man and warrior; judge and prophet; instructor and elder;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>the captain of fifty, and honourable counsellor; the skilful architect and intelligent scholar:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and I will make boys their princes; and scorners shall rule over them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And upon one another the people will fall foul, and jostle every man against his neighbour; the boy against the elder and the base against the honourable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because a man will take hold of his brother, or the head of the house of his father, saying, Thou hast clothing be thou our leader, and let me be supplied with food under thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Therefore on that day he will answer and say, I will not be thy leader, for in my house there is neither bread nor raiment, I will not be the leader of this people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Because Jerusalem is forsaken and Judea is fallen therefore their tongues concur with their transgression. They disbelieve the things relating to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Because their glory is now humbled; and the shame of their countenance is risen up against them: their sin therefore, like the Sodomites, they proclaimed and openly avowed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Alas for their souls! Because they have counselled an evil counsel against themselves, saying, Let us bind the just one, for he is disagreeable to us; let them therefore eat the fruits of their deeds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Alas for the wicked! according to the works of his hands evils shall befal him. my people!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>your task masters glean you; and exactors tyrannize over you. O my people! They who call you happy lead you astray; and disturb the path of your feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But the Lord will now arise to plead his cause; and he will arraign his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The Lord will himself come to a trial with the elders of the people and with their chiefs: Why have you burned up my vineyard? And why is the plunder of the poor in your houses?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Why do you injure my people; and cover with shame the face of the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Because the daughters of Sion are haughty and have walked with outstretched neck and wanton eyes, trailing with them in their gait flowing robes, and moving in set pace with their feet;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore God will humble the princely daughters of Sion and the Lord will expose their form to view.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>On that day the Lord will take away the finery of their attire, the cauls and the curls and the crescents,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>the solitaire and the ornament of the brow,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and the gorgeous wreathed tiar, and the necklaces and the bracelets, and the zone and the rings for the fingers, and the ornaments for the right arms,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and the earrings and the robes with purple borders,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and those the middle of which is purple, and the dresses worn at home, and the Laconian gauzes and cotton robes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and those of purple and scarlet and cotton, embroidered with gold and purple; and the summer sophas:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and instead of perfumes there shall be ashes; and instead of a girdle thou shalt be girded with rushes; and instead of a golden headdress thou shalt have baldness, on the account of thy doings; and instead of the purple robe thou shalt gird on sackcloth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And thy son the most beautiful whom thou lovest shall fall by the sword; and your mighty men shall fall by the sword and be laid low;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and your wardrobes shall mourn; and thou shalt be left solitary and shalt sit on the ground;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and seven women shall lay hold on one man, saying, We will eat our own bread and wear our own raiment, let us only be called by thy name: take thou away our reproach.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But in that day God will with glorious counsel shine on the land, to exalt and dignify the remnant of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And it shall come to pass that what is left in Sion, and what is left in Jerusalem shall be called Holy. Namely all who are enrolled for life in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because the Lord will wash away the filth of the sons and the daughters of Sion, and cleanse the blood entirely from among them; by a spirit of judgment and a spirit of burning;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore when he shall come, every part of Sion and all around it shall be overshadowed by day with a cloud as of smoke, and by night with that of the light of blazing fire; and with all this glory it shall be covered;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and this will be a shade from heat, and it shall be in a shelter and covert from storm and rain.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Let me sing for the Beloved, a song of my Beloved to His vineyard. The beloved had a vineyard on a mountain in a rich soil,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and I hedged it around and trenched it; and planted it with the vine of Sorek; and in the midst of it built a tower, and hewed out therein a wine lake; and waited for its producing grapes, and it produced poisonous berries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now therefore, inhabitants of Jerusalem and men of Juda, judge between me and my vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>What more could I do for my vineyard that I have not done for it? Because I expected that it would produce grapes, and it hath produced poisonous berries;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>now therefore I will tell you, what I purpose to do with my vineyard; I will take away the hedge thereof, and it shall be exposed to plunder; and I will demolish its wall, and it shall be for a common walk;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and I will abandon my vineyard that it may neither be pruned nor digged; and brambles shall overrun it as a waste; and I will give a charge to the clouds not to shed rain upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For the vineyard of the Lord of Hosts is the house of Israel; and the men of Juda his beloved plant. I waited for their executing justice, but they committed injustice, and promoted not righteousness, but an outcry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Woe unto them who join house to house, and who are bringing field nearer to field, that they may take something from their neighbour. Are you alone to dwell in the land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For these things have come to the ears of the Lord of Hosts. For though there be many houses they shall be for desolation; though great and fair, there shall be no inhabitants therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For the ground Worked by ten yoke of oxen will not yield a bath of wine; and he who soweth six measures shall not raise three.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Woe to them, who rise early to follow strong drink, and continue at it till late at night; for the wine will inflame them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For with kithara and psaltery, tabors and pipes, they drink wine; but they regard not the works of the Lord, nor consider the operations of his hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Therefore my people are become captives, because they did not know the Lord; and multitudes have died of famine and thirst;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and Hades hath enlarged its appetite, and opened its mouth, that there may be no want of room; and down shall go the honourable and the great, and the rich and the pestilent men of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The commoner shall be humbled; and the noble dishonoured; and the lofty eyes shall be brought down;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and the Lord of Hosts shall be exalted in judgment; and God, the Holy One, shall be glorified by righteousness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and they who have been plundered shall be fed like bulls, and lambs shall graze the waste places of them who have been removed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Woe unto them who draw out sins as for a long cable: and iniquities as for an ox chain:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>who say, Let what he is to do approach speedily that we may see; and let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel come that we may know it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Woe to them who call evil good; and good evil; who put darkness for light, and light for darkness; who put bitter for sweet; and sweet for bitter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Woe to them who are wise in their own conceit, and in their own eyes prudent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Woe to your mighty men who drink wine; and to your princes who mingle strong drink:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>who justify the wicked for rewards; and deprive the just of his right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For this cause, as stubble will be set on fire by a coal, and consumed by a neglected flame; their root shall be like touch wood, and their blossom shall ascend like dust: for they desired not the law of the Lord of Hosts: but provoked to wrath the manifestion of the Holy One of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Wherefore the Lord of Hosts was incensed against his people, and he stretched out his hand against them and smote them: and the mountains were convulsed, and their carcasses were as dung in the high way: and for all this his anger was not turned away; but still his hand is high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Therefore he will erect a standard among the nations far off, and summon them from the extremity of the earth; and behold! with speed they are coming swiftly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>They will not hunger, nor will they be weary: they will not slumber, nor lie down to sleep; nor shall their girdles be loosed from their loins, nor the latchets of their sandals broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Their arrows are sharp; and their bows are bent: the hoofs of their horses have been accounted as flint, and the wheels of their chariots are like a whirlwind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>They growl like lions, and are at hand like young lions. He will seize and roar like a wild beast and drive out the people, and there shall be none to deliver them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>On that day he will roar against them like the roaring of the billowy sea; and they will look upwards to the heaven and down on the earth; and lo! distressful darkness in their tribulation.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the year in which Ozias the king died I saw the Lord seated on a high and lofty throne; and the house was filled with his glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And seraphs stood around him, each having six wings; and with two they covered the face, and with two they covered the feet, and two they used in flying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And they cried one to another and said, Holy, holy, holy is the Lord of Hosts; the whole earth is filled with his glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the lintel of the door was shaken with the sound of their cry, and the house was filled with smoke.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Whereupon I said, Ah! Woe is me! (for I was confounded) for being a man, and having unclean lips; and dwelling among a people of unclean lips, I have seen with mine eyes the king the Lord of Hosts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then one of the seraphs was sent to me and he had in his hand a live coal which he had taken from the altar with the tongs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And having touched my lips he said, Behold this hath touched thy lips, and it will take away thine iniquities and purge away thy sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then I heard the voice of the Lord, saying, Whom shall I send? And who will go to this people? And I said, Behold, here am I: send me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he said, Go and say to this people; hearing you shall hear, though you may not understand: and seeing you shall see, though you may not perceive:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for the heart of this people is stupefied; and their ears are dull of hearing; and they have shut their eyes, that for a while they may not see with their eyes; and hear with their ears; and understand with their hearts; and return that I may heal them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Whereupon I said, For how long? Lord! And he said, Until cities be wasted so as not to be habitable; and houses, so that there be no men; and the land be left utterly desolate:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And after this God will remove the men far away. They indeed who are left in the land shall be multiplied;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for still about the tenth is in it; and shall again be for a prey, and be like the ilex and like the oak when it hath fallen from its station.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the days of Achaz the son of Joatham, the son of Ozias king of Judah, Rasin king of Aram and Phakee son of Romelias king of Israel came up against Jerusalem to war against it, but could not lay close siege to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When the house of David was informed that Aram had confederated with Ephraim, the heart of the king and the heart of his people was moved, as a tree in the forest is shaken by the wind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon the Lord said to Esaias, Go out and meet Achaz, thou and Forsaken-jasub thy son, at the pool on the upper road to the fuller's field,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and thou shalt say to him, Take heed and be quiet; be not terrified, nor let thy soul be dismayed on the account of these two smoaking firebrands: for when my fierce wrath is come I will again heal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And as for the son of Aram and the son of Romelias; because they have taken evil counsel, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let us go up to Judea and confer with the people and bring them into our measures; and let us make the son of Tabeel king over it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>thus saith the Lord of hosts. This counsel shall not stand; nor shall it take effect.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But the head of Aram shall be Damascus, and the head of Damascus, Rasin; but further, in three score and five years, the kingdom of Ephraim shall cease from being a people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>though Somoron is the head of Ephraim, and the son of Romelias, the head of Somoron, yes though you may not believe nor understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Moreover the Lord proceeded to speak to Achaz saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Ask thee a sign from the Lord thy God in the depth or in the height.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Achaz said, I will not ask, nor will I try the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thereupon he said, Hear now, house of David, Is it a small matter for you to contend with men? How is it then that you contend with the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore the Lord himself will give you a sign. Behold the virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and he shall be called Emmanuel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Doth this child, before it hath known to chuse good in preference to evil, eat butter and honey,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>because previous to its knowing good or evil it disobeyeth evil to make choice of good? The land indeed which thou fearest on account of these two kings shall be relinquished;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but God will bring upon thee and upon thy people and upon the house of thy father days which have not yet come. From the day he hath taken Ephraim from Juda he will bring the king of the Assyrians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>It shall come to pass that at that time the Lord will utter a call to the flies; to that part of them which rule over the river of Egypt; and to the bee which is in the country of the Assyrians;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and they shall all come into the vallies of this country; and into the holes of the rocks; and into the caves and into every cleft.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>On that day the Lord will shave with that razor; with that which was hired on the bank of the river; with that of the king of the Assyrians, the head and the hair of the feet: and take off the beard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day, that a man will keep a young cow and two sheep;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and by reason of the abundance he will drink milk; butter and honey will be eaten by every one left in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day every where, though there may be a thousand vineyards, each valued at a thousand shekels income: they shall be for briars and thorns.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>With bows and arrows men will resort thither. Because the whole country shall be a waste of briars and thorns,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>therefore every mountain which hath been ploughed will be ploughed, wherever terror could not come; for by reason of the country's being a waste of briars and thorns, it shall be a pasture for sheep and a range for the ox.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again the Lord said to me, Take thee a strip of a large new roll and write thereon with a man's pen Speed quickly to the plunder of the spoil, for it is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And let faithful men Ourias and Zacharias son of Barachias be witnesses for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now I had approached to the prophetess and she had conceived and when she brought forth a son, the Lord said to me, Call his name Speed to the Spoil; haste to the prey;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>for before this child shall know to pronounce father or mother, the van of the king of Assyria will take the army of Damascus and the spoils of Samaria.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Again the Lord spoke yet further to me saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because this people reject the water of Siloam which floweth gently and chuse to have Rasin and the son of Romelias to rule over them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore behold the Lord will bring upon you the water of the river which is strong and abundant; even the king of Assyria and his glory; and he will rise over all your channels, and over flow all your banks;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and sweep away from Judea every man who can raise his head, or is capable of executing any thing. And the circuit of his camp shall be such as to fill the breadth of thy country, Emmanuel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Know this, nations, and be struck with consternation. Hearken ye who are in the remotest parts of the earth; be struck with consternation ye who have made yourselves strong; for though you should again become strong; with consternation you shall again be stricken,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and what counsel soever you may take, the Lord will defeat it; and what word soever you may speak shall not take effect among you; because God is with us:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord with the strong hand, to them who refuse to walk in the way of this people</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>saying, Perhaps they may order what is hard; (for whatever this people order is hard.) Be not ye terrified with the fear of them, nor dismayed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>hallow the Lord himself, and let him be thy fear:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>for if thou hast put trust in him he will be to thee a sanctuary, and you shall not run against a stumbling stone, nor as under a falling rock. But as for the houses of Jacob, they are in a trap, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem are in a pit:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>for this cause many among them shall be weak and fall and be trodden down and men will safely approach and take them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then shall they be manifest who seal up the law that it may not be learned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then will one say, I will wait for God, who hath turned away his face from the house of Jacob; and I will trust in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Here am I and the children whom God hath given me. Now when there shall be signs and wonders in the house of Israel from the Lord of hosts, who dwelleth on Mount Sion;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>if they should say to you, Apply to the belly speakers, and to them who cause a voice to proceed from the ground. Those vain babblers who speak from the belly: should not a nation apply to their God? Why consult they the dead concerning the living?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For he hath given a law for assistance; that they may not speak like such an oracle as this, which is not worth the giving of gifts for it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Upon you indeed there shall come a grievous famine; and it shall come to pass that when you are hungry, you will fret and curse the ruler and the customs of your country. And they will look up to the heaven above,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>then down on the earth beneath, and lo distress and darkness! tribulation and anguish and a gloom so as not to see!</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But he who is in distress for a season shall not be abandoned to despair. Drink this first; do it quickly. With regard to the region of Zabulon, the land of Nephthaleim and the rest who inhabit the sea shore, and the banks of the Jordan, Galilee of the nations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>ye people who walk in darkness, behold! a great light! and ye who dwell in a region, the shade of death, on you a light shall shine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>With regard to the bulk of the people, whom thou hast brought back in thy joy, they shall rejoice in thy presence, like them who rejoice in the harvest, and like them who are dividing spoils;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>because the yoke which lay upon them, is taken away, and the rod which was over their neck. For he hath broken the rod of the exactor, as in the day of Madiam:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>for, with a renewal of friendship, they shall make compensation for every robe collected by deceit, and for every garment; and shall be willing to do so, if they were burned with fire:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>because for us a child is born, and to us a son is given, whose government is on his own shoulder; and his name is called, The Messenger of Great Counsel. For I will bring peace on the rulers and health for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>His government shall be great and to his peace there is no boundary, on the throne of David and over his kingdom, to reestablish it, and support it with judgment and justice, henceforth and forever. The zeal of the Lord of hosts will do this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>THE LORD hath sent death against Jacob; and it hath come upon Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And all the people of Ephraim shall know it, and all the inhabitants of Samaria, who with haughtiness and a lofty heart say,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The bricks are fallen; but come, let us hew stones and let us cut down sycamines and cedars and build for ourselves a tower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Though God will dash down them, who rise up against him on mount Sion; and disperse his enemies</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Syria in the east, and the Greeks in the west, who are devouring Israel with open mouth; for all this his anger is not turned away, but still his hand is lifted high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The people did not turn till they were smitten; as they indeed did not seek the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>therefore the Lord cut off from Israel, head and tail, great and little in one day;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>the aged and the honourable, this was the head; and the prophet who teacheth falsehood, he is the tail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Still there will be deceivers, who will call this people happy, and lead them astray, that they may devour them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore the Lord will have no pleasure in their young men; and on their orphans and their widows he will have no compassion; because they are all wicked and regardless of law, and every mouth speaketh perversely. For all this his wrath is not turned away but still his hand is lifted high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Still iniquity will burn like a fire, and like dry stubble it shall be consumed by fire. It shall burn in the thickets of the forest, and consume all on the hills around.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>By reason of the fierce anger of the Lord the whole country is in a flame; and the people shall be as fuel for the fire. A man will have no pity for his brother,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but will turn to the right because he is hungry, and devour on the left, but shall not be satisfied. Man is devouring the flesh of his brother's arm;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>for Manasses is devouring Ephraim, and Ephraim, Manasses; for they will both together besiege Juda. For all this his anger is not turned away; but still his hand is lifted high.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Woe to them who write wickedness! For writers are writing wickedness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>turning aside the cause of the distressed; robbing the poor of my people, of their right; that the widow</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>may be their prey and the orphan, their spoil: what then shall they do in the day of visitation? For tribulation shall come upon you from afar; and to whom can you flee for succour? And where will you leave your glory,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that you may not fall into the captive band? For all this his anger is not turned away, but still his hand is lifted high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Ho! Assyrians! The rod of my wrath, even mine anger is in their hands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I will send this anger of mine to a lawless nation; and I will order this people of mine to gather spoil and take the prey, and to trample down cities and lay them in the dust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But he did not harbour such thoughts; nor did he reason thus in his mind; but his mind will prompt him to destroy nations not a few.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Even though they should say to him, Thou alone art chief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He indeed will say, Have I not taken the whole country above Babylon and Chalene, where the tower had been builded? Nay have I not taken Arabia and Damascus and Samaria?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In the same manner as I have taken these; so will I take all the governments. Howl ye graven images in Jerusalem and in Samaria;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>for as I have done to Samaria and her images, so will I do to Jerusalem and her idols.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But it shall come to pass, when the Lord hath accomplished his whole work on mount Sion and Jerusalem; that I will cast a look on the stout heart; on the chief ruler of the Assyrians, and on the loftiness of the glory of his eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For he said, With this power I will perform exploits; and by the wisdom of mine understanding I will remove the boundaries of nations, and make a prey of their strength,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and shake inhabited cities, and seize with my hand the whole world as a nest; and carry off the inhabitants like deserted eggs. There is none who can escape me or chirp against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Shall an axe boast without him who cutteth with it; or a saw lift itself up, without him who draweth it; as one could lift up a staff or a piece of wood? No; this shall not be permitted:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>indeed the Lord of hosts will send disgrace on thy honour, and on thy glory a burning fire shall be kindled:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and the light of Israel shall be for a fire, and shall hallow him with a burning fire, and consume his substance like dry grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>On that day there shall be an extinction of the mountains, and the hills, and the forests; and it shall consume from the soul even to the flesh: and he who fleeth shall be like one fleeing from blazing fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And those of them who are left shall be few in number, so that a child may write them down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day that the remnant of Israel shall no more join, nor shall those of Jacob who have escaped, any more lean on them who have injured them; but they will place their confidence in God the Holy One of Israel, in truth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>This remnant of Jacob shall indeed be for the Mighty God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Yes: though the people of Israel be as the sand of the sea, this remnant of them shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He is closing an account and making a deduction with saving goodness. Because with the whole land the Lord will make a reckoning from which a deduction hath been made,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord of Hosts, O my people who dwell in Sion, be not daunted at the Assyrian, because he will smite thee with a rod; for I am bringing this stroke upon thee that thou mayst see the way of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For yet a little while and mine indignation shall cease; and my wrath will be against their counsel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and God will raise against them a scourge similar to that of Madiam at the place of affliction. When his wrath shall be in the western road; in the high way leading to Egypt;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>it shall come to pass in that day; that his yoke shall be taken from thy shoulder, and the terror of him from thee; his yoke shall be utterly destroyed from off thy shoulders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For he will come to the city Aggai, and pass on to Mageddo; and at Machmas he will deposit his baggage:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>then he will pass the valley and come to Aggai. Terror will seize Rama the city of Saul;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>the daughter of Galleim will flee: he will be heard of at Laisa; he will be heard of at Anathoth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When Madebena hath fainted; then, inhabitants of Gibbeir,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>comfort with the news of his halting a day on his march with the hand comfort the mount, the daughter of Sion. And as for you, hills, which are in Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>behold the sovereign Lord of hosts, with majesty confoundeth the glorious. They who are elated with arrogance shall be crushed; and the lofty shall be brought low;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>yes, the lofty shall fall by the sword; and Libanus shall fall with the lofty.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And there shall spring up a shoot from the root of Jessai; even from that root shall spring up a blooming shoot;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and the spirit of God will rest upon him; a spirit of wisdom and understanding; a spirit of counsel and majesty; a spirit of knowledge and piety:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>by this spirit he will be filled with the fear of God. He will not judge according to opinion, nor will he reprove according to report;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>but he will administer justice to the lowly, and work conviction in the meek of the earth. And he will smite the earth with the word of his mouth, and with a breath from his lips destroy the wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>His loins will be girded with saving goodness, and his reins clothed with truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And a wolf shall pasture with a lamb; and a leopard shall lie down with a kid; and the calf, and bull and lion shall pasture together, and a little child shall tend them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The cow and bear shall feed together; and together their young shall herd; and the lion shall eat chaff like an ox.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the sucking child shall lay its hand on the holes of asps and on the bed of young asps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And they shall not hurt nor have power to destroy any one on the mountain which is my sanctuary. Because the whole earth is filled with the knowledge of the Lord as abundant water covereth depths of seas;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>therefore there shall be in that day, the root of Jesse, even he who riseth up to rule nations: in him nations will put their trust, and his resting place shall be glorious.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord will proceed to shew his hand to provoke to jealousy the remnant of his people; that residue which is left from the Assyrians and from Egypt and from Babylonia, and from Ethiopia and the Elamites, and from the risings of the sun and Arabia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And he will erect a standard for the nations, and gather together the outcasts of Israel, and assemble the dispersed of Juda from the four quarters of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the envy of Ephraim shall be taken away; and the enemies of Juda shall be destroyed: Ephraim shall not envy Juda; nor shall Juda vex Ephraim:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And they shall be wafted in the ships of foreign tribes; and they shall spoil both the sea and them of the east and Idumea; and upon Moab they shall first lay their hands; but the sons of Ammon shall first obey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Lord will dry up the sea of Egypt, and lay his hand on the river with a vehement wind; and smite the seven channels, so that they may be crossed dry shod.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And there shall be a passage for my people left in Egypt. It shall be for Israel as on the day when they came up out of the land of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And on that day thou wilt say, I bless thee, Lord; because, though thou wast angry with me, thou hast turned away thy wrath and pitied me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Behold! my God is my Saviour, I will trust in him and not be afraid. Because the Lord is my glory and my praise; and hath become unto me salvation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>therefore draw ye water with gladness from the wells of thanksgiving.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thou shalt say also on that day, praise the Lord: invoke his name aloud! proclaim among the nations his glorious acts: call them up to your remembrance. Because his name is exalted;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>praise ye the name of the Lord. Because he hath done stupendous acts; proclaim them throughout the whole earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Shout for joy and be glad, inhabitants of Sion, for in the midst of it is exalted the Holy One of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A vision which Esaias son of Amos saw respecting Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>On a mount in the plain, erect a standard; raise the voice to them; beckon with the hand. Open princes!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>it is I who command. It is I, who am leading these on. Giants are coming to execute my wrath, rejoicing and at the same time arrogant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>A sound of many nations on the mountains! A tumultuous sound of many nations. A sound of kings and nations gathered together! the Lord of hosts hath issued orders to a nation trained for battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They are come from a far distant country; from the extreme butment of heaven; the Lord and his trained warriors, to destroy all that inhabited land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Raise the mournful cry! for the day of the Lord is at hand, and destruction from God will come:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore every hand shall be enfeebled; and every man's heart shall be dismayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The men in power shall be confounded; and pangs shall seize them, like those of a woman in travail. And they shall bewail their calamities, one to another, and be amazed; and their countenances will quiver like a flame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For behold the remediless day of the Lord is coming; a day of wrath and indignation, to make the empire a desolation; and to destroy the sinners out of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For the stars of heaven; even Orion and the whole host of heaven, shall not give light; even that of the rising sun shall be darkened; and the moon shall not give her light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>(Jehovah, the prophet.) I will indeed order evils for the whole empire, and on the wicked their transgressions; and destroy the arrogance of the wicked; and humble the haughtiness of the proud;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>so that those left shall be more precious than tried gold and a man more precious than the ore of Souphir.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For the heaven shall be filled with wrath; and the earth shaken from its foundations; at the fierce anger of the Lord of Hosts, on the day when his wrath shall come:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and those left shall be like a chased roe and wandering sheep; and there shall be none to collect them together; so that they may return every man to his place, when every one shall be seeking his own country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For whoever is overtaken shall be thrust through and those collected in a body shall fall by the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And their infants shall be dashed to pieces before their eyes; and their houses shall be plundered and their wives ravished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Behold I am raising up against you the Medes, who disregard silver and have no need of gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>They shall break the bows of the young men, and on your infants they will have no compassion; nor will their eyes spare thee for thy children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And Babylon, which is stiled Glorious, by the king of the Chaldeans, shall be as when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorra.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>It shall not be inhabited for a great length of time, nor shall it be entered for many generations. The Arabians shall not pass through it; nor shall shepherds make their folds therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But wild beasts shall there go to rest; and the houses shall be filled with howling. There jackals shall make their abode; and there demons shall hold their revels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And onocentaurs shall inhabit there; and porcupines shall breed in the houses. He is coming quickly and will not tarry,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>but the Lord will have mercy on Jacob, and will still make choice of Israel; and they shall rest in their own land; and the stranger shall be joined to them, and shall be added to the house of Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The nations shall take them and bring them to their place; and the house of Jacob shall possess them; when they shall multiplied in their land, for men servants and for maid servants: and they who captivated them shall be captives; and they who domineered over them shall be brought into subjection.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day when the Lord shall give thee rest from thy sorrow and thy grief; from that hard servitude of thine, with which thou hast served them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that thou wilt take up this funeral song over the king of Babylon: (the chorus) How the extortioner is laid to rest! and a stop put to his demands!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The Lord hath broken the yoke of the sinners; the yoke of the rulers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He smote a nation in wrath with an incurable wound; he smote a nation with a vengeful wound which did not spare. The confidant is gone to rest;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>the whole earth shouteth for joy;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the trees of Lebanon rejoice over thee; and the cedars of Lebanon say, Since thou hast gone to rest, no feller is come up against us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Hades from beneath was in uproar to meet thee; for thee were roused all the giants who had ruled the earth. Having roused from their thrones all the kings of nations,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>they will all accost thee saying, And art thou caught as we have been? And among us art thou enrolled?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Is thy pomp come down to Hades; all thy great festivity? Beneath thee they will strew corruption for a bed; and Worms shall be thy covering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>How is Lucifer fallen from heaven! He who was harbinger of the morning; he who sent messages to all the nations is trampled down into the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou indeed didst say in thy heart, I will ascend up into heaven; above the stars of heaven I will place my throne; I will seat myself on a lofty mountain; on the lofty mountains which face the north.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I will ascend above the clouds; I will be like the Most High.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But thou must now go down to the mansion of the dead; even down to the foundations of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They who see thee will express their amazement at thee and say, Is this the man who troubled the earth? who shook kings?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>who made the world a desert? who, when he destroyed cities, never dismissed his captives?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>All the kings of the nations have been composed to rest with honour, every man in his own house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But thou shalt be cast out on the mountains, like an abominable corse, with dying crouds, pierced with the sword, descending down to the mansion of the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>As a mantle stained with blood cannot be clean; for the same cause neither canst thou be clean. Because thou hast destroyed this land of mine, and hast slain this my people; thou shalt not be of long continuance. Wicked seed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>prepare thy sons for slaughter, for the sins of their fathers; that they may not rise and possess the land, and fill the world with wars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>I will indeed rise up against them, saith the Lord of hosts, and destroy their name and remnant and seed. Thus saith the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I will lay Babylonia waste: that porcupines may inhabit it; and it shall be a desolation. And I will plunge it in the miry gulf of destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord of hosts, as I have spoken so it shall be; and as I have determined, so it shall stand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I will destroy the Assyrians on this land of mine; and on these mountains of mine they shall be trodden down; and their yoke shall be removed from my people; and their reproach shall be taken from their shoulders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>This is the counsel which the Lord hath taken against the whole empire, and this is the hand which is lifted high against all the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For who can disannul what the holy God hath decreed? and his hand which is lifted high, who can turn aside?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In the year in which king Achaz died, this Oracle was delivered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Rejoice not, foreign tribes, with one consent, because the yoke of him who smote you is broken; for from the seed of a serpent will come forth young asps, and their offspring will be flying serpents.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For the needy will be fed by him; and in peace the needy will repose. But with famine he will destroy thy seed; even the remnant of thy seed he will destroy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Raise the mournful cry ye gates of cities; foreign tribes! let harassed cities scream with one consent: for a smoke is coming from the north, which cannot be endured;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>what then will the kings of nations say in reply? That the Lord hath founded Sion, and by him the poor of his people shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The Oracle against Moab. In the night Moab is destroyed; for by night is destroyed the bulwark of Moab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Be in bitterness for yourselves; for Debon also is destroyed. Where your altar is, thither you will go up to weep for Nabau of Moab, Raise the mournful cry. On every head be baldness; let all your arms be gashed with wounds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>In the streets thereof, gird on sackcloth, and on its house tops make lamentation; and in the streets thereof and in its lanes, raise ye all the mournful cry with weeping;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>because Esebon and Eleale have screamed: even to Jassa their voice hath been heard; therefore the lungs of Moab utter lowings; her soul will be afflicted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The heart of Moab within her uttereth lowings, which reach Segor: for she is a three headed heifer. At the ascent of Louith weepers will come up to thee; by the way of Aroniim destruction and dismay are roaring.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The water of Nemereim will be dried up; and its grass will fail; there will be no green grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But even thus it shall not be saved; for I will bring the Arabs against that valley; and they shall take it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For the cry of war touched the border of Moab at Agaleim, and the scream thereof reacheth even to the well of Aileim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As for the water of Deimon, it shall be full of blood; for I will bring the Arabians against Deimon, and carry off the seed of Moab and Ariel; and the remnant of Adama</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I will send away as reptiles on the earth. Is Petra a desert? There is the mountain of the daughter of Sion to fly to</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for thou shalt be (like the young of a flown bird carried away) Thou, Moab, shalt be a vassal; and after that there will be a greater tribute of lambs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Take counsel O Sion and make for her every where a shelter from grief. In midnight darkness they will flee. They are confounded. Be not thou incensed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let the fugitives of Moab sojourn with thee. They will be a shelter to you from the face of a pursuer. Because thy share in the war is taken away; and the chief who trampled down is destroyed from this land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore a throne shall be established with mercy, and on it one shall be seated with truth; in the tabernacle of David, executing justice, and searching out judgment and promoting righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>We have heard of the haughtiness of Moab; he is very insolent. This haughtiness I have totally removed. Is not this, is not this the oracle concerning thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Moab shall raise the mournful cry, for in the country of Moab they shall all utter the cry of Woe, but to them who dwell in the habitations of Seth thou shalt extend care and shalt not be ashamed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The plains of Esebon shall mourn; the vineyard of Sebama. Ye who drink up the nations, trample down her vineyards to Jazer. You need not march in close array: roam through the wilderness. They who were dispatched were wholly given up, for they passed through quite to the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let me therefore weep, as with the weeping of Jazer, for the vineyards of Sebama. He hath cut down thy trees, Esebon and Eleale. Because in harvest and at thy vintage I will trample down and all shall be laid prostrate;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>therefore gladness and the shout of joy shall be taken from the vineyards. And in thy vineyards they shall not rejoice, nor tread out wine in thy cisterns, for a stop is put to the shout of joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For Moab therefore will my bowels sound like a kithara, and my entrails, as when thou didst consecrate a wall;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>but it will be for the purpose of making thee ashamed. Because Moab had tired himself at the altars, therefore he will go in to the works of his hands; that they may intercede; but they shall not be able to deliver him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>This is the decree which the Lord pronounced against Moab, when he spoke.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And now I say, within three years of the years of an hireling the glory of Moab shall be debased with all his abundant wealth; and he shall be left few in number and of no estimation.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The Oracle against Damascus. Behold Damascus shall be removed from among cities, and shall be for desolation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>left for ever for the folding of flocks, and for a resting place where none will scare them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And it shall no more be a fortress for Ephraim to flee to; nor shall there be again a regal government in Damascus; ever hereafter, of the Syrians. For thou art not better than the children of Israel; (Sion.) than that which was their glory. Thus saith the Lord of hosts,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>there shall be in that day a diminution of the glory of Jacob; and the fatness of his glory shall be shaken;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and it shall be as when one gathereth the standing harvest and reapeth the ears of stalks; nay, it shall be as when one gathereth stalks in a sterile vale,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>still a stalk may be left in it: or like the unripe berries of an olive tree, two or three may be left on the topmost bough, or four or five among the branches. Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>in that day let man trust in his maker, and his eyes look to the Holy One of Israel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and let him no more put confidence in altars, nor in the works of their hands which their fingers have made, nor look to the groves nor to their abominations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>In that day thy cities shall be forsaken, as the Amorites and Evites forsook theirs because of the sons of Israel: and they shall become a desolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Because thou hast forsaken God thy Saviour, and hast not been mindful of the Lord thy helper, therefore thou shalt plant a faithless plant and a faithless seed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>On the day thou plantest thou shalt be deceived. Though thou sowest in the morning, shall it bloom for harvest? or on the day when thou shalt take possession, shalt thou as the father of man take possession for thy sons?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Alas! the multitude of many nations! Like the billowy sea so shall you be tossed, and the back of many nations shall sound like water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The multitude of nations being like a great flood, their flight shall be like that of a mighty torrent rolling on impetuously. For he will repulse them with scorn, and pursue them to a great distance, like chaff before the wind when men winnow, or as a tempest driveth the dust of a wheel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Toward evening there will be grief; before morning they shall be no more. This is the portion of them who have plundered you; and this the inheritance of them, who have taken possession of you.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Ah! wings of the land of ships! Thou who surpassest the Ethiopian streams,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>thou who art sending pledges by sea, and paper messages on the water; for swift messengers will go to a lofty nation, and to a strange and fierce people. There is one far transcending it. With regard to the nation without hope and trodden down,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>at this time, all ye streams of that land, like an inhabited country, their country shall be inhabited. As if a signal were displayed from a mountain, as with the sound of a trumpet,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>let the news be spread. For thus hath the Lord said to me, There shall be safety in this city of mine; like the light of noontide heat; and it shall be like a dewy cloud in a harvest day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Before the vintage, when the blossom is perfect, and the young grape is swelling in the blossom; the diminutive bunches are to be cut off with pruning hooks, and the small shoots, to be nipped off and cut away,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and left together for the birds of the air, and for the wild beasts of the earth. And against them will be gathered all the birds of the air; and all the wild beasts of the earth will come upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>At that time gifts will be brought to the Lord of Hosts from a people afflicted and peeled; even on account of a people great from this time and forever. A nation having hope, though trodden down, which is in a part of the river of its country, will send them to the place of him, whose name is the Lord of Hosts, even to mount Sion.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A vision concerning Egypt. Behold the Lord is seated on a swift cloud; and he will come into Egypt; and the idols of Egypt shall be moved at his presence; and the heart of the people shall melt within them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And they shall be stirred up, Egyptians against Egyptians, and shall fight; brother against brother and neighbour against neighbour, city against city, and name against name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the spirit of the Egyptians shall be troubled within them: and I will dissipate their counsel; and they will consult their gods and their idols; and them who cause a voice to proceed from the ground, namely the belly speakers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And I will deliver Egypt into the hands of men: cruel lords; and fierce kings shall have dominion over them. Thus saith the Lord of Hosts,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The Egyptians drink water even that near the sea, but the river shall fail and be dried up;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>both the streams and the canals of the river shall fail; and every collection of water shall be dried up, even every fen, where reeds and papyrus grow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And all the quick springing herbage which is around the river, and every thing which is sown by the river shall be dried up and withered by the wind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the fisher men shall mourn; all who cast drags in the river shall mourn; and they who spread nets and they who are anglers shall grieve:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and shame shall seize them who work the split flax, and them who work up the cotton.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They who are employed in such works shall be in sorrow; and they who brew beer shall mourn and be grieved in soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The princes of Tanis shall be fools, those wise counsellors of the king, their counsel shall be turned into folly. How can you say to the king, We are sons of wise men, sons of ancient kings?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Where now are these wise men of thine? Let them tell thee publickly and declare what the Lord of hosts hath determined against Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The princes of Tanis have failed; and the princes of Memphis are exalted, and they will lead Egypt astray, tribe by tribe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For the Lord hath mingled for them a spirit of error, and they with all their works have made Egypt reel, as a drunkard doth, when he is vomiting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So that there shall be no work among the Egyptians, of which one can make head or tail, beginning or end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And in that day the Egyptians shall be like women in fear and trembling because of the hand of the Lord of Hosts which he will lay upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the country of the Jews will be a terror to the Egyptians: when any one shall mention it to them, they will be in terror, because of the counsel which the Lord of Hosts hath determined against it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>In that day there shall be five cities in Egypt which shall speak the language of Chanaan. And swear by the name of the Lord of Hosts: and one of them shall be called the city of Asedek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And in that day there shall be an altar for the Lord in the country of the Egyptians, and at its boundary a pillar for the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and it shall be an everlasting sign for the Lord, in the country of Egypt. Because they will cry to the Lord on account of their oppressors, therefore he will send them a man who will save them: he will vindicate their cause and deliver them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the Lord will be made known to the Egyptians, and the Egyptians will acknowledge the Lord in that day, and offer sacrifices and make vows to the Lord and perform them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thus will the Lord smite the Egyptians and heal them, and they shall be turned to the Lord, and he will hearken to them and heal them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>In that day this will be the highway from Egypt to Assyria; and Assyrians will come to Egypt and Egyptians to Assyria; and the Egyptians shall serve the Assyrians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>In that day Israel shall be a third, among the Egyptians and among the Assyrians, blessed in the land which the Lord of Hosts hath blessed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>saying, Blessed is my people which is in Egypt, and which is in Assyria and Israel which is mine inheritance.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the year that Tanathan having been sent by Arna king of Assyria went to Azotus and fought against it and took it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>at that time the Lord spoke to Esaias son of Amos saying, Go and take the sackcloth from thy loins and loose thy sandals from thy feet; and having done so walk stripped and bare foot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the Lord said, As my servant Esaias hath walked stripped and bare foot, three years; three years he shall be for signs and wonders to the Egyptians, and Ethiopians,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that in this manner the king of Assyria will lead away the captives of Egypt and Ethiopia, young and old, naked and barefoot, exposing to view the shame of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And they being subdued shall be ashamed of the Ethiopians in whom the Egyptians had placed confidence; for they were their glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And in that day the inhabitants of this country will say, Behold we trusted to flee for help to them, who were unable to deliver themselves from the king of Assyria: how then shall we escape?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The vision of the Desert. As, when a whirlwind having passed through a desert, is rushing out of a desert, the sight from the land is terrible;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>this vision being also dreadful, was revealed to me. The treacherous dealeth treacherously; the transgressor transgresseth; the Elamites are upon me; and the elders of the Persians are coming against me. Am I now to groan and comfort myself?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For this cause my loins are filled with fainting; pangs have seized me like a woman in travail. I did wrong not to hear; I shuddered so that I could not see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>My heart is bewildered, transgression overwhelmeth me. My soul is on the brink of despair.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Prepare the table. Eat, drink ye chiefs. Having arisen prepare shields.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because thus the Lord said to me, Go set a watchman for thyself and proclaim what thou seest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thereupon I beheld a chariot with two riders, and a rider on an ass and a rider on a camel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Listen with the utmost attention, said the Lord, and call A fair breeze to the watch tower? I have kept my station all the day long, and by the camp I have stood the whole night;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and behold here cometh a man riding in a chariot, and addressing me he said, It is fallen! Babylon is fallen! and all her images, and all the works of her hands are dashed on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hear this ye who have been forsaken! and ye, who have been sorely grieved, hear what I have heard from the Lord of Hosts: what the God of Israel hath announced to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The vision concerning Idumea. TO me one calleth from Seir, Guard ye the fortifications,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I keep watch morning and night. If thou wouldst inquire; inquire and dwell near me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou mayst go to rest in the western forest, or in the way to Dedan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>inhabitants of the country of Thaiman, bring out water to meet the thirsty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>meet with bread them who are fleeing, because of the multitude of the slain; and because of the multitude of dispersed: and because of the multitude of swords; and because of the multitude of bended bows; and because of the multitude of them who have fallen in battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For thus hath the Lord said to me, Within a year, according to the year of an hireling, the glory of the children of Kedar shall fail;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and the remnant of the mighty bowmen of Kedar shall be small. For the Lord God of Israel hath spoken.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The Oracle concerning the valley of Sion. What aileth thee, that you are all now gone up to the house tops?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>This vain city is full of people shouting. Thy slain are not slain with the sword; nor have thy dead died in battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>All thy chiefs have fled and they who are taken are cruelly bound. Even the mighty men in thee have fled far away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Therefore I said, Let me alone; let me weep bitterly: labour not to comfort me, for this distress of the daughter of my people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For it is a day of trouble and destruction and treading down. There is indeed some wandering from the Lord of Hosts; in the valley of Sion they are wandering about; from the least to the greatest they are wandering on the mountains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But the Elamites have taken up their quivers; and the horsemen have mounted their horses; and the army is arrayed in order for battle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and on they will come. Thy choicest valleys shall be filled with chariots; and the horsemen will block up thy gates,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and burst open the gates of Juda; and look, on that day, into the choicest houses of the city;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and lay open the stores of the houses of David's citadel. They indeed know that they are many, and that the water of the old pool is turned into the city,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and that the houses of Jerusalem have been pulled down, to fortify the wall in the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>You have indeed provided water for yourselves, between the two walls nearer than the old pool, and have not looked to him who formed it of old, nor regarded him who created it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Though the Lord of hosts, on that day, called for mourning, and lamentation, and for shaving of hair and girding with sackcloth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>yet they indulged themselves in joy and gladness, slaying oxen and sacrificing sheep, that they might eat flesh and drink wine, saying, Let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Yes, these were their undisguised expressions, in the hearing of the Lord of hosts, therefore this sin will not be forgiven you till you die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord of Hosts, Go to the treasury; to Somnas the steward, and say to him, Why art thou here?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and what hast thou here? that thou hast hewn out for thyself a monument, and hast made for thyself a sepulchre on high, and graved for thyself a tabernacle in a rock?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Behold the Lord of hosts is now driving out and will utterly destroy men of rank, and he will take away thy robe and this gorgeous crown of thine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and whirl thee into a large immeasurable country, and there thou shalt die. And he will bring to disgrace thy splendid chariot, and make the house of thy chief a publick walk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And when thou shalt be removed from thine office and station:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>it shall come to pass in that day, that I will call my servant Eliakim son of Chelkias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and clothe him with thy robe. And this crown of thine I will confirm to him, and I will commit to his hands this office of thine: and he shall be as a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to them who dwell in Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And I will give him the glory of David, and he shall rule and there shall be no antagonist; and on his shoulder I will lay the key of the house of David; and he will open and none shall shut; and he will shut and none shall open:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and I will make him a ruler in a sure place, and he shall be a throne of glory for the house of his father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And on him will rely with confidence, every honourable man in his father's house, from the least even to the greatest. On him they shall be dependant in that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord of Hosts, The man who is now fixed in a sure place shall be removed and taken away and shall fall; and the glory which is on him shall be utterly destroyed for the Lord hath spoken it.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The Oracle concerning Tyre. Raise the mournful cry, ships of Carthage, for Tyre is destroyed and there are no arrivals from the land of the Kitians. She is carried away captive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Who could be compared with the dwellers in this island; these merchants of Phoenicia, who traversed the ocean;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>this offspring of merchants on many a water, who made a traffick of nations as of an ingathered harvest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Be ashamed, Sidon, said the sea; even the strength of the sea said, I did not travail nor did I bring her forth; nor did I nourish her youths, nor educate her virgins;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>yet when the news shall reach Egypt, sorrow for Tyre will take hold on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Away to Carthage! Raise the mournful cry, ye who inhabit that isle!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Was not she your boast of old, before she was delivered up?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who hath taken this counsel against the Tyrians? Is she inferior? Or hath she not power? Her merchants are glorious chiefs of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The Lord of Hosts hath determined to destroy all the haughtiness of the glorious; and to bring to contempt every thing glorious on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>work thy land: for ships no more arrive from Carthage,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>nor is thy hand which vexed kings, any more powerful by sea. The Lord of Hosts hath given a command, concerning Chanaan, to destroy its power:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and shall it be said, You must not proceed to insult and distress the daughter of Sidon? Nay though thou shouldst go to the Kitians; yet even there thou shalt not have rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Away to the land of the Chaldeans, though it hath been wasted by the Assyrians; because its walls had fallen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Raise the mournful cry, ships of Carthage, because your strong hold is destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day, that Tyre shall be forsaken seventy years, according to the days of a king, according to the time of a man. And it shall come to pass after seventy years, that Tyre shall be as the song of a harlot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Take a kithara, stroll about, city, O harlot long forgotten! Play skilfully; sing many songs, that thou mayst be remembered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And it shall come to pass after seventy years, that God will take account of Tyre, and she shall be restored to her former state, and be a mart for all the kingdoms of the world; which are on the face of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And her traffick and gain shall be holy to the Lord. All her gain shall not be treasured up for themselves, but for them who dwell before the Lord, that they may eat and drink and be filled, and for contributions to be kept in remembrance before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Behold the Lord is about to destroy this inhabited land! He will lay it waste and uncover the face thereof and scatter abroad them who dwell therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And it shall be as with the people so with the priest; as with the servant, so with the master; as with the maid, so with the mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller, as with the lender, so with the borrower; as with the debtor, so with the creditor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>With destruction the land will be destroyed, and with spoiling this land will be ransacked: for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The land mourned and this empire is destroyed; the lofty people of the land mourned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>As for the land, it transgressed by means of its inhabitants. Because they transgressed the law, and changed the institutions; the everlasting covenant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore a curse devoureth the land. Because they who dwell therein have sinned, therefore the inhabitants of the land shall be distressed, and few are the men who shall be left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The wine will mourn, the vineyard will mourn, and all that were merry hearted will sigh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The mirth of the tabrets hath ceased, the sound of the kithara is no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They are confounded: they have drunk no wine. The palm wine was bitter to them who drank it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Every city is desolated: the houses will be shut up that none may enter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Raise the mournful cry every where for the wine. A stop is put to all the joy of the land; all the joy of the land is gone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The cities will be left desolate, and the houses being forsaken will be destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>All this shall come to pass in this land, in the midst of the nations. As when one shall shake an olive tree, so shall they be shaken: and when the vintage is over</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>a shout will be raised. But they who are left in the land shall be gladdened with the glory of the Lord. The water of the sea will be troubled:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>for this cause the glory of the Lord will be in the isles of the sea. In the isles of the sea the name of the Lord will be glorious.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Lord the God of Israel! from the outskirts of the earth we have heard of thy wonders: there is hope for the righteous. Let them say also, Woe to the rebels who reject the law?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Terror and a pit and a snare are for you who dwell in the land:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and it shall come to pass, that he who fleeth from the terror, shall fall into the pit; and he who getteth out of the pit, shall be caught by the snare. Because the flood gates of heaven are opened, therefore the foundations of the land shall be shaken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>With confusion the land will be confounded; with perplexity this land will be perplexed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>It reeled to and fro like a drunkard when intoxicated: like a lodge in a vineyard the land shall be shaken. For iniquity hath prevailed over it; and it shall fall and shall not be able to rise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>When God shall bring his hand on the hosts of heaven, even upon the kings of this land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the congregation thereof shall have been assembled for imprisonment, and shut up as chaff for many generations; of them there shall be a visitation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>When the bricks shall have mouldered away, and the wall shall have fallen; because the Lord will commence his reign from Sion and from Jerusalem, and be glorified in the presence of the elders;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>O Lord God, thee I will glorify: in songs of praise I will extol thy name. For thou hast executed wonderful things, a counsel of old immutably true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Because thou hast reduced cities to a heap of ruins; cities made strong, that their foundations might not fall; (a city of wicked men cannot be built to last forever)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>therefore the distressed people will bless thee and the cities of injured men will give thee thanks;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>for thou hast been the support of every humble city and the defence of them who were dispirited; by reason of their weakness. From wicked men thou will deliver them. Thou art the support of the thirsty and the breath of men in distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When dispirited men shall be thirsting in Sion on account of wicked men to whom thou hast delivered us up;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>then will the Lord of Hosts make provision for all the nations. On this mount they shall drink gladness:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>they shall drink wine and be anointed with myrrh on this mount. Hand down all these things to the nations for this counsel is for all the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Mighty death had swallowed up; but the Lord God hath again wiped every tear from every face; and removed from the whole earth the reproach of this people. For the mouth of the Lord hath spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And in that day they will say, Behold our God in whom we trusted, will indeed save us. He is the Lord, for him we waited and exulted; let us therefore rejoice in our salvation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>God will give rest on this mountain. When the country of Moab shall be trodden down, as a threshing floor is trampled with cars</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and he shall cause his hands to relax, as he indeed humbled him to be slain, and shall humble his pride; those things on which he hath laid his hands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and shall lower the height of his wall of refuge; and it shall be laid low in the dust: in that day shall this song be sung in the land of Judea.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>(c.) Behold we have a strong city! he will make salvation its wall and outworks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Open the gates; let the people enter, who keep righteousness and who keep truth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>who support truth and keep peace; because their confidence is placed in thee, Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>who art to everlasting, the Mighty, the Eternal God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>who hast humbled and brought down them who dwell in lofty places. Fortified cities thou canst demolish and level them with the dust,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>that the feet of the meek and lowly may trample them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The way of the pious was straight; the way of the pious was well prepared;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>for the way of the Lord is justice. We have trusted in thy name and in that remembrance</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>which is the desire of our soul by night. To thee, God, my spirit awaketh early, because thy statutes are a light on the earth. Learn righteousness ye dwellers on earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for the wicked one is no more. Whoever will not learn justice on earth, cannot act agreeably to truth. Let the wicked be removed that he may not see the glory of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thy hand, Lord, was lifted high; but they did not know it; but when they know they will be ashamed. Zeal will seize an uninstructed people; even now a fire devoureth the adversaries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Lord, our God, grant us peace, for thou hast forgiven us all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Lord, our God, take possession of us! Besides thee, Lord, we know none other. We celebrate thy name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>As for those who are dead they would not see life, nor could physicians raise them up; therefore thou hast removed and destroyed and taken away all their males. Heap, Lord, evils upon them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Heap evils on the vainglorious of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Lord, in affliction I remembered thee. Thine instruction to us was with a small affliction;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and as a woman in labour, when near delivery, crieth in her pangs, so have we been to thy beloved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>On account of the fear of thee, Lord, we conceived and suffered the pangs of child birth, and brought forth the spirit of thy salvation; for what we did in that land we are not to fall; but all the dwellers in that land are to fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The dead shall be raised up again, even they in the tombs shall be raised up: and they in this land shall be filled with joy: for the dew from thee is healing for them; but the land of the ungodly shall fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Go my people, enter into thy chambers; shut thy door: hide thyself for a little while; until the anger of the Lord is passed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For behold the Lord from his sanctuary is about to bring wrath on the inhabitants of this land; and the land will disclose the blood on it, and will no longer cover the slain.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In that day God will bring his holy sword, even his great and powerful sword, upon the dragon, the flying serpent; Upon the dragon, the crooked serpent; he will slay the dragon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>In that day the fair vineyard; I have a mind to lead a responsive song against this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I am a strong city, a city besieged. In vain shall I supply her with drink: for by night she will be taken, and by day she will fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>There is no wall, or it hath not availed her. Will any one set me to watch a stalk in a field? On account of this warfare I have rejected her. For this cause therefore the Lord hath executed all that he determined.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I am about to be burned up. Let the inhabitants therein cry aloud, Let us make peace with him. Let us make peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They who are coming are children of Jacob. Israel shall bloom and blossom; and the world shall be filled with his fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He shall not, as he smote, be so smitten: nor, as he slew, shall he be so slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Having fought and disgraced them he will let them go. Thou hast not been visiting with this severe wind, to destroy them utterly with a blast of anger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>By means of this the iniquity of Jacob will be removed: and this will be to him a subject of thanksgiving, when I take away his sin: when they grind to powder all the hewn stones of their altars, and their groves no longer remain, and their idols hacked to pieces like a forest are far away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The folded flock shall be disconsolate, like a flock which hath been forsaken; and for a long time the country shall be for a pasture, and flocks shall there take their rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And after a time there will be no verdure in it, by reason of its being parched up. ye women who are coming from a goddess attend! For this is not a people, who have understanding; therefore he the city. the vineyard. who made them will not have pity on them; nor will he who formed them shew them any favour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But it shall come to pass in that day, that God will hedge them about from the channel of the river even to Rinocorouron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Therefore gather ye the sons of Israel together one by one. And it shall come to pass in that day, that the great trumpet shall be sounded and those shall come who are perishing in the land of Assyria, and they who are perishing in Egypt; and shall bow themselves down before the Lord, on this holy mountain in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>AH! the crown of haughtiness! The mercenaries of Ephraim! That flower which hath fallen from the glory on the top of the fertile mountain! Ye who are drunk without wine!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Behold the wrath of the Lord is a harsh and terrible thing. Like a tempest of hail furiously driven when there is no shelter, like a mighty deluge sweeping a country. In this land it will put a stop to the labour of hands;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and with the feet shall be trampled down the crown of your pride, mercenaries of Ephraim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the flower which hath dropped from the hope of the Glory, on the top of the lofty mountain, shall be like the early fruit of a fig tree, which he who seeth it will wish to devour, before he can get it into his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>In that day the Lord of Hosts will be the crown of hope; the diadem of glory to the remnant of the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They shall be left for the spirit of Justice; to administer justice and destroy the power of the opposers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For by wine these were made transgressors; they were led astray by strong drink. Priest and prophet were stupefied with strong drink; they were gorged with wine; they were agitated by drunkenness; they reeled to and fro. This is oracling!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>A curse shall devour their counsel; for their counsel is for the sake of gain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>To whom, say they have we announced evils? And to whom have we announced a message; we who have been weaned from milk, we who have been withdrawn from the breasts?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Expect affliction on affliction; hope on hope, yet a little While: yet a little while.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>On account of the mockery of their lips; because they will speak to this people with a strange tongue, saying to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The sententious speeches of the false prophets.) This is the rest for him who is hungry: and this is the destruction, but they would not hear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Therefore the oracle of God will be to them? Affliction on affliction; hope on hope, yet a little while, yet a little while? that they may proceed on and fall backwards; and they shall be broken and snared and caught.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore hear the word of the Lord, ye afflicted men, and ye rulers of this people in Jerusalem!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because you said, We have made a covenant with death: and with the grave we have made a treaty: though the furious tempest may pass through, it will by no means reach us. We have made falsehood our refuge and by this falsehood we shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Sovereign Lord; behold I lay for the foundation of Sion a stone of inestimable worth; a chosen, precious corner stone for the foundations of it, and he who believeth shall not be ashamed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And I will establish judgment for hope, and my mercy shall be for scales. But as for you who have vainly trusted in falsehood, that the tempest would not reach you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and that it would not break your treaty with death; the hope which you have with respect to the grave shall not last: when the furious tempest cometh, by it you shall be beaten down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When it cometh it will overtake you. Early, very early in the morning it will come, and at night your hope will be wretched. Learn to hear,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>We are straitened for room, we cannot fight. We are weakened by your pressing upon us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Like a mountain of wicked men the Lord will rise up; and he will be in the valley of Gabaon. With wrath he will execute his work; a work of bitterness; and his wrath will attack in a strange manner; and its severity will be unusual.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>As for you therefore, be not filled with joy, yet let not your bonds gather strength. For the things are complete and decisive which I have heard from the Lord of Hosts; which he will execute on all this land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Listen and hear my voice; attend and hearken to these words of mine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Will the ploughman plough the whole day? Or prepare seed before he hath tilled the ground?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Doth he not, when he hath levelled the face of the soil, then sow the small dill or cummin? and again sow wheat and barley and millet and rye in all thy borders?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So thou shalt be corrected by the judgment of God; and be made glad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For the dill is not cleaned with a corn drag; nor is the wheel of a wain to turn round on the cummin; but with a rod are beaten out the dill; and cummin. Yet with bread they will be eaten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For I, The I AM will not be angry with you forever, nor shall the voice of my severity destroy you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>These wonders have indeed proceeded from the Lord of Hosts.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hold consultation; exalt vain comfort. Ah city Ariel, against which David fought! collect provisions year after year; eat; for you shall eat with Moab;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for I will bring distress upon Ariel, and her strength and her riches shall be for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I will indeed encompass thee as David did; and surround thee with a rampire; and erect towers around thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But when thy words shall be brought down to the ground; and shall be as if they sounded out of the earth; and thy voice on the ground shall be feeble;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>then shall the riches of the wicked be as the dust of a wheel, and the multitude of thine oppressors as chaff blown away: and this shall be as in a moment, suddenly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For from the Lord of Hosts there will be a visitation: a hurricane and a devouring flame of fire, with thunder and an earthquake and a mighty noise;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the wealth of all the nations which encamped against Ariel, and all they who are warring against Jerusalem, and all who have been assembled against her, and those distressing her, shall be like one dreaming dreams by night:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and like men who in sleep are eating and drinking, but when they awake the dream is vain: even as a thirsty man dreameth that he drinketh, and when he waketh he is still athirst, his soul having trusted in a shadow: so shall be the wealth of all the nations, who have warred against mount Sion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Be sunk in dejection and stand astonished; be drunk and reel, not with wine nor strong drink;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for the Lord hath drenched you with a spirit of stupefaction, and will close up the eyes of them and of their prophets and their rulers. As for your seers of hidden things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>all these prophesies will be to you like the words of a book which is sealed: which when they give to a man skilled in letters, saying, Read this: He will say, I cannot read it, for it is sealed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And should the book be put in the hands of an illiterate man, and they say to him, Read that, he will say, I do not know letters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The Lord hath indeed said, This people draw near to me with their mouth; and with their lips they honour me; but their heart is far from me: and in vain do they worship me, teaching the commands and doctrines of men:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>therefore, behold, I will proceed to the removal of this people and I will remove them; and destroy the wisdom of the wise, and darken the understanding of the prudent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Alas! for them, who deeply form a design, but not by the Lord. Alas! for them, who form designs in secret, that their works may be in darkness; and who will say, Who hath seen us, and who can find out us, or what we do?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Are not you to be considered as the potter's clay? Shall the thing formed say to the former of it, thou hast not made me. Or shall the work say to the workman thou hast not made me wisely?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Is it not a little while, ere Libanus shall be changed to a likeness of Mount Carmel? And Carmel be accounted a forest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And in that day the deaf shall hear the words of a book, and they in darkness, even they in thick darkness; the eyes even of the blind shall see;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the distressed shall exult with joy because of the Lord; and the disconsolate among men shall be filled with joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The lawless one hath failed, and the haughty one is destroyed, and these are utterly cut off who maliciously commit iniquity,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and who by reasoning cause men to err. But as for all them who reprove in the gates they will indeed lay a stumbling block, because of their having turned aside the righteous one for the unrighteous,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>therefore, thus saith the Lord respecting the house of Jacob, whom he set apart from Abraham; Jacob will not be ashamed now, nor will he now change his countenance;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>but when his children shall see my works, because of me they will hallow my name. They will hallow the Holy One of Jacob, and tremble before the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they who have erred in spirit will gain knowledge, and the murmurers shall be taught obedience, and the trifling tongues will learn to speak peace.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>AH rebellious children! saith the Lord, you have formed a design, but not by me: and thou hast made convenants, but not by my spirit, that you may add sins to sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>They are setting out to go down to Egypt, without having consulted me; to be assisted by Pharao and protected by the Egyptians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the protection of Pharao will be your shame, and a disgrace to them who have trusted in Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because generals are unwelcome messengers at Tanis,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>they shall labour in vain with a people who will be of no service for assistance; but for a shame and disgrace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This is the vision of the four footed beasts in the desert; A lion and a lion's whelp were in distress and difficulty; and from them went the asps and the brood of flying serpents, who carried their wealth on asses and camels to a nation which could not profit them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>In vain and to no purpose will the Egyptians help you. Announce to them, That this application of yours is vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now therefore sit down and write these things in a tablet and make a book that they may be for the appointed time; even for the time to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Because this is a rebellious people; lying children, who would not hear the law of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>who say to the prophets, Preach not to us, and to them who see visions, Speak not to us, nay, speak to us and tell us another error,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and turn us from this way, and take from us this path, and take from us the oracle of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Holy One of Israel, because you have disbelieved these words and placed your hopes on a lie: and because thou hast murmured, and been confident in this matter;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>therefore this sin shall be to you like the tottering wall of a fortified city, which hath been taken by surprise; the fall of which is instantaneous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And its fall shall be like the breaking of an earthen vessel, the fragments of which are so small that there cannot be found among them a sherd on which thou canst carry fire or with which thou canst scoop up a little water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Lord. The Holy One of Israel, when thou shalt return sighing, then thou shalt be saved, and thou shalt know in what a situation thou wast, when thou didst trust in these vanities. Your strength was vain, yet you would not hearken,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>but said, We will flee on horses. Therefore flee you shall. And, We will mount swift coursers, therefore swift shall be your pursuers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>A thousand shall flee at the voice of one; and at the voice of five, many thousands shall flee: until you be left like a beacon on a mountain, and like a flag staff upon a hill.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But again the Lord will wait to be gracious to you, and will therefore be exalted for compassionating you. Because the Lord your God is judge, happy are they who wait for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because a holy people will dwell in Sion, and Jerusalem with weeping cried, Have mercy upon me. Therefore he will have mercy upon thee. When he heard the sound of thy cry, he hearkened to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When the Lord shall have given you bread of affliction and stinted water, they who lead thee astray shall no more come near thee. Because thine eyes will see them who are leading thee astray</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and thine ears will hear the words of the deceivers behind thee who say, This is the way let us walk in it, whether to the right or left;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>therefore thou wilt defile thine idols plated with silver, and cut to pieces those overlaid with gold, and scatter them like polluted water and cast them out as dirt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then shall there be rain for the seed of thy land, and the bread of the increase of thy land shall be both abundant and nutritive; and thy cattle shall feed in rich and large pastures.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Your bulls and your cattle which till the ground shall eat provender mixed with winnowed barley.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And there shall be on every lofty mountain, and on every high hill streams of water in that day, when many shall be perishing and when towers may be falling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun; and the light of the sun shall on that day be seven fold; when the Lord will heal the bruises of his people, and when he will cure thy painful wound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Behold the name of the Lord cometh for a time, a burning wrath. The oracle of his lips with glory is an oracle full of indignation, and the fury of the wrath devoureth like fire;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and his breath is like a sweeping flood in a valley, which will reach up to the neck and swell to confound nations for their vain errors. When error shall pursue them and overtake them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>before their face ought not you to rejoice continually and continually go to my solemnities like them who are celebrating a festival? Like them who are gladdened you should go with instrumental music to the mount of the Lord, to the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>When the Lord shall cause the glory of his voice to be heard; when, to display the fury of his arm with wrath and indignation and consuming fire, he shall utter tremendous thunder, accompanied with a furious tempest of rain and hail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For by the voice of the Lord the Assyrians shall be beaten down by the stroke with which he will smite them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>This indeed he shall have from all around him; from every place whence they had a hope of that assistance on which he relied, they will with timbrels and the kithara fight against him, after his rout.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Of thee he will previously demand (and hast thou not provided for his reign) a deep valley and wood laid up in piles; the wrath of the Lord will be fire and wood in abundance like a valley burning with brimstone.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>ALAS! They went down to Egypt for help! They trusted in horses and chariots; for they have many and their cavalry is very numerous; and did not rely on the Holy One of Israel, nor did they ask counsel of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Therefore he in his wisdom brought evils on them: and that his word may not be slighted, he will rise up against the houses of wicked men and against this hope of theirs which is vain</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>against an Egyptian; a man, not a god; against the flesh of horses in which there is no help. When the Lord shall lay his hand upon them, then shall these helpers fail and be all destroyed together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because the Lord hath thus said to me, As the lion or the young lion will roar over the prey which he hath taken; and will repeat his roaring over it, until the mountains are filled with his voice, and the multitude are subdued and terrified at his wrath: so will the Lord of Hosts descend to encamp on this mountain; on this Sion; on the summits thereof:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>as birds hover over their young, so will the Lord of Hosts protect Jerusalem; he will hover over it and spring forward, and will protect and save it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore turn to him, O children of Israel, who are taking deep and wicked counsel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Because men will in that day reject the works of their hands; their idols of silver and gold which their hands have made;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>therefore Assur shall fall; not by the sword of a man of valour, nor shall the sword of a mortal devour him; and he shall flee; (not from the face of the sword) and the young men shall be for destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For with a rock they shall be enclosed as with a rampart, and shall be subdued; and he who fleeth shall be taken. Thus saith the Lord; Happy he who hath a seed in Sion and a family in Jerusalem!</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="32">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For behold a righteous king shall reign and chiefs shall rule with justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And this man will be one who hideth his words, and he will be hid as from a rolling flood. And he will be seen on Sion like a glorious stream in a thirsty land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And they shall no more put confidence in men; but shall apply their ears to hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the heart of the weak will listen attentively; and trifling tongues will soon learn to speak peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And they will no more order the fool to govern, nor shall thy servants any more command silence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For the fool will speak foolishly, and his heart will devise vain things; that he may commit iniquity, and utter error before the Lord in order to scatter hungry souls: and the thirsty souls he will send away empty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For the counsel of the wicked will devise unlawful devices to destroy the poor with unjust pleas; and to baffle the pleas of the poor in judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But the pious have counselled with understanding; and their counsel shall be established.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Arise ye rich women and hear my voice, hearken to my words ye daughters of hope!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>make mention of a day of a year in sorrow, with hope. The vintage is destroyed; it hath failed! must it never come again any more?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Be confounded; be grieved, ye confident women! strip; make yourselves bare; gird your loins</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and beat your breasts, for the lovely field; for the fruitful vine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In this land of my people shall spring up the thorn and the briar, and joy shall be taken from every dwelling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>O rich city! houses wholly forsaken! They shall abandon city, riches, lovely houses; and until the age the villages shall be dens; the joy of wild asses, the pastures of flocks,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>till a spirit come on you from on high. Then will a desert become a Channel and Channel will be accounted a forest;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and judgment will make a lasting abode in the desert, and righteousness will dwell in Charmel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the works of righteousness shall be peace; and righteousness shall enjoy rest. As for them who have kept up their confidence till that age;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>his people shall then inhabit a city of peace and dwell secure, and they shall enjoy rest with riches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Though the hail descend, it shall not reach you: and they who dwell in the forest shall be secure as they in the plain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Happy they who sow on every water where the ox and the ass treadeth!</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="33">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Woe to them who miserably afflict you; but none can make you miserable. Even the deceiver doth not deceive you. The deceivers shall be taken and delivered up and like a moth on a garment they shall be crushed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>O Lord, have mercy upon us! for in thee we have placed our trust. The seed of the rebellious were for destruction: but thou wast our safety in the time of trouble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>At the terror of thy voice peoples were confounded; for fear of thee the nations were dispersed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now your spoils are to be gathered; the spoils both of small and great. As if one were gathering: locusts, so will they insult you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Holy is the God who dwelleth on high, Was Sion filled with judgment and justice?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>By law they were to be delivered up; in treasures is our safety. Let there be there wisdom and knowledge and piety towards the Lord, (These are the treasures of righteousness;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>then behold with the dread of you they shall be terrified; they, of whom you have been afraid, will for fear of you raise a grievous cry. Messengers will be sent weeping bitterly, suing for peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For their highways shall be deserted, the dread of the nations is at an end and the treaty with them broken. And you will account them common men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The land mourned; Lebanon was ashamed; Saron was become fens; Galilee and Charmel were bare.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now will I arise, saith the Lord, now shall I be glorified;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>now shall I be exalted; now you shall see: now you shall feel. The strength of your spirit shall be vain; a fire shall utterly devour you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and nations shall be burned up, as thorns in a field are rejected and burned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The far distant nations shall hear what I have done, they who are near shall know my power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The transgressors in Sion are fled; terror will seize the ungodly. Who will tell you that a fire is kindled? who will proclaim to you the place which is everlasting?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He who is walking in righteousness, speaking of a straight way; who hateth iniquity and injustice; who shaketh his hands from bribes; who stoppeth his ears that he may not hear a bloody sentence; who shutteth his eyes against the appearance of injustice:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>he shall dwell in a lofty cavern of a strong rock: bread shall be given him and his water shall not fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>You shall see a king with glory; your eyes shall see a far distant land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>your soul will meditate on terror. Where are the scribes? Where the counsellors? Where is he who numbereth them who are fed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>the people small and great? Alas! they gave no counsel; nor did they understand him whose voice was so low that a despised people could not hear, and he who heareth hath not knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Behold the city Sion is our salvation. Thine eyes will look upon Jerusalem. It is a rich city composed of tents which should not be shaken; nor should the pins of her tabernacle ever be moved, nor its cords broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Because the name of the Lord is great to you, it shall be to you a place of streams and canals broad and spacious. Thou shalt not pass this way; nor shall a galley with oars cross</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>for my God is great and will not pass me by. The Lord our judge; the Lord our chief; the Lord our king; the Lord will himself save us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thy tackling broke, for they had no strength, thy mast gave way. It will not support the sails, nor rear a standard until it be delivered up for a spoil; therefore many who are lame will seize the prey:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>but let not the people who dwell among these say, I am wearied out for their sin is forgiven them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="34">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Attend O nations, and hearken ye chiefs. Let the earth hear and the inhabitants thereof; The world and the people who are therein</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Because the wrath of the Lord is against all the nations, and his anger against this number of them to destroy them and deliver them up to slaughter;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>therefore their wounded and dead shall be cast out, and the stench of them shall ascend; and the mountains shall be drenched with their blood;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and all the powers of the heavens shall waste away; and the heaven shall be rolled up like a scroll and all the stars shall fall like leaves from a vine and as leaves fall from a fig tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>My sword hath drunk deep in the heaven; behold it shall come down on Idumea and on the people justly doomed to destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The sword of the Lord hath been glutted with blood; it is pampered with suet; with the blood of he; goats and lambs, and with the suet of goats and rams. Because there is a sacrifice for the Lord in Bosor, and a great slaughter in Idumea;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore the fatlings shall fall with them, namely the rams and the bulls. And the land shall be drenched with blood, and glutted with their suet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For it is the day of the Lord's vengeance, and the year for a judicial retribution to Sion:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and its torrents shall be turned into pitch, and its land into sulphur. And its land shall be like pitch burning day and night,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and which shall not be extinguished: for a long time the smoke of it shall ascend. During its generation it shall be desolate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And for a long period fowls and porcupines, ibises and crows shall dwell therein. And over it shall be stretched a line of devastation; and in it the onocentaurs shall dwell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The chiefs of it shall be no more; for its kings and its nobles shall be for destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And in their cities shall spring up brakes; and brambles shall be its fortresses: and they shall be cots for Sirens, and for the ostrich's court.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And demons shall meet onocentaurs; and bellow one to the other. Onocentaurs shall there enjoy repose having found for themselves a place of rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>There the porcupine hath made its nest; and the land hath safely kept its young. There the deer have assembled and seen each other's face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I counted them and there is not one of them lost. They have not had occasion to seek each other: for the Lord hath issued orders to them; and his spirit hath brought them together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he will himself cast the lots for them, his hand hath meted the place for them to feed. For a long time you shall inherit it. For generations of generations let them rest therein.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="35">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Rejoice, O desert; shout for joy, O thirsty desert and blossom like a lilly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Let the deserts of Jordan also bloom and rejoice; to it hath been given the glory of Lebanon an the honour of Channel. And my people shall see the glory of the Lord, and the majesty of our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Be strong ye hands which are feeble, and ye knees which are without strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Take comfort ye who are faint hearted; take courage, be not terrified; behold our God retributeth judgment; he will indeed make retribution; he himself will come and save us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then shall be opened the eyes of the blind; and the ears of the deaf will hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then will the lame bound like a hart; and the stammering tongue will speak plain. Because water is burst forth in the desert, and torrents in a thirsty land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore the glowing sand shall become pools, and for the thirsty soil there will be fountains of water. The reedy beds and the pools there will be the joy of birds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>There will be there a pure highway, which shall be called The Holy way. And the unclean shall not come there; nor shall there be there an unclean way. But as for the dispersed, they shall travel it, and shall not be led astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>No lion shall be there; nor shall any ravenous beast come up thither, nor ever be found there; but in it the redeemed will walk, and they who have been collected for the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They indeed shall return and come to Sion with joy, and everlasting joy shall crown their head: for on their heads will be praise and rapture; and gladness shall have full possession of them. Pain and sorrow and sighing are fled.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="36">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the fourteenth year of the reign of Ezekias, Sennacherim king of the Assyrians came up against the fortified cities of Judea, and took them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the king of the Assyrians sent Rabsakes from Lakes to Jerusalem, to king Ezekias, with a great army. And he halted at the canal of the upper pool in the high way to the fuller's field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And to him went out Eliakim the son of Chelkias the steward, and Somnas the scribe, and Joach son of Asaph the recorder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Rabsakes said to them, Tell Ezekias, Thus saith the great king, the king of the Assyrians, On what hast thou placed confidence?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Notwithstanding negotiation and fair speeches, are not preparations making for war? Now therefore on whom hast thou relied, that thou rebellest against me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Behold thy reliance is on that staff; that staff of reed; that broken reed, Egypt; on which if a man lean, it will pierce his hand and go through it. Such is Pharao king of Egypt to all who rely on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But if you say, Our confidence is in the Lord our God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>were you now in close connexion with my master the king of the Assyrians; and were I to give you two thousand horses; could you put riders on them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>How then can you revolt and affect to be petty princes. Those are reduced to slavery who have trusted in the Egyptians for charioteers and cavalry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Besides, are we now come up without the Lord against this land to war against it? The Lord hath said to me, Go up against this land and destroy it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then Eliakim and Somnas and Joach said to him, Speak to thy servants in Syriac, for we understand it. Therefore speak not to us in the Jewish language. Why speakest thou to the ears of the men on the walls?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thereupon Rabsakes said to them, Hath my lord sent me to your lord or to you to speak these words? Was it not to those men; to them who are stationed on that wall, that they may eat dung and drink urine, both they and you together?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Rabsakes stood and cried with a loud voice in the Jewish language and said, Hear the words of the great king, the king of the Assyrians,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thus saith the king, Let not Ezekias deceive you with speeches. He cannot deliver you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and let not Ezekias say to you, God will deliver you; and this city shall not be delivered into the hand of the king of the Assyrians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Hearken not to Ezekias. Thus saith the king of the Assyrians, If you wish to be happy, come out to me; and eat, every one, of his own vine and his own fig trees, and drink water from your own cisterns,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>until I come and take you to a land like your own; a land of corn and wine, and of bread and vineyards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Let not Ezekias deceive you saying, God will deliver you. Have the gods of the nations, delivered every one his own country out of the hand of the king of the Assyrians?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Where is the God of Emath and Arphath? And where is the God of the city Eppharuim? Were they able to deliver Samaria out of my hand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Who is there of all the gods of the nations who hath delivered his country out of my hand, that God should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But they were silent and none answered him a word, because the king had given a charge that none should answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Eliakim the son of Chelkias the steward, and Somnas the secretary at war and Joach the son of Asaph the recorder went to Ezekias with their clothes rent and told him the words of Rabsakes.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="37">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when Ezekias heard them he rent his clothes and put on sackcloth and went up to the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And he sent Eliakim the steward and Somnas the scribe and the elders of the priests clothed with sackcloth to Esaias son of Amos the prophet with this message to him, Thus saith Ezekias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>This day is a day of trouble and of reproach and of rebuke and of wrath; for pangs are come on a woman in travail and she hath not strength to bring forth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>That the Lord thy God may attend to the message of Rabsakes which the king of the Assyrians hath sent to reproach the Living God; and refute the words which the Lord thy God hath heard, thou shouldst pray to the Lord for these poor remains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So when the servants of king Ezekias came to Esaias</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>he said to them, Thus shall you say to your lord, Thus saith the Lord, Be not terrified at the words which thou hast heard; with which the messengers of the king of the Assyrians have reproached me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold I am about to put such a spirit in him, that he having heard news will return to his own country: and he shall fall by the sword in his own land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So Rabsakes returned and found the king of the Assyrians besieging Lobna, for he heard that he had removed from Lachis;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and Thoraka king of the Ethiopians came out to give him battle. Upon hearing this, he retreated, and sent messengers to Ezekias, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thus shall you say to Ezekias king of Judea, Let not thy God, on whom thou reliest, deceive thee, saying, Jerusalem shall not be delivered into the hand of the king of the Assyrians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Hast thou not heard what the kings of the Assyrians have done? How they have destroyed all the land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And shalt thou be delivered? Have the gods of the nations delivered them whom my ancestors destroyed? Either, Goza or Charran or Raphath which are in the country of Theemath?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Where are the kings of Emath? And where those of Arphath? And where those of the city Eppharuim, of Anagougana?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When Ezekias received the letter from the messengers and had read it, he went up to the house of the Lord; and having spread it before the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Ezekias prayed to the Lord, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>O Lord of Hosts the God of Israel, who art enthroned on the cherubim! Thou alone art the God of every kingdom of the world. Thou hast made the heaven and the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Incline, Lord, thine ear! Lord, hearken! Open, O Lord, thine eyes! Lord, look down and behold the words of Sennacherim which he hath sent to reproach the Living God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>In truth, Lord, the kings of the Assyrians have laid waste this whole inhabited land and the country of those here mentioned</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and have cast their idols into the fire; for they were not gods; but works of mens' hands, stocks and stones;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>therefore they destroyed them. But now, Lord, our God, save us out of their hands that every kingdom of the earth may know, that thou alone art God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thereupon Esaias son of Amos was sent to Ezekias and said to him, Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel, I have heard the prayer which thou hast made to me concerning Sennacherim king of the Assyrians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>This is the word which the Lord hath spoken concerning him, The virgin daughter of Sion hath despised thee and mocked thee; at thee the daughter of Jerusalem hath shaken her head;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>whom hast thou reproached and provoked? Or against whom hast thou exalted thy voice, (without lifting up thine eye to the Holy One of Israel?)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>That by thy messengers thou hast reproached the Lord? For thou hast said, By the multitude of my chariots, I have ascended the height of mountains, and to the utmost limits of Libanus, and cut down the lofty cedar and beautiful cypress, and entered the stately part of the forest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I have laid bridges and dried up waters and every collection of water</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Hast thou not heard those things of old which I have done? From ancient times I gave command and have now pointed out to lay waste nations in strong places and them Who dwell in fortified cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>I weakened their hands and they were dried up, and became like dry grass on house tops, and like a blasted ear of corn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And now I know thy resting place and thy going out and thy coming in. As the rage with which thou hast been inflamed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and thy bitterness are come up to me; I will therefore put a hook in thy nose and a bridle in thy jaws; and turn thee back by the way in which thou camest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now this shall be a sign to thee. Eat this year what thou hast sown, and in the second year what is left; but in the third year sow ye and reap; plant vineyards and eat the fruit thereof;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>for they who are left shall continue in Judea. They shall strike root downwards and bear fruit upwards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For they of Jerusalem shall be left and they of mount Sion shall be saved. The zeal of the Lord of Hosts will do this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, With regard to the king of the Assyrians, he shall not enter this city; nor shoot an arrow against it; nor present against it a shield; nor enclose it with a rampire</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But by the way which he came, by the same he shall return; and into this city he shall not come. Thus saith the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>I will cover this city with my shield to save it for mine own sake and the sake of my servant David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>So an angel of the Lord went forth and slew of the camp of the Assyrians a hundred and eighty five thousand. And when they arose in the morning they found all these dead bodies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Thereupon Sennacherim king of the Assyrians retreated and went and dwelt in Ninive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And as he was Worshipping, in his house, Nasarach his ancestor; Adramelech and Sarousar his sons smote him with their swords; and, they having made their escape to Armenia, Asardan his son reigned in his stead.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="38">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time Ezekias was seized with a mortal sickness; and Esaias son of Amos, the prophet, came to him and said to him, Thus saith the Lord, Give orders respecting thy household, for thou art at the point of death and shall not live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thereupon Ezekias turned his face to the wall and prayed to the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>saying, O Lord, remember how I have walked before thee with truth and with an upright heart, and have done the things which are pleasing in thy sight. And Ezekias wept bitterly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And a word of the Lord came to Esaias saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Go and say to Ezekias, Thus saith the Lord, the God of thy father David, I have heard thy prayer and seen thy tears, Behold I will add to thy term fifteen years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of the Assyrians and cover this city with my shield.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And this shall be a sign to thee from the Lord, that God will perform this decree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Behold I will bring back the shadow of the steps the ten steps of the house of thy father, which the sun hath gone down. I will bring back the sun those ten steps. So the sun reascended the ten steps which the shadow had gone down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The prayer of Ezekias, king of Judea, when he had been sick, and was recovered from his sickness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I said in the height of my days I shall go down to the gates of Hades, I shall leave the years which remain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I said, I shall no more see the salvation of God in the land of the living; I shall no more see the salvation of Israel on the earth; I shall behold man no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I am cut off from my generation, I have left the remainder of my life. He is gone and departed from me, like one striking a tent, having just pitched it. My soul within me was like a web which the weaver was in act to sever from the loom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In that day I was delivered up until morning as to a lion. So did he break to pieces all my bones. For from day to night I was delivered up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Like a swallow so let me twitter; and like a turtle dove so let me moan; for mine eyes were too weak to look up to the vault of heaven; to the Lord who hath rescued me</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and taken from me the sorrow of my soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Of this indeed thou, O Lord, wast told, and thou hast restored my breath and I am comforted and live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For thou hast rescued my soul that it should not perish; and hast cast behind thee all my sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For those in the mansion of the dead cannot praise thee; nor can the dead return thee thanks, nor they in Hades hope for thy kindness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The living will praise thee even as I do; for from this day I shall raise up children, who will proclaim this loving kindness of thine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>God of my salvation; and I will never cease praising thee with a psaltery, all the days of my life over against the house of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now Esaias had said to Ezekias, Take a cake of figs and bruise and apply it as a poultice and thou shalt recover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Whereupon Ezekias said, Let this be a sign to Ezekias, that I shall go up to the house of God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="39">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At the time when Marodach Baladan the son of Baladan the king of Babylon sent letters and ambassadors and presents to Ezekias (for he heard that he had been sick unto death and had recovered:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and Ezekias was rejoiced at their arrival and shewed them the house of Nechotha and that of the silver and of the gold; and that for stacte, and for perfumes and for myrrh; and all the treasure houses and all that he had in his treasuries; there being nothing in his house nor in all his dominion which Ezekias did not shew them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Esaias the prophet then went to king Ezekias and said to him, What say those men? And, whence are they come to thee? And Ezekias said, They are come to me from a far distant land, from Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Esaias said, What have they seen in thy house? To which Ezekias replied, They have seen all that are in my house. There is nothing in my house which they have not seen: nay, they have seen also what are in my treasuries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thereupon Esaias said to him, Hear the word of the Lord of hosts!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Behold days are coming, when they shall seize all that are in thy house. And all that thy fathers have collected even to this day shall go to Babylon; and nothing shall be left behind. Moreover God hath said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>That of thy children whom thou shalt beget, they will take some and make them eunuchs in the house of the king of the Babylonians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And Ezekias said to Esaias, Good is the word of the Lord which he spake: let there be, I pray, peace and righteousness in my days.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="40">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, saith God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>priests, speak to the understanding of Jerusalem; comfort her; for her humiliation is accomplished; her iniquity is pardoned: for she hath received from the hand of the Lord blessings double to the punishment of her sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>A voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare the way of the Lord; make straight the roads for our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let every valley be filled up, and every mountain and hill be levelled: and let all the crooked be made a straight road, and the rough way, smooth plains:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and the glory of the Lord will appear: And all flesh shall see the salvation of God. For the Lord hath spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>A voice of one saying, Proclaim. Wherefore I said, What shall I proclaim? All flesh is grass; and all the glory of man as a flower of grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The grass is withered and the flower fallen; but the word of our God will endure forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Ascend a lofty mountain, thou who proclaimest good news to Sion: exalt thy voice with strength, thou who bringest glad tidings to Jerusalem: raise it up; be not afraid; say to the cities of Juda, Behold, your God!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>behold the Lord! The Lord is coming with majesty; and his arm with dominion. Behold his11 reward is with him; and his work, before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Like a shepherd he will tend his flock; and with his arm he will gather the lambs, and comfort the ewes that are with young.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Who hath measured the water with his hand, and the heaven with a span and the whole earth with a hand breadth? Who hath weighed the mountains in scales and the dales with a balance?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Who hath known the mind of the Lord? and who hath been of his counsel to teach him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>or whom hath he consulted that he might instruct him? or who hath pointed out judgment to him? or who hath shewn him the way of knowledge?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If all the nations are as a drop from a cask; and are accounted as the turning of a balance; may be reckoned as spittle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>if Lebanon is not sufficient for a fire, nor all the beasts sufficient for an homage offering:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and all the nations are as nothing and reckoned as nothing:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>to whom have you likened the Lord? and to what likeness have you compared him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Hath a carpenter when he hath made an image, or the goldsmith when he hath melted gold and gilded it, prepared this as a likeness of him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for the carpenter chuseth a sound piece of timber and will inquire wisely, how he may place his image that it may not be moved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Will you not know? will you not hear? hath it not been told you from the beginning? have you not known the foundations of the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He it is, who occupieth the circuit of the earth; and the inhabitants thereon are as grasshoppers. He it is, who established the heaven as an arch, and spread it out as a tent to be dwelt in;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>who giveth chiefs as a nothingness to govern: and hath made the earth as a mere nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For they could not plant nor could they sow, nor could their root strike into the ground; he blew upon them and they withered, and a whirlwind will sweep them away like stubble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now therefore to whom have you likened me; that I may be exalted? said the Holy One.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Raise your eyes upwards and take a view: who hath displayed all those? He who bringeth out his host by number can call them all by name. On the account of abundant glory, by reason of the mightiness of his power he hath in no wise escaped thy notice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>wherefore, thou, Jacob, shouldst not say, yet what hast thou, Israel, spoken? My way is hidden from God? and, My God hath put off my cause and is gone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Hast thou then not known? hast thou not heard? The everlasting God, the God who fitted up the ends of the earth, cannot hunger, nor can he be weary; nor can his under standing be searched out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He it is who giveth strength to the hungry and grief to them who have not had sorrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For youths will hunger and young men be weary, and chosen warriors will become strengthless;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>but they who wait upon God shall have new strength; they shall put forth fresh feathers like eagles; they shall run and not be wearied; they shall march on and shall not faint.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="41">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Dedicate yourselves to me, Islands, for the Arehons will gather new strength. Let them draw near and confer together, then let them announce judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Who raised up righteousness from the East; called upon it to attend his steps? when he marcheth on, he will exhibit it before nations and confound kings and dash their swords to the ground, and their bows shall be driven away like stubble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When he pursueth them, the road for his feet shall pass through to peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Who hath performed and done these things? He who called that righteousness; who from the generations of the beginning is calling it I God the First, and to the succeeding ages, THE I AM.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The nations saw and were affrighted; the ends of the earth drew near and came together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Every one is determining to help his neighbour and his brother, and one will say,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The carpenter had strength, so had the smith who beateth with a hammer and plateth it. Sometimes indeed one will say, It is a beautiful composition? These things they made strong with nails; they will fix them up that they may not be moved:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but thou Israel my servant; thou Jacob, whom I have chosen; thou seed of Abraham whom I loved!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>have I not taken thee from the ends of the earth, and from the speculations thereof called thee, and said to thee, Thou art my servant I have chosen thee and have not forsaken thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Fear not, for I am with thee; be not led astray, for I am thy God. I have strengthened thee and helped thee, and secured thee with my just right hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Behold all thine adversaries shall be ashamed and confounded; for they shall be as nothing and all thine opponents shall be destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thou mayst seek but thou shalt not find the men, who through drunkenness will dare to insult thee. For they shall be as mere nothing: and they who war against thee shall be no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For I am thy God, who have hold of thy right hand, and who say to thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Fear not, Jacob, diminutive Israel! I have helped thee, saith thy God, who redeemeth thee, Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Behold I have made thee like the wheels of a wain bruising to pieces a brood of pigeons: thou indeed shalt grind mountains and reduce hills to small pieces, and make them like dust:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and thou shalt winnow them; and a wind shall take them up, and a whirlwind shall sweep them away; but thou shalt be gladdened in the sanctuaries of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and the poor and the needy shall exult with joy: for when they shall seek water and there shall be none, and their tongue is parched with thirst; I the Lord their God, I the God of Israel will hear and will not forsake them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>but will open rivers on the mountains, and fountains in the midst of plains: I will turn the wilderness into watery fens, and with streams refresh the thirsty ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I will plant in the dry wilderness the cedar and box, the myrtle and cypress and elm:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>that they may see and know, and consider and understand at once that the hand of the Lord hath done these things; even what the Holy One of Israel hath pointed out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The trial of you is near, saith the Lord God; your councils are nigh at hand, saith the king of Jacob;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>let them draw near and tell you what will happen, or such things as these before they come to pass. Tell us that we may apply our understanding, and that we may know the final issue, and the train of events leading to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Tell us, announce to us the things in successive train to the issue; and we will acknowledge that you are gods. Confer favours and inflict punishments, and we will pay respect and see at once,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>that wherever you are thence is your operation. They have chosen you an abomination from the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but I have raised up that one from the north, and that other from the risings of the sun; they shall be called by my name: let the Arehons come, and as the clay of the potter; even as a potter treadeth clay so shall you be trampled down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Who now can tell these things from the beginning, that we may know, even these things before hand: that we may say, The prediction is true. There is none who predicteth, nor doth any one hear your words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>I will first give notice to Sion and I will comfort Jerusalem on the way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For of the nations behold there is none, and of the idols none giveth warning. And should I ask them, Whence are you? They could not make me any answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For are these they who made you? They are indeed those who vainly lead you astray.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="42">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>JACOB is my servant, I will uphold him, Israel is my chosen one, my soul hath embraced him; I have put my spirit upon him; he will publish judgment to the nations. (Jehovah, the prophet)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He will not scream, nor urge with vehemence: nor will his voice be heard abroad in the streets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>A bruised reed he will not break, nor extinguish a dimly burning taper; but will publish judgment to establish truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He will shine out, and shall not be broken until he hath established judgment on the earth. In his name therefore let the nations trust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, the God who made the heaven and fixed it; who established the earth and the things therein and who giveth vital air to the people on it, and breath to them who tread thereon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I the Lord God have called thee for saving mercy, and I will take hold of thy hand and strengthen thee; for I have given thee for the covenant of a race; for the light of nations:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>to open the eyes of the blind; to lead out from chains them who are bound, and out of prison, them who are sitting in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I am the Lord God; this is my name: this glory of mine I will not give to another, nor these powers of mine to the graven idols.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>With regard to the former predictions, behold they are come to pass; and these are new things which I now declare; and before their promulgation, they are revealed to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Sing to the Lord a new song, ye, his government! Praise his name, ye from the utmost border of the earth, ye who go down on the sea and navigate it, ye islands, and ye who dwell therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Let the desert be glad and the villages thereof; the folds for flocks and them who inhabit Kedar: let the inhabitants of Petra rejoice; let them shout from the top of the mountains:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>to this God let them ascribe glory; let them proclaim his powers among the isles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The Lord God of Hosts will come forth and tread down battle; he will rouse up his zeal, and shout against his enemies with majesty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have been silent; but shall I always keep silence and forbear? Like a woman in travail I have endured suffering; I will strike with astonishment and wither at once.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I will lay waste mountains and hills, and dry up all the herbage on them. I will make rivers islands and dry up pools,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and lead the blind in a way which they know not, and cause them to walk in paths which they have not known. For them I will make the darkness light, and the crooked ways a straight road. These things I will do, and I will not forsake them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but as for them they have turned backwards! be whelmed in shame, ye who trust in graven images; who say to the molten images, ye are our gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Hear, ye deaf; and ye blind, look up that you may see:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Who indeed is blind but my servants? And deaf, but those who rule over them? Even the servants of God are become blind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>You have seen again and again but have not regarded: your ears have been opened, but you did not hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The Lord God came to a determination, that he might be justified and might magnify praise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Whereupon I beheld and the people were plundered and dispersed: for the snare was every where in the private chambers, and in the houses also where they had hidden themselves. They were for a prey and there was no rescuer; for a spoil; and there was none who said, Restore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Who is there among you who will give ear to these things? Attend to those leading causes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>for which he hath given Jacob for a spoil, and Israel to them who plundered him. Hath not God, against whom they sinned, and in whose ways they would not walk, and whose law they would not obey;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>hath not he brought upon them his fierce anger? Though war prevailed over them, and they who were burning them up were all around, yet they did not, any of them know, nor lay it to heart.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="43">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Still however thus saith the Lord, the God who made thee Jacob, and who formed thee, Israel! fear not. Because I have redeemed thee; have called thee by thy name; thou art mine;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>therefore when thou passest through water, I am with thee, and the streams shall not overwhelm thee: and when thou passest through fire, thou shalt not be burned up; the flame shall not quite consume thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Because I the Lord thy God, the Holy One of Israel am thy Saviour, I have given Egypt for thy ransom and Ethiopia and Soena in thy stead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because thou hast been precious in my sight; hast been honoured and I loved thee; therefore I will give men for thee and chiefs for thy life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Fear not. Because I am with thee, from the east I will bring thy seed, and gather thee together from the west:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I will say to the north, Give up; and to the south, Keep thou not back; bring my sons from afar and my daughters from the ends of the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>all that are called by my name. For I have prepared him for my glory, I have fashioned him and made him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and have brought out a blind people: for their eyes are as if they were blind; and they are deaf, though they have ears.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>All the nations were assembled together; now let all the archons be assembled: can any among them announce these things? Or can any tell you these things before hand? Let them produce their witnesses and be justified, and let them hear and tell things true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Be you witnesses for me: and as for me I myself am a witness saith the Lord God; and this servant of mine whom I have chosen; that you may know and believe and understand that with respect to me, The I AM, There is no other God before me; and after me none will exist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I am God and there is no Saviour besides me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I have announced and saved; I reproached when there was no strange god among you. You are witnesses for me; and I the Lord am still the same God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>from the beginning; and there is none who can rescue out of my hands. I will act; and who can prevent it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, the God who redeemed you, the Holy One of Israel; For your sakes I will send to Babylon, and rouse up all who are fleeing; and the Chaldeans shall be bound in ships.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I am the Lord God, your Holy One, who pointed out Israel your king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord who made a highway in a sea, and a path in the mighty water;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>who brought out chariots and horses and a mighty host, but they lay down to sleep and shall rise no more: they were extinguished like an extinguished taper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Mention not these former things, nor reason from the things of old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Behold I am in act to do new things, which shall now spring up and you shall know them; I will make a way in the wilderness, and streams of water in the desert.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The wild beasts of the field will bless me; the Seirens and the daughters of the ostrich; because I have given water in the wilderness, and flowing streams in the desert, to give drink to this race of mine which I have chosen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>my people whom I have preserved to recount my praises.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>I had not now called upon thee, Jacob, nor caused thee Israel, to weary thyself:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>thou hadst not brought me thy sheep of thy whole burnt offering; nor honoured me with thine incense offerings: I had not burdened thee with sacrifices of flour; nor wearied thee with demands of frankincense:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>nor hadst thou purchased with silver perfumes for me; nor had I desired the suet of thy sacrifices: but thou stoodest before me in thy sins and in thine iniquities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I even I, THE I AM, am he who blotteth out thy transgressions for mine own sake; and of thy sins I will no more make mention:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>but do thou mention them and let us be judged; do thou first state thy transgressions, that thou mayst be acquitted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Your fathers first, then your chiefs transgressed against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When the chiefs polluted my sanctuary, then I gave up Jacob to be destroyed, and Israel to reproach.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="44">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But now, hear, Jacob my servant, and thou Israel, whom I have chosen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, the God who made thee, and who formed thee from the womb, still thou shalt be helped. Fear not, thou my servant Jacob, and thou, beloved Israel, whom I have chosen:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>for I will give water in their thirst to them who are travelling in a desert. I will put my spirit on thy seed, and my blessings on thy children;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and they shall spring up like grass among water, and like a willow by the side of a flowing stream.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>One will say, I belong to God; and another will call himself by the name of Jacob; and another will write on his hand, I belong to God; and will surname himself by the name of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thus saith God, the King of Israel, and his Redeemer, the God of Hosts, I am the first and I am the last: be sides me there is no God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Who is like me? Let him stand up and call and announce, and make ready for me: In as much as I have made a man for this age, let them now tell you the train of events before they come to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Hide not yourselves nor be led astray. Have you not heard from the beginning? And have I not told you? You are witnesses whether there be any God besides me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And have not then the fashioners and engravers heard? They are all fools making things to please their fancies; things which cannot profit them: but shame shall cover these god makers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and all the engravers of these useless things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When all by whom they were made are dried up; then let all the stupid among men be collected and stand together, and let them be confounded and ashamed together:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>for the carpenter sharpened an axe, with a hatchet he modelled it; then he put it into a lathe and with his strong arm fashioned it. Though he be hungry and faint, he must not drink water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The carpenters having chosen a piece of wood framed it by rule and glued the parts together, and made it in the form of a man and with the comeliness of a man, to set it in a house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He cut wood from the forest which the Lord planted; a pine tree, which the rain had nourished,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>that it might be fuel for the use of man: and having taken some of it he warmed himself; and with other pieces they made a fire and baked cakes, and of the residue they made gods and worshipped them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Did he not burn half of it in the fire, and, with the coals of that half, bake cakes; and having roasted meat with it did he not eat and was satisfied; and when warmed say, Aha! I am warmed, I have enjoyed the fire?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Yet of the residue he made a carve god, and worshippeth it, and prayeth to it, saying, Deliver me, for thou art my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>They had not sense to think; for they were so involved in darkness that they could not see with their eyes, nor understand with their hearts:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>nor did any reason in his mind, nor by his understanding recollect, that he had burned half of it in the fire, and on the coals thereof baked cakes, and had roasted flesh and eaten, and of the residue had made an abomination; so they bow themselves down to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Know thou that their heart is ashes, and they are led astray and none can deliver his soul. Take a view of it, will you not say, There is indeed a lie in my right hand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Remember these things, Jacob, even thou Israel, for thou art my servant. I have made thee my servant; therefore O Israel do not thou forget me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For, lo! I have made thy transgressions vanish like a cloud; and thy sins like the murky vapour. Return to me and I will redeem thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Rejoice, O heavens! because God hath compassionated Israel. Utter sounds of joy, ye foundations of the earth! Burst forth into songs, ye mountains and hills, and all ye trees which are thereon! Because God hath redeemed Jacob and Israel shall be glorified. (the chorus)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, who redeemed thee; even He who formed thee from the womb; I am the Lord the Maker of all things; I alone stretched out the heavens and firmly established the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Who else can dispel from the heart the signs of belly speakers and divinations? I am he who turneth sages backwards and maketh their counsel foolish;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>but establisheth the word of his servant, and verifieth the counsel of his messengers; who saith to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be inhabited; and to the cities of Idumea, Ye shall be re builded, and in its deserts vegetation shall spring up:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Who saith to the deep, Thou shalt be wasted, and I will dry up the rivers:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>who saith, to Cyrus I will give wisdom, and he shall execute all my pleasure. Who saith to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be rebuilded and the house dedicated to me I will found.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="45">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord God, For mine anointed, for Cyrus, (whose right hand I have taken hold of that nations may listen before him) I will break the power of kings; I will open gates before him, and cities shall not be shut up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I will go before thee and level mountains; I will break in pieces the gates of brass, and burst asunder the bars of iron;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and give thee treasures of darkness; deep, hidden, unseen treasures I will disclose to thee, that thou mayst know, that I, the Lord thy God, who calleth thee by thy name, am the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For the sake of my servant Jacob, and of Israel my chosen one, I will call thee by thy name and receive thee kindly. As for thee, thou didst not know me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Because I am the Lord God and there is no God else besides me; I strengthened thee when thou didst not know me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>that they from the risings of the sun and they from its goings down may know, that there is no God besides me. I the Lord am God and there is none else.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>It was I who provided light and made darkness; who make peace and create evils: I the Lord God am he who doth all these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Let the heaven above be glad; and the clouds shower down righteousness. Let the earth spring and bloom with mercy and let it cause righteousness to spring up with it. I the Lord am he who created thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Is any thing endowed with excellence? I fashioned it like the clay of a potter. Will the ploughman plough the ground all the day long? Will the clay say to the potter, What art thou making? Or the work to the workman, Thou hast not hands? Will the thing formed reply against him who formed it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Will one say to his father, What wilt thou beget? Or to his mother, What art thou bringing forth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Wherefore thus saith the Lord God, the Holy One of Israel, even he who made the train of events; Do you question me concerning my children; and concerning the works of my hands give me directions!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>It was I who made the earth and man on it: it was I who with my hand established the heaven: it was I who gave direction to all the stars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>It is I who have raised him up with righteousness to be king; and all his ways shall be straight. He shall rebuild this city of mine, and send back the captives of this my people, not for ransom nor reward, said the Lord of Hosts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord of Hosts, That for which Egypt laboured and the traffick of the Ethiopians, and the Sabeans men of tall stature shall come over to thee; and they shall be thy vassals and shall follow thee bound with chains. They will come over to thee and pay thee homage and pray to thee because God is in thee. There is indeed no God besides thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For thou art God and we knew it. The God of Israel is a Saviour:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>let all that oppose him be ashamed and confounded and in shame let them march along. Dedicate yourselves to me, ye islands!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The Lord hath saved Israel with an everlasting salvation. They shall not be put to shame nor confounded any more forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord who made the heaven, the same God who displayed the earth to view, and who, having made it, parcelled it out: he did not make it to be waste, but formed it to be inhabited: I</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>am the Lord and there is none else. I have not spoken in secret nor in an obscure part of the earth. I have not said to the seed of Jacob, Seek ye a vain thing. I am THE I AM, the Lord, who speak righteousness and proclaim truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Assemble yourselves together and come; consult together ye who escape from among the nations. They are devoid of knowledge, who carry the wood; their carved image; and who pray to gods which cannot save them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>If they will proclaim, let them draw near and know at once, who hath published these things from the beginning: then let them be announced to you. I am God and there is no other besides me; a just God and a saviour be sides me there is none.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Turn to me and ye shall be saved, ye from the farthest part of the earth, I am God and there is none else.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>By myself I swear (righteousness shall proceed from my mouth; my words shall not be reversed) that to me every knee shall bow and every tongue shall swear, with respect to God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>saying, Righteousness and glory shall come to him, and all that make distinctions among them shall be ashamed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>On account of the Lord they shall be acquitted; and in God all the seed of Israel will glory.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="46">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Bel is fallen; Nabo is broken to pieces, Their graven images were a load for wild beasts and cattle, You are carrying them bound like a burden on the weary, fainty, and hungry, who are all without strength</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and unable to escape from battle; and as for them, they are carried away captives!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Hearken to me house of Jacob and all ye remnant of Israel, who have been carried from the womb, and instructed from childhood to old age;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I am the self existent, even till you grow old, I am, I sustain you: I made you and I will bear with you; I will lift you up and I will save you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>To what have you likened me? Look! Contrive, ye wanderers!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Collecting gold from a bag, and silver by weight they will put it in a balance; and having hired a goldsmith they made handiworks and bowing themselves down they will worship them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They carry it on the shoulder and move on; but if they set it in its place, there it remaineth. It cannot move itself. And if any one cry to it, it cannot hear, nor can it save him from evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Remember these things and groan; reform, ye who have been led astray: return with the heart</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and remember the things of old, that I am God and there is none besides me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>who can declare events before they happen, as if they were already accomplished. When I have spoken, all my counsel shall stand; and all that I have determined, I will effect.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Calling from the east a winged fowl, even from a far distant land, for purposes which I have resolved on, I have spoken and brought, I have created and made, I have brought it and made its way prosperous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Hear me, ye who have lost understanding; who are far from righteousness!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I have brought my saving mercy near; and the salvation which is from me I will not delay. I have placed in Sion salvation for Israel, for a subject of glory.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="47">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Come down, sit on the ground, Virgin daughter of Babylon! Sit on the ground, daughter of the Chaldeans! for thou shalt no more be called tender and delicate!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Take a millstone and grind corn. Doff thy veil; uncover thy grey locks. Make bare thy leg: wade through rivers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thy shame shall be exposed; thy nakedness shall be seen. This vengeance I will take on thy account and no more deliver thee up to men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thy deliverer is the Lord of Hosts, his name is the Holy One of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Sit in compunction: enter into darkness, daughter of the Chaldeans! thou shalt no more be called the strength of a kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I was angry with my people: thou didst pollute my heritage, I delivered them into thy hand: and thou didst shew them no mercy. The yoke of the aged thou madest very heavy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and saidst, I shall be empress forever. These things did not enter thy heart; nor didst thou call to mind what might at last befal thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now, therefore, hear these things, thou voluptuary! thou who art seated at ease, who thinkest thyself secure; who sayest in thy heart; I am and there is none else. I shall not sit a widow, nor shall I know the loss of children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But now upon thee shall come these two things, suddenly, in one day. The loss of children and widowhood shall come suddenly on thee, in the midst of thy sorcery, in the full strength of thy mighty enchantments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Confiding in thy wickedness thou indeed saidst; I am and there is none else. Know thou, the consciousness of these things and thy whoredom shall be thy shame. Thou indeed saidst in thy heart, I am and there is none else;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>but upon thee shall come destruction, and thou shalt not know; a pit; and into it thou shalt fall. Yes, upon thee shall come misery, of which thou shalt not be able to rid thyself: and destruction shall come upon thee suddenly of which thou wilt have no apprehension.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Persist now in thine incantations and in thy manifold sorcery, which thou hast learned from thy youth: if thou canst be benefited by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou hast wearied thyself with thy counsels: let the astrologers now stand up and save thee; let them who gaze on the stars tell thee what is instantly coming upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Behold like brambles on a fire they shall all be burned up; and shall not deliver their own life from the flame. Seeing thou hast coals of fire, sit upon them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>will they give thee relief? Thou hast wearied thyself with this traffic from thy youth. The men have wandered away, every one to his own home; but for thee there shall be no safety.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="48">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hear these things, ye house of Jacob, ye who are called by the name of Israel! ye who are descendants of Juda! ye who swear by the name of the Lord God of Israel, making mention of it, but not with truth, nor with righteousness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and who stay themselves on the name of this holy city, and rely for support on the God of Israel, whose name is the Lord of Hosts. I have already told you former things:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>when they proceeded from my mouth and were published, I did them speedily and they came to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I know that thou art of an untractable temper, that thy neck is a sinew of iron and thy brow, brass;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore I told thee beforehand what would come upon thee; I published them that thou mightest not say, The idols have done this to me, nor say, The graven or molten images have ordered it for me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>you have heard all these things, and did not yourselves know them. But now I have made thee hear new things, which shall hereafter come to pass. Yet hast thou not said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Things done now and not formerly! Yes, never in former days didst thou hear these things. Thou shouldst not say, Indeed I know them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thou didst neither know nor didst thou believe, nor did I from the beginning open thine ear: for I knew that, being in rebellion, thou wilt continue to rebel and wilt still be called a transgressor from the womb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For mine own name's sake I will shew thee my wrath, and bring upon thee my marvellous things; that I may not cut thee off utterly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Behold I sold thee; but not for money; and I have rescued thee out of the furnace of affliction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For mine own sake I will deal with thee; because my name hath been profaned, and my glory I will not give to another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Hearken to me, Jacob! and thou Israel whom I call. I am the first and am forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>My hand hath founded the earth, and my right hand hath established the heaven. Let me summon them and let them stand together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Let them all be assembled and listen. Who hath told them these things? I who love thee have executed thy will on Babylon, to take away the seed of the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I have spoken, I have called, I have brought him, and have made his way prosperous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Draw near to me and hear these things: from the beginning I have not spoken in secret. When it was doing I was there. And now the Lord Lord hath sent me and his spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord who hath redeemed thee, the Holy One of Israel, I am thy God. I pointed out to thee, how to find the way in which thou shouldst walk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And hadst thou hearkened to my commandments thy peace would have been like a river and thy righteousness like a wave of the sea;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and thy seed would have been as the sand, and the issue of thy bowels as the dust of the ground. Still however thou shalt not be utterly cut off; nor shall thy name perish from before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Haste out of Babylon! flee from the Chaldeans: proclaim the joyful news: and let this be published. Proclaim even to the end of the earth: Say, The Lord hath delivered his servant Jacob;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and if they shall thirst (for he will lead them through a desert) a rock shall be cleft and water shall gush forth, that my people may drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>There is no peace, saith the Lord, for the wicked.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="49">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hearken to me, isles; and ye nations attend! (After a long time one will stand up saith the Lord.) From my mother's womb he mentioned my name (The Messiah)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and made my mouth like a sharp sword and hid me under the cover of his hand. He made me like a chosen shaft, and in his quiver kept me concealed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and said to me, Thou Israel art my servant, and by thee I shall be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon I said, I have laboured in vain; for vanity and for nought I have spent my strength; therefore my cause is with the Lord; and my labour is before my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And now thus saith the Lord who formed me from the womb. To be his servant to gather Jacob to him, and Israel. I shall be gathered and glorified before the Lord. And my God will be my strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Moreover he said to me, Is it a great thing for thee to be called my servant to reestablish the tribes of Jacob and bring back the dispersion of Israel? Behold I have given thee for the covenant of a race; for the light of nations; that thou mayst be for salvation to the farthest part of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord who delivered thee; the God of Israel, Hallow him who despised his life, him who was abhorred by the nations, the slaves of the Arehons. Kings shall see him and chiefs shall rise up and they shall worship him for the sake of the Lord; because the Holy One of Israel is faithful, therefore I have chosen thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, In an acceptable time I have hearkened to thee, and in a day of salvation helped thee; and have formed thee and given thee for the covenant of nations that thou mayst reduce the earth to order and possess desolate heritages,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>saying to them who are in bonds, Go forth; and to them who are in darkness, Come into light. In all the highways they shall be fed, and there shall be pasture for them in all the paths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They shall not hunger nor shall they thirst, nor shall the burning wind nor the sun smite them; but he who hath compassion on them will comfort them and lead them to bursting springs of water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And I will make every mountain a highway, and every path a pasture for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Behold they from afar shall come, some from the north and the west and others from the land of the Persians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Rejoice heavens; and let the earth be glad, let the mountains resound with bursts of joy; for God hath compassionated his people, and comforted those of his people who were afflicted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Hath Sion then said, The Lord hath quite forsaken me, and, Why hath the Lord forgotten me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>can a woman forget her child? or not have compassion on the offspring of her womb? Grant that a woman may forget even these, but I will not forget thee, said the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Behold I have engraven thy walls on my hands; and thou art continually before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And thou shalt be speedily rebuilt by them who destroyed thee; and they who laid thee waste shall become thine offspring.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Look up with thine eyes all around and view them all; behold they are gathered together and coming to thee. As I live saith the Lord, Thou shalt clothe thyself with them all, as with raiment, and wrap them about thee as a bride doth her dress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because thy waste and desolate and ruinated places will now be too narrow for the inhabitants, and they who devoured thee shall be removed far from thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>therefore thy sons whom thou hast lost will say in thine ears, This place is too strait for me: make room for me, where I may dwell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whereupon thou wilt say in thy heart, Who hath begotten these for me? I indeed was childless and a widow, Who then hath brought up these for me? I was abandoned and alone; whence then have I these?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Lord, Behold I will lift up my hand to the nations, and I will erect my standard for the isles. And they shall bring thy sons in their bosoms and carry thy daughters on their shoulders:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and kings shall be thy foster fathers; and their queens thy nursing mothers. And on the face of the ground they shall pay thee homage, and lick the dust of thy feet. And thou shalt know that I am the Lord, and that they who wait for me shall not be ashamed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Can any one take spoils from a giant? And if any one captivate unjustly shall he be safe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, When one captivateth a giant he shall take spoils. But can one take from a mighty man and be safe? But it is I who vindicateth thy cause, and I will deliver thy children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And they who afflicted thee shall eat their own flesh, and drink like new wine their own blood and be made drunk; and all flesh shall know that it is I the Lord who delivered thee. And who uphold the strength of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="50">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Of what sort was the bill of your mother's divorce with which I divorced her? Or to what creditor have I sold you? Behold you were sold for your transgressions; and for your iniquities I divorced your mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Why, when I came, was there no man? And why, when I called, did none answer? Is my hand unable to save? Or have I no power to rescue? Behold with my rebuke I can dry up the sea, and make the rivers a desert, so that the fishes thereof shall shrivel for want of water, and die for thirst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I can clothe the heaven with darkness, and make its covering like sackcloth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The Lord Lord giveth me an instructed tongue, to know when it is proper to speak a word. He gave it me in the morning; he gave me in addition an ear to hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the instruction of the Lord, Lord openeth mine ears and I am not rebellious, nor do I gainsay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>My back I have given to scourges, and my cheeks to be slapped with an open hand, and I turned not my face from the shame of spittles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Indeed the Lord Lord was my helper; therefore I was not ashamed, but kept my countenance firm as a rock. I knew indeed that I should not be confounded,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>because he who justified me is near at hand. Who is he that contendeth with me? Let him stand up with me face to face. Yes, let my accuser, whoever he be, come near me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Behold the Lord, Lord will be my advocate; who can do An objection stated. The answer. me any evil? Behold you shall all wax old like a mantle, and the moth shall consume you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Who is there among you who feareth the Lord, let him hearken to the voice of his servant. Ye who walk in darkness and have no light, trust in the name of the Lord and stay your selves on God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Behold you are all kindling a fire and increasing the flame; walk in the light of your fire and by the flame which you have kindled. On my account these things have befallen you. You shall lie down in sorrow.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="51">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hearken to me ye who are in pursuit of righteousness and who are seeking the Lord. Look at that hard rock which you have been hewing, and into that deep pit which you have digged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Look to Abraham your father, and to Sarah who brought you forth. For he was an individual when I called him; and I blessed him and loved him and multiplied him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And now Sion, I will comfort thee. I have indeed comforted all her desolations, and I will make her waste places like a garden; and those west of her like the garden of the Lord. In her shall be found joy and gladness, thanksgiving and the sound of praise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hear me; hear me, my people, and ye kings; listen to me; for from me shall proceed a law; and my judgment shall be for the light of nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>My deliverance is approaching speedily, and my salvation shall go forth as light; and on mine arm nations will rely. The islands will expect me and on mine arm they will rely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Turn up your eyes to heaven; then look down on the earth below! for the heaven is like smoke condensed, and the earth shall grow old like a garment, and like those things the inhabitants shall perish: but my salvation shall endure forever, and my saving mercy shall never fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Hearken to me, ye who know judgment; ye people, in whose heart is my law. Fear not the reproach of men, nor be overcome by their contempt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For they are like a garment which shall be worn out by time, and like woollens which shall be devoured by a moth; but my saving mercy shall endure forever, and my salvation to generations of generations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Awake, awake, Jerusalem! and clothe thyself with the strength of thine arm. Awake as at the beginning of day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Art thou not as the generation of old, which dried up the sea; the swelling water of the deep? Which made the depths of the sea a road for the delivered and redeemed to pass?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For under the guidance of the Lord they shall be brought back, and shall come to Sion with joy and everlasting gladness; for praise shall crown their head and joy shall overtake them. Grief and sorrow and sighing are fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I THE I AM am he who comforteth thee. Recollect what thou wast when terrified at a mortal man, and at a son of man who are withered like grass;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and forgot test the God who made thee; him who made the heaven and founded the earth; and wast every day in continual dread of the furious countenance of thine oppressor. For how did he consult to carry thee away! But where now is the fury of thine oppressor?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For when thou art saved he shall not stand; nor long continue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because I thy God am he who tempesteth the sea and causeth the billows thereof to roar; the Lord of Hosts is my name;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I will put my words in thy mouth, and cover thee under the shelter of my hand with which I made the heaven and founded the earth; and say to Sion, Thou art my people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Awake, awake, stand up, Jerusalem who hast drunk from the hand of the Lord the cup of his indignation. For thou hast drunk the cup of horror; the great cup of his wrath; and drained it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And of all thy children which thou didst bring forth there was not one who comforted thee, nor was there one who took hold of thy hand: no, not of all the sons whom thou didst raise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because these things have befallen thee, who will condole with thee? Desolation and destruction, famine and the sword; who will comfort thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thy sons? Some are astounded; some asleep at the head of every way, like a parboiled beet; Some are full of the indignation of the Lord, enervated by the Lord God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore hear, thou, who hast been humbled, and who art drunk, but not with wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, the God who judgeth his people, Behold I have taken out of thy hand the cup of horror; the great cup of mine indignation; and thou shalt no more drink it again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And I will put it into the hands of them, who have injured thee and oppressed thee; who have said to thy soul, Crouch down that we may walk over thee, when thou hadst bent thy body down level with the earth in the street, to them passing along.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="52">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Awake, awake, Sion! clothe thyself, Sion, with thy strength. Put on thy glory. O Jerusalem, thou holy city! No more shall the uncircumcised and the unclean pass through thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Shake off the dust, and stand up: assume thy seat, O Jerusalem! Loose the chain from thy neck, O captive daughter of Sion!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, You were sold for nought; and you shall be ransomed, not with money.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, My people went down to Egypt at first to sojourn there; and to the Assyrians they were carried by force.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now therefore why are you here? Thus saith the Lord, Because my people were taken away for nought, (express your amaze; and raise the mournful cry! Thus saith the Lord, On your account my name is continually reviled among the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore in that day my people shall know my name. Because I THE I AM, the same who am speaking, am at hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>like beauty on the mountains; like the feet of one proclaiming peace, like one proclaiming glad tidings. Because I will cause thy salvation to be proclaimed, Saying, Sion, thy God will reign;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>because the voice of thy watchmen is lifted up; with the voice therefore let all at the same time express joy. Because eyes will look to eyes when the Lord compassionateth Sion;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>let the ruins of Jerusalem break out together with bursts of joy. Because the Lord hath compassionated her and delivered Jerusalem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>let the Lord therefore make bare his holy arm in the sight of all the nations! and let all the ends of the earth see the salvation come from our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Depart, depart; come out thence, and touch no polluted thing. Come out from the midst of her; be clean, ye who carry the vessels of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For you shall not come out in haste, nor by flight march along; for the Lord will march before you in front; and the God of Israel will bring up your rear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Behold my servant will mind and be exalted and highly glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>In the same manner as many will be astonished at thee; (so devoid of glory for men will be thine appearance and thy glory for the sons of men)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>so many nations will express admiration at him; and kings will shut their mouths, because they, to whom no publication was made concerning him, shall see; and they, who had not heard, will understand.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="53">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Lord, who hath believed this report of ours, and to whom hath the arm of the Lord been made manifest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>We have made proclamation as a child before him: as a root in a thirsty soil, he hath no appearance, nor glory. We have seen him; and he hath neither appearance nor beauty:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>but his appearance is mean and defective beyond the sons of men. Being a man in affliction and acquainted with grief, because his countenance was dejected, he was despised and disesteemed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>This man beareth away our sins; and for us he is in sorrow: And we considered him as being in trouble and under a stroke and in affliction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But he was wounded for our sins, and afflicted for our iniquities. The chastisement of our peace was upon him; by his bruises we are healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>We all like sheep had strayed; every man wandered in his way: and the Lord delivered him up for our sins:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and he, on account of his affliction, openeth not his mouth. He was led as a sheep to be slaughtered. And as a lamb before its shearer is dumb, so he openeth not his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>In this humiliation his legal trial was taken away. Who will declare his manner of life. Because his life is taken from the earth; for the transgressions of my people he is led to death;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>therefore for his funeral I will give up the wicked, and the rich for his death. Because he committed no iniquity, nor practised guile with his mouth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and the Lord determineth to purify him from this stroke: when his soul shall be given up for a sin offering; of you he shall see a seed which shall prolong their days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>More over it is the determination of the Lord to remove him from the trouble of his soul; to shew him light and fashion him for knowledge; to justify the Righteous One who is serving many well, when he shall bear away their sins;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>therefore he shall inherit many and divide the spoils of the strong. Because his soul was delivered up to death and he was numbered among transgressors and bore away the sins of many and on the account of their iniquities was delivered up;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="54">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>rejoice thou barren, who bearest not; break forth with shouts of joy, thou who sufferest not the pangs of child birth; for many more are the children of the desolate than of her who hath a husband. For the Lord said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Enlarge the place of thy tent and thy curtains; fix up; spare not; lengthen thy cords and make thy stakes strong.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Extend still farther to the right and left. And thy seed shall inherit nations and thou shalt inhabit wasted cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Be not terrified because thou hast been exposed to shame; nor blush because thou hast been reproached. For thou shalt forget the shame of ancient times, and the reproach of thy widowhood</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>thou shalt remember no more. For the Lord who is thy maker, whose name is the Lord of Hosts; even he who delivered thee, shall be called the God of Israel, in the whole earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The Lord hath not called thee as a wife forsaken and disconsolate; nor as a wife that hath been hated from her youth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thy God hath said, I left thee for a little while; but with great mercy I will compassionate thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>in a short wrath I turned away my face from thee; but with everlasting kindness I will have mercy on thee. The Lord who delivered thee hath said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>From the flood which was in Noah's time this is my purpose; as I solemnly promised him at that time that I would no more be angry with the earth on thine account, nor in rebuking thee overturn the mountains;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and that thy hills should no more be moved; so my kindness for thee shall not fail, nor shall the covenant of thy peace ever be changed: for he said for thee, Be appeased, Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>thou afflicted and storm beaten! Art thou not comforted? Behold I am preparing for thee carbuncles for thy building stones, and the sapphire for thy foundations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and for thy battlements I will lay jasper; and crystal, for thy gates; and for thy circumambient walls, precious stones:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>even thy sons, all instructed of God; and thy children in great prosperity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And with righteousness thou shalt be rebuilded. Abstain from injustice and thou shalt not be affrighted; and as for terror, it shall not approach thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Behold proselytes shall come to thee for my sake; and they shall sojourn with thee and fly to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Behold I have created thee, not like a coppersmith blowing coals and using a tool for the work. But I have created thee, not for destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Perish every weapon formed against thee! I will not prosper it. Though every voice should rise up against thee for judgment, thou shalt overcome them all and in the trial they shall be condemned. There is an inheritance for them who serve the Lord, therefore you are to be just for me, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="55">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>HO! ye who are thirsting, come to water! And ye who have no money, come buy and eat, without money and without price, wine and the choicest bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Why are you expending money and labour for that which will not satisfy? Hearken to me and you shall eat good things; and your soul will be regaled with delicacies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Incline your ears and follow in my paths; hearken to me and your soul shall live on good things; and I will make with you an everlasting covenant; the gracious promises to David which are faithful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Behold for a testimony to nations I gave him, a chief and a lawgiver to nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Nations which knew thee not will fly to thee, for the sake of the Lord thy God, the Holy One of Israel, because he hath glorified thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Seek ye the Lord; and when you find him call upon him. And when he draweth near to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>let the wicked man forsake his ways, and the unrighteous man his counsels, and turn to the Lord and he shall find mercy; for he will abundantly pardon your sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For my counsels are not as your counsels: nor are my ways as your ways, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But distant as the heaven is from the earth, so is my way distant from your ways; and your thoughts from my understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For as the rain when it descendeth, or snow, from the heavens, doth not return thither, till it hath watered the earth, and caused it to generate and bloom and yield seed for the sower and bread for food;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>so shall it be with my word: when it hath proceeded from my mouth, it shall not be reversed, till all are accomplished which I willed; and till I prosper thy ways and my commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For with gladness you shall go forth; and with joyfulness you shall be taught: for the mountains and hills shall leap for joy, expecting you; and all the trees of the field will clap with their branches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And instead of the briar, shall spring up the cypress; and instead of the thistle, shall come up the myrtle. And the Lord shall be for a name, and for an everlasting sign which shall not fail.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="56">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Keep judgment and practise righteousness; for my salvation is near, just ready to come, and my saving kindness to be revealed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Happy the man who doth these things and the mortal who adhereth to them; and who is careful not to profane my sabbaths, and who restraineth his hands from doing evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Let not the stranger who cleaveth to the Lord say, The Lord will separate me from his people. Nor let the eunuch say, I am a dry tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord to the eunuchs, whoever of them shall keep my sabbaths, and chuse the things in which I delight and adhere to my covenant;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I will give them, in my house and within my walls, an honourable place better than sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name which shall not fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And with regard to the strangers who cleave to the Lord to serve him, and love the name of the Lord; to be his man servants and maid servants, even all who are careful not to profane my sabbaths and who adhere to my covenant;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>them I will bring to my holy mountain and make them joyful in my house of prayer; their burnt offerings, and their sacrifices shall be acceptable on mine altar; for my house shall be called a house of prayer for all the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>THE LORD who gathereth the dispersed of Israel said, Because I will gather a congregation for him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>O all ye beasts of the field come! all ye beasts of the forests, devour!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>you see that they are all blind; that they have not knowledge. They are dumb dogs, they cannot bark: they are asleep in bed, they love to slumber:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>yet these dogs are of untamed appetite; they can never have enough. They are indeed mischievous, they have no consideration. They all followed their own courses, every one according to his own purpose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="57">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>You see how a righteous one was destroyed, and no one layeth it to heart. And righteous men are taken away, and no one observeth, that on account of iniquity the righteous one was taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>His sepulture shall be in peace. He is taken from among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But as for you, draw near hither, ye lawless sons! ye seed of adulterers and of fornication!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>in what have you indulged yourselves? and at whom have you opened your mouth, and at whom lolled your tongue? are you not children of destruction; a lawless race?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>invoking idols under shady trees, slaying your children in the valleys among the rocks?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This shall be thy portion; this thy lot; as thou hast poured out libations to them and to them offered up sacrifices, shall I not for these things be incensed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>On a high and lofty mountain thou hast made thy bed, and caused thy sacrifice to ascend thither;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and behind the posts of thy door thou hast set up thy memorial. Didst thou think, that, if thou departedst from me, thou shouldst have something more? Thou hast loved them who lay with thee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and multiplied thy fornication with them, and hast done it with many who are far from thee; and hast sent ambassadors beyond thy borders; and humbled thyself even to Hades;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>With thy long journies thou hast wearied thyself and hast not said, I will take some rest. Because in thy full strength thou hast done this; therefore thou shouldst not supplicate me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Of whom hast thou been so anxiously afraid that thou hast dealt falsely with me, and has not remembered nor taken me into thy thoughts, nor into thy heart? When I saw and neglected thee thou didst not fear me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now I will declare my righteousness and thine evil deeds which shall not avail thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>lo When thou criest; let them deliver thee in thine affliction. A wind indeed shall overtake them all; and a whirlwind shall sweep them away. But they who adhere to me shall possess the land, and inherit my holy mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And they will say. Clear the ways before him, remove obstructions out of the road of my people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thus saith the Most High, who on high inhabiteth eternity, who is Holy among holies; whose name is THE MOST HIGH; who at rest in the holies giveth patience to the humble, and life to them who are of a contrite heart;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I will not contend with you forever, nor will I be continually angry with you, for from me spirit is to proceed and I have made every breathing soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Because of sin I grieved him a little while and smote him and turned away my face from him; and he was grieved and went his ways sorrowing;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I have seen his ways and healed him, and comforted him, and given him true consolation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>peace upon peace to them near and to them far off. So the Lord said, I will heal them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But the wicked shall be tossed like waves and shall not be able to rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>There is no peace, said God, to the wicked.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="58">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>CRY aloud and spare not; raise thy voice like a trumpet: proclaim to my people their sins, and to the house of Jacob their iniquities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Day after day they seek me, and desire to know my ways; like a people who have practised righteousness, and who have not forsaken the ordinance of God. They now ask of me a just decision and desire to draw near to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Saying, Why have we fasted and thou hast not seen? We have humbled our souls and thou hast not known. In the very days of your fasts you enjoy your own pleasures and goad all them who are under your controul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>You fast for strife and debate; and smite the poor with your fists. Why fast ye for me as today that by a cry your voice may be heard?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>This is not such a fast as I have chosen, that a man should afflict his soul for a day. No: though thou shouldst bend thy neck like a hook and lay sackcloth and ashes under thee: even in that case you are not to call it an acceptable fast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>It is not such a fast as this that I have chosen, saith the Lord. But loose every bond of iniquity; dissolve the obligations of onerous contracts; set at liberty them who are oppressed, and tear in pieces every unjust stipulation in writing:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>deal out thy bread to the hungry, and take into thy house the poor who have no shelter; if thou seest one naked, clothe him, and look not scornfully on dependants of thy race;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>then shall thy light break forth like the morning, and thy remedies shall spring up speedily: and thy righteousness shall go before thee, and the glory of the Lord will surround thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then thou shalt cry and God will answer thee; and whilst thou art speaking he will say, Lo I am here. If thou remove from thee the bond, and the vote and decree which occasion murmuring,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and from thy soul give bread to the hungry and satisfy an afflicted soul; then shall thy light spring up in darkness; and thy darkness shall be as the noon day:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and thy God will be with thee continually; and thou shalt be satisfied as thy soul desireth; and thy bones shall be made fat and be like a watered garden, and like a spring whose water never failed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And thine old waste places shall be rebuilded; and thy foundations shall last for generations of generations: and thou shalt be called the repairer of breaches, and shalt enjoy rest in the midst of thy paths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If on account of the sabbaths thou restrain thy foot from doing thy pleasure on that holy day; and call the sabbaths delightful, dedicated to God; and wilt not lift up thy foot for any work; nor utter a word in anger from thy mouth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and trust continually in the Lord; he will then mount thee on the good places of the land and feed thee on the inheritance of thy father Jacob: for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken these words.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="59">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>It is not that the hand of the Lord is unable to save; nor that his ear is grown dull to hear;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>but your sins make a separation between you and your God; and on account of your sins he hath turned away his face from you that he may not exercise compassion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For your hands are polluted with blood, and your fingers with sins; your lips have spoken iniquity, and your tongue contriveth injustice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>None speaketh just things, nor is there any just judgment. They trusted in vanities and they speak lies. Because they hatch mischief, therefore they bring forth iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They hatched the eggs of asps, and are weaving a spider's web; and he who was about to eat some of their eggs, upon breaking one that was hatched found therein a viper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Their web will not serve for a mantle, nor can they clothe themselves with their works; for their works are works of iniquity</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Their feet are running to evil; they are swift to shed blood. And their reasonings are reasonings for murders. Destruction and misery are in their ways,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the path of peace they do not know, nor is there any judgment in their ways; for the paths which they travel are crooked and peace they do not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Therefore judgment is far from them, and saving mercy shall not overtake them. When they were waiting for light, darkness came upon them, expecting a blaze of light they walked in obscurity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They shall grope like blind men for a wall and feel about like men who have no eyes, and fall at midday as at midnight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When dying they will groan like a bear and mourn like a dove; and at their departing say, We waited for judgment and there is none: and as for safety, it is far from us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For our manifold iniquity is before thee; and our sins are risen up against us: for our iniquities are in us, and we know our transgressions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>We have sinned: we have lied, and turned back from following our God; we have spoken things unjust, and have been disobedient; we have conceived and meditated from our heart lying words,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>we have indeed turned judgment backward, therefore saving mercy standeth aloof. Because truth was destroyed in their ways and; they could not walk in straight paths;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and truth was removed and they substituted opinion in place of knowledge, therefore the Lord took a view, and it displeased him that there was no judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When he took a view and there was no man; and made close observation, and there was no helper; then with his own arm he defended them and with mercy supported them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he put on righteousness as a breast plate, and placed on his head the helmet of salvation, and threw around him the mantle of vengeance; and his cloak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>as about to retribute retribution; reproach to his adversaries:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and they from the west shall revere the name of the Lord; and they from the rising of the sun, his glorious name. For he will come like an impetuous stream; for the wrath of the Lord will come with fury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For the sake of Sion the Deliverer will come, and turn away ungodliness from Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And this shall be my covenant with them, said the Lord, this spirit of mine which is upon thee, and these words which I have put in thy mouth shall not fail from thy mouth, nor from the mouth of thy seed, (for the Lord hath spoken) from this time forth forever.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="60">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Be enlightened: be enlightened, Jerusalem! for thy light is come; and the glory of the Lord is risen upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Behold darkness will cover the earth and thick darkness the nations: but upon thee the Lord will shine and his glory over thee will be conspicuous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And kings will walk by thy light: and nations by thy splendour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Raise thine eyes around and behold thy children gathered together; all thy sons are come from afar, and thy daughters shall be carried on shoulders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then thou wilt look and be filled with awe and astonished at heart; because the riches of the sea and of nations and peoples will pour in upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And for thee will come herds of camels and those of Madiam and Gaipha will cover thee, and those of Saba will come bringing gold and will also bring frankincense, and with joy proclaim the salvation of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And all the flocks of Kedar shall be gathered together; and the rams of Nabaioth will come; and acceptable offerings will be made on mine altar, and my house of prayer will be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who are those? They are flying like clouds, and like doves with their young towards me!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For me the islands waited, and among the first the ships of Tarsis to bring thy children from afar and their silver and their gold with them. And because of the holy name of the Lord, and because the Holy One of Israel is glorious;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>therefore strangers shall rebuild thy walls and their kings shall wait upon thee. For on account of my wrath I smote thee, but for mercy's sake I have loved thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and thy gates shall be open continually (by day or by night they shall not be shut) to introduce to thee the wealth of nations and their kings pompously attended.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For the nations and kings which will not serve thee shall perish; such nations indeed shall be utterly laid waste.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The glory of Lebanon also shall come to thee, with the cypress and the pine and the cedar, to adorn the place which is dedicated to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And to thee shall come trembling the sons of them who afflicted and humbled thee, and thou shalt be called, City Sion of the Holy one of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because of thy having been forsaken and hated when there was no helper, I will make thee an everlasting boast; a joy for perpetual generations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And thou shalt suck the milk of nations, and feed on the wealth of kings, and shalt know that I the Lord am thy Saviour, and that thy Redeemer is the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And instead of brass I will bring thee gold; and instead of iron I will bring thee silver; and instead of wood I will bring thee brass and instead of stones iron. And I will make thy chiefs peaceful and thine overseers righteous;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and violence shall no more be heard in thy land, nor destruction nor misery in thy borders; but thy walls shall be called Salvation and thy gates, sculpture.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And thou shalt no more have the sun for a light by day nor shall the rising of the moon enlighten thy night; but the Lord will be to thee an everlasting light; and thy God will be thy glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For thy sun shall not go down nor shall thy moon ever wane: For the Lord will be to thee an everlasting light; and the days of thy mourning shall be ended.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And thy people shall be all righteous, they shall inherit the land forever, preserving the plant, the works of their hands, for glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The fewest in number shall become thousands, and he who is smallest, a great nation. I the Lord in due time will gather them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="61">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>THE SPIRIT of the Lord is upon me, for the business for which he anointed me. He hath sent me to publish glad tidings to the poor, to heal them who are brokenhearted; to proclaim a deliverance to captives, and a recovery of sight to the blind:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to proclaim an acceptable year of the Lord and a day of retribution. To comfort all who are mourning;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>that to the mourners in Sion may be given, glory instead of ashes, oil of joy to the mourners, robes of praise for the spirit of heaviness; that they may be called generations of righteousness, a plant of the Lord for glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the wastes of old times shall be rebuilded; and former desolations shall be repaired, and wasted cities renewed which had lain in ruins for ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And strangers shall come and feed thy flocks and6 foreigners shall be thy ploughmen and vine dressers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But you shall be called priests of the Lord, ministers of God. You shall eat the wealth of nations and for their riches be admired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thus shall they again inherit the land; and everlasting joy shall be on their head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For I am the Lord who love righteousness and hate the spoils of injustice; and I will give the righteous the fruit of their toil and make an everlasting covenant with them</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and their seed shall be distinguished among the nations? and their offspring in the midst of peoples. Every one who seeth them will know them, that they are a seed whom God hath blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And they shall rejoice in the Lord with joy. Rejoice in the Lord, my soul, for he hath clothed me with the mantle of Salvation, and with an under garment of gladness, he hath crowned me as a bridegroom with a crown and adorned me as a bride, with jewels,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and like the earth blooming with flowers. And as a garden causeth its seeds to vegetate, so will the Lord cause righteousness to spring up and joy in the presence of all the nations.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="62">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For Sion's sake I will not be silent, and for the sake of Jerusalem I will not rest; until the righteousness thereof break forth as light, and my salvation blaze like a torch;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and nations see thy righteousness, and kings this glory of thine. When he shall call thee by a new name which the Lord himself will give thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>then thou shalt be a crown of beauty in the hand of the Lord, and a royal diadem in the hand of thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And thou shalt no more be called, Forsaken; nor shall thy land any more be called, The desert; but thy name shall be called My delight; and that of thy country, The inhabited land. Because the Lord is well pleased with thee therefore thy land shall be thickly inhabited:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and as a youth cohabiting with a virgin bride, so shall thy sons inhabit it: and 'as a bridegroom will rejoice in his bride, so will the Lord rejoice over thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now upon thy walls, Jerusalem, I have set watchmen all the day; and all the night, they will not cease continually to mention the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for there is none like you. When he shall have reestablished and made Jerusalem a boast on the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the Lord hath sworn by his glory and by the power of his arm, I will no more give thy corn and thy food to thine enemies; nor shall the sons of strangers any more drink thy wine, for which thou hast laboured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But they who reap the harvest shall eat and praise the Lord; and they who gather the vintage shall drink wine in my holy courts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Go through my gates and prepare the way for my people and throw the stones out of the way. Erect a standard for the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For lo! the Lord hath published this to the end of the earth. Say to the daughter of Sion, Behold the Saviour is come for thee, having his own reward and his work before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And he will call this a holy people, redeemed by the Lord; and thou shalt be called the city sought and not forsaken.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="63">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Who is this who is coming from Edom? What redness of mantles from Bosor! He so magnificent in apparel? He marcheth with majesty! I proclaim righteousness and the judgment of salvation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Why are thy garments red and thy clothing, as from a trodden wine vat?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I am full of a country trodden down; and of the nations there is not a man with me. I have trodden them down in my wrath, and crumbled them like dust and shed their blood on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For the day of retribution came upon them and the year of redemption is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>When I looked and there was no helper and observed that none upheld; then mine own arm delivered them. Mine indignation indeed was roused,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and I trampled them down in mine anger and shed their blood on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>I recollected the loving kindness of the Lord; the mercies of the Lord in all those things which he retributeth for us. The Lord is a good judge to the house of Israel. He dealeth with us according to his tender mercy and according to the abundance of his saving goodness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and said Is not this my people? Children should not rebel. And he became their Saviour from all their distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>It was not an ambassador nor a messenger; but he himself saved them. Through his love and his indulgence to them, he himself redeemed them and took them up, and exalted them all the days of old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But they rebelled and provoked his holy spirit; so he became their enemy. He fought against them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>though he remembered the days of old. O! where is he who caused the shepherd of his flock to come up out of the sea? Where is he, who put his holy spirit in them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>That glorious arm of his which led Moses by the right hand? He forced back the water from before him, to make himself an everlasting name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He led them through the deep, like a horse through a desert; and they were not fatigued:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and like cattle through a plain. A spirit from the Lord descended and conducted them. Thus thou didst lead this people of thine, to make thyself a glorious name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Return from heaven and take a view from the house of thy sanctuary and thy glory. Where is thy zeal and thy majesty? Where the abundance of thy loving kindness and tender affections, that thou hast withdrawn thyself from us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For thou art our father. Because Abraham knoweth us not, and Israel hath not acknowledged us; do thou, Lord, our father, do thou deliver us. From the beginning thy name is upon us;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>why, O Lord hast thou suffered us to wander from thy way, and our hearts to be hardened so as not to fear thee? Return for the sake of thy servants; for the sake of the tribes of thy heritage,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>that we may inherit a little of thy holy mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>We are become as at the beginning, when thou didst not rule over us, and when we were not called by thy name.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="64">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>If thou wilt open the heaven, at thy presence terror will seize the mountains, and they will melt</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>as wax melteth before fire; and a fire will burn up the adversaries, and thy name will be manifest to the adversaries; At thy presence the nations will be troubled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When thou executest thy glorious works, because of thee, terror will seize the mountains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Never have we heard, nor have our eyes seen a God besides thee; nor works such as thine, which thou wilt do for them who wait for mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For it will meet them who practise righteousness, and they will remember their ways. Behold thou wast angry when we sinned; because of this we wandered</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and became all of us as unclean, and all our righteousness was like a polluted rag; and for our iniquities we have fallen like leaves; so that the wind will sweep us away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>There is indeed none who invoketh thy name, or who remembered to lay hold on thee; because thou hast turned away thy face from us, and delivered us up for our sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But now, Lord, thou art our father. Though we are clay, we are all the works of thy hands:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>be not angry with us to the uttermost; nor remember forever our sins: but, O, look down now upon us; for we are all thy people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The city of thy sanctuary is become a desert: Sion is become like a desert; Jerusalem, for a curse.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The house, our sanctuary; even that glory which our fathers blessed, is utterly burnt up with fire, and all our glorious things are in ruins;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>yet for all these things, thou, Lord, hast refrained, and been silent. Thou hast humbled us exceedingly.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="65">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I became manifest to them who inquired not for me; I was found by them who sought me not. I said, Behold here I am? to the nation which did not invoke my name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I stretched out my hands all the day long to a disobedient and gainsaying people, who were walking not in a good way, but following their own sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>This people are provoking me continually to my face. They will sacrifice in the gardens and burn incense on the tiles, to demons which have not an existence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They sleep in tombs and in caverns for the purpose of dreaming: they eat swine's flesh, and the broth of sacrifices; all their vessels are polluted;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>yet they say, Keep at a distance from me; come not near me, for I am clean. This is a smoke which causeth my wrath; a fire is kindled by it every day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Behold it is written before me: I will not keep silence, until I have retributed into their bosom</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>their sins; and the sins of their fathers, saith the Lord. They have burned incense on the mounts, and treated me with scorn on the hills, I will retribute their works into their bosom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, as when a good grape is found in the cluster, they will say, Destroy it not; for there is a blessing in it, so will I do for the sake of him who serveth me; for his sake I will not destroy them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I will indeed bring forth the seed from Jacob namely, from Juda, and he shall inherit my holy mountain: and my chosen ones and my servants shall inherit and dwell there;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and there shall be in the forest folds for flocks; and the valley of Achor shall be a resting place of herds, for my people who have sought me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But as for you, who forsake me and forget my holy mountain, and who prepare a table for the Demon, and fill up a mixed potion for Fortune,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>you I will deliver up to the sword; you shall all bow down to slaughter. Because I called and you answered not: I spake and you would not listen; but did what is evil in my sight; and chose the things in which I did not delight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold my servants shall eat; but you shall be hungry: behold my servants shall drink; but you shall be thirsty: behold my servants shall rejoice; but you shall be ashamed:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>behold my servants shall triumph with joy: But you shall scream for sorrow of heart, and howl for anguish of spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For you shall leave your name for a loathing to my chosen. As for you, the Lord will destroy you; but to my servants, a new name shall be given</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>which shall be blessed on the earth: for they will bless the true God: and they who swear on the earth, will swear by the true God. For they will forget their former affliction and it shall not recur to their mind:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>for there shall be a new heaven and the earth shall be new: and they shall no more remember former things, nor shall they ever come again into their mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But in this they shall find joy and gladness: for behold I am about to make Jerusalem a subject of joy, and this people of mine a subject of rejoicing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I will exult in Jerusalem and rejoice in my people; and there shall no more be heard therein, the voice of wailing nor the sound of a mournful cry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Nor shall there any more be there an untimely birth, nor an old man, who shall not complete his term. For he who is a hundred years old shall be young; and the sinner, who dieth at a hundred years, shall be deemed accursed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they shall build houses and dwell therein: and they shall plant vineyards and eat the fruits thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>They shall not build, and others inhabit: nor shall they plant and others eat: for according to the days of the tree of that life, shall be the days of this my people: for they shall wear out the works of their toils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>My chosen ones shall not labour in vain, nor shall they bring forth children for a curse. Because they are a seed blessed of God, both they and their offspring:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>therefore it shall come to pass, that before they call I will answer them: and while they are yet speaking I will say, What is the matter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then shall the wolves and the lambs feed together: and the lion shall eat straw like the ox. But the serpent shall eat dust as bread. They shall not hurt, nor shall they destroy on my holy mountain, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="66">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, The heaven is my throne, and the earth, my footstool: what sort of an house will you build for me? And of what sort shall be the place of my rest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For all these things my hand hath made: and all these things are mine saith the Lord. Upon whom therefore will I look down, but upon him only who is humble and quiet, and who trembleth at my words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>As for the wicked man, who sacrificeth to me a young bull: he is one who slayeth a dog: and though he offereth me fine flour: it will be as the blood of swine. Though he offereth incense for a memorial, he is as a blasphemer. As they have chosen their own ways: and their soul hath delighted in their abominations:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I also will chuse their delusions, and pay them back their sins. Because I called them and they did not answer; I spake, but they did not listen: but did that which is evil in my sight, and chose the things in which I did not delight;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>hear the decisions of the Lord; ye who tremble at his word, say, O our brethren; (to them who hate you and are abominable, that the name of the Lord may be glorified and appear to their joy, when they shall be ashamed)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>a sound of screaming from the city! a sound from the temple! the voice of the Lord rendering a recompense to his adversaries!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>That a woman hath brought forth before she travailed; that before her pangs came on, they are over and a male child born;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>who hath heard such a thing, or who hath seen the like? Did ever the earth bring forth in a day, or was ever a nation born at once? That Sion should travail and bring forth her children,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I myself gave this expectation; yet thou didst not remember me, saith the Lord. Behold did I not make her who beareth; and her who is barren? Said thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Rejoice Jerusalem! and sing praises therein, all ye who love her! Be exceedingly joyful with her, all ye who mourn for her!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>That you may suck and be satisfied from the breast of her consolation; that you may suck and be fed deliciously, at the commencement of her glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, Behold I will glide to them like a peaceful stream, and like a torrent deluging the glory of nations. Their children shall be carried on shoulders, and shall be dandled on knees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>As one whom his mother comforteth, so will I comfort you, and in Jerusalem you shall find consolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And you shall see it, and your heart shall rejoice; and your bones shall flourish like a green herb. And the hand of the Lord will be made known to them who fear him. And it will terrify them who are disobedient.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For behold! the Lord will come as a fire, and his chariots as a whirlwind, to execute his vengeance with wrath and his rebuke with flaming fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For with the fire of the Lord all this land shall be tried, and all flesh with his sword. Many shall be the slain of the Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They who consecrate and purify themselves for the gardens, and they who, in the outer courts, eat swine's flesh, and the abominations and the mouse, shall for this be consumed together, said the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>As I know their works and their reasoning I am coming to gather together all the nations and the tongues, and they shall come and see my glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I will leave among them a sign, and those of them who escape I will send to the nations; to Tharsis and Phud and Lud and Mosach and to Thobel and Greece and to the far distant isles. They who have not heard my name nor seen my glory; even they shall proclaim my glory among the nations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and they shall bring your brethren from all the nations, as a gift for the Lord with horses and chariots, in litters borne by mules with umbrellas over them, to the holy city Jerusalem, said the Lord; as the children of Israel brought up their sacrifices for me with songs of praise to the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And of them I will take priests and Levites, said the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For as the new heaven and the new earth, which I make, shall remain in my presence, saith the Lord; so shall your seed and your name be established.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And it shall be, that month after month and sabbath after sabbath, all flesh shall come to worship before me, in Jerusalem, said the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And they shall go forth, and see the carcasses of those men, who have transgressed against me. For their Worm shall not die and their fire shall not be quenched, and they shall be a spectacle to all flesh.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>