<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word of God which came to Jeremias the son of Chelkias, one of the priests who dwelt at Anathoth in the land of Benjamin;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>as the word of God came to him in the days of Josias son of Amos king of Juda, in the thirteenth year of his reign</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and came to him in the days of Joakim son of Josias king of Juda even to the eleventh year of Zedekias son of Josias king of Juda, even to the capture of Jerusalem, in the fifth month</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When this word of the Lord came to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Before I formed thee in the womb, I knew thee, and before thou wast born I hallowed thee. I have appointed thee a prophet for nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thereupon I said, self-existent sovereign, Lord! behold I know not how to speak, for I am a child.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the Lord said to me, say not For I am a child. For thou shalt go to all, to whomsoever I send thee; and according to all that I command thee thou shalt speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Be not afraid of them; for I am with thee to deliver thee saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then the Lord stretched forth his hand towards me and touched my mouth; and the Lord said to me, Behold I have put my words in thy mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Behold I have this day set thee over nations and over kingdoms to root out and demolish and destroy; and to rebuild and plant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then a word of the Lord came to me saying, What dost thou see. Whereupon I said, I see a rod of an almond tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the Lord said to me, Thou hast seen well: for I have watched over my words to perform them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Again a word of the Lord came to me a second time saying: What dost thou see? And I said, A kettle; its bottom glowing hot; and its mouth from the north.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me, From the north shall blaze out the evils against all the inhabitants of this land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For behold I am calling together all the kingdoms of the earth from the north, saith the Lord; and they shall come and set, every one his throne against the vestibules of the gates of Jerusalem and against all the walls thereof round about, and against all the cities of Juda:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and I will speak to them with a judicial process touching all their wickedness. As they have forsaken me and sacrificed to strange Gods, and worshipped the works of their hands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore gird thou up thy loins and stand up and speak all that I command thee. Be not afraid of them, nor terrified at their presence; for I am with thee to deliver thee, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold I have made thee this day, like a fortified city and like a wall of brass, too strong for all the kings of Juda and the chiefs thereof and the people of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Though they fight against thee they cannot prevail over thee; for I am with thee to deliver thee saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then he said, Thus saith the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I remembered mercy in thy youth; and love, in thy mature age,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>that thou mightest follow the Holy Israel, saith the Lord. The Holy Israel is to the Lord the chief of his productions, all that devour him shall be guilty of trespass: evils shall come upon them, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Hear a word of the Lord, house of Jacob and every family of the house of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, What fault did your fathers find in me, that they have withdrawn from me; and have gone after vanities and become vain:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and did not say, Where is the Lord, who brought us up out of the land of Egypt; who led us through the wilderness; through a boundless and untrodden land; through a land without water and without fruit; through a land which no man traversed, and where no man had a fixed abode.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When I brought you to Channel that you might eat its fruits and the good things thereof; you entered in and polluted my land; and made my heritage an abomination.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The priests did not say, Where is the Lord? and they who studied the law did not know me; the pastors also transgressed against me; and the prophets prophesied for Baal and went after an unprofitable thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For this also I will emplead you; and your childrens' children I will emplead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For go to the isles of Chettim and see; and send to Kedar and make strict inquiry; and see if such things have ever happened:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>have nations changed their Gods, though they are no Gods? but my people have changed their glory for that which will not profit them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>At this the heaven was astonished and shocked exceedingly, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Because my people did two things which are both evil: they forsook me, the fountain of living water; and hewed out for themselves broken cisterns which cannot hold water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Is Israel a slave or a home born servant? Why was he for a prey?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Against him lions roared and uttered their voice: they have made his land a desert and his cities are demolished so as to be uninhabitable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Even the sons of Memphis and Taphnas have known and derided thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Hath not thy forsaking me, saith the Lord thy God, brought these things upon thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now therefore what hast thou to do with the way to Egypt? Is it to drink the water of Geon? Or what hast thou to do in the way to the Assyrians? Is it to drink the water of rivers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Let this apostacy of thine correct thee. And thy wickedness work conviction in thee. And know and see how bitter a thing it is to forsake me, saith the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Further, I have no pleasure in thee, saith the Lord thy God, because of old thou hast broken thy yoke, and burst thy bands, and said, I will not serve thee; but I will go up every high mount: and under every shady tree, I will there indulge my wantonness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I indeed planted thee an entirely good and fruitful vine: how art thou, degenerate vine, turned to bitterness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Though thou wash thyself with nitre and use much soap: thou art stained by thine iniquities in my sight, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>How canst thou say, I am not polluted, nor have I gone after Baal? View thy ways in the grave yard, and recollect what thou hast done. In the evening her voice raised the mournful cry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>She enlarged her ways to the waters of a desert: by the desires of her soul she was transported into raptures. She is delivered up: who will bring her back? None who seek her will weary themselves. In her humiliation they shall find her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Turn thy foot from a rugged way, and thy throat from thirst. But she said, I will act like one come to maturity. Because she loved strangers, therefore after them she did go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>As a thief when taken, is ashamed; so shall the children of Israel be put to shame. They and their kings and their chiefs and their priests and their prophets,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>said to a stock, Thou art my father; and to a stone, Thou hast begotten me. And turned their backs to me and not their faces: yet in the time of their troubles they will say, Arise and save us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Where now are thy gods which thou hast made for thyself? Will they arise and save in the time of thy trouble? Since according to the number of thy cities were thy gods Juda; and according to the number of the streets of Jerusalem they burned incense to Baal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>why do you address me? You are all guilty of impiety; and you have all transgressed against me, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>In vain have I smitten your children, you did not receive instruction: a sword devoured your prophets, like a ravening lion; and you were not terrified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Hear a word of the Lord! Thus saith the Lord, Was I a desert to Israel or a desolate land? Why did my people say, We will not be lorded over, nor come to thee any more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Will a bride forget her attire; or a virgin, the ornaments that deck her bosom? Yet my people have forgotten me, days without number.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Wilt thou yet study any decency in thy ways in search of love? Far from that, thou hast abandoned thyself to wickedness to pollute thy ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And on thy hands hath been found the blood of innocent souls. These I did not find in breaches into houses, but in every grove of oaks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Yet thou sayest, I am innocent; let His wrath be turned from me: behold I will emplead thee for saying, I have not sinned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Because thou hast made very light of repeating thy journies, therefore thou shalt be made ashamed of Egypt, as thou hast been, of Assyria:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>for thou shalt come up thence with thy hands on thy head, for the Lord hath rejected thy confidence and thou shalt not prosper in it.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>If a man divorce his wife and she depart from him and marry another, can she return again to him? would not such a wife be altogether polluted? Yet thou hast played the harlot with many shepherds and hast returned to me saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Raise thine eyes, look forward and take a view! where is there a place in which thou hast not prostituted thyself? In the highways thou hast sat for them like a deserted daw, and polluted the land with thy whoredoms and with thy wicked acts,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and retained many shepherds for a stumbling block to thyself: yet with the face of a harlot and behaving indecently before them all,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>hast thou not returned home and called me father and the guide of thy youth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Will anger continue forever? Shall it be kept up to the last? Behold thou hast spoken and done these evil things: yet thou hast prevailed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Again the Lord said to me in the days of Josias the king, Hast thou seen what the house of Israel have done to me? They have gone up upon every high mountain and under every shady tree and have there committed whoredom;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and after she had committed all these acts of whoredom I said, Return to me; but she returned not. And the treacherous Juda saw this treachery;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and I saw that when for all the whoredoms which Israel had committed and in which she had been caught, I had put her away and given her a bill of divorce in her hands, the treacherous Juda was not terrified, but went and committed the like herself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Indeed the other's fornication was as nothing; she committed adultery with stocks and stones,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and for all this the treacherous Juda turned not to me with her whole heart but only feignedly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me, Israel hath justified herself more than the treacherous Juda;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>go and proclaim these words to the north and thou shalt say, Return to me, house of Israel, saith the Lord, and I will not set my face against you. For I am merciful, saith the Lord and will not be angry with you forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Nevertheless acknowledge thine iniquity; that thou hast transgressed against the Lord thy God, and opened thy ways for strangers under every shady tree; and hast not hearkened to my voice, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Return, O apostate children, saith the Lord: for I will exercise dominion over you, and take one of a city and two of a family and bring you to Sion:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and I will give you pastors according to mine own heart, and they shall tend and feed you with knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when you are multiplied and increased in the land, saith the Lord, in those days they shall no more say, The ark of the covenant of the Holy Israel. It shall no more come to mind nor be named; nor shall it be covered nor made any more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>In those days and at that time Jerusalem shall be called The Throne of the Lord, and all the nations shall be gathered to it. And they shall no more follow the desires of their own wicked heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>In those days the house of Juda shall unite with the house of Israel, and they shall come together from the land of the north and from all those countries, to the land which I put in possession of their fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>(Whereupon I said, so be it, Lord.) Because I am to rank thee among children and give thee a choice land; the heritage of God the Supreme Ruler of nations; therefore I said, Call me Father, and, From me you shall not turn away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But as a wife dealeth treacherously with her husband, so the house of Israel dealt treacherously with me, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>A sound from the lips was heard, of the wailing and supplication of the children of Israel; because they had transgressed in their ways; had forgotten God their Holy One.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Return, return, O children, and I will heal your bruises. Behold we will be thy servants for thou art the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>False indeed have been the hills and the strength of the mountains, but from the Lord our God is the salvation of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>This shame consumed the labours of our fathers from our youth; Their flocks and their herds, their sons and their daughters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>We lay down in our shame and our dishonour covered us; because we sinned against our God; both we and our fathers from our youth to this day; and hearkened not to the voice of the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>If Israel will return, saith the Lord; let him return to me. And if he will remove his abominations from his mouth, and on account of me be filled with holy awe; and swear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As the Lord liveth? with truth in judgment and justice: then shall the nations bless by him, and by him praise God in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord to the men of Juda and inhabitants of Jerusalem, Break up for yourselves fallow grounds and sow not among thorns:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>be circumcised for your God and circumcise the stubbornness of your hearts, O men of Juda and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem; lest my wrath break out like a fire and burn; and there be none to quench it, because of the wickedness of your devices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Make proclamation in Juda and let it be heard in Jerusalem. Say, Sound the trumpet in the land; raise the screaming cry! Say, Assemble together and let us go into the walled cities!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Break up and flee to Sion; make all haste; tarry not: for I am bringing evils from the north and a great destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>A lion has gone up from his den: a destroyer of nations hath begun his march and is come from his place to make this land a desolation; and the cities shall be demolished so as to be uninhabitable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For these things gird on sackcloth; wail and utter lamentation. Because the wrath of the Lord is not turned away from you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>therefore it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord; that the understanding of the king shall be destroyed; and the understanding of the chiefs; and the priests shall be confounded and the prophets amazed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon this I said, O Sovereign Lord! hast thou indeed deceived this people and Jerusalem, saying, There shall be peace, when lo! the sword hath reached their very soul?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>At that time let it be said to this people and to Jerusalem, there is a spirit of wandering in the wilderness. The way of the daughter of my people is not to purity nor to holiness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A spirit of execution shall come for me and I am now denouncing my judgments on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Behold he shall come up like a cloud, and his chariots like a whirlwind. His horses are swifter than eagles. Alas for us! we are undone!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Jerusalem! wash thy heart from wickedness that thou mayst be saved. How long do ill grounded reasonings for thy troubles remain in thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because the voice of a messenger will come from Dan and distress will be heard from mount Ephraim;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Call to mind the nations: behold they are come. Proclaim in Jerusalem, Predatory bands are coming from afar, and have uttered their voice against the cities of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Like men watching a field they are all around her. Because thou wast not mindful of me saith the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>thy ways and thy devices have done these things to thee. It is owing to thy wickedness that they are bitter; that they have reached thy very heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>My bowels! my bowels are pained! and every sensation of my heart. My soul throbbeth! my heart is torn. I cannot keep silence; for my soul hath heard the trumpet's sound; the din of war and of distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>It calleth for contrition; for the whole land is in deep distress. My tent is suddenly whelmed in ruin; my curtains are rent to pieces. How long shall I see men fleeing!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>How long hear the sound of trumpets!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Because the rulers of my people did not know me, they are foolish children and devoid of understanding. They are wise to do evil; but to do good they have no knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I beheld the earth and lo! a void! Then the heaven; and its lights were gone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>I beheld the mountains; and they were trembling, and all the hills were in perturbation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I looked; and lo! there was not a man; and all the birds of the air were flown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I beheld; and lo! Karmel was a desert; and all the cities were burned with fire. At the presence of the Lord; and because of his fierce anger, they are utterly destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, The whole land shall be a desert; but I will not make a complete end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For these things let the land mourn; and the heaven above be covered with darkness; for I have spoken and I will not change my mind, I have made an assault and will not withdraw from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>At the sound of the cavalry and bended bow all the country had fled. They had skulked into caves; and hidden themselves in forests; and upon rocks they had climbed up. Every city was deserted; in them not a man dwelt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And as for thee what wilt thou do? Though thou clothe thyself with scarlet and deck thyself with ornaments of gold; though thou paint thine eyes with stibium, thy decoration will avail nothing; thy lovers have cast thee off. They will seek thy life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For I have heard a sound as of one in labour; of thy groan, as of one who beareth her first child. The voice of the daughter of Sion shall be weak: and she shall let her hands hang down. Woe is me! for my soul fainteth on account of the slain.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Run to and fro through the streets of Jerusalem; and look, and inquire, and search in her broad ways. If you can find; if there be a man, who executeth judgment and seeketh truth, I will be merciful to them saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>They say, As the Lord liveth. Do they not on this very account swear to falsehoods?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Lord, thine eyes look for faithfulness. Thou hast chastised them: but they have not grieved. Thou hast consumed them and they would not receive instruction. They have made their faces harder than a rock and refused to return.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then I said, perhaps they are poor, therefore they could not. Because they have not known the way of the Lord and the judgment of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I will go to the nobles and speak to them. Because these knew the way of the Lord and the judgment of God, and lo! with one consent, have broken the yoke and burst the bands;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore a lion from the forest hath smitten them and a wolf hath destroyed them even in their houses, and a leopard hath lain in wait against their cities. Let all who go out from them be hunted down. Because they have multiplied their iniquities; have strengthened themselves in their apostacies;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for which of these can I be merciful to thee? Thy children have forsaken me, and sworn by things which are no Gods. When I fed them plentifully, they committed adultery, and revelled in the houses of harlots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>They became furious wanton steeds; they neighed every one for his neigh hour's wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Shall I not visit for these things, saith the Lord, and on such a nation as this shall not my soul be avenged?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Go up against her battlements and demolish them: but you must not make a complete destruction; leave her buttresses, for they are the Lord's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Because the house of Israel have broken faith with me, saith the Lord, and the house of Juda have given the lie to their Lord and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>These things are not so. Evils will not come upon us; we shall see neither sword nor famine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Our prophets are but wind and the word of the Lord was not in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord Almighty, because you have spoken this word; behold I have made these words of mine for thy mouth, a fire; and this people fuel; and it shall devour them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Behold I am about to bring against you, house of Israel, saith the Lord, a nation from afar; a nation the sound of whose tongue thou wilt not understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They are all mighty men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and they shall devour your harvest and your bread; and they shall devour your sons and your daughters; and they shall devour your flocks and your herds; and they shall devour your vineyards and fig trees and olive orchards, and smite with the sword your fortified cities, in which you trusted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But it shall come to pass in those days, saith the Lord thy God; That I will not make an entire end of you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now when you say, Why hath the Lord our God done all this to us? then thou shalt say to them, Because you served strange Gods in your land, therefore you shall serve strange Gods in a land which is not yours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Proclaim these things to the house of Jacob and let them be published to the house of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Hear these things I beseech you, O foolish and stupid people! They have eyes, but they do not see; ears they have, but they do not hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Will you not fear me, saith the Lord, nor be struck with awe at the presence of me who have by an everlasting decree, made sand a boundary to the ocean, so that it shall not pass it. Though it be tossed with a tempest, it shall not prevail; though the waves thereof roar, they shall not overpass it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But this people have a revolting and disobedient heart. They have turned aside and are gone:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and did not say in their heart, let us now fear the Lord our God, who giveth us the former and the latter rain, according to the time of completing the appointed harvest. Though he had reserved these for us,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>your iniquities have turned them out of their course: and your sins have removed good things from you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Since there have been found among my people wicked men, who have set snares to destroy men and have caught them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>As a trap which hath been set is full of birds, so their houses are full of deceit, therefore they became great and rich</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and overleaped judgment; they did not administer justice to the orphan, nor decide righteously the cause of the widow;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>shall I not visit for these things, saith the Lord, and on such a nation as this shall not my soul be avenged?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Astonishing and horrible things have been done in this</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>land. The prophets prophesy falsehoods, and the priests clapped with their hands, and my people loved to have it so. Now what will you do in regard to the consequences?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Assume courage ye sons of Benjamin who are from the midst of Jerusalem, and give a signal with the trumpet at Thekoe; and on Bethacharma erect a standard. Because evils from the north are apparent, and a great destruction is begun,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>therefore thy loftiness shall be destroyed. With regard to the daughter of Sion;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>to her shepherds shall come with their flocks, and pitch their tents around against her and feed. They will say every one to his band</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Prepare yourselves for battle against her, arise and let us go up against her at noon. Alas for us the day is declined, Because the shadows of the day fail,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>arise and let us go up against her by night, and let us destroy her foundations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, Cut down her trees: discharge engines against Jerusalem: lying city! in it all is oppression.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>As a reservoir sendeth forth water, so her wickedness gusheth out. Open wickedness and misery may be heard in her continually. With anguish and scourging</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>be instructed, Jerusalem! lest my soul be alienated from thee; lest I make thee an untrodden land, which shall not be inhabited.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, Glean, glean as a vineyard the remains of Israel. Return again and again like a grape gatherer to his basket.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>To whom shall I speak and give warning that he may hearken? behold their ears are uncircumcised and they cannot hear. Behold the word of the Lord was to them an object of reproach and they would not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore my wrath, which I filled up and restrained that I might not destroy them, I now pour out on infants in the streets, and on the congregation of youths at the same time. Because husband and wife shall be comprehended; the elder with him who is full of days;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>therefore their houses shall be transferred to others; their fields and their wives together. Because I will stretch forth my hand against the inhabitants of this land, saith the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>because from the least of them to the greatest, they have all committed unrighteous deeds; from the priest to the false prophet, they have all practised falsehoods,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and healed the hurt of my people by underrating it and saying Peace, Peace; but where is there peace?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Were they ashamed because they failed? even in that case they were not ashamed; nor were they sensible of their infamy; therefore they shall fall in the common ruin; and in the time of visitation they shall perish, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Stand in the highways and take a view and inquire for the ancient paths of the Lord, and see which is the good way and walk in it, and you shall find a purification for your souls: but they said, We will not go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I have set watchmen over you; hearken to the sound of the trumpet. But they said, We will not listen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore the nations heard; even they who were tending their flocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Hear earth, behold upon this people I am bringing evils; the fruit of their apostacy, because they attended not to my words and rejected my law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Why do you bring me incense from Saba, and cinnamon from a far distant country? Your whole burnt offerings are not acceptable; nor were your incense offerings sweet to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold I send weakness on this people, and weak shall be fathers and sons with them; and neighbour with neighbour shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Behold a people is coming from the north; and nations shall be roused from the extremity of the earth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>they will grasp the bow and the spear: they are haughty and will show no mercy: their voice is like the roaring sea: on horses and in chariots they will draw up in array like fire, for battle against thee, O daughter of Sion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>We have heard the fame of them. Our hands are enfeebled. Anguish hath taken hold of us; pangs, as of a woman in travail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Go not out to the fields and in the highways walk not, because the sword of the enemy dwelleth all around</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>O daughter of my people gird thee with sackcloth; strew thyself with ashes: utter for thyself piteous lamentation like the mourning for a beloved. For misery will suddenly come upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>I have made thee an assayer for trying peoples: and thou shalt know me when I try their ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>They are all disobedient and walk perversely. Being brass and iron they are all utterly consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The bellows could not stand the fire: the lead is consumed. In vain doth the silversmith try to extract silver. Their wickedness was not to be melted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>You shall call them rejected silver, for the Lord hath rejected them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear a word of the Lord, all ye of Judea!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>thus saith the Lord the God of Israel: amend your ways and your pursuits: and I will cause you to dwell in this place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Trust not in yourselves; in lying words: for you will derive no benefit from them who say, The temple of the Lord! it is the temple of the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For if you thoroughly amend your ways and your pursuits, and actually execute judgment between man and man:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and do not oppress the stranger and orphan and widow, nor shed innocent blood in this place, nor go after strange gods to your hurt:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>then will I cause you to dwell in this place; (in the land which I gave to your fathers) from age to age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But if you continue to trust in lying words from which you can derive no benefit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and commit murder, and adultery and steal and swear to a falsehood, and burn incense to Baal; and when you have gone after strange gods which you did not know;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>you, because of your calamities, have then come and stood before me, in the house which is called by my name, and said, We have been restrained from committing these abominations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>is not this house of mine, which is called by my name, become in your eyes a den of robbers? Now behold I have seen this, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Go then to my place which was at Selo, where I caused my name to dwell at first; and see what I have done to it, for the wickedness of my people Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now therefore because you have done all these things: and I have spoken to you and you have not hearkened to me; and I have called you and you have not answered;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I therefore will do to this house which is called by my name, and in which you have placed your confidence; and to this place which I gave to you and your fathers; as I did to Selo.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And I will drive you from my presence, as I have driven out your brethren, the whole seed of Ephraim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And as for thee, pray not thou for this people; nor supplicate for compassion to be shewn them: neither pray nor intercede with me for them; for I will not listen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Dost thou not see what they are doing in the cities of Juda and in the streets of Jerusalem?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Their sons are collecting wood; and their fathers are kindling a fire: and their wives are kneading dough to make cakes for the host of heaven: and they have poured out libations to strange gods, to vex me. Do they vex me? Saith the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>do they not vex themselves; that their faces may be covered with shame?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold my anger and my fury is poured upon this place and on these men; and on the cattle and on every tree of their field and on all the products of the ground, and it shall burn and shall not be quenched.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Collect your whole burnt offerings with your sacrifices and eat flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Because I did not speak to your fathers nor give them a charge, on the day when I brought them up out of the land of Egypt, concerning the whole burnt offerings and sacrifices;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>but only gave them this charge saying, Hearken to my voice and I will be your God and you shall be my people; and walk in all my ways which I command you that it may be well with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But they hearkened not to me nor inclined their ear; but walked in the devices of their own wicked heart, and went backward and not forward</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>from the day their fathers came out of the land of Egypt to this day: though I sent to you all my servants the prophets; daily and early though I sent them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>yet they hearkened not to me nor inclined their ears; nay they hardened their necks more than their fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>therefore thou shalt deliver to them this message.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>This is the nation which hearkened not to the voice of the Lord, nor received instruction: faithfulness is gone from their mouth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>shave thy head and throw away the hair, and take up with thy lips a song of lamentation, for the Lord hath rejected and cast off the generation which hath done these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Because the children of Juda have done evil in my sight, saith the Lord, have set up their abominations in the house called by my name, to pollute it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and have built up the altar of Tophet which is in the valley of the son of Ennom, to burn their sons and their daughters with fire; a thing which I never commanded them and which never entered my mind;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>therefore, behold days are coming saith the Lord, when they shall no more say, The altar of Tophet, and the valley of the son of Ennom, but, The valley of them who were slain. For they shall bury in Tophet for want of room.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the carcasses of this people shall be for food for the birds of the air and the wild beasts of the earth; and there shall be none to scare them away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And I will cause to cease from the cities of Juda and from the streets of Jerusalem, the voice of joy and the voice of gladness; the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride; for the whole land shall be a desolation.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time saith the Lord, they shall carry out the bones of the kings of Juda, and the bones of his chiefs, and the bones of the priests, and the bones of the prophets, and the bones of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, out of their graves;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and expose them to the sun and moon and to all the stars, and to all the host of heaven which they loved and served, and after which they went and to which they were attached, and to which they bowed down. They shall not be lamented nor buried; but shall be for a spectacle, on the face of the earth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>(because they chose death rather than life) even to all the residue left of that generation, in every place whither I shall drive them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Doth not he who falleth rise again? Or doth not he who turneth aside, return back?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Why then hath this my people shamefully turned aside, and persisted in their error and refused to return?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Hearken now and hear! Will they not speak thus, There is not a man who repenteth of his wickedness, saying, What have I done? He who was running stop'd in his course like a horse tired with whinnying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The stork in the heaven knoweth her season; so doth the dove and the swallow of the field; the ostriches observed the time of their coming; but my people do not know the judgments of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>How can you say, We are wise and the law of the Lord is with us. In vain was it made; the scribes had a lying pen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Are the wise ashamed? They are indeed dismayed and taken. Because they rejected the law of the Lord; therefore be their wisdom what it may,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I will give their wives to others and their fields to them who will take possession, that they may gather the products thereof, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>There is not a cluster on the vine nor is there a fig on the fig trees, even the leaves are fallen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Why sit we still? Assemble and let us go into the fortified cities; and let us be cast oft' there; since God hath cast us off. He hath indeed given us water of gall to drink because we have sinned against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>We assembled for peace; but there is no good; for a time of healing and behold trouble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>From Dan we can hear the sound of the snorting of his horses; with the neighing of his cavalry the whole earth is shaken. And on he will come and devour the land and the fulness thereof, the cities and them who dwell therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For behold I am sending against you deadly serpents, which cannot be charmed, and they will bite you</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>with incurable wounds, which shall pain your throbbing heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Hark! a sound of the cry of the daughter of my people from a distant land! Is not the Lord in Sion? Is he not king there? Because they provoked me to anger with their graven images and with strange vanities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The summer is past; the harvest is over and we are not saved,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>at the destruction of the daughter of my people I was whelmed in darkness: in distress I was seized with pangs like those of a woman in travail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Is there no balm in Gilead? Is there no physician there? Why is not healing come for the daughter of my people. (The chorus, the inhabitants of the country. Jehovah, The prophet.)</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>O that my head were water! and mine eyes a fountain of tears! That I might weep day and night for this people of mine; for the slain of the daughter of my people!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>O that I had a remote lodging in the wilderness, that I might leave my people and go away from them! Because they are all adulterers, an assembly of treacherous men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and have bent their tongue like a bow; lying and infidelity prevailed in the land; because they have proceeded from evils to evils, and have not known me, saith the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>be upon your guard every man against his neighbour, and in your own brothers place no confidence; for every brother will supplant, and every friend walk deceitfully;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>every one will treat his friend with contempt. They cannot speak truth; their tongue hath learned to speak lies. They have done injustice, and have not stopped to rectify it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>There is usury upon usury, deceit upon deceit; they refused to know me, saith the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold I will melt them and try them. What else can I do on account of the wickedness of the daughter of my people?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Their tongue is a wounding dart: the words of their mouth are deceitful. To his neighbour one speaketh peace; when inwardly he harboureth enmity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Shall I not visit for these things, saith the Lord; and on such a nation shall not my soul be avenged?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Take ye up a lamentation for the mountains, and for the paths of the wilderness, a song of woe; for such is the desolation that there are no men, nor is there a sound of existence heard from birds of the air, nor from cattle. They were confounded. They are fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I will indeed deliver up Jerusalem to captivity and make it a den for jackals; and the cities of Juda an uninhabitable desolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whoever is a wise man, let him understand this; and let him, who hath a word from the mouth of the Lord, declare to you, for what cause the land is destroyed; burned up like a desert, so as not to be travelled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Again the Lord said to me, Because they have forsaken my law which I set before them and have not hearkened to my voice;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but have gone after the pleasures of their own wicked heart, and after the idols which their fathers taught them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord the God of Israel, behold I will feed them with Wormwood, and give them the water of gall to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And I will scatter them among the nations, which neither they nor their fathers have known, and send a sword after them till they are consumed by it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Call the mourning women and let them come; send for the well instructed and let them utter a plaintive sound</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and take up a mournful lamentation for you: and let your eyes collect tears, and your eye lids gush out water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because a sound of wailing is heard in Sion; Oh how wretched we are! how greatly confounded because we have left our land, and abandoned our habitations:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>hear I beseech you, women! a word of God: and let your ears receive the words of his mouth: and teach your daughters a song of Woe; and every woman, her neighbour the mournful dirge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For death is gone up through your windows: it is come into your land, to destroy infants at home and young men in the streets:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the carcasses of the men shall be for a spectacle on the open field throughout your land, like grass after a mower and there will be none to gather.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Let not the wise man boast of his wisdom: nor the mighty man boast of his strength; neither let the rich man boast of his riches:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>but let him who boasteth, boast of this only, that he understandeth and knoweth, that I am the Lord, who exercise mercy and judgment and justice on the earth: that in these things is my delight, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Behold days are coming, saith the Lord, when I will visit upon all the uncircumcised, their uncircumcisions</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Upon Egypt, and upon Idumea, and upon Edom, and upon the Ammonites, and upon the Moabites, and upon all that have their foreheads shaven; namely them who dwell in the wilderness. Because all the nations are uncircumcised in flesh, and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in their hearts;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hear the word of the Lord which he hath spoken for you house of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Learn not the ways of the nations, and at the signs of heaven be not dismayed, because they are terrified at these appearances,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>because the ordinances of the nations are vain. Timber is cut from the forest:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>a carpenter's work and a molten image are adorned with silver and gold. Having fastened them with mallets and nails they will place them and they are not to be moved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They are silver which can be turned in a lathe; they cannot walk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They are silver which can be formed into plates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>From Tharsis will come the gold of Mophaz, and the hand of men skilled in casting gold. They are all the workmanship of artists. With blue and purple raiment they are to be clothed:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They must be taken up and carried; for they cannot walk. Fear them not for they can do you no harm, and there is no good in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thus shall you say to them. Let the gods, which have not made heaven and earth, perish from the earth and from under heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>It is the Lord who made the earth by his power, who established the world by his wisdom: and by his understanding spread out the heaven,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and the multitude of waters in heaven: when he brought up clouds from the extremity of the earth; he made the lightning for rain, and brought light forth from his treasuries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Every man on account of knowledge became foolish. Every melter of gold was put to shame for his graven images, because he cast falsities and there is no breath in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>These ridiculous works are vain; in the time of their visitation they shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Unlike to these is the portion of Jacob: for he who formed all things is his inheritance. His name is, The Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He hath collected from abroad the substance of thee, dwelling in chosen places.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, Behold I am about to subvert with affliction the inhabitants of this land, that the stroke may reach thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Alas for thine affliction! the stroke given thee is painful. Upon this I said, This is a wounding thee indeed! it hath sunk deep in thee!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>thy tent is in a miserable state. It is ruined. And all thy curtains are torn to pieces. My children and my flocks are no more. There is not a trace of my tent left; no remains of my curtains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Because the shepherds were foolish and sought not the Lord, therefore the whole flock was thoughtless and they are scattered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A noisy sound! Hark! it is coming. And a great commotion from the land of the north, to make the cities of Juda a desolation and a haunt of ostriches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I know, Lord, that the way of man is not in himself, nor can a man who travelleth ensure to himself a prosperous journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Correct us, O Lord, but with judgment and not with wrath, that thou mayst not make us few in number.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Pour out thy wrath on the nations that knew thee not, and on the families which have not invoked thy name. Because they have devoured Jacob and consumed him, and have made his pasture a desolation.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came to Jeremias from the Lord, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear ye the words of this covenant: and thou shalt speak to the men of Juda, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and say to them, Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel, Cursed is the man who will not hearken to the words of that covenant</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>which I enjoined on your fathers, at the time when I brought them out of the land of Egypt; out of the iron furnace saying, Hearken to my voice, and do all that I command you: and you shall be my people, and I will be your God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>that I may perform the oath which I sware to your fathers to give them a land flowing with milk and honey, as at this day. Thereupon I answered and said, So be it, O Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me, Read these words in the cities of Juda and in the streets of Jerusalem, and say, Hear the words of this covenant and do them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when they did not:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>the Lord said to me, A conspiracy is found among the men of Juda and among the inhabitants of Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They have turned back to the iniquities of their fathers, who refused to hearken to my words. And lo they are going after strange gods to serve them. Both the house of Israel and the house of Juda have broken my covenant which I made with their fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold I am bringing upon this people evils, from which they shall not be able to escape. And when they cry to me I will not hearken to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let the cities of Juda and the inhabitants of Jerusalem go and cry to the gods, to which they burn incense; but which cannot save them in the time of their adversity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Since according to the number of thy cities were thy gods, O Juda; and according to the number of the streets of Jerusalem, you erected altars to burn incense to Baal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>therefore pray not thou for this people, nor intercede for them with supplication and prayer; for I will not hearken when they call on me in the time of their distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>What! my beloved hath committed abomination in my very house! will prayers and holy meats remove from thee thy wickedness? or by means of these shalt thou escape?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The Lord called thy name The beautiful shady olive. At the sound of lopping it, a fire was kindled against it. Great is the affliction coming upon thee. Its branches are destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The Lord who planted thee hath denounced evils against thee, for the wickedness of the house of Israel and the house of Juda, for they have brought this upon themselves by burning incense to Baal to provoke me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Inform me, Lord, and let me know! Then I saw their devices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>As for me I like a lamb led to slaughter did not know. Against me they had formed a wicked design, saying, Come, let us put poison in his bread, and cut him off from the land of the living; and let his name be mentioned no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Lord, who judgest righteously, trying reins and hearts! let me see thy vengeance on them, for to thee I have laid open my cause.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>On this account, thus saith the Lord to the men of Anathoth, who seek my life, who say thou shalt not prophesy in the name of the Lord; if thou dost; thou shalt die by our hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Behold I will punish them. Their young men shall die by the sword. And their sons and their daughters shall die by famine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And there shall not be a remnant of them left; for I will bring evils on the inhabitants of Anathoth in the year of their visitation.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Righteous as thou art, O Lord, can I defend a cause against thee? but let me speak to thee in respect to judgments. Why is the way of wicked men prosperous? Why are they happy who have been all guilty of perfidy?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thou hast planted them and they have taken root, they have generated and produced fruit. Thou art near in their mouth, but far from their reins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But thou, Lord, knowest me. Thou hast tried my heart before thee. Prepare them for the day of their slaughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>How long shall the land mourn, and all the grass of the field be withered, for the wickedness of them who dwell therein? The cattle and fowls are vanished; because they said, God will not regard our ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thy feet run and fail thee: what preparation canst thou make, for horses? In thy land of peace hast thou been secure? how wilt thou act at the swelling of Jordan?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>since even thy brethren and the house of thy father have dealt perfidiously with thee; when they have raised the cry of war; have assembled in pursuit of thee, wilt thou trust them, because they speak thee fair?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>I have forsaken my house, I have abandoned my heritage, I have given the beloved of my soul into the hands of her enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>My heritage became to me like a lion in a forest; against me it roared; therefore I hated it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Is not this heritage of mine the den of a hyena? to me indeed it is the den around her. Go, collect all the beasts of the field and let them come and devour it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Many shepherds have destroyed my vineyard, they have defiled my portion, they have made my beloved portion a trackless desert:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>it is given up to total destruction. On my account the whole land is utterly desolated: because there is not a man who layeth this to heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>against every outlet by the wilderness destroyers are come: because the sword of the Lord devoureth from one end of the land to the other; there is no peace for any flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Sow wheat and reap brambles. Their portions shall not profit them. Be ashamed of your boasting, of reproaches against the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, respecting all those malignant neighbours, who touch my inheritance which I parcelled out to my people Israel; behold I am about to pluck them out of their land, and I will drive out Juda from among them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but after I have driven them out, I will return and have compassion on them, and settle them every one in his inheritance even every one in his own land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And it shall come to pass, if they will diligently learn the way of my people to swear by my name, As the Lord liveth; as they taught my people to swear by Baal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>they shall be established among my people: but if they will not return; I will assuredly root out that nation with ruin and destruction.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Go and get thee a linen girdle and gird it about thy loins; but it must not be washed with water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when I had procured the girdle according to the word of the Lord and had girded it about my loins,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>a word of the Lord came to me saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Take the girdle which is about thy loins, and arise and go to the Euphrates and hide it there in the hole of the rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So I went and hid it by the Euphrates as the Lord commanded me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And after many days the Lord said to me, Arise and go to the Euphrates and take thence the girdle, which I commanded thee to hide there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So I went to the river Euphrates and digged and took the girdle out of the place where I had buried it; and behold it was rotten and good for nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then a word of the Lord came to me saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, So will I mar the haughtiness of Juda, and the haughtiness of Jerusalem, that great haughtiness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>them who refuse to hearken to my words, and have gone after strange gods to serve them and worship them: and they shall be like this girdle which is good for nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For, as the girdle is tightly bound around the loins of its owner, so did I bind to myself the house of Israel and the whole house of Juda; that they might be for me a renowned people, and for a boast and for a glory. But they have not hearkened to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore thou shalt say to this people, Every leathern bottle is to be filled with wine. And if they say to thee, Do we not know very well that every leathern bottle is to be filled with wine?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then thou shalt say to them, Thus saith the Lord: Behold I will fill the inhabitants of this land, both their kings who are seated' as sons of David on their thrones, and the priests and the prophets, even Juda and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, with drunkenness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And I will scatter them, their heads of families and their brethren, both fathers and their sons at the same time. I will not have compassion, saith the Lord, nor will I spare, nor pity them for their destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Hearken and give ear and be not elated; for the Lord hath spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Give glory to the Lord your God, before the darkness cometh, and before your feet stumble on the dark mountains; when you will wait for light; and the shadow of death will be there; and they shall be placed in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But if you will not hearken, your soul shall weep in secret for your haughtiness; and tears shall gush from your eyes; because the flock of the Lord is destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Say to the king and the rulers: Humble yourselves and sit on the ground; for from your head is taken your crown of glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The cities of the south shall be shut up and there shall be none to open. Juda is removed; they have made a complete removal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Raise thine eyes, O Jerusalem, and see them who are coming from the north! Where is the flock that was given thee; the flock of thy glory?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>What wilt thou say, when these visit thee, seeing thou thyself hast taught them against thyself lessons for government. Will not pangs seize thee as a woman in travail?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now shouldst thou say in thy heart, Why have such things befallen me? For the greatness of thine iniquity thy back is uncovered, that thy heels may be exposed to view!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Will an Ethiopian change his skin and a leopard her spots? As for you, then, will you who have learned these evils be able to do good?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore I have scattered them like stubble whirled by wind to a desert;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>this, then, shall be thy lot and portion for your disobeying me, saith the Lord. As thou hast forgotten Me and trusted in lies;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I therefore will expose thee naked to view that thy shame may be seen; namely, thy adultery and thy neighing and the lewdness of thy whoredom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>On the mounts and in the fields I have seen thine abominations. Alas for thee, Jerusalem, because thou hast not purified thyself to follow Me. How much longer will it be before thou wilt?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>There came also to Jeremias a word of the Lord concerning the drought.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Judea mourned and her gates were deserted: and darkness overspread the land and the cry of Jerusalem ascended.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>When her nobles sent their underlings for water; they went to the wells and found no water and returned with their vessels empty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>A stop was put to the works of the field because there was no rain. The husbandmen were confounded; they covered their heads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The hinds calved in the field and left their young because there was not a green plant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The wild asses stood in the forests and snuffed up the wind: their eyes failed because there was no grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Our sins have risen up against us. O Lord, deal with us for Thine own sake: for our sins are many in Thy sight; for we have sinned against Thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thou, O Lord, art the hope of Israel, and savest in time of troubles. Why art Thou become as a stranger in the land; as a traveller turning aside for a lodging?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Wilt Thou be lie a man asleep or like a head of a family who cannot save? as Thou, O Lord, art among us and we are called by Thy name, O! do not forget us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord to this people: They have loved to wander and did not refrain, therefore God hath not prospered their ways, He will now remember their iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me, Pray not for the prosperity of this people;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>for though they fast I will not hear their prayer; and though they offer whole burnt offerings and sacrifices, I will not accept them. For with sword, and with famine, and with pestilence, I will utterly consume them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thereupon I said, O self-existent Lord! Behold their prophets prophesy and say, You shall not see the sword; nor shall there be famine among you. For I will give truth and peace in this land and in this very place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me: These prophets prophesy falsehood in My name; I did not send them, nor command them, nor did I speak to them. Because they prophesy to you lying visions and divinations, and auguries, and the devices of their own hearts;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord concerning those prophets: Those who prophesy falsehoods in My name, and who say (though I did not send them), There shall be no sword nor famine in this land, they shall die a direful death; and by famine these prophets shall be consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the people to whom they prophesy, with their wives and their sons and their daughters, shall, by reason of the sword and the famine, be cast out in the streets of Jerusalem; and there shall be none to bury them, when I pour out these evils on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore thou shalt deliver to them this word: Collect tears for your eyes day and night and let them not fail; for with a bruise the daughter of My people is bruised, and the wound is exceedingly painful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If I go out into the field, behold the slain of the sword! and if I go into the city; behold the distress of famine! Seeing priest and prophet are gone to a land which they knew not:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>hast Thou utterly rejected Juda and is Thy soul alienated from Sion? Why hast Thou smitten us, and there is no cure for us? We waited for peace, and there was no good; for a time of healing, and behold trouble!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>We acknowledge, O Lord, our sins and the iniquities of our fathers; that we have sinned against Thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>O be appeased for Thy name's sake. Destroy not the throne of Thy glory; remember, O dissolve not Thy covenant with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Is there any among the idols of the nations who can give rain? and if the heaven shed its abundance, art Thou not He who causeth it. Therefore we will wait on Thee, O Lord, for Thou hast done all these things</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me, Though Moses and Samuel stood before Me, My soul is not towards them. Send away this people and let them go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And if they say to thee, Whither shall we go? then thou shalt say to them, Thus saith the Lord, such as are for pestilence, to pestilence, and such as are for the sword, to the sword; and such as are for famine, to famine; and such as are for captivity, to captivity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For I will send against them four kinds of avengers, saith the Lord, the sword to slay; and the dogs to tear; and the wild beasts of the earth, and the birds of the air to devour and destroy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And I will deliver them up to distress in all the kingdoms of the earth, on account of Manasses son of Ezekias king of Juda-for all that he did in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who will pity thee, Jerusalem? or who will bemoan thee? or who will turn aside to inquire after thy welfare?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thou hast turned thy back on Me, saith the Lord: backwards thou shalt go. And I will stretch forth My hand and destroy thee. I will no longer bear with them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>but utterly disperse them. In the gates of My people they are bereaved of children; My people are destroyed because of their wickedness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Their widows are multiplied above the sand of the sea. Against a mother I have brought soldiers-misery at noon-day. Upon her I have cast suddenly terror and consternation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>She who was the mother of seven is childless; her soul is afflicted, the sun set upon her while it is yet mid-day; she is ashamed and confounded: the rest of them I will deliver up to the sword before their enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Woe is me, O my mother, what sort of a person hast thou bore me! a man of strife and contending with all this land! I have neither lent on usury: nor hath any one lent to me; yet my strength is spent among them who curse me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Be it so; O Lord, while they enjoy prosperity. Did I not stand by thee, in the time of their calamities and in the time of their affliction, for good with the enemy?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Shall the sword be felt and thy strength be a coat of mail?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thy treasures indeed I will give for a spoil in all thy borders, as a ransom for all thy sins;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and I will make thee a slave to thine enemies around in the land which thou hast not known. For afire is kindled from My wrath and against you it shall blaze.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>O Lord, remember me and visit me and save me from them, who are persecuting me past forbearance. Consider how I have for Thy sake borne reproach from them who despise my words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Bring them to an end. But let Thy word be to me the joy and rejoicing of my heart. Because I am called by Thy name, O Lord Almighty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I did not sit in the council of those scorners; but was struck with awe because of Thy hand. I sat alone because I was full of bitterness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Why do they who grieve me prevail over me? My wound is deep, how can I be healed? It is indeed become to me like deceitful water which cannot be trusted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord: If thou wilt return I will reinstate thee; and in My presence thou shalt stand. And if thou wilt lead out the precious from the vile, thou shalt be as My mouth; and they shall turn to thee and thou shalt not turn to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And I will make thee to this people like a strong wall of brass: though they fight against thee, they shall not prevail over thee; for am with thee to save thee and rescue thee out of the hand of the wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And I will redeem thee out of the hand of pestilent men.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But thou must not take a wife, saith the Lord God of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>nor shall a son or a daughter be born to thee in this place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord concerning the sons and concerning the daughters born in this place, and concerning the mothers who bore them, and concerning their fathers who begot them in this land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>by a direful death they shall die; they shall not be lamented, nor shall they be buried; they shall be for a spectacle on the face of the earth; they shall be for the wild beasts of the earth, and the birds of the air. By the sword they shall fall, and by famine they shall be consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord: Join not in their funeral entertainments; go not to make lamentation nor bewail them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Since I have taken away My peace from this people, no lamentation shall be made for them; nor shall any cut themselves nor be shaved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>There shall neither be bread broken in their mourning, to comfort them for the dead; nor shall a cup of consolation be given to any one for his father or mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Into a house of feasting thou shalt not enter, to sit with them to eat and to drink:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>for thus saith the Lord the God of Israel: Behold I am about to remove out of this place, before your eyes and in these your days, the sound of joy and the sound of mirth, the voice of the bride groom and the voice of the bride.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now when thou hast proclaimed to this people all these words and they say to thee, Why hath the Lord denounced against us all these evils? What is our iniquity? And what is our sin which we have committed against the Lord our God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then thou shalt say to them, Because your fathers have forsaken Me, saith the Lord, and have run after strange gods and served them and worshipped them, and have forsaken Me and have not kept My law;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and you have done evil worse than your fathers; and lo! you walk every one after the desires of your wicked heart, that you may not hearken to Me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>therefore I will hurl you out of this land, into a land which neither your nor your fathers knew; and you shall there serve strange gods which will shew you no mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, when they shall no more say, 'As the Lord liveth Who brought up the Israelites out of the land of Egypt':</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but, 'as the Lord liveth, Who brought up the house of Israel from the north, and from all the countries to which they were driven'; for I will bring them again to their land which I gave to their fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Behold I will send many fishers, saith the Lord, and they shall fish them: and after that I will send many hunters and they shall hunt them, on every mountain and every hill, and out of the holes of the rocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Because Mine eyes are on all their ways, and their iniquities are not hid from Mine eyes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>therefore I will doubly requite them for their wickedness and their sins-for their having defiled My land with the carcasses of their abominations, and for their acts of iniquity with which they have caused My heritage to transgress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>O Lord, Thou art my strength and my help, and my refuge in days of affliction. To Thee nations will come from the extremity of the earth and say, What lying idols did our fathers possess! there is no advantage in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>If a man make gods for himself, they are indeed no gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For this purpose, behold! I will at that time manifest My hand to them and make known to them My power, and they shall know that My name is The Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Cursed is the man whose hope is on man; who shall fix the flesh of his arm on him, and whose heart hath departed from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He shall be like the wild myrtle in the desert. He shall not see when good cometh; but shall dwell in parched places and in a desert-in a salt land which is uninhabited.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But blessed is the man who hath trusted in the Lord; and whose hope is the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He will be like a thriving tree near waters which shall shoot out its roots in a moist soil. It will not be afraid when heat cometh, though its stock be loaded with branches. In a year of drought it will not be afraid, nor will it fail to bear fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The heart is deep beyond all things; so also is a man, who then can know Him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I the Lord search hearts and try reins, to give to everyone according to his ways, and according to the fruit of his devices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>A partridge whistled and collected young which it did not bring forth, increasing its wealth but not with judgment; in the midst of its days they will leave it, and at its end it will be a fool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Our sanctuary is an exalted throne of glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou, O Lord art the hope of Israel. Let all who forsake Thee be ashamed; let them who have apostatised be enrolled in the dust, because they have forsaken the Lord the fountain of lie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Heal me, O Lord, and I shall be healed. Save me, and I shall be saved. Because Thou art my boast, behold they say to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Where is the word of the Lord? Let it come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>As for me, I was not weary of following Thee, nor did I desire the day of a man: Thou knowest. The words which pass my lips are before Thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>be not estranged from me. Spare me in an evil day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Let my persecutors be ashamed; but let me not be shamed. Let them be dismayed; but let not me be dismayed. Bring upon them an evil day. Crush them with a double crush.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord: Go and stand in the gates of the children of thy people at which the kings of Juda come in and at which they go out, even at all the gates of Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and thou shalt say to them, Hear the word of the Lord, O kings of Juda and all Juda and all Jerusalem, who enter in by these gates!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Take heed to yourselves and carry no burdens on the sabbath day; nor go out of the gates of Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Neither carry burdens out of your houses on the sabbath day nor do any work. Hallow the sabbath day as I commanded your fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Though they did not hearken, though they did not incline their ear, but stiffened their necks more than their fathers, that they might not hearken to Me nor receive instruction;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>yet if you will hearken to Me, saith the Lord, and not carry burdens through the gates of this city on the sabbath day, but hallow the sabbath day by doing no work thereon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>there shall enter in at the gates of this city, kings and chiefs seated on the throne of David and riding in chariots and on horses, they and their chiefs, the men of Juda and the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and this city shall be inhabited for the age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And there shall come from the cities of Juda and from around Jerusalem and from the land of Benjamin and from the plain and from the mountain and from the country to the south, people bringing whole burnt offerings and sacrifices and incense and fine flour and frankincense; bringing offerings of thanksgivings to the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But if you will not hearken to me to hallow the sabbath day, so as not to carry burdens nor come in at the gates of Jerusalem on the sabbath day, I will kindle a fire in the gates thereof and it shall consume the streets of Jerusalem and shall not be quenched</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came to Jeremias from the Lord, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Arise and go down to the house of the potter and there thou shalt hear my words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So I went down to the house of the potter; and behold he was making a piece of work on stones;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and the vessel, which he was fashioning with his hands, fell, whereupon he again made it a vessel of another sort as it seemed good to him to make it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then a word of the Lord came to me saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Cannot I do with you, house of Israel, as this potter? Behold you are in my hands like the clay of the potter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When I speak to a nation or kingdom; that I will remove and destroy them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>if that nation turn from all their evils, I will relent in respect to the evils which I was resolving to bring on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when I speak to a nation and kingdom that I will build up and replant:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If they do evil in my sight so as not to hearken to my voice, I indeed will alter my mind in respect to the good things which I spoke of doing for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now I have said to the men of Juda and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, Behold I am preparing evils against you and forming against you a determination; turn therefore every one from his evil way and make better things the objects of your pursuit:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>but they said, We will act like men. We will follow our own courses; and what every one findeth agreeable to his own wicked heart that we will do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Inquire among the nations. Who hath heard of such horrible things as the virgin of Israel hath sedulously done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Will crags forsake a rock or snow quit Libanus? Or water turn aside when furiously driven by wind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because my people have forgotten me; have burned incense to vanity; they will therefore break down the everlasting barriers in their ways that they may walk in paths having no road for travelling;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>that they may make the land a desolation; an everlasting object of pity. All that pass through it shall be astonished and shake their head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Like a burning wind I will scatter them before their enemies. I will shew them the day of their destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Upon this they said, Come let us settle on account with Jeremias. Because law shall not perish from the priest, nor counsel from the wise, nor a word from the prophet, Come and that we may smite him with the tongue, let us hear all his words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Hear me, Lord, and hearken to my justification.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Shall evils be returned for good offices? Because they contrived designs against my life and concealed the punishment they intended for me. Remember how I stood before thee to intercede for them; to turn away thy wrath from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For this cause deliver up their sons to famine and give them up in multitudes to the sword. Let their wives become childless and widows; and the husbands be cut off by pestilence and their young men fall by the sword in battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Let a scream be heard in their houses. Thou wilt bring robbers suddenly on them because they contrived a speech to entrap me and concealed the snares they had set for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thou indeed, Lord, knewest all their designs against me to put me to death. Absolve them not from their wickedness, nor blot out their sins from before thee. Let their weakness be before thee. Deal with them in the time of thy wrath.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Lord said to me, Go and get a pitcher of earthen ware and thou shalt take out some of the elders of the people and of the priests</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and go out to the common grave yard which is at the entrance of the gate Charseith and read there all these words which I shall speak to thee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and thou shalt say to them, Hear the word of the Lord, ye kings of Juda and ye men of Juda and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem, and ye who enter in at these gates. Thus saith the Lord, the God of Israel, Behold I am bringing evils upon this place, so that the ears of every one who heareth them shall tingle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because they have forsaken me and profaned this place; and have burned incense in it to strange gods, which neither they nor their fathers knew; and the kings of Juda have filled this place with the blood of innocents;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and have built high places to Baal to burn their sons with fire, things which I never commanded, and which never came into my mind;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, When this place shall no more be called, The end of hope, and The grave yard of the sons of Ennom; but The grave yard of slaughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For I will slaughter the council of Juda and the council of Jerusalem in this place; And cause them to fall by the sword before their enemies, and by the hands of them who seek their lives. And I will give their carcasses to be meat for the birds of the air and the wild beasts of the earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and make this city a desolation and an object of pity. Every one who passeth by it shall be sad and express the sound of pity for the stroke which it hath received.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They shall indeed eat the flesh of their sons and the flesh of their daughters; and they shall eat, every one, the flesh of his neighbour, in the blockade and siege with which their enemies shall besiege them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then thou shalt break the pitcher before the eyes of the men who went out with thee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and say, Thus saith the Lord, So will I break this people and this city: as this earthen pitcher is broken and cannot be mended,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>so will I do, saith the Lord, to this place and to the inhabitants thereof, that this city may be dashed down like that hopeless vessel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the houses of the kings of Juda shall be like this hopeless place, because of their impurities in all the houses on the tops of which they burned incense to all the host of heaven and poured out libations to strange gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now when Jeremias returned from the grave yard whither the Lord had sent him to prophesy, he stood up in the court of the house of the Lord and said to all the people, Thus saith the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Behold I am bringing upon this city and upon all the cities belonging to it and upon all the villages thereof all the evils which I have denounced against it, because they have hardened their necks so as not to hearken to my commandments.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Whereupon Paschor son of Emmer, the priest who was appointed ruler of the house of the Lord, when he heard Jeremias prophesying these words,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>smote him and committed him to the prison which was in the upper story of the gate to the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when Paschor took Jeremias out of prison, Jeremias said to him, He hath not called thy name Paschor, but Exile.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, Behold I will send thee with all thy friends into exile; and they shall fall by the sword of their enemies and thine eyes shall see it. I will deliver thee and all Juda into the hands of the king of Babylon; and they shall be exiled and slain with swords.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I will deliver all the strength of this city and all the labours thereof and all the treasures of the king of Juda into the hands of his enemies and they shall carry them to Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And thou and all that dwell in thy house shall go into captivity and thou shalt die in Babylon and be buried there, thou and all thy friends to whom thou hast prophesied falsehoods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Hast thou, Lord deceived me? and have I been deceived? Thou hast taken hold and hast prevailed. I am become a subject of laughter: all the day long I endure reproach.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Because for my bitter word I am to be derided, shall I appeal to a breach of covenant and misery? because the word of the Lord became a reproach to me; a subject of mockery all the day long;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>therefore I said, I will not name the name of the Lord; I will not speak any more in his name. But there was kindled as it were a burning fire in my bones and I became dejected and cannot bear it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Because I heard the whisper of many collected from all around saying, Join in conspiracy and let us all conspire against him; ye men who are his friends watch his thoughts; if he can be deceived, we shall then prevail over him and take our revenge on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But the Lord was with me as a mighty warrior, therefore they persecuted and could not contrive. They were put to great confusion. Because they had not a due sense of their infamous practices, which are never to be forgotten;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Lord, who provest righteous things, who knowest reins and hearts I might have seen thy vengeance on them. For to thee I laid open my cause.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Sing to the Lord; sing praises to him, because he hath rescued the soul of the needy out of the hand of evil doers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Let the day be cursed in which I was born; the day in which my mother bore me; Let it not be mentioned with expressions of joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Let the man be cursed who brought tidings to my father saying, A male child is borne to thee making him glad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let that man be like the cities which the Lord overthrew in wrath and relented not, Let him hear a scream in the morning and the cry of Woe at noon-day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>because he did not kill me in the womb, and my mother was not made my grave, and her womb always with child.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>To what purpose this? I came forth from the womb to see labours and sorrows, and my days have been spent in shame.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came from the Lord to Jeremias when king Sedekias sent to him Paschor son of Melchias, and Sophonias son of Basaias the priest saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Inquire of the Lord concerning us for the king of Babylon is come against us. Will the Lord do according to all his wonderous works that he may depart from us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thereupon Jeremias said to them, Thus shall you say to Sedekias king of Juda,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Behold I turn back the weapons of war with which you fight against the Chaldeans who have besieged you without the wall. And I will bring them into this city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I myself indeed will fight against you with an outstretched hand and a strong arm, with wrath and with great indignation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I will smite all the inhabitants of this city, both men and beasts with a great pestilence, and they shall die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And after that, saith the Lord, I will deliver Sedekias king of Juda and his servants and the people left in this city from the pestilence and from the famine and from the sword, into the hands of their enemies who seek their lives, and they shall smite them with the edge of the sword. I will not spare them, nor will I have compassion on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And to this people thou shalt say, Thus saith the Lord, Behold I have set before you the way of life and the way of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He who abideth in this city, shall die by the sword and famine, but he who goeth out to the Chaldeans who have besieged you, he shall live. His life shall be given him for a spoil and he shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For I have set my face against this city for evils and not for good. It shall be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon and he will burn it with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>With respect to the house of the king of Juda, hear a word of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>O house of David. Thus saith the Lord, Administer judgment in the morning and relieve and deliver the spoiled out of the hand of him who wrongeth him, that my wrath may not be kindled like a fire and blaze so that none can quench it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Behold I am against thee who inhabitest the vale of Sor; that plain; Them who say who can terrify us? Or who can come into our habitation?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And I will kindle a fire in its forests and it shall devour all things.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Go down to the house of the king of Juda and thou shalt speak there this word</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and say, Hear a word of the Lord, king of Juda, who art seated on the throne of David, thou and thy household and thy people and they who enter in at these gates!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Execute judgment and justice and deliver the spoiled out of the hand of him who wrongeth him; and over the stranger and the orphan and the widow tyrannise not; nor be guilty of impiety; nor shed innocent blood in this place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For if you faithfully execute this charge, there shall enter in at the gates of this house, kings seated on the throne of David and riding in chariots and on horses, they and their servants and their people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But if you will not perform these things, by myself I have sworn, saith the Lord, This house shall be a desolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord against the house of the king of Juda, though thou wert to me as Galaad, as the top of Libanus, I will make thee a7 desolation, cities uninhabitable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>I will indeed bring against thee a destroyer, a man with his axe; and they shall cut down thy choice cedars and throw them into the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when nations shall pass by this city, they will say, every one to his neighbour, Why hath the Lord dealt thus with this great city?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>To which it will be said in reply, Because they forsook the Lord their God and worshipped strange gods and served them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Weep not for him who is dead, nor utter lamentations for him, weep bitterly for him who is going away; for he shall never return, nor see any more his native country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord respecting Sellem son of Josias, who reigned in the room of his father and who is gone from this place; he shall not return hither any more:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>but in the place to which I have transported him, there he shall die and this land he shall see no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>With regard to him who is building himself a house, but not with righteousness, and lofty stories, but not with justice: he useth the service of his neighbour for nothing, and will not pay him his wages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou hast built thyself a well proportioned house, lofty chambers well fitted with windows, and cieled with cedar and painted with vermillion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Is it thy desire to be made king? because thou art instigated by thy father Achaz, are there not feasts? are there not entertainments? better were it for thee to execute judgment and justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They did not take cognisance, they did not administer justice to the lowly, nor decide righteously the cause of the needy, is not this owing to thy not knowing me? saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Behold thine eyes are not good, neither is thy heart; but they are bent upon thine inordinate desires and on the shedding of innocent blood, and on injustice, and on murder; that thou mayst perpetrate these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord respecting Joakim son of Josias, king of Juda, even concerning this man, they shall not utter for him the lamentation Alas Brother? nor shall they bewail him saying, Alas lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He shall be buried with the burial of an ass; being blotted out he shall be cast forth without the gates of Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Ascend Libanus and scream: ascend Basan, and shout. Shout till thy voice reach the sea coast; for all thy lovers are destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I spake to thee respecting thy fall; but thou saidst, I will not listen. This hath been thy way from thy youth, thou hast not hearkened to my voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>All thy shepherds shall be fed with wind; and all thy lovers shall go into captivity; that thou mayst then be ashamed and confounded on the account of them who love thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>inhabitant of Lebanon, who hast thy nest in the cedars, thou shalt groan bitterly when pangs come upon thee like those of a woman in travail:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>as I live saith the Lord though Jechonias may be made a son of Joakim, a king of Juda, a signet on my right hand I will drag thee out thence</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and deliver thee into the hands of them who seek thy life; of them whose countenance thou dreadest; into the hands of the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And I will cast out thee and the mother who brought thee forth, into a land where thou wast not born, and there thou shalt die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Into the land which their souls long for they shall not return.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Jechonias is dishonoured like a vessel which is useless, because he is hurled away and cast into a land which he knew not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>O earth, earth, hear a word of the Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>record the chieftain himself as a man of low rank, exiled by the voice of a herald; for no increase from his seed shall sit on the throne of David, nor any more be chief in Juda.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>HA! the shepherds are destroying and scattering the sheep of their pasture.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord to the shepherds of my people, You have scattered my flock and driven them away and have not watched them; behold I will punish you according to your malignant doings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I will gather the remains of my people in every land whither I have driven them and bring them back to their own pasture and they shall increase and multiply.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And I will raise up shepherds for them who will feed them. And they shall no more be terrified nor affrighted, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, when I will raise up for David a righteous shoot, who shall reign king and understand and execute judgment and justice on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In his days Juda shall be saved and Israel shall dwell securely. And the name which the Lord will give him by the prophets shall be Josedek Lord of righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, When they shall no more say, As the Lord liveth who brought up the house of Israel, out of the land of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but, As the Lord liveth who gathered all the seed of Israel from the land of the north and from all the countries whither he had driven them and reestablished them in their own land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>My heart within me was broken. All my bones quivered. I was like a man sore bruised and like a man staggering with wine, at the presence of the Lord, and at the comeliness of his glory;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>because on account of them the land mourned and the pastures of the wilderness were parched up; because their course was bad and suitably thereto their strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Because priest and prophet are polluted, and in my house I have seen their wickedness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>let their way therefore be slippery and dark, that they may stumble and fall therein. For I will bring evils upon them in the year of their visitation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Among the prophets of Samaria I saw indeed unlawful doings; they prophesied in the name of Baal and led my people Israel astray:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but among the prophets of Jerusalem I saw horrible things; some committing adultery, and some walking in lies, and some strengthening the hands of the multitude, that none might turn from his evil way. To me they are all become like Sodom, and the inhabitants thereof like Gomorra:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold I will feed them with worm wood, and give them the water of gall to drink. Because from the prophets of Jerusalem pollution has gone forth through all the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>thus saith the Lord Almighty, Hearken not to the words of these prophets; for they contrive for themselves a foolish vision: they speak from their own hearts and not from the mouth of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They say to them who reject the word of the Lord, You shall have peace. Even to all who are walking by their own desires, and to every one walking in the error of his own heart they say, Evils shall not come upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For which of them hath stood in the council of the Lord and seen? who hath hearkened and heard his voice?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Behold a tempest from the Lord and wrath like a hurricane is issuing forth: it will come like a whirlwind upon the wicked;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and from the purpose of his heart the wrath of the Lord will not turn away; until it hath executed it; and until he hath established it. In the last of these days they shall perceive this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I did not send these prophets, but they ran of themselves; I did not speak to them, yet they prophesied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now had they stood in the firm belief of me and heard my word, they might have turned my people from their wicked pursuits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I am God when near, saith the Lord; and am I not God when far off?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Can any one hide himself in secret places; and I not see him? Do I not fill the heaven and the earth? saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I have heard what these prophets speak; what they prophesy in my name, saying falsely, I have dreamed a dream.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>How long shall it be in the heart of these prophets, who prophesy lies, that by prophesying the desires of their own hearts;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>they may count upon causing my name to be forgotten, by their dreams which they tell, every one to his neighbour; as their fathers forgot my name by using Baal?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Let the prophet, who hath a dream, tell his dream: and let him, to whom my word cometh, declare it with truth. Why is the chaff added to the wheat?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Is not this the case with my words? saith the Lord. Behold are not my words like fire? saith the Lord; and like a sledge which breaketh a rock?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Therefore behold I am against those prophets, saith the Lord, who steal my words every one from his neighbour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Behold I am against those prophets, who belch forth prophesies of the tongue and drowse their dozy drowsings:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>therefore behold I am against those prophets who prophesy false dreams. Have they not told them and led my people astray by their lies and their errors? As for me, I neither sent them nor commanded them; therefore they cannot in any wise benefit this people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Now if this people or a priest or a prophet should ask, What is the burden of the Lord? Thou shalt say to them, You are that burden and I will cast you off, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>As for the prophet and the priests and the people who say, The burden of the Lord; I will punish that man and his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Thus you shall say every one to his neighbour and every one to his brother, What hath the Lord answered, and, What hath the Lord spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>So mention no more the burden of the Lord: since every man's word shall be his burden.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>But why hath the Lord our God spoken?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For this cause, saith the Lord our God, because you have used this expression, The Burden of the Lord, though I sent to you saying, You shall not say, The Burden of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Therefore behold I will take and dash down you and this city which I gave to you and your fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and I will bring upon you everlasting reproach, and everlasting dishonour which shall not be forgotten.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The Lord shewed me two baskets of figs set before the temple of the Lord, after Nabuchodonosar the king of Babylon had carried away Jechonias son of Joakim king of Juda and the chiefs and the artisans and the prisoners of war and the rich men from Jerusalem and brought them to Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The one was a basket of very fine figs, such as are first ripe; and the other was a basket of very bad figs, so bad that they could not be eaten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the Lord said to me, What seest thou, Jeremias? And I said, Figs. The good figs, very good: and the bad figs, very bad so bad, that they cannot be eaten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then a word of the Lord came to me saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel, Like these good figs so will I acknowledge for good those banished Jews whom I have sent from this place to the land of the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I will fix mine eyes upon them for good and re-establish them in this land for good. And I will build them up and not pull them down: and I will plant them and not root them up:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and I will give them a heart to know me, that I am the Lord: and they shall be my people, and I will be their God; for they will turn to me with their whole heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But like those bad figs which for their badness cannot be eaten, thus saith the Lord, So will I deliver up Zedekias king of Juda and his nobles and the remnant of Jerusalem; them who are left in this land and them who dwell in Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Them indeed I will devote to dispersion in all the kingdoms of the earth; and they shall be for a reproach and for a by-word and for a taunt and a curse in every place whither I shall drive them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And I will send against them famine and pestilence and the sword, until they are utterly consumed from this land which I gave them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came to Jeremias concerning all the people of Juda in the fourth year of Joakim son of Josias king of Juda,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>which he spoke to all the people of Juda and to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>From the thirteenth year of Josias son of Amos king of Juda even to this day, for three and twenty years I have spoken to you rising early and speaking:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and I have sent to you my servants the prophets; rising early and sending them, though you have not hearkened nor inclined your ears;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>saying, Turn ye every one from his evil way, and from your wicked pursuits and you shall dwell in this land, which I gave to you and your fathers from age to age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Go not after strange gods to serve them, and worship them, that you may not provoke me by the works of your hands to bring evils upon you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But you hearkened not to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Since you have not believed my words,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>behold I am sending, and I will take a family from the north and bring them against this land and against the inhabitants thereof and against all the nations around it. And I will lay them waste and make them a desolation and an object of pity and an everlasting reproach.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And I will destroy from among them the sound of joy and the sound of gladness; the voice of the bridegroom, and the voice of the bride; the odour of myrrh and the light of the lamp.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the whole country shall be a desolation. And they shall be slaves among the nations seventy years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when the seventy years are compleated I will execute vengeance on that nation, and make them an everlasting desolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I will indeed bring against that land all these words of mine which I have spoken against it; all the things which are written in this book which Jeremias prophesied against the nations,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>in the manner the Lord, the God of Israel said, Take this cup of wine; this strong wine from my hand, and thou shalt make all the nations, to which I send thee, drink it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And they shall drink and vomit and rave, because of the sword which I send among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So I took the cup out of the hand of the Lord and made all the nations drink to which the Lord sent me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>namely Jerusalem, and the cities of Juda, and the kings of Juda, and his chiefs, to make them a desolation and a waste and an object of pity;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>also Pharao king of Egypt and his servants and his nobles and all his people;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and all the mixed people; and all the kings of the Philistines, (namely Ascalon and Gaza and Akkaron and the remnant of Azotus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and Idumea and Moab and the children of Ammon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the kings of Tyre and the kings of Sidon; and the kings on the border of the sea;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and Daidan and Thaiman and Ros, and all that had their foreheads shaven;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and all the mixed people who dwell in the desert;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and all the kings of Ailam and all the kings of the Persians</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and all the kings north of the sun, far and near, every one adjoining his brother, even all the kingdoms on the face of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And thou shalt say to them, Thus said the Lord Almighty, Drink and be drunk, and you shall vomit, and fall and rise no more because of the sword which I send among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And if they refuse to take the cup out of thy hand to drink, then thou shalt say, Thus saith the Lord, You shall drink it:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>for in the city which is called by my name I am beginning to inflict calamity and with purification you shall not be purified; for I am calling for a sword against all the inhabitants of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Therefore thou shalt prophesy against them all these words and say; The Lord from on high will solemnly pronounce sentence from his sanctuary; he will utter his voice; in his place he will utter a triumphant shout and some like the treaders of grapes will answer. When destruction hath come on the inhabitants of this land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>upon a part of the earth; because the Lord hath a controversy with the nations, he will come to judgment with all flesh; and the wicked shall be given up to the sword, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Behold evils are coming from nation to nation. A mighty tempest is issuing forth from the extremity of the earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and the slain of the Lord shall be in the day of the Lord from one end of the earth to the other. They shall not be buried. They shall be for dung on the face of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Raise the mournful cry, ye shepherds; utter loud moans and lamentations, ye rams of the flock; for the days for your slaughter are accomplished, and ye shall fall like choice rams;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and the shepherds shall have no way to flee, nor the rams of the flock to escape.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Hark! a sound of the shepherds' screaming! and a doleful bleating of the sheep and the rams! For the Lord hath utterly destroyed their pastures</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and because of his fierce anger he will put an end to the remains of peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Like a lion he hath quitted his covert; therefore their land is become a trackless desert by reason of the mighty sword.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the beginning of the reign of Joakim son of Josias, this word came from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Stand in the court of the house of the Lord and thou shalt solemnly pronounce to all the Jews and to all who come to worship in the house of the Lord all the words which I have commanded thee to prophesy to them; keep not back a word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Perhaps they may hearken and turn every one from his evil way, that I may refrain from all the evils which I am resolving to do to them, because of their wicked pursuits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And thou shalt say, Thus saith the Lord, Unless you hearken to me so as to walk by the ordinances which I have set before you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and hearken to the words of my servants the prophets, whom I send to you, whom I, rising early, have sent to you, though you have not hearkened to them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I will make this house like Selo; and this city I will make a curse for all the nations of the whole earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So the priests and the false prophets and all the people heard Jeremias pronouncing these words in the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when Jeremias had done speaking all that the Lord had commanded him to deliver to all the people; the priests and the false prophets and all the people seized him, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou shalt be put to death, because thou hast prophesied in the name of the Lord saying, This house shall be like Selo, and this city shall be desolate, without inhabitants. And all the people were assembled against Jeremias in the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When the chiefs of Juda heard the affair, they went up from the king's house to the house of the Lord and sat down in the vestibule of the new gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the priests and the false prophets addressed the chiefs, and said to all the people, Let sentence of death pass on this man, because he hath prophesied against this city as you have heard with your ears.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whereupon Jeremias addressing the chiefs, spoke to all the people saying, The Lord hath sent me to prophesy against this house and against this city, all the words which you have heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now therefore amend your ways and your doings, and hearken to the voice of the Lord; and the Lord will refrain from all the evils which he hath denounced against you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>As for me, behold I am in your hands. Do with me as seemeth good and best to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But be assured that if you put me to death, you bring innocent blood on yourselves and upon this city and upon the inhabitants thereof. For in truth, the Lord hath sent me to you to speak all these words in your hearing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then the chiefs and all the people said to the priests and the false prophets, This man is not liable to death, for he hath spoken to us in the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And there stood up some principal men of the elders of the land, and said to all the assembly of the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Michaias the Morasthite lived in the days of Ezekias king of Juda, and he said to all the people of Juda, Thus said the Lord, Sion shall be ploughed like a field; and Jerusalem shall be a desolation; and the mountain of this house, a grove of a forest:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but did Ezekias and all Juda put him to death? No. Because they feared the Lord; and because they intreated the favour of the Lord: therefore the Lord refrained from the evils which he had denounced against them. Now as for us, we have committed great evils against our souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now there was a man who prophesied in the name of the Lord, namely Ourias son of Samaias of Kariathiarim; and he prophesied against this land according to all the words of Jeremias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And when king Joakim and all the chiefs heard all his words, and sought to kill him and Ourias heard it, he fled to Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And the king sent men to Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>who fetched him out thence and brought him to the king; and he slew him with the sword and threw him into the common grave yard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But the hand of Achikam son of Saphan was with Jeremias that they should not deliver him up into the hands of the people, nor kill him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, Make thee chains and yokes and put them about thy neck;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and thou shalt send them to the king of Idumea and to the king of Moab and to the king of the Ammonites and to the king of Tyre and to the king of Sidon by the hands of their ambassadors, who are coming to meet those sent to Jerusalem to Sedekias king of Juda:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and thou shalt charge them to say to their masters, Thus said the Lord, the God of Israel, Thus shall you say to your masters,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>As I have made the earth by my great power and by my outstretched arm, I can give it to whom it seemeth good in mine eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I have given this land to Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon to serve him, and the beasts of the field to work for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the nation and the kingdom; all who will not submit their neck to the yoke of the king of Babylon, them I will visit with sword and famine, said the Lord, until they are consumed by his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Therefore hearken not to your false prophets, nor to them who divine or dream for you, nor to your augurers, nor your sorcerers who say, You shall not serve the king of Babylon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for they prophesy lies to you to remove you far from your land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But the nation which shall submit its neck to the yoke of the king of Babylon and work for him, that nation I will leave in its own hand. It laboureth for him and it shall dwell therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So I spoke to Sedekias king of Juda according to all these words, saying, Submit your neck to work for the king of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For these men prophesy falsehoods to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>for I have not sent them, saith the Lord. They indeed prophesy in my name for falsehood to destroy you; therefore you shall be destroyed, both you and your prophets who prophesy to you for unjust falsehood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>To you and to all this people and to the priests I have spoken, saying, Thus said the Lord, Hearken not to the words of those prophets who prophesy to you saying, Behold the vessels of the house of the Lord shall be brought back from Babylon. For they prophesy falsities to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I have not sent them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If they are prophets; if the word of the Lord is in them, let them meet me. For thus saith the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Even the residue of the vessels</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>which the king of Babylon did not take when he carried away Jechonias from Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>shall go to Babylon, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again it came to pass in the fourth year of Sedekias king of Juda, in the fifth month, that Ananias son of Azor, the false prophet from Gabaon spoke to me in the house of the Lord, in the presence of the priests and of all the people, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>yet two years of days</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and I will bring back to this place the vessels of the house of the Lord, and Jechonias and the captives of Juda; for I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thereupon Jeremias said to Ananias in the presence of all the people and in the presence of the priests who were standing in the house of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>May the Lord indeed do so, said Jeremias; may he establish the word which thou hast spoken, by bringing back the vessels of the house of the Lord and all the captives from Babylon to this place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Nevertheless hear ye the word of the Lord, which I speak in your hearing and in the hearing of all the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>There have been prophets of old before me, and before you, who have prophesied of war against many a land and against great kingdoms.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As for the prophet who hath prophesied peace; when his word com eth to pass let the people acknowledge him as a prophet whom the Lord hath indeed sent to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then in the presence of all the people, Ananias took the yokes from the neck of Jeremias and broke them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And Ananias spoke before all the people, saying, Thus said the Lord, So will I break the yoke of the king of Babylon from the necks of all the nations. So Jeremias went his way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And there came a word of the Lord to Jeremias, after Ananias had broken the yokes from his neck, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Go and speak to Ananias and say, Thus said the Lord, Thou hast broken wooden yokes; but instead of them I will make yokes of iron.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, I have put an iron yoke on the neck of all the nations, that they may work for the king of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Jeremias said to Ananias, the Lord hath not sent thee; and thou hast made this people trust in a lie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For this cause thus saith the Lord, Behold I send thee from the face of the earth. This very year thou shalt die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So he died in the seventh month.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now these are the words of the letter which Jeremias sent from Jerusalem to the elders of the captivity and to the priests and to the false prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>After the departure of king Jechonias and of the queen and the chamberlains and of every nobleman and prisoner of war and artificer from Jerusalem I sent to Babylon</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>by the hand of Eleason son of Saphan and of Gamarias son of Chelkias whom Sedekias king of Juda sent to the king of Babylon at Babylon, a letter for the captives addressed to all the people saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thus said the Lord the God of Israel to the captivity whom I have exiled from Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Build houses and dwell therein; and plant orchards and eat the fruits thereof;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and take wives and beget sons and daughters; take wives also for your sons and give your daughters in marriage; and multiply and be not diminished;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and study the peace of the country to which I have exiled you; and pray to the Lord for the people; for in their peace you will have peace</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For thus said the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let not the false prophets among you deceive you; nor let your diviners deceive you; nor hearken to your dreams which you dream. For they prophesy falsehood to you in my name, and I have not sent them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, When seventy years shall be accomplished at Babylon, I will visit you and establish my words for you by bringing back your people to this place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When I plan a purpose of peace and not evils against you, to grant you this,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>then pray to me and I will hearken to you: then seek me diligently and you shall find me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Because you will seek me with your whole heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>therefore I will manifest myself to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Because you said, The Lord hath raised up prophets for us in Babylon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>thus said the Lord against Achiab and against Sedekias, behold I deliver them into the hands of the king of Babylon and he will smite them before your eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And among all the captives of Juda at Babylon; they shall from them use an execration saying, The Lord deal with thee as he did with Sedekias, and as he did with Achiab whom the king of Babylon roasted with fire,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>because they have committed iniquity in Israel and have committed adultery with the wives of their fellow citizens, and have delivered as prophets a word in my name, which I did not give them in charge: I myself am witness saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And to Samaias the Ailamite thou shalt say,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I did not send thee: yet in my name he said to Sophonias son of Maasias, the priest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The Lord hath made thee priest in the room of Jodae the priest, to be a ruler in the house of the Lord, over every man who prophesieth, and over every man who divineth, that thou mayst commit him to prison, and confine him in a dungeon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now why have you reviled Jeremias of Anathoth who prophesied to you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Was it not for this purpose that information was given that within this month he had sent to you to Babylon, saying, Your return is far off; build houses and dwell therein; plant orchards and eat the fruits thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>When Sophonias read this letter in the hearing of Jeremias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>a word of the Lord came to Jeremias saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Send to the captives, and say, Thus said the Lord, against Samaias the Ailamite, Because Samaias hath prophesied to you, and I did not send him, and he hath made you trust in falsehoods,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>therefore thus said the Lord, Behold I will punish Samaias and his family, and there shall not be a man of them among you to see the good things which I will do for you. They shall not see them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came from the Lord to Jeremias, to wit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus spake the Lord the God of Israel, saying, Write all the words which I have delivered to thee in a book:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>for behold the days are coming saith the Lord when I will bring back the captivity of my people Israel and Juda, said the Lord; and I will bring them to this land, which I gave to their fathers and they shall rule over it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now these are the words which the Lord spake concerning Israel and Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, You shall hear the sound of terror. It is terror and not peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Inquire and see! Hath a male ever brought forth? Now with respect to the terror, in which they will hold their loins, it is indeed for a deliverance. Why then have I seen every man with his hands on his loins? Their faces are turned to paleness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>It is because that great day is come which is unparalleled. It is indeed a distressful time to Jacob, but by this he shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>In that day, saith the Lord, I will break the yoke from their neck, and burst their bonds asunder; and they shall no more work for strangers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But they must work for the Lord their God and I will raise up for them David their king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, I raised up affliction; thy wound was grievous;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>there is none to plead thy cause; the attempts to cure thee increased thy pain; there is no relief for thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>all thy friends forgot thee; they would make no inquiry for thee; because I inflicted on thee the wound of an enemy, a severe chastisement for all thine iniquity; thy sins had multiplied:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For the multitude of thine iniquities (thy sins indeed were multiplied) they have done all these things to thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>therefore all that devour thee shall be devoured, and all thine enemies shall eat their own flesh but they who plunder thee shall be for plunder; and all who have preyed upon thee, I will give for a prey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Because I will bring up the cure for thee I will cure thee, saith the Lord, of thy painful wound; because thou wast called the Outcast, the hunt is up after thee; because there is none who seeketh this outcast,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>thus saith the Lord, Behold I myself will bring back the outcast of Jacob, and his captivity I will compassionate. And the city shall be rebuilt on its height; and the people shall sit for the administration of justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And from them shall come forth singers; the sound of the sportive; and I will multiply them and they shall not be diminished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And their sons shall come in as in former times; and their judicatories shall be established in my presence. And I will punish them who afflict them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>His own mighties shall preside over them; and from him his own chief shall come forth; and he will gather them that they may return to me? that he who hath given his heart, whoever he is, may return to me, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Because the anger of the Lord hath gone forth; hath gone forth a furious anger, it will come whirling on the wicked;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the fierce anger of the Lord will not turn back, till he hath done; till he hath executed the purpose of his heart. In the latter days you will know these things.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time, said the Lord, I will be the God of the family of Israel and they shall be my people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, I found him warm in the wilderness among them who had perished by the sword. Go: you shall not destroy Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The Lord from afar hath appeared for him: with everlasting love I have loved thee; therefore I have drawn thee into compassion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For I will rebuild thee, and thou shalt be rebuilt. virgin of Israel, again thou shalt take thy timbrel, and go forth with a congregation of rejoicers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>As you have planted vineyards on the mountains of Samaria, plant and sing praises;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>for there shall be a day of invitation to them who make apologies on the mountains of Ephraim, Arise and go up to Sion to the Lord your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For thus said the Lord to Jacob, Rejoice and shout at the head of nations; issue proclamations and sing praises; say, The Lord hath saved his people, the remnant of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Behold I will bring them from the north and gather them from the extremity of the earth. At the festival of Phasek he shall have a multitude of children who shall return hither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They set out with weeping; but I will bring them up with consolation, causing them to rest at fountains of water in a straight road; and in it they shall not be led astray, for I am become a father to Israel, and Ephraim is my first born.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hear the words of the Lord, ye nations! and proclaim them to the far distant isles. Say, He, who scattered Israel, will gather them, and guard them as a shepherd doth his flock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Because the Lord hath redeemed Jacob; hath rescued him out of the hand of them who were stronger than he;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>therefore they shall come and rejoice on mount Sion. They shall indeed come to the good things of the Lord; to a land of corn and wine, and of fruits and herds and flocks; and their soul shall be like a fruitful tree; and they shall no more be hungry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then shall virgins rejoice in the assembly of youths; the elders also shall be filled with joy; for I will turn their mourning into joy and make them glad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I will enlarge and satisfy the soul of the priests the sons of Levi. And my people shall be regaled with my good things. Thus said the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>There was heard at Rama a sound of lamentation and weeping and wailing; Rachel, weeping for her children, refused to be comforted, because they are no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Let thy voice refrain from lamentation and thine eyes from tears. For there is a reward for thy works and they shall return from the enemies land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>It is firmly established for thy children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I have heard the voice of Ephraim moaning, Thou hast chastised me and I have been chastised. I like a bullock was uninstructed, bring me back that I may return; for thou art the Lord my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For after my captivity I reformed and after I gained knowledge I groaned for my days of shame and shewed thee that I was ashamed of my youth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Ephraim is a beloved son; my darling child; since my words are in him I will surely remember him. For this cause I have been anxious for him, I will surely have mercy upon him, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Establish thyself, Sion; take revenge; rouse up thy courage. By the way thou wentest return, virgin of Israel; return to thy cities, mourner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>How long shall it be, ere thou wilt return, despised daughter! Since the Lord hath created safety for a new plantation, with safety men may walk about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For thus saith the Lord, Again they shall use this form of words in the land of Juda and in his cities when I have brought back his captivity, Blessed be the Lord on his righteous, his holy mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>It shall be used by them who dwell in the cities of Juda and in all his land, and shall be repeated by the husbandman and among the flocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For I have satisfied with drink every thirsty soul; and every soul that was hungry I have filled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Upon this I awoke and beheld and my sleep was sweet to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Therefore behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, when I will sow Israel and Juda with the seed of man and the seed of beast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And it shall be, that as I watched over them to pull down and waste, so I will watch over them to build up and plant, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>In those days they shall no more say, Our fathers ate a sour grape and the childrens' teeth are set on edge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But every one shall die for his own sin. And whoever eateth the sour grape, his teeth shall be set on edge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, when I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and the house of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Not according to the covenant which I made with their fathers on the day when I took them by the hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt. Because they did not abide by this covenant of mine, therefore I took no care of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>For this, saith the Lord, is my covenant which I will make with the house of Israel; after those days, saith the Lord, I will adapt my laws to their understanding and write them on their hearts, and I will be their God and they shall be my people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And they shall no more teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord; for all will know me from the greatest to the least of them: for I will be merciful to their iniquities and no more remember their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Thus said the Lord who hath given the sun to enlighten the day and the moon and stars to enlighten the night, and hath caused the sea to roar and its billows to resound, the Lord Almighty is his name;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>If these laws cease to operate in my presence, saith the Lord, then may the race of Israel cease from being a nation before me forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Though the heaven is exalted very high, saith the Lord, and the surface of the earth is depressed far below, yet I will not reject the race of Israel, saith the Lord, for all that they have done,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Behold days are coming, saith the Lord, when a city shall be built to the Lord from the tower of Anameel to the gate of the corner;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>the diameter thereof shall extend forward as far as the hills of Gareb: and it shall be enclosed around with choice stones;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and all the Asaremoth as far as Nachal Kedron, even to the corner of the horse gate eastward shall be dedicated to the Lord, and it shall no more fail nor shall it be demolished until the age.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="32">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came from the Lord to Jeremias in the tenth year of king Sedekias; this was the eighteenth year of the reign of Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When the army of the king of Babylon was besieging Jerusalem, and Jeremias was confined in the court of the prison which is in the king's house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>to which king Sedekias had confined him, saying, Why dost thou prophesy and say, thus said the Lord, Behold I deliver this city into the hands of the king of Babylon and he shall take it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and Sedekias shall not escape out of the hands of the Chaldeans, for he shall assuredly be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon who shall speak to him mouth to mouth and his eyes shall see his eyes:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and Sedekias shall go to Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now when he was there, the word of the Lord came to Jeremias, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold Anameel son of Salom thy father's brother is coming to thee and will say, Buy thee my field which is at Anathoth, for the right of purchase is in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Accordingly Anameel son of Salom my father's brother came to me in the court of the prison and said, Buy thee my field which is in the land of Benjamin, that at Anathoth, for the right of purchase is in thee as thou art the eldest. Upon this I knew that it was a word of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>so I bought the field of Anameel, my father' s brother's son and paid him seventeen shekels of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when I had signed the writing and sealed it and had it witnessed and had paid the money by weight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I took the deed of possession which was sealed and gave it to Baruch, son of Nerias son of Maasias in the presence of Anameel my father's brother's son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and in the presence of the byestanders who had signed the deed of purchase, and in the presence of the Jews who were in the court of the prison;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and in their presence I gave a charge to Baruch, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thus said the Lord Almighty, Take this deed of possession, even this deed which hath been read, and put it in an earthen vessel that it may remain there many days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, Fields and houses and vineyards shall again be possessed in this land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And after I had given the deed of purchase to Baruch son of Nerias, I prayed to the Lord, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>self-existent Lord, Thou hast made the heaven and the earth by thy great power and by thy high and exalted arm. From thee nothing can be hid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thou shewest mercy to thousands and retributest the sins of fathers into the bosoms of their children after them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou art the God, the Great, the Mighty One, the Lord of great counsel, and mighty in works, the Mighty Omnipotent God, and the Lord of great renown. Thine eyes are on the ways of the children of men to give to every one according to his way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou hast done signs and wonders in the land of Egypt which continue even to this day; and in Israel and among the inhabitants of the earth; and hast made thyself a name as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thou didst bring thy people Israel out of the land of Egypt with signs and wonders and with a strong hand and an outstretched arm and with stupendous visions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and gavest them this land which with an oath thou hadst promised to their fathers, a land flowing with milk and honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But when they entered in and had taken possession of it, they hearkened not to thy voice nor walked in thy statutes. They did not do all that thou commandedst them, so they have brought upon themselves all these evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Behold a multitude is come up against this city to take it; and this city is about to be delivered into the hands of the Chaldeans who are fighting against it, by reason of the sword and famine. As thou hast spoken, so it hath come to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now thou sayest to me, Buy thee a field for money. Accordingly I have signed the deed of purchase and sealed it and had it witnessed; though the city is about to be delivered into the hands of the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then a word of the Lord came to me saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>I the Lord am the God of all flesh. From me nothing can be hid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Therefore thus said the Lord the God of Israel, This city will assuredly be given up into the hands of the king of Babylon, and he will take it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And the Chaldeans who are fighting against this city will come and burn this city with fire; and they will burn those houses on the tops of which they have offered incense to Baal and poured out libations to strange gods, to provoke me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Because the children of Israel and the children of Juda have done nothing but evil before mine eyes from their youth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>because this very city hath been an object of my wrath and of my resentment from the day it was built to this day;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>let him remove it from my presence on account of all the iniquities of the children of Israel and Juda, which they and their kings and their chiefs and their priests and their prophets, the men of Juda and the inhabitants of Jerusalem have done to provoke me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>For they have turned to me their back and not their face. Though I taught them betimes, they would no more receive instruction,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>but have set up their abominations in the house which is called by my name, and polluted it with their impurities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and have built up the altars to Baal which were in the valley of the son of Ennom to offer up their sons and their daughters to king Moloch; a thing which I never commanded them, nor did it ever come into my mind that they should commit such an abomination to cause Juda to transgress heinously.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But now thus said the Lord the God of Israel respecting this city, which as thou sayest shall be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon by sword and by famine and by pestilence;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>behold I will gather them from every land through which I have in my wrath and in my great indignation dispersed them: and I will bring them back to this place and cause them to live securely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And they shall be my people and I will be their God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And I will give them another way and another heart that I may be always feared and may be for good to them and their children after them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And I will make an everlasting covenant with them, which I will not turn away from them; and I will put my fear in their heart, that they may not apostatise from me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>and I will watch over them to do them good, and plant them in this land with faithfulness even with my whole heart and soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, as I have brought upon this people at these great evils, so I will bring upon them all these good things, which I have spoken concerning them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And fields shall again be purchased in this land which as thou sayest shall be untrodden by men and beasts when they are delivered into the hands of the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And they shall purchase fields for money. And thou shalt subscribe deeds and seal them and cause them to be witnessed in the land of Benjamin and around Jerusalem and in the cities of Juda and in the cities of the mountain and in the cities of Sephela and in the cities of Nageb; for I will bring back their captivities.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="33">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Again a word of the Lord came to Jeremias a second time while he was still a prisoner in the court of the prison, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, the maker of the earth, who formed it that he might regulate it. His name is the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Cry to me and I will answer thee and shew thee great and marvellous things which thou hast not known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For thus said the Lord concerning the houses of this city; and concerning the houses of the king of Juda which have been pulled down to make mounts and ramparts</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>to fight against the Chaldeans and to fill the city with the carcasses of men whom I have slain in mine indignation and in my wrath; and from whom I have turned away my face for all their wicked deeds;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>behold I am raising up for it a cure for wounds and a restorative, which I will shew them, and I will heal it and give it peace</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and fidelity. And I will bring back the captivity of Juda and the captivity of Israel; and I will build them up as in former times.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And I will cleanse them from all their iniquities which they have committed against me, and no more remember the sins which they sinned against me, when they apostatised from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And it shall be for a joy and praise and for a subject of exultation to all the people of the earth who shall hear all the good things which I will do. And they will be struck with awe and remorse for all the good and for all the peace which I will procure for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, In the place which you say is a desert without men and beasts; in the cities of Juda and in the streets of Jerusalem which have been desolate so as to have neither man nor beast,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>there shall be heard again the sound of joy and the sound of mirth; the voice of bridegroom and the voice of the bride; the voice of people, saying, Praise the Lord Almighty; for the Lord is gracious; for his mercy endureth forever. And they shall bring gifts to the house of the Lord. For I will bring back all the captivity of this land, as in former times, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord of hosts, There shall be again in this very place which shall be desolate, without man or beast, in all the cities belonging to it lodging places for shepherds folding flocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In the cities of the hilly country and in the cities of Sephela, and in the cities of Nageb and in the land of Benjamin and in those around Jerusalem and in the cities of Juda, flocks shall again pass under the hand of him that counteth them, said the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="34">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came to Jeremias from the Lord, when Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon, with all his army and every country under his dominion were warring against Jerusalem, and against all the cities of Juda, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, Go to Sedekias king of Juda and say to him, Thus said the Lord, This city shall assuredly be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon; and he shall take it, and burn it with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And thou shalt not escape out of his hand. Thou shalt indeed be taken and delivered into his hands; and thine eyes shall see his eyes; and to Babylon thou shalt go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Nevertheless hear the word of the Lord, Sedekias king of Juda, Thus said the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thou shalt die in peace; and as they bewailed thy fathers who reigned before thee so will they bewail thee with Alas Lord? and utter a lamentation for thee at thy burial; for I have spoken the word said the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So Jeremias delivered to king Sedekias all these words at Jerusalem</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>when the army of the king of Babylon was warring against Jerusalem and against the cities of Juda namely against Lachis and against Azeka; for they were the only fortified cities which were left of the cities of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The word which came to Jeremias from the Lord. After king Sedekias had made a covenant with the people to proclaim a release,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>that every man should set free his man servant and his maid servant of Hebrew extraction so that no person of Juda should continue in slavery;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>when all the nobles and all the people who had entered into covenant, to set free every one his man servant, and his maid servant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>altered their minds and compelled them to become their servants;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>thereupon a word of the Lord came to Jeremias saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, I made a covenant with your fathers, at the time I brought them out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When six years are accomplished thou shalt set at liberty thy brother, a Hebrew, who shall be sold to thee. When he hath Worked for thee six years, thou shalt let him go free. But they have not hearkened to me, nor inclined their ear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And now when they turned to do what is right in my sight, by proclaiming a general release, every one to his neighbour; and had made a covenant in my presence in the house which is called by my name;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>you have turned back and profaned my name, by causing every one his man servant, and every one his maid servant whom you had sent away free at their own disposal, to return and become your servants:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore thus said the Lord, You have not hearkened to me to proclaim a general release, every one to his neighbour; behold, I proclaim a dismission of you to the sword, and to pestilence and to famine; and I will deliver you up to dispersion in all the kingdoms of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I will indeed give up the men who have transgressed my covenant; them, who have not stood to this covenant of mine which they entered into in my presence; as the labouring bullock which they sacrificed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I will deliver up the chiefs of Juda and the rulers, and the priests,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and the people themselves to their enemies: and their carcasses shall be meat for the birds of the air and the beasts of the earth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and I will deliver Sedekias king of Judea, and their chiefs, into the hands of their enemies. And as for the army of the king of Babylon, even to them who are retreating,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>behold I am about to issue orders, saith the Lord, and I will cause them to return to this city. And they shall fight against it, and take it and burn it with fire. And I will make the cities of Juda a desolation, without inhabitants.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="35">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came to Jeremias from the Lord in the days of Joakim king of Juda, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Go to the family of Archabin and thou shalt bring them to the house of the Lord, into one of the courts, and give them wine to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Accordingly I brought Jechonias son of Jeremin son of Chabasin with his brethren and his sons, even all the family of Archabin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and took them into the house of the Lord, to the chamber of the sons of Jonan son of Ananias son of Godolias, a man of God, which is near the house of the chiefs who are above the house of Maasias son of Selom, the keeper of the court.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And having set before them a pot of wine and drinking cups, I said, drink wine. Thereupon they said, We must not drink wine. For Jonadab son of Rechab our father gave us a charge, saying, You shall not drink wine;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>neither you nor your sons forever;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>neither shall you build houses, nor sow seed, nor have a vineyard; for you shall dwell in tents all your days, that you may live many days in the land where you sojourn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Accordingly we have hearkened to the voice of Jonadab our father so as not to drink wine all our days, neither we nor our wives, nor our sons nor our daughters;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and we have not built houses here to live in, nor have we vineyard, or field or seed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but have dwelt in tents and have hearkened and done according to all that our father Jonadab commanded us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So when Nabuchodonosar came up against the land, we determined upon coming and came to Jerusalem out of the way of the army of the Chaldeans and out of the way of the army of the Assyrians, and here we have made our abode.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Upon this a word of the Lord came to me, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Go and say to the men of Juda and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, Will you never receive instruction to hearken to my words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The children of Jonadab son of Rechab have stedfastly observed the command which he gave them not to drink wine: and they have not drunk any. But I have spoken to you, rising early; and you have not hearkened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Though I have sent to you my servants the prophets; saying, Turn ye, every one from his evil way, and amend your doings, and go not after strange gods to serve them, and you shall dwell in the land which I gave to you and your fathers; yet you have not inclined your ears nor hearkened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The sons of Jonadab son of Rechab have stedfastly observed the command of their father; but this people have not hearkened to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold I will bring upon Juda and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem all the evils which I have denounced against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Seeing the sons of Jonadab son of Rechab have obeyed the command of their father and have done as he ordered them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>there shall never be wanting a man of the sons of Jonadab son of Rechab to stand before me all the days of this land.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="36">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the fourth year of Joakim son of Josias king of Juda, a word of the Lord came to me, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Take thee a roll of a book and write therein all the words which I have spoken to thee against Jerusalem and against Juda and against all the nations from the day I first spoke to thee; from the days of Josias king of Juda even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Perhaps the house of Juda will hear all the evils which I purpose to do to them, that they may turn from their evil way and that I may be merciful to their iniquities and their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon Jeremias sent for Baruch, son of Nerias, and he wrote in a book, from the mouth of Jeremias, all the words which the Lord had spoken to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Jeremias gave a charge to Baruch, saying, I am watched so that I cannot go to the house of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore thou shalt read from this roll in the hearing of the people in the house of the Lord on the fast day, even in the hearing: of all Juda who come from their cities thou shalt read to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Perhaps they may find favour in the sight of the Lord and turn from their evil way, for great is the wrath and the anger of the Lord which he hath denounced against this people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So Baruch did according to all that Jeremias commanded him, that he might read from the book the words of the Lord in the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And it came to pass that in the eighth year of the reign of Joakim, in the ninth month, all the people in Jerusalem and the house of Juda kept a solemn fast before the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Baruch read from the book the words of Jeremias in the house of the Lord in the house of Gamarias son of Saphan the scribe, in the upper court at the vestibule of the new gate of the house of the Lord and in the hearing of all the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when Michaias son of Gamarias son of Saphan heard all the words of the Lord from the book,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>he went down to the king's house, to the house of the secretary; and lo! all the chiefs were there in council, namely, Elisama the secretary, and Dalias son of Selemias, and Jonathan son of Achobar and Gamarias son of Saphan and Sedekias son of Ananias and all the chiefs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when Michaias told them all the words which he had heard, which Baruch read in the hearing of the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>all the chiefs sent Judin son of Nathanias son of Selemias, son of Chusi to Baruch, saying, Take in thy hand the roll thou art reading to the people and come. Accordingly Baruch took the roll and went down to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And they said to him, Read it again to us. So Baruch read it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when they had heard all the words, they consulted, and said one to another, We must certainly inform the king of all these words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then they questioned Baruch and said, Where didst thou write all these words?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then they said to Baruch, Go and hide, both thou and Jeremias and let no man know where you are.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And Baruch said, From his mouth. Jeremias dictated to me all these words and I wrote them in a book.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then they went to court to the king, but left the roll in safe keeping in the house of Elisamas and they told the king all the words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the king sent Judin for the book. And Judin having brought it from the house of Elisamas read it in the hearing of the king and in the hearing of all the chiefs who were standing round the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now the king was sitting in the winter house and there was a grate with fire in it before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So as Judin read three or four folds, he cut them off with the secretary's knife and threw them into the fire in the grate, till the whole roll was consumed in the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But neither the king nor his servants, who heard all these words, made any inquiry nor rent their clothes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Nay Elnathan and Godolias suggested to the king to burn the roll.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then the king commanded Jeremeel the king's son and Saraias son of Esriel to apprehend Baruch and Jeremias. But they had hid themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And after the king had burned the roll; all the words which Baruch had written from the mouth of Jeremias, a word of the Lord came to Jeremias, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Take thee another roll and write all the words which were in that roll which king Joakim hath burned,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and thou shalt say, Thus saith the Lord, Thou hast burned that roll, saying, Why hast thou written therein and said the king of Babylon shall surely come and lay waste this land, so that neither man nor beast shall be left therein;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>therefore thus said the Lord respecting Joakim king of Juda, He shall not have one to sit on the throne of David; and his carcass shall be exposed to the heat of the day and to the frost of the night:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and I will keep a watch upon him and on his family and upon his servants and bring upon him and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem and upon the land of Juda all the evils which I have denounced against them and to which they have not hearkened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>So Baruch took another roll and wrote thereon from the mouth of Jeremias all the words of the book which Joakim had burned and to it were added more words similar to them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="37">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Sedekias son of Josias, whom Nabuchodonosar had made king over Juda, reigned in the room of Joakim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and neither he nor his servants nor the people of the land hearkened to the words which the Lord spoke by the ministry of Jeremias and king Sedekias:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>sent Joachel son of Selemias and Sophonias son of Maasias the priest to Jeremias saying, Pray now to the Lord for us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>(Now Jeremias went out and came in through the midst of the city and they had not committed him to prison,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and the army of Pharao had come out of Egypt, and the Chaldeans had heard the news of them when they came up against Jerusalem.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then a word of the Lord came to Jeremias, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, Thus shalt thou say to the king of Juda who hath sent to thee to inquire of me, Behold the army of Pharao which is coming to your assistance shall turn back to the land of Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the Chaldeans shall return and fight against this city and take it and burn it with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, Flatter not yourselves, saying, The Chaldeans are retreating; they will depart from us. For they shall not depart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Nay, though you should smite all the army of the Chaldeans who are warring against you and only some wounded men should be left, every one in his place; these shall rise up and burn this city with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now when the army of the Chaldeans left Jerusalem, on account of the army of Pharao,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Jeremias was going out of Jerusalem among the people with a design to go to the land of Benjamin, to make thence some purchase;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>but when he was at the gate of Benjamin, a man there at whose house he stopped namely Sarouia son of Selemias, son of Ananias, took hold of Jeremias, saying, Thou art fleeing to the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>To which he replied, It is false. I am not fleeing to the Chaldeans. But Sarouia hearkened not to him, but took hold of Jeremias and brought him to the chiefs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the chiefs were enraged at Jeremias and smote him and committed him to the house of Jonathan the scribe; for they had made that a prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when Jeremias had gone into the lowest apartment, even into the Chereth, and had been there many days, Sedekias sent for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the king asked him privately to tell him whether there was a message from the Lord. And Jeremias said, There is. Thou shalt be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then Jeremias said to the king, Wherein have I offended thee and thy servants and this people, that thou hast committed me to prison?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Where now are your prophets who prophesied to you saying, The king of Babylon shall not come against this land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now therefore, my Lord the king, let me find favour in thy sight. Why art thou sending me back to the house of Jonathan the scribe? Must I not die there?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thereupon the king gave orders and they committed him to the guard house and gave him a loaf of bread a day from the bake house until all the bread in the city was spent. So Jeremias remained in the court of the prison.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="38">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Saphanias son of Nathan and Godolias son of Paschor and Joachal son of Semelias, heard the words which Jeremias spoke concerning the people saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus said the Lord, He who abideth in this city shall die by the sword and the famine; but he who goeth out to the Chaldeans shall live. He shall have his life for a spoil. He shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, This city shall certainly be delivered into the hands of the army of the king of Babylon and he shall take it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>they said to the king, Let this man, we pray thee, be put out of the way; for he weakeneth the hands of the warriors who are left in the city and the hands of all the people by making such speeches to them. For this man prophesieth not peace to the people, but only evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the king said, Behold he is in your hands. For the king could not withstand them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So they threw him into the dungeon of Melchias the king's son which was in the court of the prison. And when they had lowered him down into the dungeon, there was no water in the dungeon, but there was mire; and he was in the mire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But when Abdemelech, the Ethiopian, who was in the king's family, heard that they had put Jeremias in the dungeon, as the king was at the gate of Benjamin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>he went out to him and spoke to the king, and said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou hast done wrong in ordering this man to be put to death out of the way of the famine, for there is no bread in the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thereupon the king gave orders to Abdemelech, saying, Take hence with thee thirty men and draw him up out of the dungeon, that he may not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So Abdemelech took the men and went to the king's house, into the cellar, and took thence old rags and old ropes and threw them down to Jeremias into the dungeon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and said, Put those under the ropes. And when Jeremias had done so,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>they drew him up with the ropes out of the dungeon. And Jeremias abode in the court of the prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the king sent and ordered him to come to him to the house Aseleisel which is in the house of the Lord. And the king said to him, I will ask thee a word and thou must not conceal any thing from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Jeremias said to the king, If I tell thee, wilt thou not put me to death? And if I give thee counsel, perhaps thou wilt not hearken to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then the king swore to him, saying, As the Lord liveth who made us this soul, I will not put thee to death, nor will I deliver thee into the hands of those men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Jeremias said, Thus said the Lord, if thou wilt go out to the generals of the king of Babylon, thy soul shall live and this city will not be burned with fire. Both thou and thy family shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But if thou wilt not go out, this city will be delivered into the hands of the Chaldeans and they will burn it with fire; and thou shalt not escape.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the king said to Jeremias, I am afraid of the Jews who have fled to the Chaldeans, lest upon being delivered into their hand they make me a mocking stock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Jeremias replied, Thou wilt not be delivered up to them, Hear the word of the Lord which I speak to thee and it will be better for thee and thy soul shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But if thou wilt not go out, this is the word which the Lord hath revealed to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And behold all the women who were left in the house of the king of Juda were brought out to the chiefs of the king of Babylon. And they said, Thy men of peace deceived thee, and will prevail over thee. And with a fall they will weaken thy foot. They are gone from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And thy wives and thy children shall be brought out to the Chaldeans. And thou shalt not escape. For by the hand of the king of Babylon thou shalt be taken and this city shall be burned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then the king said to him, Let no man know any of these words, and thou shalt not be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And if the chiefs hear that I have spoken to thee and come to thee and say, Tell us, What did the king say to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Hide it not from us and we will not put thee to death. What did the king say to thee? Then thou shalt say to them, I presented my supplication before the king that he would not send me back to the house of Jonathan to die there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So when all the chiefs came to Jeremias and questioned him, he answered them according to all the words which the king commanded and they were silent; for the word of the Lord was not heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>So Jeremias remained in the court of the prison until Jerusalem was taken.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="39">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now it came to pass that in the ninth year and ninth month of Sedekias king of Juda, Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon with all his army came against Jerusalem and besieged it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And in the eleventh year of Sedekias in the fourth month on the ninth day of the month, a breach was made into the city;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and all the generals of the king of Babylon entered and sat in the middle gate, namely, Marganasar, and Samagoth and Nabusachar and Nabusaris, Nagargas, Naserrabamath, and the rest of the generals of the king of Babylon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and they sent and took Jeremias out of the court of the prison and committed him to Godolias son of Achikam son of Saphan. And when they brought him out he sat down among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now there had come to Jeremias in the court of the prison a word of the Lord, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Go and say to Abdemelech the Ethiopian, Thus said the Lord the God of Israel, Behold I will bring my words on this city for evils and not for good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But I will save thee on that day and not deliver thee into the hands of those men of whom thou art afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For I will save thee and thou shalt not fall by the sword. And thou shalt have thy life for a spoil, because thou hast trusted in me, said the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="40">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came from the Lord to Jeremias after Nabusardan the chief cook, he who was of Rama, had dismissed him: When the chief cook found him in chains in the midst of the captives of Juda who were to be carried to Babylon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he took him and said to him, The Lord thy God hath denounced all these evils against this place,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and the Lord hath done them, because you sinned against him and did not hearken to his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Behold I have loosed thee from the chains which were on thy hands. If it seemeth good to thee to go with me to Babylon, I will have an eye over thee. But if not, Go thy way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Return to Godolias son of Achikam son of Saphan whom the king of Babylon hath set over the land of Juda and dwell with him among the people in the land of Juda. Go whithersoever it seemeth best in thine eyes to go. So the chief cook gave him gifts and dismissed him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and he went to Godolias to Massepha and dwelt among his people who were left in the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now when all the generals of the army in the country, both they and their men heard that the king of Babylon had set Godolias over the land, and had committed to him the men and their wives whom he had not removed to Babylon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>there came to Godolias, at Massepha, Ismael son of Nathanias and Joanan son of Karae and Saraias son of Thanaemeth and the sons of Jophe the Netophathite and Ezonias son of Mochathi, they and their men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and Godolias swore to them and their men, saying, Be not afraid of the Chaldeans: dwell in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will be better for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>As for me, behold I reside before you, at Massepha to meet the Chaldeans who may come against you. But as for you, collect wine and summer fruits and oil and lay them up in your vessels and dwell in the cities which you have taken possession of.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>All the Jews also who were in Moab and among the Ammonites and those in Idumea and in all that country, when they heard that the king of Babylon had left a remnant for Juda and had set Godolias son of Achikam over them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>came to Godolias into the land of Juda to Massepha, and collected wine and summer fruits in great abundance, and oil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And Joanan son of Karae and all the generals of the army who were in the country came to Godolias to Massepha</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and said to him, Dost thou know that Beleissa king of the Ammonites hath sent Ismael to thee, to take thy life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But Godolias did not believe them. And when Joanan said privately to Godolias at Massepha, Let me, I pray thee, go and smite Ismael and let none know it; lest he kill thee; and all Juda who are gathered to thee, be dispersed and the remnant of Juda perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Godolias said to Joanan, Thou must not do this: for what thou sayest of Ismael is false.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="41">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now it came to pass that in the seventh month Ismael son of Nathanias son of Eleasa of the royal family and ten chief men with him came to Godolias at Massepha and they there ate bread together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Ismael arose and the ten chiefs who were with him, and smote Godolias whom the king of Babylon had set over the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and all the Jews who were with him at Massepha and all the Chaldeans who were found there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And it happened that on the second day after he had slain Godolias and it was not generally known,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>there came eighty men from Sychem and from Salem and from Samaria, with their beards shaven and their clothes rent and in deep mourning, with manna and frankincense in their hands, to make an offering for the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And Ismael went out to meet them as they were proceeding on in their journey weeping, and said to them, Come to Godolias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when they were come into the midst of the city he slew them at the pit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But there were ten men among them who said to Ismael, Do not kill us; for we have treasures in a field, wheat and barley, honey and oil. So he forbore and did not kill them among their brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now the pit, into which Ismael threw all that he had slain, was that great pit which king Asa had made for fear of Baasa king of Israel. This Ismael filled with the slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And Ismael carried away all the people who were left at Massepha and the king's daughters whom the chief cook had committed to the care of Godolias son of Achikam; and fled towards the borders of the Anmonites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But when Joanan son of Karae and all the generals of the army who were with him heard all the evils which Ismael had done,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>they drew out their whole army and marched with speed to fight him and came up with him at the great waters at Gabaon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when all the people who were with Ismael saw Joanan and the generals of the army who were with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>they turned back to Joanan;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but Ismael escaped with eight men and fled to the children of Ammon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then Joanan and all the generals of the army who were with him took all the remnant of the people whom they had rescued from Ismael;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the men fit for war and the women and children and the eunuchs whom they brought back from Gabaon and marching with speed they encamped at Gaberochama which is near Bethlehem with an intent to go to Egypt</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for fear of the Chaldeans. For they were afraid of them because Ismael had slain Godolias whom the king of Babylon had set over the land.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="42">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And all the generals of the army with Joanan and Azarias son of Maasias and all the people small and great</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>came to Jeremias the prophet and said to him, Have compassion on us, we beseech thee and pray to the Lord thy God for this remnant; for we are left only few of many as thine eyes see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now let the Lord thy God point out to us the way which we should go and what we are to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon Jeremias said to them, I have heard. Behold, I will pray for you to the Lord our God according to your words and whatever answer the Lord our God shall give that I will declare to you. I will not hide anything from you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And they said to Jeremias, The Lord be a true and faithful witness between us, that we will act conformably to the word, whatever it be, which the Lord shall send to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whether it be agreeable or disagreeable we will hearken to the voice of the Lord our God in respect to that for which we send thee to him, that it may be the better for us. We will obey the voice of the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So after ten days a word of the Lord came to Jeremias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>where upon he sent for Joanan and the generals of the army, and all the people small and great,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and said to them, Thus said the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If you will abide in this land I will build you up, and not pull you down; and I will plant you, and not root you up; for I am appeased by the evils which I have done to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Be not afraid of the king of Babylon of whom you are in dread. Be not afraid of him, saith the Lord, for I am with you to deliver you, and to save you out of his hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And I will shew you mercy, and have compassion on you, and bring you back to your own land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But if in direct disobedience to the voice of the Lord you say,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>We will not abide in this land; for we will go to the land of Egypt, that we may not see war nor hear the trumpet's sound, nor pine for want of bread; and we will dwell there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then hear the word of the Lord, Thus said the Lord, If you set your face for Egypt, and go there to make your abode;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the sword of which you are afraid shall find you in the land of Egypt; and the famine which you wish to avoid shall follow and overtake you in Egypt, and there you shall die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For all the men even all the strangers who have set their faces towards the land of Egypt to dwell there, shall perish by the sword and by famine, and not one of them shall escape from those evils which I bring upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, As my wrath was poured out on the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so shall my wrath be poured out upon you, if you go to Egypt; and you shall be wasted and made slaves, and be for an execration and reproach; and shall never see this land again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>These are the things which the Lord hath spoken respecting you, the remnant of Juda; that you may not go to Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For now you must be sensible that you did evil in your hearts when you sent me saying, Pray for us to the Lord, and we will act conformably to all that the Lord shall say to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For you have not hearkened to the voice of the Lord, which he hath sent by me to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now therefore you shall perish by the sword and by famine, in that place to which you are determined to go there to make your abode.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="43">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when Jeremias^ had made an end of speaking all these words of the Lord to the people, even all the words which the Lord had sent him to speak to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Azarias son of Maasias and Joanan son of Karae, and all the men who had spoken to Jeremias, said in reply, It is false. The Lord hath not sent thee to us, saying, You shall not go to Egypt to dwell there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But Baruch son of Nerias setteth thee on against us, that thou mayst deliver us into the hands of the Chaldeans to be put to death, or banished to Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So Joanan and all the generals of the army and all the people hearkened not to the voice of the Lord to dwell in the land of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And Joanan and all the generals of the army took all the remnant of Juda, who had returned to dwell in the land,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>the men fit for war, and the women and the children which were left and the king's daughters, even all the souls which Nabusardan had left with Godolias son of Achikam, including Jeremias the prophet, and Baruch son of Nerias, and went to Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Because they hearkened not to the voice of the Lord, therefore when they came to Taphnas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>a word of the Lord came to Jeremias at Taphnas, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Take thee large stones and bury them at the entrance of the gate of Pharao's house at Taphnas, in the presence of the men of Juda</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and thou shalt say, Thus said the Lord, Behold I send and I will bring Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon and he shall place his throne over these stones, which thou hast hidden, and pile his arms over them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when he is come he will smite the land of Egypt, sentencing to death them who are for death; and to banishment such as are for banishment; and to the sword such as are for the sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And he will kindle a fire in the houses of their gods, and burn the houses and carry away the god's captives: and he will search the land of Egypt, as a shepherd doth his garment, and shall go thence in peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And he will break in pieces the pillars of Heliopolis, even those of On, and burn their houses with fire.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="44">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which came to Jeremias for all the Jews who dwelt in the land of Egypt: for them settled at Magdolus, and at Taphnas, and in the land of Pathoura, saying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus said the Lord the God of Israel, You have seen all the evils which I brought upon Jerusalem, and upon the cities of Juda;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and behold they are desolate, without inhabitants because of their wickedness which they committed to provoke me, by going to burn incense to strange gods, which you knew not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Though I sent to you my servants the prophets, rising early and sending them, saying, Do not commit this abominable thing which I hate;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>yet they hearkened not to me, nor inclined their ear to turn from their wickedness so as not to burn incense to strange gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore my wrath and mine indignation was poured out and kindled to a flame in the cities of Juda, and in the streets of Jerusalem, and they became a desolation and a waste, as at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now then, thus said the Lord Almighty, Why do ye commit great evils against your souls, to cut off every man and woman of you, with the infant and suckling out of Juda,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>so that none of you may be left; to provoke me with the works of your hands; by burning incense to strange gods in the land of Egypt, where you are come to dwell; that you may be cut off and become an execration and a reproach, among all the nations of the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Have you forgotten the evils of your fathers, and the evils of the kings of Juda, and the evils of your chiefs, and the evils of your wives, which they committed in the land of Juda, and in the streets of Jerusalem?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>They have not indeed even to this day desisted, nor have they adhered to the ordinances which I set before their fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>therefore thus said the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Behold I am setting my face to destroy all the remnant in Egypt; and they shall fall by the sword and by famine and die, both small and great: and they shall be for reproach and for destruction and for a curse.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For I will visit those settled in Egypt as I visited Jerusalem with sword and with famine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>so that none of this remnant of Juda who dwell in Egypt, shall be saved to return to the land of Juda, to which they earnestly hope to return, save those only who have made their escape thither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then all the men who knew that their wives burned incense, and all the women, a great congregation, and all the people who were settled in the land of Egypt at Pathoura answered Jeremias, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>In regard to this word which thou hast spoken to us in the name of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>we will not hearken to thee; for we will continue to perform every word which shall proceed from our mouth to burn incense to the queen of heaven and pour out libations to her; as we and our fathers and our kings and our chiefs did in the cities of Juda and in the streets of Jerusalem; for we had then plenty of bread and were in happy circumstances and saw no evils:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>but soon as we left off burning incense to the queen of heaven, we all became fewer in number, and were wasted by sword and famine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now grant that we have burned incense to the queen of heaven, and poured out libations to her, have we without our husbands, made cakes for her or poured out to her libations?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In reply to this Jeremias said to all the people, to the men in authority, and to the women and all the people who made him this answer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>This incense which you offered in the cities of Juda and in the streets of Jerusalem, you and your fathers, and your kings and your chiefs, and the people of the land, did not the Lord remember?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Did it not come into his mind so that the Lord could no longer forbear on the account of your evil doings and on the account of your abominations which you committed? So your land was made a desolation and a waste,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and for a curse as at this day because of the incense, which you offered, and the sins which you committed against the Lord. As you hearkened not to the voice of the Lord, nor walked in his statutes and in his law and in his testimonies; therefore these evils have come upon you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then Jeremias said to the people, particularly to the women, Hear a word of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord the God of Israel, Ye women have spoken with your mouths and with your hands confirmed it, saying, We will continue to perform the vows which we made to burn incense to the queen of heaven, and pour out libations to her. You have obstinately adhered to your vows, and have actually performed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Therefore hear a word of the Lord, all ye of Juda, who are settled in the land of Egypt; behold by my great name I have sworn said the Lord, my name shall no more be mentioned by the mouth of any Jew in all the land of Egypt, saying, As the Lord liveth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Because I have watched over them, to afflict them, and not to do them good, therefore all the Jews who are dwelling in the land of Egypt, shall perish by sword and by famine, until there be an end of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>They indeed who have escaped from the sword being few in number, shall return to the land of Juda; but the remnant of Juda, who have staid in the land of Egypt to settle there, shall know whose word shall stand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now this shall be a sign to you, that I will visit you for evil:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>thus said the Lord, Behold I deliver up Onaphre king of Egypt, into the hands of his enemy, and into the hands of him who seeketh his life, as I delivered Sedekias king of Juda into the hands of Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon, his enemy, and who sought his life.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="45">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The word which Jeremias the prophet spoke to Baruch son of Nerias, when he was writing the words in the book, from the mouth of Jeremias, in the fourth year of Joakim son of Josias king of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus said the Lord concerning thee Baruch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>because thou saidst, Ah Woe is me! for the Lord hath added grief to my sorrow: I laid me down with sighing; no rest did I find.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Say to him, Thus said the Lord, Behold! them whom I built up, I am pulling down; them whom I planted, I am rooting up;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and wilt thou seek great things for thyself? Seek them not. For behold I am about to bring evils on all flesh, saith the Lord; but I will give thee thy life, for a spoil in every place whither thou shalt go.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="46">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>To Egypt, respecting the army of Pharao Nechao, king of Egypt, who was by the river Euphrates, at Charmis, whom Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon defeated, in the fourth year of Joakim king of Juda.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Arm with buckler and shields, and advance to battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Harness the horses. Horsemen mount! and stand firm in your helmets. Having put on your breast plates, charge with your lances.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Why are they daunted, and falling back? Because their mighty men will be cut down, they fled amain; they rallied not, being hemmed in on all sides, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let not the swift flee, nor the mighty escape to the north. The forces at the river Euphrates are weak and have fallen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Who is this that will rush forth like the river, and whose stream will billow like a flood?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The waters of Egypt will rush forth like a river: for he said, I will issue forth and overwhelm the earth, and destroy the inhabitants thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Mount your horses, prepare your chariots: march forth ye warriors of Ethiopia! and ye Libyans well clad in armour! go up also ye Lydians who bend the bow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>This is indeed a day for the Lord our God: a day of vengeance, to execute vengeance on his enemies. And the sword of the Lord shall devour and be filled; it shall indeed be glutted with their blood; for there is a sacrifice for the Lord in the land of the north at the river Euphrates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Go up, Galaad, and take balm for the virgin daughter of Egypt. In vain hast thou multiplied thy medicines; there is no cure for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The nations heard thy voice and with thy screams the land was filled: because warrior added to warrior were weak, they both fell together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The words which the Lord spoke by the ministry of Jeremias, that the King of Babylon would come and smite the land of Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Despatch messengers to Magdolus; send also to Memphis. Say, to arms! and be ready! for a sword hath laid waste thy grove.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Why did Apis flee from thee? Thy chosen bull, why did he not stand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>because the Lord made him weak and thy multitude was weak and fell. Therefore every one said to his fellow, Let us arise and return to our people, to our native land, from the face of the Grecian sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Call the name of Pharao Nechao king of Egypt, Saon-Esbie-Moed. (Meaning an Empty sound)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>As I live, saith the Lord God, like Itaburion among the mountains, and like Channel which is by the sea he shall come. Get ready utensils for thy removal,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>well housed daughter of Egypt! for Memphis shall be a waste and shall be called, Alas? because in it there are no inhabitants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Egypt was a beautiful heifer; a detachment from the north came against her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the mercenaries, which she had with her, were like fatted bulls which she had fed. For they turned and fled with one consent: they made no stand, because the day of destruction came upon them and the time of their visitation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Their sound is that of a hissing serpent; for they march in dust. With axes they will come against her;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>like fellers of timber they will cut down her groves, saith the Lord. Because she would not be assimilated. Because she increaseth more than locusts which are innumerable;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the daughter of Egypt is put to shame: she is delivered into the hands of a people from the north.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Behold I will punish her son Ammon in the person of Pharao, and in the persons of them who trusted in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But thou Jacob my servant be not afraid; and thou Israel be not dismayed. For behold I will save thee from afar and thy seed from their captivity. And Jacob shall return and enjoy rest and sleep; and there shall be none to discompose him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Fear not, my servant Jacob, saith the Lord, since I am with thee. This fearless and luxurious one is delivered up, for I will make an end of every nation to which I have driven thee; But of thee I will not make an entire end. But I will correct thee for judgment and not suffer thee to go unpunished.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="47">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Concerning the Philistines,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, Behold waters are coming from the north, and they shall become an overwhelming flood, and shall overwhelm the land and the fulness thereof; the cities and them who dwell therein: and the men shall utter the scream of distress, and all the inhabitants of the land, a doleful cry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>At the sound of his impetuous onset; at the armour of his infantry; at the rushing of his chariots; the rumbling of his wheels; fathers looked not back on their children, by reason of the feebleness of their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>In the day which is coming to destroy all the Philistines I will destroy also Tyre and Sidon and all the residue of their help. Because the Lord will utterly destroy the remnants in the isles,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>baldness is come upon Gaza: Ascalon is overthrown and the remnant of Enakim.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>How long wilt thou hew down, sword of the Lord? How long will it be ere thou wilt rest? Return into thy scabbard, rest and be removed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>How can it rest when the Lord hath given it a charge against Ascalon and the cities on the sea coast and to be lifted up against them whom remain?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="48">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Respecting Moab, Thus said the Lord, Alas! for Nabo; for it is destroyed. Kariathaim is taken. Amath and Agath are put to shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>There is no more a cure for Moab; a boasting in Esebon. He hath devised evils against her. We have cut her off from being a nation and she shall go to rest. Behind thee the sword shall stalk on.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Because there is a sound of screaming from Oronaim; destruction and great tribulation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Moab is trodden down. Despatch news to Zogora that Aloth is filled with lamentation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>she will go up weeping by the way of Oronaim. You have heard the scream of distress;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>flee and save your lives; and you shall be like a wild ass in the desert.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Seeing thou hast trusted in thy fortifications; therefore thou shalt be taken; and Chamos shall go into banishment, and his priests and his chiefs with him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and destruction shall come on every city, none shall escape. The vale also shall be destroyed and the plain wasted as the Lord hath said.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Set up marks for Moab; for with destruction she shall be destroyed; and all her cities shall be for desolation. Whence can she have an inhabitant?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He is cursed who doth the work of the Lord negligently, withholding his sword from blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Moab enjoyed rest from his youth and trusted in his glory; he hath not been decanted from vessel to vessel; and into banishment he hath never gone. Therefore his taste remaineth in him and his flavour is not lost:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore behold the days are coming saith the Lord, when I will send decanters and they shall decant him; and they shall break his vessels and cut to pieces his drinking horns;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and Moab shall be put to shame for Chamos, as the house of Israel were for Baithel their confidence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>How can ye who have put confidence in them, say, We are strong, and a man mighty for feats of war.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Moab is destroyed with his cities; and his chosen men are gone down to slaughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The day of Moab is near at hand, and with speed his calamity is approaching.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Shake your heads for him, all ye around him; pronounce his name, all of you, say, How the beautiful sceptre is broken! the sceptre of majesty</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I Come down from glory and sit low in mire. Daibon shall be trampled down because Moab is destroyed. The demolisher of thy strong hold is come up against thee. Stand by the way side and take a view,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>inhabitant of Aroer! ask him who is fleeing and making escape, and say, What is the news?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Moab is put to shame; for he is utterly discomfited. Raise the mournful cry and scream; proclaim in Arnon, that Moab is destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Judgment is indeed coming on the land of Misor, upon Chalon, and Kephas, and Mophas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and on Daibon, and on Nabo, and on the house of Daithlathaim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and on Kariathaim, and on the house of Gaimol, and on the house of Maon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and on Karioth, and on Bosor, and on all the cities of Moab far and near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The horn of Moab is hacked to pieces, and his prowess is broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Make him drunk. Because he magnified himself against the Lord, he will therefore clap with his hand at Moab that he may be an object of derision;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for was not Israel an object of mirth to thee and found among thy stolen goods, because thou didst fight against him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The inhabitants of Moab have left their cities and made their abode among rocks. They were like pigeons nestling in rocks at the mouth of a cave.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>I have heard indeed of the pride of Moab: he was very proud; and of his haughtiness; his heart was elated.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But as for me I know his works: is not this his desert? Hath he not acted thus?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore raise on all sides the mournful cry for Moab; scream for the men of Keiradas-anchmon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>With the wailing of Jazer I will wail for thee, vine of Aserema. Thy branches extended to the sea; they reached to the cities of Jazer. When thy fruit was ripe; destruction came upon thy grape gatherers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Joy and gladness were snatched from Moab, when the vine was in thy lakes. In the morning there was no treading, and in the evening no shouts of joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>At the scream of Esebon which reached to Aitam, their cities from Zogar to Oroaim uttered their voice, and spread the news with an alarm. Because the water of Nebrin also shall be dried up;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>therefore I will destroy Moab, saith the Lord, when he is going up to the altar and burning incense to his gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For this let the heart of Moab groan like drone pipes. Let my heart sound like a drone for the men of Keiradas. Because all that every man had procured is utterly destroyed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>let them every where shave the whole head; and let the whole beard be shaven and all hands gashed; and let there be sackcloth on every loin</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and on all the house tops of Moab and in every street: for I have broken him, saith the Lord, like a vessel that is useless.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>How did he deprecate! How did Moab turn his back! Moab was ashamed and became a subject of laughter and derision to all around.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For thus said the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Karioth is taken and the strong holds are surprised;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and Moab shall be destroyed from being a multitude. Because he magnified himself against the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>a trap, a scare-net and a pit are prepared for thee, inhabitant of Moab!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>He who fleeth from the scare-net shall fall into the pit; and he who getteth up out of the pit shall be caught in the trap. For I will bring these things on Moab in the year of their visitation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="49">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Respecting the children of Ammon. THUS said the Lord, Hath Israel no sons? or have they no heir? Why then hath Melchol taken possession of Galaad? Shall his people dwell in their cities?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For this cause behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, when I will cause the tumult of battles against Rabbath to be heard; and they shall be for desolation and destruction; and her altars shall be consumed with fire; and Israel shall assume his government.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Raise the mournful cry, Esebon, for Gai is destroyed. Scream, ye daughters of Rabbath; gird on sackcloth and mourn; for Melchol shall go into banishment and his priests and his chiefs with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>What! are you exulting with joy in the vales of Enakim! daughter of wantonness who trustest in thy treasures: who sayest, Who shall come against me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Behold I am bringing terror against thee, said the Lord, from every neighbour around thee: and you shall be scattered every one before it; and there shall be none to collect you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Respecting Idumea. THUS said the Lord, There is no more any wisdom in Thaiman. Counsel is perished from the prudent. Wisdom is fled from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Their place hath been led into error. O inhabitants of Daidan! retire to a deep settlement for he hath brought on calamities. I brought them on him at the time when I visited him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Because grape gatherers are come, who will not leave thee a gleaning. Like thieves by night they will lay to their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Because I plundered Esau and discovered their hidden stores; They could not be concealed, they were destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>By means of the hand of his brother my neighbour, there is indeed no place for thine orphan to be left that it may live. But I will cause it to live. In me the widows have trusted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Because they (said the Lord) who had a law not to drink the cup, drank it; thou therefore shalt not escape unpunished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For by myself I have sworn saith the Lord, thou shalt be a desolation and a reproach and a curse in this country and all its cities shall be perpetual wastes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have heard a report from the Lord. He hath sent messengers to the nations, saying assemble and come against her; arise for battle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I have made thee little among the nations, very contemptible among men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thine insolency hath entrapped thee; the wantonness of thy heart destroyed the holes of rocks. It took possession of a strong, lofty mountain. Because like an eagle thou hast built thy nest high; thence I will pull thee down:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and Idumea shall be a desolation. Every passenger shall express for it the sound of pity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>As in the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorra and the neighbouring cities, said the Lord Almighty, no man shall abide there, nor shall a son of man dwell there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Behold they shall be like the lion which must go up from the swelling of Jordan to Aitham. For I will speedily drive them from that place. Therefore set ye chosen warriors against it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Because who is like me? Or who can withstand me? And who is the shepherd who can stand before me? Therefore hear the counsel of the Lord which he hath taken against Idumea, and the determination he hath come to against the inhabitants of Thaiman: Let all but the tenderest of the flock be destroyed; let all but a resting place for them be made a desolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>At the sound of their fall the earth trembled, so that the roaring of the sea was not heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Behold he will take a view like an eagle, and expand his wings against her fortifications; and the heart of the valiant men of Idumea shall be on that day like the heart of a woman in travail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Respecting Damascus. EMATH and Arphath are overwhelmed in shame. Because they heard bad news they were confounded; they boiled with rage; they cannot take rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Damascus is enervated. She turned to flee: terror seized her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>How can it be otherwise? She forsook my city. Did they regard a single village?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Therefore thy young men shall fall in thy streets; and all thy valiant warriors shall fall, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And I will kindle a fire in the wall of Damascus and it shall consume the palaces of Son of Ader.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Respecting Kedar the queen of the court, which Nabuchodlonosar king of Babylon smote. THUS said the Lord; arise and go up against Kedar; and glut the sons of Kedem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Let them seize their tents and their flocks: let them take for themselves their clothing, all their utensils and their camels: and call ye for destruction against all them around.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Flee, retire very deep to a settlement, inhabitants at the court. For against you the king of Babylon hath taken counsel, and hath come to a determination, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Arise and go up against a wealthy nation dwelling at ease who have neither gates nor bars nor bolts; who dwell alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Let their camels be for a prey and the multitude of their cattle for slaughter. For I will winnow with every wind them who have their foreheads shaven and from all sides I will bring destruction on them, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the court shall be a lodging place for ostriches and a waste forever. No man shall abide there, nor shall a son of man there make his dwelling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>In the beginning of the reign of king Sedekias came this word concerning Ailam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, The bow of Ailam is broken, the instrument of his dominion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And I will bring upon Ailam four winds from the four quarters of heaven and I will scatter them with these winds; so that there shall not be a nation to which the outcasts of Ailam shall not come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And I will terrify them before their enemies who seek their lives; and bring against them according to the fury of my wrath, and send against them my sword, until it utterly consume them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And I will set my throne in Ailam and drive thence kings and nobles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But it shall come to pass at the last of these days I will bring back the captivity of Ailam, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="50">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A word of the Lord which he spake against Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Proclaim among the nations, publish and conceal not; say, Babylon is taken; Bel is confounded; the fearless, the luxurious Mairodach is delivered up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For a nation is gone up against her from the north, which will make her land a desolation, so that none shall dwell therein, neither man nor beast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>In those days, even at that time, shall come up the children of Israel, they and the children of Juda together: walking slow and weeping they will march on seeking the Lord their God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They will ask the way to Zion; for thitherward they will set their face; and they will come and flee to the Lord their God; for the everlasting covenant shall not be forgotten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>My people have been lost sheep. Their shepherds caused them to stray. On the mountains they caused them to wander. From mountain to hill they roamed. They forgot their place of rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>All that found them devoured them. Their enemies said, Let us not spare them because they sinned against the Lord. He who gathered their fathers hath a pasture of righteousness:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>remove out of Babylon and from the country of the Chaldeans, and go out and be like dragons before sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For Lo! I am raising up against Babylon assemblies of nations from the north; and they shall be drawn up in array against her. Thence one shall be taken like the dart of a skilful warrior which shall not rebound in vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So Chaldea shall be for a prey. All that plunder it shall be satisfied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Because you rejoiced and triumphed when you were plundering my heritage; because you frisked about like calves in a pasture, and brandished your horns like bulls;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>your mother shall be greatly ashamed: she who brought you forth for prosperity shall be confounded. Being the hindmost of nations,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>a desert because of the wrath of the Lord, she shall not be inhabited; but shall be entirely a desolation. Sorrow will cover the countenance of all who travel through Babylon; and at all their calamity they will express pity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Set yourselves in array all around against Babylon. All ye who bend the bow shoot at her: spare not your arrows,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>you must needs subdue her. Her hands are weakened; her bulwarks have fallen, and her wall is undermined. Because it is a vengeance from the Lord; execute vengeance on her. As she hath done, do ye to her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Destroy utterly the seed of Babylon, him who handleth the sickle in harvest. Let them return from the face of the Grecian sword, every one to his own people; and let every one flee to his own land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Israel was a wandering sheep. Lions scared him away. The first who devoured him was the king of Assur, and this last, the king of Babylon gnawed his bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold I will execute vengeance on the king of Babylon and his land as I executed vengeance on the king of Assyria.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I will bring back Israel to his pasture, and he shall feed on Carmel, and on mount Ephraim, and on Galaad; and his soul shall be satisfied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In those days and at that time, search shall be made for the iniquity of Israel; but none shall remain: and for the sins of Juda; but none shall be found. For I will be merciful to them who are left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>With respect to this land, saith the Lord. Go up with bitterness against it and against them who dwell in it; take vengeance, sword, and destroy utterly; saith the Lord, and do according to all that I command thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A sound of battle and great distress in the land of the Chaldeans!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>How the hammer of the whole earth is broken and dashed to pieces! How Babylon is become a desolation among the nations!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>They will come upon thee and thou shalt not know; like Babylon itself and thou shalt be taken. Thou art found out and taken, because thou didst set thyself against the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The Lord hath opened his arsenal and brought out the instruments of his wrath; because the Lord God hath a work to perform in the land of the Chaldeans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Because her time is come; open ye her treasuries, search her like a cave; and destroy her utterly. Let not a remnant of her be left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Lay waste all her fruits and let them go down to destruction. Alas for them; for their day is come and the time of their visitation!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Hark! a sound of men fleeing and escaping out of the land of Babylon to inform Sion of the vengeance of the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Issue these orders to many against Babylon; to every one bending a bow; Encamp against her round about; let none escape out of her. Render to her according to her works; according to all that she hath done, do ye to her. Because she set herself against the Lord, the holy God of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>therefore her young men shall fall in her streets and all her mighty warriors shall be laid low, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Behold I am against thee, thou essence of haughtiness, saith the Lord. Because thy day is come and the time of thy punishment;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>therefore thy haughtiness shall be abated and fall, and none shall continue to support it. For I will kindle a fire in her forest, which shall devour all around her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, The children of Israel and the children of Juda have both been oppressed; all who captivated them tyrannised over them. Because they refused to let them go;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>therefore their Redeemer; the Mighty One, whose name is The Lord Almighty will plead their cause with their adversaries. In order that he may remove this land out of the way he will sharpen for the inhabitants of Babylon</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>a sword against the Chaldeans and against the inhabitants of Babylon; and against her grandees and against her counsellors;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>a sword against her warriors and they shall be destroyed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>a sword against their horses and against their chariots; a sword against their warriors and the mixed multitude in the midst of her and they shall be like women; a sword against her treasures; and they shall be rifled;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>against them who are on her waters and they shall be exposed to shame. Because it is a land of the graven images and it was in these islands where they boasted;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>therefore imageries shall dwell in those islands and in her shall dwell the daughters of Sirens and she shall never more be inhabited.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>As God overthrew Sodom and Gomorra and the neighbouring cities, said the Lord, no man shall dwell there, nor shall a son of man make his abode there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Behold a people is coming from the north, even a mighty nation, and many kings shall be roused up from the extremity of the earth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>handling the bow and sword. They are haughty and will shew no mercy: their voice will roar like the sea. On horses they will come prancing, in array like fire, for battle against thee, daughter of Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>The king of Babylon heard the report of them and his hands were enfeebled; anguish seized him like the pangs of a woman in travail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Behold he will be like the lion which must go up from the swelling of Jordan to Gaitham, for I will speedily drive men from her, and set every youth against her: for who is like me and who can withstand me? And who is the shepherd who can stand before me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Therefore hear the counsel which the Lord hath taken against Babylon; and the determination he is come to against the Chaldean inhabitants, let all but the lambs of the flock be destroyed; let all but a pasture for them be made a desolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>For at the sound of the capture of Babylon the earth shall be shaken, and a scream shall be heard among the nations.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="51">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thus said the Lord. Behold against Babylon and against the Chaldean inhabitants I am raising up a hot destroying wind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And against Babylon I will send scorners who will treat her with scorn and waste her land. Woe shall surround Babylon on all sides on the day of her affliction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Let him, who bendeth the bow, bend it; and him, who hath armour put it on; shew no compassion to her youths, and destroy utterly all her host.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And let the wounded fall in the land of the Chaldeans, and those who are pierced through, fall in her streets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Since Israel and Juda are not quite forsaken by their God, the Lord Almighty, on account of their land being filled with iniquity by reason of the sanctuaries of Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>flee out of Babylon and save every one his life and be not involved, in her iniquity. For the time of her punishment is come from the Lord, and he is rendering to her a recompence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Babylon was a golden cup in the hand of the Lord, furnishing a plentiful draught to all the nations. Of her wine the nations drank, therefore they reeled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But Babylon is suddenly fallen and broken. Utter a lamentation for her. Get balm for her deadly wound; perhaps she may be cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>We have administered, medicines to Babylon, but she is not healed. Let us leave her and depart every one to his own land: for her judgment hath reached to heaven and mounted up to the stars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The Lord hath published his decree. Come let us proclaim in Sion the works of the Lord our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Prepare the arrows. Fill the quivers. The Lord hath stirred up the spirit of the king of the Medes. For his wrath is against Babylon to destroy her utterly. For it is the vengeance of the Lord; the avengement of his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>On the walls of Babylon erect a standard; set the watch; have arms ready. Because the Lord hath undertaken; therefore he will accomplish what he hath spoken against the inhabitants of Babylon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>against them who dwell on many waters, and against the multitude of her treasures. Thine end is come, it is come indeed into thy bowels:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>for the Lord hath sworn by his arm, I will fill thee with men as with locusts; and they who go down shall utter a sound against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The Lord is he who made the earth by his power, who fitted up the world by his wisdom. By his understanding he stretched out the heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>At his voice there was in heaven a sound of water, and he brought up clouds from the extremity of the earth. He made the lightning for rain and brought out light from his treasuries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Every man by knowledge became stupefied, every melter of gold was put to shame for his graven images; for their molten images were falsehoods, there is no breath in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>They are works of vanity and objects of derision. In the time of their visitation they shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The portion of Jacob is not such as these, for he who formed all things is his inheritance: his name is the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thou art dispersing for me implements of war, but in thee I will disperse nations and remove kings out of thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and in thee I will disperse the horse and his rider;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and in thee I will disperse chariots and charioteers; and in thee I will disperse the youth and the virgin; and in thee I will disperse the husband and the wife;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and in thee I will disperse the shepherd and the flock; and in thee I will disperse the husbandman and his husbandry; and in thee I will disperse the generals and leaders of armies,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and retribute to Babylon and all the Chaldean inhabitants all the evils which they have done to Sion in your sight, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Behold I am against thee, corrupted mountain which corruptest the whole earth, and I will stretch out my hand against thee and roll thee down on rocks; and I will make thee like a mountain which hath been burned to ashes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>so that they shall not take of thee a stone for a corner nor a stone for a foundation. For thou shalt be a desolation for ever, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Erect a standard in the land. Sound a trumpet among the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Prepare the nations against her. Issue orders against her. Carry them, kings, from me even to the Achanazeans. Erect towers against her. Bring up against her, cavalry like a multitude of locusts. Bring up against her nations, the king of the Medes and of the whole earth; his generals and all the leaders of his army.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The earth was in commotion and oppressed with toil, because the determination of the Lord against Babylon had roused it, to make the land of Babylon a desolation and uninhabitable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The warriors of Babylon declined to fight. They will sit still there during a siege. Their mighty power is broken. They are become like women. Her habitations are burned with fire. Her bars are broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Courier will run to meet courier and messenger to meet messenger to tell the king of Babylon that his city is taken;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>that the passages one after another are forced; that the barriers are burned with fire and his warriors are fleeing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>For thus said the Lord, the houses of the king of Babylon shall be threshed like a floor full of ripe grain. Yet a little while and her harvest will come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>She devoured me; she chewed me to pieces: thick darkness overwhelmed me. Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon swallowed me down; like a dragon he tilled his belly with my dainties. They have cast me up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Let the inhabitants of Sion say, My troubles and my miseries be upon Babylon! and let Jerusalem say, My blood be upon the Chaldean inhabitants!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For this cause, thus saith the Lord, Behold I will judge thine adversary and avenge thy cause; and I will drain off her sea and make her fountain dry,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and Babylon shall be a desolation and shall not be inhabited.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Because they roused together like lions and like lions' whelps;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>in their heat I will give them a draught and make them drunk; that they may be stupefied and sleep a perpetual sleep and never awake, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Down, down with them, like lambs to slaughter and like rams and he goats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>How the boast of the whole earth is hunted and taken! how Babylon has become a desolation among the nations!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>The sea came up against Babylon with its roaring waves, and she is overwhelmed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Her cities are become like a land without water, an untrodden desert. Not an individual can dwell there: nor can a son of man lodge in her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>I will indeed punish Babylon and bring forth out of her mouth what she hath swallowed. And the nations shall no more be gathered together to her;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>nor shall the victims of the whole earth fall by Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Away from her country, ye who have escaped; and tarry not; ye who are far off, remember the Lord; and let Jerusalem recur to your mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>We are ashamed; because we have heard our reproach, disgrace hath covered our face; strangers have entered our sanctuaries; into the house of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Therefore behold the days are coming, saith the Lord, when I will execute vengeance on her graven images, and among all them her wounded shall fall in that land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>For though Babylon should mount up to heaven; though she fortify her walls with all her might, from me shall come forth those who shall destroy her, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>A sound of screaming in Babylon! and great destruction in the land of the Chaldeans!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>For the Lord hath utterly destroyed Babylon, and put an end to her din, which was like the sound of great waters. Her din he hath given up to destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>For misery is come upon Babylon. Her warriors are taken. Their bow is confounded; for God rendereth them retribution.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>The Lord rendereth them retribution; and he will make utterly drunk her leaders and her wise men and her generals, saith the king whose name is The Lord Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord, The wall of Babylon was made broad; It shall be totally demolished and her lofty gates shall be burned with fire; and the peoples shall not labour in vain, though the nations may at first fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>The word which the Lord commanded Jeremias the prophet to deliver to Saraias son of Nerias son of Maasias when he was going from Sedekias king of Juda to Babylon in the fourth year of his reign. Now Saraias had the charge of the homage gifts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>When Jeremias had written in a book all the evils which were to come upon Babylon, even all the words above written against Babylon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>Jeremias said to Saraias; When thou art come to Babylon and shalt have seen and read all these words,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>then thou shalt say, O Lord, Lord, thou hast spoken against this place, that thou wilt destroy it utterly, so that none shall dwell therein, neither man nor beast; for it shall be a desolation forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>And when thou hast finished reading the book, then thou shalt tye a stone to it and throw it into the midst of the Euphrates,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>and say, So shall Babylon sink and rise no more by reason of the evils which I bring upon it.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="52">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Sedekias was twenty one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem and his mother's name was Ameital. She was a daughter of Jeremias of Lobena.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And it came to pass in the ninth year of his reign in the fifth month, on the tenth of the month, Nabuchodonosar king of Babylon, came with his whole army against Jerusalem, and they besieged it and built a wall around it of square stones,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and the city was besieged until the eleventh year of king Sedekias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>On the ninth day of the; month there was a grievous famine in the city and there was no bread for the people of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When a breach was made into the city, all the men who were warriors went out by night by the way of the gate between the outer and the inner wall, which was along the king's garden, (though the Chaldeans were all around the city;) and took the road to Araba.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the army of the Chaldeans pursued the king and overtook him on the borders of Jericho. And all his servants being dispersed from him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>they took the king and carried him to the king of Babylon at Deblatha, who passed sentence on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the king of Babylon slew the sons of Sedekias before his eyes. He slew also all the chiefs of Juda at Deblatha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then he put out the eyes of Sedekias and bound him with chains. And the king of Babylon led him to Babylon and committed him to the slave prison where he continued till the day of his death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And on the fifth month on the tenth of the month Nabouzardan the chief cook, who stood in the presence of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and burned the house of the Lord and the king's house. He burned also with fire all the public buildings of the city and every stately house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the army of the Chaldeans which was with the chief cook demolished all the wall of Jerusalem round about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But the chief cook left the remains of the people for vine dressers and husbandmen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The Chaldeans also broke to pieces the pillars of brass which were in the house of the Lord and the bases and the sea of brass which was in the house of the Lord, and took the brass and carried it to Babylon with the crown,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and the cups and the flesh forks and all the utensils of brass with which they sacrificed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the Apphoths and the Masmaroths and the oil vessels and the candlesticks and the censers and the cups: those which were of gold, or gilded, and those which were of silver, or plated, the chief cook took.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>As for the two pillars and the sea and the twelve oxen of brass under the sea, which king Solomon had made for the house of the Lord, there was no weighing the brass thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The height of each of the pillars was thirty five cubits and a fillet of twelve cubits encircled it, the thickness of which was four fingers all around.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And there was a chapiter of brass on each of them of the height of five cubits with a ball on the top of each and a piece of net work and pomegranates around on each chapiter; all of brass; eight pomegranates to a cubit for the twelve cubits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So that there were ninety six pomegranates on the sides and all the pomegranates on the net work round about were one hundred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And the chief cook took the chief priest, and the priest who was second to him, and the three who guarded the way;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and a eunuch who was over the men of war, and seven men of renown who attended in the king's presence, who were found in the city, and the scribe of the armies, who mustered the people of the land; and sixty chief men, of the people of the country, who were found in the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>These Nabuzardan the chief cook, took and brought to the king of Babylon at Deblatha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the king of Babylon slew them at Deblatha in the land of Aimath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And it came to pass in the thirty seventh year of the captivity of Jechonias king of Juda, in the twelfth month, on the twenty fourth of the month, Oulaimadachar king of Babylon, in the first year of his reign, took and raised up the head of Jechonias king of Juda, and caused him to be shaven and released him from the prison, in which he was confined,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and spoke kindly to him and set his seat above the kings, who were with him in Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And changed his prison dress, and caused him to eat in his presence, all the days of his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And he had a portion continually given to him, day by day, from the king of Babylon, to the day of his death.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>