<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A word of the Lord which came to Joel son of Bathuel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear these things ye elders! And give ear all ye inhabitants of the land! Have such things happened in your days, or in the days of your fathers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Of these things give an account to your children; and let your children tell their children; and their children, another generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The leavings of the palmer Worm have been devoured by the grasshopper, and the leavings of the grasshopper have been devoured by the locust. And the mildew hath consumed what the locust left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Awake ye drunkards, from your wine and weep. Sing a mournful song all ye who drink wine to drunkenness; for joy and gladness are gone from your mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For against my land a nation is come up, strong and innumerable. Their teeth are the teeth of lions; and their grinders, those of a young lion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They have made my vineyard a desolation; and my fig orchards, a waste. They have searched it thoroughly and it is gone to wreck; they have made the branches thereof white.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Let thy song of Woe before me be more plaintive than that of a bride clothed with sackcloth for the husband of her youth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Sacrifice and libation are taken away from the house of the Lord. Mourn ye priests, who minister at the Lord's altar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>because the fields are wasted. Let the land mourn: because the corn hath suffered grievously: wine is dried away; oil is diminished;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>husbandmen are parched up: Mourn, ye farms, for the wheat and barley, because the harvester is perished from the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The vines are withered and the fig trees are diminished; peach and palm and citron trees and all the trees of the field are withered. Because the children of men are ashamed of joy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>gird yourselves, ye priests, and lament bitterly: sing the song of Woe, ye who minister at the altar; go in and sleep in sackcloth, ye ministers of God. Because sacrifice and libation are withheld from the house of your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Set apart a fast; proclaim a solemn service; assemble the elders; all the inhabitants of the land, to the house of your God, and cry to the Lord incessantly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Ah me! Ah me! Ah me! for the day. For the day of the Lord is at hand; and it will come like destruction on destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Food is utterly destroyed before your eyes; joy and gladness, from the house of your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The heifers startled at their stalls. Stores are exhausted; wine lakes are gone to ruin, as the corn is blasted,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>what shall we substitute for ourselves? The herds of cattle uttered mournful lowings, because there was no pasture for them; and the flocks of sheep are utterly destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>To thee, Lord, let me cry for myself, because a fire hath consumed the pleasant places of the wilderness, and a flame hath blasted all the trees of the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>To thee indeed the cattle in the plain have looked up, because the springs of water are quite dry, and a fire hath devoured the pleasant places of the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Blow the trumpet in Sion; make proclamation on my holy mountain. And let all the inhabitants of the land be alarmed. For the day of the Lord is approaching; for it is near;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>a day of darkness and gloom; a day of clouds and thick darkness. Like dawn, there shall be poured out on the mountains a people numerous and powerful, the like of them hath never been, nor shall be any more to the years of all generations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Before them is a kindling fire, and all behind them a glowing flame. Before them the land is like a pleasure garden, and behind them, a scene of desolation: and there is none who can escape them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Their appearance is like the appearance of horses; and like horsemen they can pursue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>With a noise like that of chariots they will bound over the tops of mountains and their noise is like that of a flaming fire consuming stubble. They are like a people numerous and powerful, arrayed for battle</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>At their presence peoples will be appalled and every face covered with blackness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They can run like warriors and like mighty warriors scale walls; and every one will march in his own path. They will not alter their lines of march;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>nor will any one separate from his comrade. They will march loaded with their arms, and though they fall on their weapons they shall not be killed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They will surprise the city and run upon the walls; they will climb up the houses and enter at windows like thieves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>At their presence the earth will be confounded and the heaven shaken, and the sun and the moon will be darkened, and the stars will withdraw their refulgence,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and the Lord will utter his voice before his army. Because the circuit of his camp is very large; because the operation of his words is irresistible; because the day of the Lord is great, extremely awful; who therefore shall be able to abide it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now therefore saith the Lord your God, turn to me with your whole heart, and with fasting and with weeping and with mourning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Rend your hearts and not your garments, and turn to the Lord your God; for he is gracious and merciful, long suffering and full of compassion, and relenteth at evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Who knoweth but he will turn and relent, and leave behind him a blessing and a sacrifice and a libation for the Lord your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Sound the trumpet in Sion. Appoint a fast; proclaim a solemn act of worship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Assemble the people; sanctify the congregation; choose elders. Bring together infants at the breast. Let the bridegroom come forth from his chamber and the bride from her wardrobe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>At the foot of the altar, let the priests who minister to the Lord, weep, and say, Spare, Lord, thy people; and give not up thy heritage to reproach; for the nations to rule over them. That they may not say among the nations, Where is their God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>the Lord was indeed jealous for his land and spared his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the Lord answered and said to his people, Behold I will send you corn and wine and oil, and with them you shall be plentifully supplied. And I will no more make you a reproach among the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>This army from the north I will remove from you, and drive it to a land without water, and destroy its front in the first and its rear in the last sea: and its smell shall come up and its stench shall ascend, because it hath magnified its works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Take courage, land, rejoice and be glad; for it is the Lord who made it great to perform exploits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Take courage, beasts of the field; for the plains of the wilderness are in bloom. Because the trees have yielded their fruit; the fig tree and the vine have put forth their strength;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>rejoice therefore, ye children of Sion and exult in the Lord your God: for he hath given you this food for righteousness, and he will distil upon you the former and the latter rain as heretofore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And your threshing floors shall be filled with corn, and your vats shall overflow with wine and oil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I will indeed make you compensation for what hath been devoured by the grasshopper and the locust, the palmer Worm and the mildew; that great army of mine which I sent against you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And you shall eat plentifully and be satisfied, and shall praise the name of the Lord your God, who hath dealt wonderfully with you; and my people shall never be put to shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And you shall know that I am in the midst of Israel, and that I the Lord am your God and besides me there is no other; and my people shall never be put to shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And it shall come to pass after these things that I will pour out a portion of my spirit on all flesh, and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy; and your old men shall dream dreams; and your young men shall see visions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And on my servants and on my hand maids in those days I will pour out a portion of my spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And I will exhibit wonders in heaven and on the earth, blood and fire and smoky vapour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the coming of the great and illustrious day of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But whoever will call on the name of the Lord shall be saved; for on mount Sion and in Jerusalem shall be the Saviour, as the Lord hath said, and the publishers of glad tidings, whom the Lord hath called.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Because, lo! Here I am in those days and at that time when I have brought back the captivity of Juda and Jerusalem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and I will gather all the nations and bring them down to the valley of Josaphat and plead with them there for my people and my heritage, Israel, who have been scattered among the nations. They indeed divided my land among themselves</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and cast lots for my people; they gave my boys to harlots and sold my girls for wine and drank it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now what have you, Tyre and Sidon and all Galilee of foreign tribes, to do with me? Are you rendering me a retribution? Or are you venting your spite against me? On your heads I will severely and speedily return your retribution.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Because you have taken my silver and my gold, and carried my choicest goods into your temples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and sold the sons of Juda and the sons of Jerusalem to the Greeks, that you might remove them far from their borders;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore behold I will raise them up from the places whither you sold them, and return your retribution on your heads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And I will deliver your sons and your daughters into the hands of the sons of Juda; that they may sell them as captives to a far distant nation. Because the Lord hath spoken,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>proclaim these things among the nations. Declare war: rouse the warriors: assemble and march up, all ye men of war.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Beat your ploughshares into swords and your pruning hooks into spears. Let the weak say, I am strong.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Assemble and come all ye nations around and be there gathered together. Let the man of peace become a soldier.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let all the nations be roused and come up to the valley of Josaphat; for there I will sit to judge all the nations around.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Put to the sickles, for the harvest is come; go in and tread for the vat is full. Cause the wine lakes to overflow; for their wicked deeds have been multiplied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Screams resound in the valley of Judgment! Because the day of the Lord in the valley of Judgment is at hand</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The sun and the moon shall be obscured in darkness; and the stars shall withdraw their refulgence;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and the Lord will utter a shout from Sion, and from Jerusalem he will send forth his voice; and the heaven and the earth shall be shaken: but the Lord will spare his people and strengthen the sons of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And ye shall know that I am the Lord your God, who dwell in Sion my holy mountain, and Jerusalem shall be holy and strangers shall no more pass through it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day, that the mountains shall distil new wine; and the hills shall send forth streams of milk; and all the fountains of Juda shall pour out water; and a fountain shall issue from the house of the Lord, which shall water the valley of bulrushes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Egypt shall be a desolation, and Idumea a scene of destruction, for the injuries done to the children of Juda; for their having shed innocent blood in their land:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but Judea shall be inhabited for ever, and Jerusalem for generations of generations:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and I will make inquisition for their blood, and will not pass it over unrevenged: and the Lord will dwell in Sion.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>