<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When a word of the Lord came to Jonas the son of Amathi, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Arise and go to Ninive that great city and proclaim in it, That the cry of its wickedness is come up to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Jonas arose to flee to Tharsis from the presence of the Lord, and went down to Joppa, and finding a ship bound to Tharsis, he paid his fare and went on board with a design to sail with them to Tharsis, from the presence of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But the Lord raised a wind on the sea, and there was a great tempest in the sea, so that the ship was in danger of foundering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the mariners were terrified, and cried every one to his god, and threw overboard some of the cargo, to lighten the vessel. Now Jonas had gone down into the ship's hold, and was asleep and snoring.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the master of the ship came to him and said to him, What! art thou snoring? Arise and call on thy God, that thy God may save us, and that we may not perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then they said, one to another, Come let us cast lots and know on whose account this calamity is come on us. So they cast lots, and the lot fell upon Jonas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Whereupon they said to him, Tell us. What is thy business? And whence comest thou? And of what country, and of what people art thou?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he said to them, I am a servant of the Lord; and I worship the Lord God of heaven, who made the sea and the dry land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon this the men were greatly terrified and said to him, Why hast thou done this? (For the men knew that he was fleeing from the presence of the Lord, for he had told them.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then they said to him, What shall we do to thee that the sea may be calmed for us? For the sea rolled and grew more and more tempestuous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Jonas said to them, Take me up and throw me into the sea, and the sea will be calm for you; for I know that on my account this great tempest is come upon you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When the men had laboured hard to reach land, but could not because the sea ran high, and grew more tempestuous against them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>then they cried to the Lord and said, Forbid it, Lord, that we perish, for the life of this man, and bring not upon us innocent blood; for thou, Lord, hast done according to thy pleasure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then they took Jonas and cast him into the sea. Whereupon from raging the sea became still.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the men feared the Lord exceedingly, and offered a sacrifice to the Lord and made vows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now the Lord had commanded a great fish to swallow Jonas, so Jonas was three days and three nights, in the belly of the fish.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when out of the belly of the great fish, Jonas prayed to the Lord his God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and said, In my affliction I cried to the Lord my God, and he hearkened to me: thou didst hear my cry from the womb of Hades: thou didst hearken to my prayer:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>thou hast cast me into the depths of the heart of the sea. When streams encompassed me; all thy billows and thy waves passed over me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then I said, I am cast out from thy sight; nevertheless I will continue to look towards thy holy temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The water was poured around me to my soul; and the lowest abyss encompassed me; my head hath gone down into the clefts of mountains;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I have gone down to a land, the bars of which are everlastingly fixed: let my soul now, corrupted as it is, ascend, Lord, my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When my soul was fainting I remembered the Lord; let my prayer now come to thee into thy holy temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>They who worship vanities and lies have forsaken their mercy:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But I will sacrifice to thee with the voice of praise and thanksgiving. I will pay thee what I have vowed to the Lord for my deliverance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon this a command was given by the Lord to the fish, and it cast forth Jonas upon the dry ground.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then a word of the Lord came to Jonas a second time saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Arise and go to Ninive that great city, and proclaim in it according to the former proclamation which I spoke to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So Jonas arose and went to Ninive as the Lord had spoken. Now Ninive was an exceeding great city, of about three days' journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And Jonas began at his entering the city, and for about one day's journey cried with a loud voice and said, Yet three days and Ninive shall be destroyed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the men of Ninive believed God and proclaimed a fast, and put on sackcloth from the greatest to the least.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>When the word reached the king of Ninive, he arose from his throne and stripped off his robes and clothed himself with sackcloth and sat in ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And proclamation was made and orders issued in Ninive from the king and from his nobles, saying, With regard to men and beasts, including herds and flocks, Let them not taste any thing; let them neither feed nor drink water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So both men and beasts were covered with sackcloth; and there was an incessant cry to God; and every one turned from his evil way, and from the wickedness of their hands, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Who knoweth but God will relent and turn away from his fierce wrath, so that we may not perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And God saw their works, that they turned from their evil ways. And God relented at the evil which he said he would do to them, and did it not.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Thereupon Jonas was exceedingly grieved and confounded,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he prayed to the Lord and said, Lord were not these my words, when I was yet in my own country? For which cause I attempted to flee to Tharsis. For I knew that thou art compassionate and merciful, long suffering and abundant in kindness and relentest at evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now, therefore, Sovereign Lord, take my life from me, for it is better for me to die than to live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the Lord said to Jonas, Art thou very sorry?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>(Now Jonas had gone out of the city and sat over against it, and had made for himself a booth and sat under it until he should see what would befal the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the Lord had given orders to a colocynthis, and it had sprung up over the head of Jonas to be a shade over his head to shade him on account of his sufferings; and Jonas was exceeding glad of the colocynthis.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But early the next morning God gave orders to a Worm and it smote the colocynthis and it withered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when the sun rose God ordered a burning wind to spring up and the sun beat upon Jonas' head so that he became fainty and abandoned himself to despair and said, It is better for me to die than to live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And God said to Jonas, Art thou very sorry) for the colocynthis. And he said I am sorry even to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thereupon the Lord said, Thou hast compassion for the colocynthis, for which thou hast not toiled and which thou hast not nourished, which sprang up in a night and perished in a night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And shall not I have compassion on Ninive this great city, in which there are more than one hundred and twenty thousand of the human species, who know not their right hand and their left; and also much cattle.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>