<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A word of the Lord came to Micah the Morasthite in the days of Joatham and Achaz and Ezekias kings of Juda; with regard to those things which he saw touching Samaria and touching Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear, O peoples, words! and let this land attend and all who are in it And let the Lord, Lord among you be a witness: the Lord from his holy temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For behold the Lord is coming forth from his place; and he will come down and walk on the heights of this land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and under him the mountains will tremble, and the vallies shall melt like wax before fire, and be like water rolling down a precipice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>All this is on account of the impiety of Jacob, and for the sin of the house of Israel. What is the impiety of Jacob? Is it not Samaria? And what is the sin of the house of Juda? Is it not Jerusalem?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore I will make Samaria like a hut of a field and like a plant of a vineyard, and I will drag the stones thereof into a ditch and lay her foundations bare.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And all her graven images shall be hacked to pieces; and all her earnings shall be burned with fire; and all her idols I will utterly destroy. Because from the earnings of fornication she collected, and from the earnings of fornication, amassed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>therefore she shall wail and utter lamentations: she shall walk barefoot and naked; she shall utter a wailing like that of jackals; and moanings like the daughters of the ostrich.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Because her wound is large; because it hath come even to Juda and reached the gate of my people, even to Jerusalem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>magnify not yourselves ye men of Gath, and ye Enakims, rebuild not from a house, in derision. According to your derision you shall sprinkle yourselves with dust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Sennaar, who dwelt at ease in her cities, went not forth to bewail a neighbouring house; from you she shall receive a painful wound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Who led the way to good for her who was dwelling in sorrows, because evils from the Lord, a sound of chariots and horsemen came down against the gates of Jerusalem?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Was it the inhabitant of Lachis? She is a leader to sin for the daughter of Sion. Because in thee have been found the impieties of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>therefore even to the inheritance of Gath he will give up idolatrous houses as abandoned. To the kings of Israel they were of no avail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>inhabitant of Lachis! until the true heirs shall be brought in; O! Odollam! until an inheritance, the glory of the daughter of Israel shall come,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>shave thy locks and make thyself bald for thy delicate children; lengthen out thy widowhood like an eagle, for they shall be carried from thee into captivity.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>They planned mischief; they contrived evils on their beds, and soon as it was day they executed them; for they did not lift up their hands to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>They coveted fields and plundered orphans and tyrannised over houses; they plundered a man and his household; a man and his inheritance;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>therefore thus saith the Lord, Behold against this tribe I am planning evils, from which you shall not withdraw your necks, nor walk erect suddenly. Because it is an evil time,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>a parable will in that day be taken up against you, and a song of lamentation will be sung, saying, With affliction we have been afflicted! the portion of my people hath been measured with a line, and there was none to hinder or turn it aside. Your fields have been parcelled out,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore there shall be none to stretch a line for thee by lot, in the congregation of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Weep not bitterly, nor let tears be shed for these things, for reproaches will not be cast off even by him who saith,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The house of Israel hath provoked to wrath the spirit of the Lord. Are not these his purposes? Are not his words good with him? Have these walked in a straight course?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Indeed this people of mine have openly risen up for enmity. In direct opposition to his peace they have even stripped off his skin, that the extreme horror of war might destroy hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The leaders of my people shall be hurled from their houses of pleasure; for their wicked devices they have been expelled; draw ye near to the everlasting mountains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Arise and depart, for this is not a rest for thee. By reason of impurity you are utterly corrupted:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>you have been put to flight when there was no pursuer: a spirit hath set up a lie: it hath dropped on thee for wine and plenty. Yet it shall come to pass that from a drop of this people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Jacob with all his sons shall be gathered together. With expectation I will expect the remnant of Israel. I will place together them who are about to return. Like sheep in distress, like a flock in their fold, they shall rush out from among men through a breach before them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They have broken through and passed the gate; they are gone through it and their king is gone out before them; and the Lord will be their leader,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and he will say, Hear these things ye children of the house of Jacob, and ye remnant of the house of Israel, is it not your business to know judgment?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As for them who hate good and seek evil, who tear off the skin from these and the flesh from their bones:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>as they have devoured the flesh of my people and have flayed off their skin from them; and have broken their bones and chopped them up, as flesh for a kettle and as pieces of meat for a pot:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>so they shall cry to the Lord but he will not hearken to them; but will turn away his face from them at that time, because by their devices they have committed evil against these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thus saith the Lord against the prophets who led my people astray, who gnash with their teeth and proclaim peace for them, though it was not put in their mouths; they have raised up war against them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore from vision you shall have night; and from prophesying you shall have darkness. And the sun shall set upon the prophets, and upon them the day shall darken:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the seers of dreams shall be put to shame; and the diviners shall be laughed to scorn, and reviled by all; for none will hearken to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>None but I can, by the spirit of the Lord, supply strength both of judgment and might to declare to Jacob his impiety and to Israel his sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Hear these things I beseech you, ye leaders of the house of Jacob, and ye remnant of the house of Israel, who abhor judgment and pervert all equity,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>who are building up Sion with blood and Jerusalem with injustice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Her rulers have judged for rewards; and her priests have given answers for hire; and her prophets have prophesied for silver, without waiting for the Lord, saying, Is not the Lord among us? No evils shall come upon us:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>therefore because of you, Sion shall be ploughed like a field; and Jerusalem shall be like a temporary building for summer fruits; and the mountain of the house shall be for a grove of a forest.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But it shall come to pass in the last of these days, that the mountain of the Lord shall be conspicuous: it shall be established on the tops of the mountains, and raised high above the hills; and peoples shall hasten to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And many nations shall come; they will say, Come, let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, and to the house of the God of Jacob; that they may point out to us his ways, and that we may walk in his paths. For out of Sion shall go forth a law; and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And he will judge among many peoples, and rebuke nations of extensive power. And they shall beat their swords into ploughshares, and their spears into pruning hooks. Nation shall no more lift up a sword against nation; nor shall they any more learn to fight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But they shall rest every man under his own vine, and every man under his own fig tree; and there shall be none to make them afraid. Because the mouth of the Lord Almighty hath spoken these things:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>because all the people will walk every one in his own way, let us therefore walk in the name of the Lord our God until that age and beyond it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In that day, saith the Lord, I will gather her that hath been bruised; and take back her who was cast off and them whom I had put away:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and I will make the bruised a remnant, and her who was put away, a mighty nation. And the Lord will reign over them on mount Sion henceforth and forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And as for thee, thou squalid tower of a flock, thou daughter of Sion; to thee he will come, when the chiefdom, the first royal government shall have come from Babylon for the daughter of Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now therefore why hast thou known evils? Was there no king for thee? Or was thy counsel destroyed, that pangs of a woman in travail have seized thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Be in pangs, but take courage and draw near to delivery, daughter of Sion. For thou art now to go from a city and to make thy abode in a field, and go even to Babylon. Thence he will deliver thee; yes, thence the Lord thy God will redeem thee out of the hands of thine enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now indeed many nations are assembled against thee, saying, Let us rejoice exceedingly and let our eyes look upon Sion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But they did not know the determination of the Lord nor understand his counsel. Because he hath gathered them as sheaves for a threshing floor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>arise daughter of Sion and tread them out. Because I will make thy horns iron and thy hoofs I will make brass; therefore thou shalt break many peoples in pieces, and devote the multitude of them to the Lord, and their substance to the Lord of the whole earth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now shall a daughter be hedged in with a hedge. He hath ordered a siege against us. With a rod they will smite on the cheek the tribes of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But as for thee, Bethlehem, thou house of Ephratha, art thou too little to be one of the chiliads of Juda? Out of thee one shall come forth for me to be the chief of Israel. His goings forth have been from the beginning; from the days of an age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore he will continue them till the time of one bringing forth. She shall bring forth and the rest of their brethren shall turn to the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And they will stand and look and the Lord will feed his flock with majesty; and in the glory of the name of the Lord their God they shall subsist; because they shall now be magnified to the ends of the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore she shall have peace. As for Assur, when he hath come against your land, and when he hath passed over your country; against him shall be raised up seven shepherds. And there shall be eight bites of men</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and they will feed Assur with a sword and the land of Nebrod in its enclosure. So he will deliver from the Assyrian, when he hath come against your land and when he hath passed over your borders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the remnant of Jacob shall be among the nations in the midst of many people, like dew falling from the Lord and like lambs upon the wilds. That none may be ungathered or left behind among the children of men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>the remnant of Jacob shall be among the nations in the midst of many peoples, like a lion among beasts of the forest, and like a young lion among flocks of sheep; so that when he passeth through and hath made a choice, he may tear and there shall be none to deliver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thy hand shall be raised up against them who afflict thee; and all thine enemies shall be utterly cut off.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord, that I will destroy the horses from the midst of thee and destroy thy chariots</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and I will root out the cities of thy land and demolish thy fortifications.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And I will cut off thy sorceries out of thy hands and in thee shall be no diviners.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And I will cut off thy graven images and thy pillars from the midst of thee; and thou shalt no more worship the works of thy hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And I will cut down the groves from amidst thee and utterly destroy thy cities;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and with indignation and with wrath I will execute vengeance among the nations because they have not hearkened.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hear, I beseech you, a word. The Lord, Lord, hath commanded. Arise; come to judgment before the mountains; and let the hills hear thy voice!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Hear ye mountains the controversy of the Lord! And ye vallies the foundations of the earth! For the Lord hath a controversy with his people, and with Israel</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>he will plead. my people, what have I done to thee? Or wherein have I grieved thee? Or what molestation have I given thee? Answer me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For I brought thee up out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the house of bondage, and sent before thee Moses and Aaron and Mariam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>my people call now to remembrance what counsel Balak king of Moab took against thee; and what answer was made him by Balaam son of Beor, That from Schoinon the righteousness of the Lord may be made known to Galgal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>(Balak.) By what mean shall I gain over the Lord? Shall I take him for my God most high? Shall I gain him over by whole burnt offerings; by calves of a year old?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Will the Lord accept me for thousands of rams or myriads of fat goats? Must I give my first born for iniquity; the fruit of my body for the sin of my soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>(Balaam.) Must thou, man, be told what is good? What doth the Lord require from thee, but to do justice and to love mercy, and to be prepared to walk with the Lord thy God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>(6) Let the voice of the Lord be proclaimed in the city and it will save them who fear his name. Hear, tribe! Who is the man that will adorn a city?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Will fire and the house of an unrighteous man do it? Or he who is treasuring up unlawful treasures and iniquities with haughtiness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Will an unrighteous man be justified by a balance, or false weights by a bag</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>with which they have increased their wicked wealth? As they who inhabit it have spoken lies and their tongue hath been exalted in their mouth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>therefore I will begin with smiting thee; I will make thee desolate for thy sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou shalt eat but shalt not be satisfied. Though darkness come and warn thee thou shalt not escape; and if any escape, to the sword they shall be delivered up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thou shalt sow but thou shalt not reap. Thou shalt press the olive, but shalt not anoint thyself with oil. You shall make wine, but shall not drink it. And the ritual services of my people shall be utterly destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>As thou hast kept the statutes of Zambri, and all the works of the house of Achab; and you have walked in their ways, that I might deliver thee up to desolation, and the inhabitants of this city to hissing; therefore you shall bear the reproaches of peoples.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Woe is me! for I am like one picking up stalks in harvest, and like one gathering a gleaning at the vintage? Not a bunch of the first fruits is left for me to eat. Ah Woe is my life,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>that the pious is perished from the land, and among men there is not an upright man left! They are all indicted for capital crimes: they grievously afflict every man his neighbour:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>they are preparing their hands for evil. The chief asketh and the judge hath spoken words of peace! He is entirely at his devotion;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>therefore I will take away their good things, like a consuming moth advancing regularly in the day of visitation. Alas! alas! thy punishments are come; now will their lamentations be;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Trust not in friends, nor confide in rulers, against the wife of thy bosom be on thy guard; to trust nothing to her:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>for a son dishonoureth a father; a daughter will rise up against her mother; a daughter in law against her mother in law; all a man's household are his enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But as for me I will look to the Lord; I will wait for the God who is my saviour; he who is my God will hearken to me. (The chorus, or Sion.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Rejoice not over me, mine enemy, because I have fallen. I shall rise again, for though I sit in darkness the Lord will give me light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I will bear the indignation of the Lord, because I have sinned against him; until he vindicate my cause. He will do me justice and bring me out into light;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and shame shall cover her who saith, Where is thy God? Mine eyes shall see her. She shall now be trodden down like dirt in the streets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The day for anointing a plinth; that day will be the unanointing of thee, that day will indeed destroy thy ritual services.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And thy cities shall become plains and be distributed among the Assyrians: even thy fortified cities shall be for distribution, from Tyre to the river and from sea to sea, and from mountain to the mountain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the land shall be for desolation with them who inhabit it, for the fruits of their devices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Feed thou thy people with thy crook; the flock of thy heritage; them who are by themselves in a forest in the midst of yonder Carmel. They shall feed in Bashan and Gilead, as in the days of old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And as in the days of thy coming out of Egypt, you shall see wonderful things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Nations shall see and be confounded, and because of all the mighty power of these, they will lay their hands on their mouths. Their ears will be stopped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They will lick dust like serpents trailing on the ground; they will be confounded in their enclosure. At the Lord our God let them be confounded and struck with terror because of thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Who is a God like unto thee, taking away iniquities, and passing by the transgressions of the remnant of his heritage? He hath not kept his anger in remembrance; because he delighteth in mercy;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>he will turn and have compassion on us: he will bury deep our iniquities: they shall be whelmed in the depths of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>All our sins he will give up for truth to Jacob, as an act of mercy to Abraham as he sware to our fathers, according to the days which have been heretofore.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>