<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The genealogy of Jesus Christ, son of David, son of Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Abraham begat Isaak, and Isaak begat Jacob, and Jacob begat Judas and his brethren,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and Judas had Phares and Zara by Thamar, and Phares begat Esrom, and Esrom begat Aram,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and Aram begat Aminadab, and Aminadab begat Naasson, and Naasson begat Salmon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and Salmon had Boaz by Rahab, and Boaz had Obed by Ruth, and Obed begat Jesse,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Jesse begat David the king, and David the king had Solomon by her who had been the wife of Urias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and Solomon begat Roboam, and Roboam begat Abia, and Abia begat Asa,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and Asa begat Josaphat, and Josaphat begat Joram, and Joram begat Ozias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and Ozias begat Jotham, and Jotham begat Achaz, and Achaz begat Hezekias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and Hezekias begat Manasses, and Manasses begat Amon, and Amon begat Josias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and Josias begat Jechonias and those brothers of his at the removal to Babylon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and after the removal to Babylon Jechonias begat Salathiel, and Salathiel begat Zorobabel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and Zorobabel begat Abiud, and Abiud begat Eliakim, and Eliakim begat Azor,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and Azor begat Sadok, and Sadok begat Achim, and Achim begat Eliud,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and Eliud begat Eliazar, and Eliazar begat Matthan, and Matthan begat Jacob;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Jacob begat Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus who is called the Christ:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>all the generations therefore from Abraham to David were fourteen generations, and from David to the removal to Babylon there were fourteen generations, and from the removal to Babylon till the Christ fourteen generations,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and the genealogy of Jesus Christ was thus; for his mother Mary having been espoused to Joseph was, before they came together, found to be with child by the holy Spirit,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and Joseph her husband, being a just man and not willing to expose her, determined to divorce her privately;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but while he was thinking of this, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream and said to him, Joseph, son of David, fear not to take home Mary thy wife; for her pregnancy is from the Holy Spirit?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and she will bear a son, and thou shalt call his name Jesus, for he will save his people from their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>All this was done, so that there was a fulfilment of what was spoken by the prophet, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The virgin shall conceive and bear a son and thou shalt call his name Emmanuel, the meaning of which is, God with us:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>so when Joseph awoke from his sleep he did as the angel of the Lord commanded him, and took home his wife,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but knew her not until she brought forth this her son, The First BORN and he called his name Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After the birth of Jesus at Bethlehem of Judea, in the days of Herod the king, behold there came magians from the east2 to Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>saying, Where is he who is born to be king of the Jews? For we have seen his star at its rise, and are come to pay him homage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Upon hearing this, Herod the king was alarmed and all Jerusalem with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And having assembled all the chief priests and the scribes of the people, he inquired of them, where the Christ should be born.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And they told him. At Bethlehem of Judea. For thus it is written by the prophet,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And thou Bethlehem in the land of Judea art by no means the least among the leaders of Juda; for out of thee shall come a leader, who shall tend my people Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then Herod, having privately called the magians, got exact information from them concerning the time of the star's appearing;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and sending them to Bethlehem, he said, Go and make exact inquiry about the child. And when you have found him bring me word, that I also may go and pay him homage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So in obedience to the king they departed; and lo! the star which they had seen at his rise moved on before them, till it came and stood over the place where the child was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When they saw the star, they rejoiced exceedingly:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and having entered the house they found the child with Mary his mother. Whereupon, prostrating themselves, they did him homage. Then opening their treasures they presented him gifts, gold and frankincense and myrrh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And being warned in a dream not to return to Herod, they went to their own country by another way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when they were gone, behold an angel of the Lord appeareth to Joseph in a dream, saying, Arise, and take the child and his mother and flee to Egypt, and stay there till I order thee; for Herod will seek the child to destroy him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Accordingly he arose and took the child and his mother by night and went to Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>where he continued till the death of Herod, so that there was a fulfilment of what the Lord spoke by the prophet, saying, Out of Egypt I called my son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When Herod saw that he was treated with contempt by the magians, he was highly incensed, and he sent and slew all the male children in Bethlehem and all the territory belonging thereto, from those who had entered the second year and under, according to the time, of which he had. got exact information from the magians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then was fulfilled what was spoken by Jeremias the prophet, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A cry was heard at Rama; lamentation and weeping and great mourning; Rachel weeping for her children refused to be comforted, because they are no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now when Herod was dead, behold an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>saying, Arise and take the child and his mother and go to the land of Israel, for they who sought the child's life, are dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Accordingly he arose and took the child and his mother and came to the land of Israel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>but hearing that Archelaus reigned over Judea in the room of his father Herod, he was afraid to go thither. And being warned in a dream, he withdrew to the district of Galilee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and went and dwelt in a city called Nazareth; so that what was spoken by the prophets was fulfilled: that he should be called a Nazarene.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In those days cometh John the baptist, proclaiming in the wilderness of Judea, and saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Reform; for the reign of the heavens is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For this is the person spoken of by the prophet Esaias, saying, A voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare the way of the Lord: make the roads for him straight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now John had his raiment made of camel's hair, and a leathern girdle about his waist: and his food was locusts and wild honey:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>then went out to him Jerusalem and all Judea and all the country along the Jordan,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and by him they were baptized in the Jordan, confessing their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And seeing many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to his baptism, he said to them, Brood of vipers! who hath prompted you to flee from the impending wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Produce therefore fruits worthy of this reformation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and presume not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham for our father! For I say to you, God is able out of these stones to raise up children for Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now the axe is at the root of the trees. Every tree therefore which doth not produce good fruit is to be cut down and cast into the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I indeed baptize you in water for a reformation; but he who is coming after me is mightier than I, whose sandals I am not worthy to carry. He will baptize you in a holy spirit and fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>His winnowing instrument is in his hand. He will thoroughly clean his floor, and gather his wheat for the granary; but the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then cometh Jesus from Galilee, along the Jordan, to John, to be baptized by him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but John earnestly opposed him, saying, I have need to be baptized by thee. And thou comest to me!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And Jesus in reply said to him, Permit this at present: for thus it becometh us to confirm all righteousness. Then John permitteth him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and Jesus being baptized was just coming up from the water, when lo! the heavens were opened for him, and John saw the spirit of God descending like a dove and coming upon Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and lo! a voice from heaven said, This is my son, the Beloved, in whom I am well pleased.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Jesus was led up by the spirit into the wilderness to be tempted by the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And having fasted forty days and forty nights, he was at last hungry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon the tempter coming to him, said, If thou art Son of God, command these stones to become loaves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus said, It is written, Man can live not by bread only, but by anything which God is pleased to appoint.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then the devil taketh him along to the holy city and placeth him on the battlement of the temple,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and saith to him, If thou art Son of God, cast thyself down; for it is written, He will give his angels a charge concerning thee, and with their hands they will bear thee up shouldst thou perchance strike thy foot against a stone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Jesus said to him, It is also written, Thou shall not try the Lord thy God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Again the devil taketh him along with him to a very high mountain and pointeth out to him all the kingdoms of the world and the glory of them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and saith to him, All these I will give thee if thou wilt prostrate thyself and worship me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus said to him, Be gone, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God and serve him alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then the devil leaveth him, and lo! angels came and ministered to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now when Jesus heard that John was committed to prison he withdrew into Galilee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and having left Nazareth he went and dwelt at Capernaum, a sea port at the confines of Zebulon and Nephthaleim;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>so that there was an accomplishment of what was spoken by the prophet Esaias saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The land of Zabulon and the land of Nephthaleim, the sea coast, the banks of the Jordan, Galilee of the nations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the people who sat in darkness saw a great light; and to them who sat in the region and shadow of death, light is sprung up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>From that time Jesus began to make proclamation and say, Reform; for the reign of the heavens is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now as Jesus was walking along the sea of Galilee, he saw two brothers, Simon called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a drag net into the sea; for they were fishermen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and he said to them, Follow me and I will make you fishers of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thereupon they immediately left their nets and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And passing on he saw other two brothers, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, in the vessel with their father Zebedee, mending their nets, and he called them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Whereupon they immediately left the vessel and their father, and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then Jesus went through all Galilee teaching in their synagogues, and proclaiming the good news of the reign and curing every disease, and every malady among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And the fame of him spread through all Syria; and they brought to him all their sick, seized and tormented with various distempers; demoniacs, and lunatics and paralytics, and he cured them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And great multitudes followed him from Galilee, and Decapolis and Jerusalem and Judea, and from the banks of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>On seeing these multitudes he went up to the mount and sat down, and his disciples came to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he opened his mouth and taught them, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Happy the poor in spirit; for the kingdom of the heavens is theirs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Happy they who mourn; for they shall be comforted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Happy the meek; for they shall inherit the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Happy they who hunger and thirst for righteousness; for they shall be satisfied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Happy the merciful; for they shall obtain mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Happy the pure in heart; for they shall see God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Happy the peace makers; for they shall be called children of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Happy they who are persecuted for righteousness' sake; for the kingdom of the heavens is theirs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Happy are ye when men will revile and persecute you, and accuse you falsely of every evil thing on my account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Rejoice and exult triumphantly; for great will be your reward in heaven: for thus they persecuted the prophets who were before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>You are the salt of the earth. Now if the salt become insipid, with what can it be made salt? It is no longer fit for any thing, but to be thrown out of doors, and trampled under foot by men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>You are the light of the world. A city situate on a mountain cannot be hid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>A lamp is not lighted and put under the corn measure, but on the stand, that it may give light to all the family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thus let your light shine before men, that they may see your good works and glorify your father who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Do not imagine that I am come to annul the law and the prophets. I am not come to annul, but to confirm them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For verily I say to you, Until that heaven and this earth shall have passed away, not one jot nor a tittle of the law shall be annulled till all be accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore whosoever shall weaken the force of one of the commandments, were it even the least, and teach men accordingly, he shall be the least esteemed in the reign of the heavens; but whoever shall practise and teach them, he shall be highly esteemed in the reign of the heavens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For I say to you, Unless your righteousness exceed that of the Scribes and Pharisees, you can in no wise enter the kingdom of the heavens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>You have heard that it was said to them of old, Thou shalt not commit murder. And, Whosoever shall commit murder shall be liable to the sentence of the judges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But I say to you, Whosoever is angry with his brother without cause, shall be liable to the sentence of the judges: and whoever shall say to his brother, Raca, a contemptuous word shall be liable to the sentence of the Sanhedrim; and whoever shall say, Moreh, a reproachful word shall be liable (to be sentenced) to the vale of fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If therefore thou bring thy gift to the altar and recollect there that thy brother hath ground of complaint against thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>leave there thy gift before the altar and go away. First of all be reconciled with thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Come speedily to a friendly agreement with thine adversary, whilst thou art on the road with him; lest the adversary deliver thee up to the judge; and the judge consign thee to the officer, and thou be thrown into prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Verily I say to thee, thou shalt not be released until thou hast discharged the last farthing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>You have heard that it hath been said to the ancients, Thou shalt not commit adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But I say to you, whoever looketh on a married woman so as to lust after her, hath already committed adultery with her in his heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Therefore if thy right eye cause thee to stumble, pluck it out and cast it from thee; for it is better for thee to lose one of thy members, than that thy whole body be cast into a vale of fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And if thy right hand causeth thee to stumble, cut it off and cast it from thee; for it is better for thee to lose one of thy members, than that thy whole body be cast into a vale of fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>It hath also been said, Whosoever would put away his wife, let him give her a bill of divorce.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But I say to you, Whosoever shall put away his wife, except for whoredom, causeth her to commit adultery: and whoever shall marry her who is put away, committeth adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Again you have heard that it hath been said to the ancients, Thou shalt not forswear thyself; but shalt perform thine oaths to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But I say to you, Swear not at all: neither by heaven, for it is God's throne:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>nor by the earth, for it is his footstool; nor by Jerusalem; for it is the city of the great king,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>neither shalt thou swear by thy head; for thou canst not make one hair white or black.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>But let your word yes, be yes; and your no, no; for whatever exceedeth these, proceedeth from that which is evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>You have heard that it was said, An eye for an eye: and a tooth for a tooth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But I say to you, Contend not with the injurious: but if one smite thee on the right cheek, turn to him the other also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And if any determine to sue thee at law for thy vest, give it up to him, nay were it even thy mantle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And if one press thee to go one mile, go with him two.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Give to him who asketh thee. And from him who would borrow of thee, turn not thou away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>You have heard that it was said, Thou shalt love thy neighbour and hate thine enemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>But I say to you, Love your enemies. Bless them who curse you. Do good to them who hate you: and pray for them who spitefully use you and persecute you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>that you may be the children of your Father in heaven: for he causeth the sun to rise on bad and good, and sendeth the rain on just and unjust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>For if you love them who love you, what reward have you? Do not even the publicans the same?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And if you salute your brethren only, wherein do ye excel? Do not even the publicans do the same?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>You therefore are to be perfect, as your Father, who is in heaven, is perfect.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Take heed not to practise your righteousness before men in order to be observed by them; otherwise you have no reward from your father who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Therefore when thou dost an act of charity, sound not a trumpet before thee as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets that they may be extolled by men. Verily I say to you, they have their reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But when thou art doing an act of charity, let not thy left hand know what thy right hand is doing;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that thine act of charity may be in secret; and thy father who seeth in secret will himself reward thee openly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when thou prayest, be not like the hypocrites. Because they love to pray standing in the synagogues and at the corners of the streets that men may observe them; verily I say to you, They have their reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But as for thee, when thou wouldst pray, retire to thy closet, and having shut the door pray to thy father who is in secret, and thy father who seeth in secret will reward thee openly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when you pray, use not a vain multiplicity of words as the heathen do. For they think they shall be heard for their much speaking.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Be not ye therefore like them; for your father knoweth what things you have need of, before you ask him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>In this manner therefore pray ye, Our Father, who art in the heavens, hallowed be thy name;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>thy reign come; thy will be done on the earth, as it is in heaven;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>give us to day our daily bread;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and forgive us our debts, as we do forgive our debtors;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and bring us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil for thine is the kingdom and the power and the glory for the ages, amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For if you forgive men their offences, your heavenly father will also forgive you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but if you do not forgive men their offences, neither will your father forgive your offences.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when you fast, be not like the hypocrites, of a dismal countenance; for they disfigure their faces, that men may observe that they are fasting. Verily I say to you, They have their reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But when thou keepest a fast, anoint thy head and wash thy face,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>that thy fasting may not appear to men, but to thy father who is in secret, and thy father who seeth in secret will reward thee openly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Lay not up for yourselves treasures on the earth, where moth and rust consume, and where thieves break through and steal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust consumeth; and where thieves do not break through and steal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For where your treasure is, there will your heart also be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The eye is the lamp of the body. If therefore thine eye be sound thy whole body will be enlightened:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>but if thine eye be distempered, thy whole body will be dark. If then the light which is in thee be darkness, how great will the darkness be!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>No man can serve two masters: for he will either hate one and love the other; or he will attend to one and neglect the other. You cannot serve God and a worldly temperent</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Therefore I say to you, Be not anxious about your life, what you shall eat or what you shall drink; nor about your body, what you shall wear. Is not life a greater gift than food; and the body, than raiment?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Observe those birds of the air: they neither sow nor reap, nor lay up in granaries; yet your heavenly father feedeth them. Are not you much more valuable than they?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Besides, which of you can by his anxiety prolong his life one hour?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And with respect to raiment, why are you anxious? Consider those lilies of the field, how they grow. They neither toil nor spin:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>yet I affirm, that even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now if God thus arrayeth the herbage which is today in the field, and tomorrow to be cast into a furnace, will he not much more clothe you, O ye mistrustful?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore be not anxious, saying, What shall we eat; or, what shall we drink; or, with what shall we be clothed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For about all such things the nations are solicitous: for your heavenly father knoweth that you have need of all these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But seek first the kingdom of God, and the righteousness required by him, and all those things will be superadded to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Wherefore be not anxious about the morrow; for the morrow will be anxious about its own concerns. Sufficient for every day is its own trouble.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Judge not, that you may not be judged;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for as you judge, you shall be judged: and the measure which you mete, shall be measured to you again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now why art thou observant of the mote in thy brother's eye, and insensible to the splinter in thine own eye?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Or, how canst thou say to thy brother, Hold! let me take the mote out of thine eye, when lo! there is a splinter in thine own eye?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Hypocrite, first take the splinter out of thine own eye; and then thou wilt see clearly to remove the mote out of thy brother's eye.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Give not that which is holy to dogs; nor cast your pearls before swine; lest they trample them under foot, and turning tear you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Ask, and ye shall obtain; seek and ye shall find; knock, and the door will be opened to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For every one who asketh, obtaineth; and he who seeketh, findeth; and to him who knocketh the door will be opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Is there any man among you, who, when his son asketh bread, will give him a stone;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>or if he ask for a fish will give him a serpent?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If you therefore, bad as you are, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your father who is in heaven give good things to them who ask him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whatsoever therefore you would that men should do to you, do ye even so to them, for this is the law and the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Enter in at the strait gate. Because the gate is wide and the way broad which leadeth to destruction, therefore many there are who go in through it:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>because the gate is strait and the way narrow, which leadeth to life, therefore there are few who find it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now beware of false teachers, who come to you in sheep's clothing, but are inwardly ravenous wolves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>By their fruits you may know them. Are grapes gathered from thorns? Or figs from thistles?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So every good tree beareth good fruit; and every bad tree beareth bad fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A good tree cannot bear bad fruit; nor a bad tree, good fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Every tree which beareth not good fruit is cut down and cast into the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So then by their fruits you will know them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Not every one who saith to me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven, but he who doeth the will of my father who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Many will say to me on that day Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in thy name and in thy name cast out demons, and in thy name done many miracles,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>to whom I will then declare, I never acknowledged you; Depart from me ye who work iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore whoever heareth these words of mine and putteth them in practice, him I will compare to a prudent man, who built his house upon the rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house, it did not fall, because it was founded on the rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But whoever heareth these words of mine, and doth not put them in practice, may be compared to a foolish man, who built his house on the sand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>When the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; it fell, and great was the ruin thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When Jesus finished this discourse, the crouds were astonished at his manner of teaching;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>for in teaching them he was like one having authority, and not like the scribes.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And as he was going down from the mount great multitudes followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And lo! a leper came and prostrated himself before him, and said, Sir, if thou wilt, thou canst cleanse me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus stretched forth his hand and touched him, saying, I will: Be thou cleansed. And immediately he was cured of his leprosy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Jesus saith to him, See thou tell no one; but go and shew thyself to the priest, and offer the gift which Moses prescribed, for a testimony to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And as Jesus was entering Capernaum, a centurion met him and in treated him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>saying, Sir, my servant lieth at home struck with a palsy, in great torture.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus saith to him, I was coming; I will cure him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>In reply to which the centurion said, Sir, I am not worthy that thou shouldst come under my roof; but only speak a word and my servant will be cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For even I, who am myself under command, having soldiers under me, say to one, Go; and he goeth: and to another, Come; and he cometh: and to my slave, Do this; and he doth it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon hearing this Jesus expressed admiration, saying to them who followed him, Verily I say to you, I have not found even in Israel such a belief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now I say to you that many will come from the east and west, and will be placed at table with Abraham and Isaak and Jacob, in the kingdom of the heavens,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and the children of the kingdom will be cast out into the outer darkness. Weeping and gnashing of teeth will be there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Jesus said to the centurion, Go thy way and be it done for thee as thou hast believed. And that very instant his servant was cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Jesus also having gone to Peter's house, saw his wife's mother confined to her bed and sick of a fever,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and he touched her hand; thereupon the fever left her and she arose and entertained them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And in the evening there were brought to him many demoniacs. And he expelled the spirits with a word, and cured all that were sick</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>so that there was an accomplishment of that which was spoken by the prophet Esaias, saying, He took our infirmities and bore away our diseases.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When Jesus saw great crowds around him, he gave orders to go over to the opposite shore;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>whereupon a certain scribe accosting him, said, Teacher, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, the foxes have holes and the birds of the air have roosts; but the son of man hath not where to lay his head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Another of his disciples said to him, Master, permit me to go first and bury my father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And to him Jesus said, Follow me, and let the dead bury their own dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then having gone aboard the vessel, his disciples followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And behold there came on a mighty tempest in the sea, so that the vessel was covered with the waves, and he was asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thereupon his disciples came and awoke him, saying, Master, save us! we are perishing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And he said to them, Why are you fearful, O ye of little faith? Then he arose, and rebuked the winds and the sea, and a great calm ensued.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the men in amaze, said, What sort of a man is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when he arrived at the opposite shore in the country of the Gergesenes, there met him two demoniacs coming out of the tombs, so furious that nobody durst pass that way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And instantly they screamed, saying, What hast thou to do with us, Jesus son of God! Art thou come hither before the time to torment us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now there was at some distance from them a herd of many swine, feeding:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and the demons besought him, saying, If thou cast us out, permit us to go into that herd of swine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And he said to them, Go. Thereupon they went out and entered into the herd of swine. And instantly the whole herd ran violently down a precipice into the sea, and perished in the waters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And they who fed them fled; and having gone to the city, they told all the circumstances, including the case of the demoniacs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And presently all the city came out to meet Jesus, and having seen him they intreated him to. withdraw out of their territory.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So having gone onboard the vessel, he crossed over, and came to his own city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And lo! they brought to him a paralytic laid on a bed: and Jesus, seeing their faith, said to the paralytic, Take courage, my son; thy sins are forgiven thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thereupon some of the Scribes said within themselves, This man blasphemeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But Jesus knowing their thoughts, said, Why do ye harbour evil thoughts in your hearts?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For which is easier? To say, Thy sins are forgiven thee; or to say, Arise and walk?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But that you may know that the son of man hath power on earth to forgive sins, Arise (saith he then to the paralytic) take up thy bed and go home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Accordingly he arose and departed to his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when the multitude saw this they expressed their admiration and glorified God who had given such power to men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When Jesus was going thence he saw a man, named Matthew, sitting at the custom house; and he saith to him, Follow me. Whereupon he arose and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when he was at table in the house, behold many publicans and sinners came and placed themselves at the table with Jesus and his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When the Pharisees saw this, they said to his disciples, Why doth your teacher eat with these publicans and sinners?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Jesus hearing this, said to them, They who are well have no need of a physician, but they who are sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Go then and learn what this meaneth, I desire mercy rather than sacrifice; for I did not come to call righteous men, but sinners to reformation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then John's disciples, accosting him, said, Why do we and the Pharisees fast frequently, but thy disciples never fast?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And to them Jesus said, Can bridemen mourn, while the bridegroom is with them? The days indeed will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them and then they will fast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>No one mendeth an old garment with a patch of undressed cloth; for such a patch teareth the garment and maketh a greater rent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Neither do men put new wine into old leathern bottles, otherwise the bottles burst, and the wine is spilled, and the bottles are lost. But new wine is put into new bottles, so both are preserved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>While he was thus speaking to them, behold a chief came and, making obeisance to him, said, My daughter is at the point of death, but come and lay thy hand on her and she will live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus arose and with his disciples followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And lo! a woman who had been twelve years afflicted with an efflux of blood, came behind and touched the tuft of his mantle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For she said within herself, If I can only touch his mantle, I shall be cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And Jesus turned about and when he saw her, said, Daughter, take courage; thy faith hath cured3 thee. And from that instant the woman was cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when Jesus came to the house of the chief and saw the minstrels and the crowd in a bustle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>he saith to them, withdraw, for the damsel is not dead but asleep, Whereupon they derided him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But when the crowd was turned out, he went in and took her by the hand, and the damsel arose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the fame of this spread over all that country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>As Jesus was departing thence, two blind men followed him, with loud outcries, saying, Son of David, take pity on us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when he went into the house, the blind men came to him. And Jesus saith to them, Do you believe that I can do this? They say to him, Yes, master.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then he touched their eyes, saying, According to your belief, be it to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Whereupon their eyes were opened. Then Jesus restrained them, saying, See that none know this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But when they went out, they spread his fame through all that country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>At their going out, behold a dumb man, a demoniac, was brought to him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and the demon being expelled, the dumb man spake, and the crowds expressed their amazement, saying, Nothing like this was ever seen in Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But the Pharisees said, By the prince of the demons he expelleth the demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then Jesus took a circuit through all the cities and villages, teaching in their synagogues and proclaiming the good news of the reign, and healing every disease and every malady among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And seeing the multitudes, he had compassion on them because they were fainty and forlorn, like sheep without a shepherd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then he saith to his disciples, The harvest indeed is plentiful, but the labourers are few.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Supplicate therefore the Lord of the harvest to send forth labourers for his harvest.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then having called to him his twelve disciples, he gave them power over unclean spirits, so as to cast them out; and to cure diseases and maladies of every kind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now the names of the twelve disciples were these. First, Simon, called Peter, and Andrew his brother, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Philip and Bartholomew, Thomas and Matthew the publican, James the son of Alpheus and Lebbeus called Thaddeus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Simon the Chananite and Judas Iscariot, even he who delivered him up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>These twelve Jesus sent forth, having given them a charge, saying, Go not away to the Gentiles, nor enter a city of the Samaritans;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but go rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and as you go proclaim, saying, The reign of the heavens is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Heal the sick; cleanse lepers; raise the dead; cast out demons; freely you have received; give freely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Provide neither gold, nor silver, nor brass for your purses;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>nor a scrip for the journey; nor two coats; nor pairs of sandals; nor a staff: for the workman is worthy of his sustenance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore into whatever city or village you enter, inquire who in it is worthy, and continue there till you leave the place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when you enter the house, salute the family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And if the family be worthy, the peace you wish them will come upon them; but if they be not worthy, the peace you wish will rebound upon your selves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And whosoever will not receive you, nor hear your words, when you leave that house or that city shake off the dust of your feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Verily I say to you, it will be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorra in a day of judgment, than for that city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Behold I send you forth like sheep in the midst of wolves; be ye therefore wise as the serpents and harmless as the doves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And be upon your guard against these men, for they will deliver you up to councils and scourge you in their synagogues;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and you will be brought before governors and kings for my sake, for a testimony to them and the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But when they deliver you up, be not anxious how or what you shall speak: for what you are to speak will be suggested to you at the very instant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For it is not you who speak, but the spirit of your father that speaketh in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now brother will deliver up brother to death; and a father, a son; and children will rise up against parents and cause them to be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And you will be hated by all men on the account of my name. But he who persevereth to the end shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now when they persecute you in one city, flee to another. For, verily I say to you, before you shall have gone through all the cities of Israel, the son of man will come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The scholar is not greater than the teacher; nor the servant, than the master.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>It is enough for the scholar to be as his teacher; and the servant, as his master. If they have called the master of the family Beelzebub, how much more, his domestics.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Therefore be not afraid of them; for there is nothing hid, which shall not be revealed; nor anything secret, which shall not be known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>What I say to you in darkness, speak ye in the light; and what is whispered in your ear, proclaim on the house tops.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And be not afraid of them who kill the body, but are not able to kill the soul: but rather fear him, who can destroy both soul and body in hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Are not two sparrows sold for an assar, yet neither of them falleth to the ground without your father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Nay, the very hairs of your head are all numbered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Fear not therefore; for you are of more value than many sparrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Whosoever therefore will acknowledge me before men, him I will acknowledge before my father, who is in heaven:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>but whosoever shall disown me before men, him I will disown before my father who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Do not imagine that I am come to send peace on the earth. I am not come to send peace, but a sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>For I am come to set a man at variance with his father; and a daughter with her mother; and a daughter in law with her mother in law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Even the man's own domestics will be his enemies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>He who loveth father or mother more than me, is not worthy of me. And he who loveth son or daughter more than me, is not worthy of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And he who doth not take up his cross and follow me, is not worthy of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>He who hath found his life shall lose it. But he, who shall lose his life for my sake, shall find it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>He who receiveth you, receiveth me; and he who receiveth me, receiveth him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>He who receiveth a prophet on the account of his being a prophet, shall receive a prophet's reward. And he who receiveth a righteous man on the account of his being a righteous man, shall receive a righteous man's reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And whoever shall give any one of these little ones, were it only a cup of cold water to drink, on the account of his being a disciple, verily I say to you, he shall not lose his reward.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when Jesus had finished his instructions to these his twelve disciples, he departed thence to teach and make proclamation Ln their cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now John, having heard in prison of the works of the Christ, sent two of his disciples</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>with this message to him; Thou art the one coming; May we expect another? In reply to which,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Go and tell John what you hear and see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Blind men see, and lame walk. Lepers are cleansed and deaf hear. Dead are raised and poor have glad tidings proclaimed to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And happy is he to whom I shall not prove a stumbling block.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And as they were going away, Jesus began this discourse to the people concerning John, What did you go out to the wilderness to see? A reed shaken by the wind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But what went ye out to see? A man clothed with soft raiment? Behold they, who wear delicate apparel, frequent the palaces of kings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But what went ye out to see? a prophet? Yes I tell you, and something more than a prophet;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for this is he of whom it is written, Behold I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Verily I say to you, among them who are born of women, there hath not arisen a greater than John the baptist: but the least in the kingdom of heaven is a greater than he.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now ever since the days of John the baptist, the kingdom of the heavens is invaded and invaders are forcibly taking possession of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For till the appearance of John, all the prophets and the law were the public instructors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Indeed, if you will bear to be told it, he is Elias who was to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Whoever hath ears to hear let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now to what shall I compare this generation? It is like boys in the market place who call to their playfellows,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>saying, We have played to you on the pipe, but you have not danced; We have sung to you songs of woe, and you have not lamented.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For John came, abstaining from meat and drink, and they say he hath a demon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The son of man came eating and drinking; and they say, Behold a gluttonous man and a wine drinker; a friend of publicans and sinners. But wisdom is justified by her children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then he began to upbraid the cities in which the most of his miracles had been done, because they had not reformed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Alas for thee Chorazin! Alas for thee Bethsaida! For had the miracles, which have been performed in you, been done in Tyre and Sidon they would have repented long ago in sack cloth and ashes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But I say to you, the condition of Tyre and Sidon will in a day of judgment, be more tolerable than yours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And thou Capernaum, which hast been exalted to heaven, shalt be brought down to the mansion of the dead; for if the miracles, which have been done in thee, had been done in Sodom, it would have remained to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But I say to you, that the condition of the land of Sodom will, in a day of judgment, be more tolerable than thine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>At that time Jesus took occasion to say, I thank thee, O father, Lord of heaven and earth; that thou having hid these things from the wise and prudent, hast revealed them to babes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Yes, O father, because it thus seemed good in thy sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>All things are delivered up to me by my father; and none but the father knoweth the son; nor doth any know the father, but only the son, and he to whom the son is pleased to reveal him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Come to me all ye who labour and are heavily burdened and I will give you rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Take upon you my yoke and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart, and ye shall find rest for your souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For my yoke is easy and my burden is light.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>About this time, as Jesus was walking through corn fields on the sabbath days, his disciples were hungry and began to pluck some ears, and eat them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When the Pharisees saw this they said to him, See Thy disciples are doing that which it is not lawful to do on a sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon he said to them, Have you not read, what David did when he was hungry, and they who were with him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>How he went to the house of God and ate the presence loaves, which it was not lawful for him or his company to eat, but only for the priests?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Or have you not read in the law, that on the sabbath days the priests in the temple break the sabbath and are blameless?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now I say to you, There is one here greater than the temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And if you had known the meaning of this,. I desire mercy rather than sacrifice, you would not have condemned the innocent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For the son of man is lord even of the sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Having departed thence, he went into their synagogue</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and lo! there was a man there who had his hand withered. And they asked him with a design to accuse him; Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath days?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And he said to them, What man is there among you, who having one sheep, if it fall into a pit on the sabbath days, will not take hold of it and lift it up?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Of how much greater value then is a man than a sheep? Therefore it is lawful to do good on the sabbaths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then he said to the man, Stretch forth thy hand. And he stretched it out. And his hand was restored sound as the other.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thereupon the Pharisees went out and conspired against him that they might destroy him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But Jesus, knowing this, withdrew from that place; and great multitudes followed him, and he healed them all;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and strictly charged them not to make him known;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>so that there was a full confirmation of what was spoken by the prophet Esaias saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold my servant whom I have chosen! My beloved in whom my soul is well pleased! I will put my spirit upon him; and he will publish judgment to the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He will not contend nor raise a clamour; nor shall any one hear his voice in the streets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>A bruised reed he will not break, nor extinguish a dimly burning taper, until he render his judgment victorious.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>In his name therefore let the nations trust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then there was brought to him a demoniac, blind and dumb, and he healed him, so that he who was blind and dumb both spake and saw.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And all the people were astonished and said, Is this the son of David?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But the Pharisees, hearing them said, This man expelleth the demons, only by Beelzebub, the chief of the demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus, knowing their thoughts, said to them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation. And no city or family divided against itself can subsist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now if Satan expelleth Satan, he is at variance with himself, how then can his kingdom subsist?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Besides if I expel demons by Beelzebub, by whom do your sons expel them? Let them therefore be your judges.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But if I expel the demons by the Spirit of God, then indeed the reign of God over you is come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>How can anyone enter the house of the strong and plunder his goods, unless he first bind the strong one, in which case he may then plunder his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He who is not for me is against me; and he who gathereth not with me, scattereth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore I say to you, all manner of sin and slander may be forgiven men; but this slanderous speaking against the spirit is not to be forgiven men</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Even though one speak against the son of man, it may be forgiven him; but whoever shall speak against the holy Spirit is not to be forgiven, either in the present age, or in that to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Either make the tree good and its fruit good, or make the tree bad, and its fruit bad. For the tree is known by its fruit</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Brood of vipers! how can you who are evil speak good things? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The good man out of the good treasure of his heart produceth good things; and the bad man, out of his bad treasure produceth bad things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Now I assure you in respect to every idle word which men shall utter, they shall give an account thereof in a day of judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shall be condemned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then some of the Scribes and Pharisees interposed, saying, Teacher, we desire to see a sign from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>In reply to which he said to them, an evil, and an adulterous generation demand a sign, but no sign shall be given them, save the sign of the prophet Jonas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For as Jonas was three days and three nights in the belly of the great fish, so the son of man will be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The men of Ninive will be raised up at the judgment with this generation, and will condemn it; because they repented at the proclamation of Jonas; and behold something greater than Jonas is here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>The queen of the south will be raised up at the judgment with this generation, and will condemn it, because she came from the extremities of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon. And behold something greater than Solomon is here,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>When the unclean spirit hath gone out of the man, it walketh through dry places seeking rest, but doth not find it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Then it saith I will return to my habitation from which I came out. And when it is come, it findeth it unoccupied, swept and furnished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Then it goeth and bringeth with it seven other spirits worse than itself, and they enter and dwell there. So the last state of that man is worse than the first. Thus also will it be with this wicked generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Now, while he was speaking to the people, lo! His mother and his brethren were standing without, desiring to speak with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And one said to him, lo! thy mother and thy brethren are standing without, desiring to speak with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>In reply to which he said to him who told him, who is my mother? And who are my brethren?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Then, stretching out his hand towards his disciples, he said, Behold my mother, and my brethren!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>for whoever will do the will of my father who is in heaven, the same is my brother and sister and mother.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And on the same day, Jesus having gone out of the house, sat down by the sea side;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>but such great multitudes flocked to him that he went on board the vessel and sat down, and all the multitude stood on the shore,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and he spake many things to them in parables, saying, Behold the sower went out to sow;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and as he was sowing, some grains fell on the highway and the birds came and devoured them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And others fell on rocky ground, where they had little earth; these sprang up immediately, because they had no depth of soil;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but soon as the sun arose they were scorched; and for want of root withered away:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and some fell among the thorns, and the thorns sprang up and choaked them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And some fell on good ground and yielded increase; some an hundred; some, sixty; and some, thirty fold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Whoever hath ears to hear, let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then the disciples accosted him, saying, Why speakest thou to them in parables?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And he in reply said to them, To you it hath been granted to know the secrets of the reign of the heavens; but to them it hath not been granted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For to him who improveth, more shall be given and he shall abound: but from him who improveth not, even that which he hath shall be taken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>To them I speak in parables for this reason, because they overlook what they see, and are inattentive to what they hear; and they do not understand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and in them is fulfilled this prophesy of Esaias, which saith, Hearing you shall hear, though you may not understand, and seeing you shall see, though you may not perceive;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>for the heart of this people is callous, and their ears are dull of hearing, and they have shut their eyes, that for a while they may not see with their eyes and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and return that I may heal them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But blessed are your eyes, because they see, and your ears, because they hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For verily I say to you, Many prophets and righteous men have earnestly desired to see what you see, and have not seen them; and to hear what you hear and have not heard them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Hear then the parable of the sower.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When any one heareth the doctrine of the kingdom and doth not mind it, the evil one cometh and snatcheth away what was sown in his heart. This is the meaning of that sown on the highway.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And that sown on rocky ground denoteth him, who, upon hearing the word, receiveth it at first with joy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but not having it rooted in him, it is only temporary; and when tribulation and persecution cometh on account of the word, he is immediately stumbled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And that sown among thorns denoteth him, who heareth the word, but worldly care and the delusion of riches choak the word and it becometh unfruitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But that sown on good ground denoteth him who heareth and mindeth the word, and who beareth fruit and bringeth forth, one a hundred, and another sixty, and another thirty fold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Another parable he stated to them, saying, The reign of the heavens may be compared to a man sowing good seed in his field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But when the men were asleep; his enemy came and sowed darnel among the wheat, and went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when the blade sprang up and put forth the ear, then the darnel appeared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Whereupon the servants of the householder came and said to him, Master, didst thou not sow good seed in thy field whence then hath it darnel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And he said to them, An enemy hath done this. Then the servants said to him, Is it thy pleasure then that we go and weed it out?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And he said, no. Perhaps in weeding out the darnel you may pull up the wheat with it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Let them both grow together till the harvest. And at the season for reaping I will say to the reapers, Gather the darnel first and bind it in bundles to be burned; then gather the wheat into my barn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Another parable he stated to them, saying, The reign of the heavens is like a grain of mustard seed which a man took and sowed in his field,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>which is indeed the smallest of all seeds, but which, when grown, is the largest of the herbs and becometh a tree, so that the birds of the air come and take shelter among the branches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Another parable he stated to them, saying, The reign of the heavens is like leaven which a woman took and covered up in three measures of meal, till the whole was leavened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>All these things Jesus spake to them in parables, and did not speak to them without a parable,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>so that there was a full accomplishment of that which was spoken by the prophet, saying, I will open my mouth with parables, I will utter things kept hid from the foundation of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then Jesus dismissed the multitude and went into the house, and his disciples came to him and said, Explain to us the parable of the darnel in the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And he answering, said to them, He who soweth the good seed is the son of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>The field is the world. The good seed are the children of the kingdom, and the darnel are the children of the evil one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>The enemy who sowed it is the devil. The harvest is the conclusion of the age, and angels are the reapers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>As the darnel therefore is gathered and burned with fire, so shall it be at the conclusion of this age.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The son of man will send his angels, and they will gather out of his kingdom all the stumbling blocks, and the workers of iniquity,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and cast them into the fiery furnace. Weeping and gnashing of teeth will be there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then shall the righteous shine like the sun in the kingdom of their father. Whoever hath ears to hear, let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Again the kingdom of the heavens is like treasure hid in the field, which, when a man found, he concealed, and for joy thereof goeth away and selleth all that he hath, and purchaseth that field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Again the kingdom of the heavens is like a merchant in quest of fine pearls,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>who, having met with one of great value, went and sold all that he had and purchased it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Again the kingdom of the heavens is like a sweep net cast into the sea, which enclosed fishes of every kind,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>which, when it was full, they dragged to the shore; and then sitting down, gathered the good into vessels and threw the bad away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>So shall it be at the conclusion of this age. The angels will go forth and sever the wicked from among the righteous</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>and cast them into the fiery furnace. Weeping and gnashing of teeth will be there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Jesus saith to them, Have you understood all these? They say to him, Yes, Master.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Then he said to them, Every Scribe then who is instructed for the kingdom of heaven is like a master of a family who bringeth out of his treasury things new and old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Now when Jesus had finished these parables he departed thence;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>and being come into his own country, he taught them in their synagogues, so that they were astonished, and said. Whence hath this man this wisdom and these miraculous powers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Is not this the carpenter's son? Is not his mother called Mary and his brethren, James and Joses and Simon and Judas?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>And his sisters, are they not all among us? Whence then hath this man all these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>And they were stumbled at him. Thereupon Jesus said to them, A prophet is not without honour save in his own country and in his own family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>So he did not perform many miracles there because of their unbelief.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time Herod the tetrarch hearing of the fame of Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>said to his servants, This is John the Baptist. He is raised from the dead, and therefore miracles are performed by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>(For Herod had apprehended John and bound him, and put him in prison on account of Herodias, the wife of his brother Philip:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>for John had said to him, It is not lawful for thee to have her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon which Herod would have put him to death, but he was afraid of the people, because they looked upon him as a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But when Herod's birth day was kept, the daughter of Herodias danced before the company and pleased Herod.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Whereupon he promised with an oath to give her whatever she would ask.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And she at the instigation of her mother, said, Give me here in a basin the head of John the Baptist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Though the king was sorry, yet from a regard to the oath and the guests, he ordered it to be given her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So he sent and beheaded John in the prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And his head was brought in a basin and given to the damsel, who carried it to her mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And his disciples went and took up the body, and buried it, and came and told Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When Jesus heard this he departed thence, in a vessel, privately, to a desert place; and the people, being informed, followed him by land out of the cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when Jesus landed he saw a great multitude, and had compassion on them, and healed their sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And towards evening his disciples accosted him, saying, This is a desert place and the hour is now past, dismiss the multitude that they may go to the villages and buy themselves victuals.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And Jesus said to them, They need not go. Give them, ye yourselves, something to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And they said, We have here only five loaves and two fishes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whereupon he said, Bring them hither to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then he ordered the multitude to arrange themselves, as at table, on the grass. And having taken the five loaves and the two fishes, he looked up to heaven and pronounced a blessing. Then he brake and gave the loaves to the disciples and the disciples distributed them to the multitudes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And they all ate and were satisfied. And there were carried away twelve panniers full of the fragments which remained.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now they who had eaten were about five thousand men, besides women and children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then Jesus immediately constrained his disciples to embark, and cross over to the other side before him, while he dismissed the multitudes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when he had dismissed the multitudes he went up, by himself, to the mountain, to pray And in the course of the eve, he was there alone,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and the vessel was now in the midst of the sea tossed by the waves, for the wind was contrary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And in the fourth watch of the night, Jesus went to them, walking on the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>When the disciples saw him walking on the sea, they were terrified, and said it is an apparition, and cried out for fear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus immediately spake to them, saying, Take courage: it is I; be not afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In reply to which Peter said, Master, if it be them, bid me come to thee on the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Jesus said, Come. So Peter having gone down from the vessel, walked on the waves to go to Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But perceiving the wind strong, he was afraid, and, beginning to sink, he cried out, saying, Master, save me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And Jesus immediately stretched forth his hand and took hold of him, saying, Distrustful man, why didst thou doubt?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And when they were come into the vessel the wind ceased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And they who were in the vessel came and bowed down to him, saying, Thou art indeed Son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And when they had crossed over, they landed in the territory of Gennesaret.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the men of that place, knowing him, sent to all the country around, and they brought to him all that were sick,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and intreated him that they might only touch the tuft of his mantle. And as many as touched were perfectly cured.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then some Scribes and Pharisees from Jerusalem accosted Jesus, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Why do thy disciples transgress the doctrine of the elders? For they do not wash their hands when they eat bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>In reply to which he said to them, Why do you transgress the commandment of God, from a regard to your doctrines?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For God commanded saying, Honour thy father and thy mother, and whosoever revileth father or mother let him be put to death:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but you say, Whoever shall say to his father or to his mother, Let that by which thou mightest be benefited by me, be dedicated,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>must not honour either his father or his mother. Thus you have annulled the commandment of God from a regard to your doctrines.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Hypocrites! well did Esaias prophesy concerning you, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>This people draw near to me with their mouth; and with their lips they honour me, but their heart is far from me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and, in vain do they worship me, teaching doctrines, the commands of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then having called the multitude to him, he said to them, Hear and understand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>It is not that which goeth into the mouth which defileth the man; but it is that which cometh out of the mouth, which defileth the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then his disciples coming to him said, Dost thou know that the Pharisees, when they heard that saying, were offended?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In reply to which he said, Every plant which my heavenly father hath not planted, is to be rooted up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Let them alone. They are blind leaders of blind. Now if the blind lead the blind, they will both fall into a ditch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then Peter addressing him said, Explain to us this parable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus said, Are you also yet without understanding?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Do you not yet perceive, that whatever entereth in at the mouth, goeth into the belly, and is thrown out into the sink?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And that what proceed from the mouth come from the heart, and that these defile the man?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For out of the heart come malicious surmises, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false testimonies, calumnies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>These are the things which defile the man: but to eat with unwashen hands doth not defile the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Jesus having left that place, withdrew into the confines of Tyre and Sidon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And lo! a Chananitish woman from those quarters came out and cried with a loud voice, saying to him, Have pity on me, O my lord, Son of David; my daughter is grievously afflicted by a demon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But he made her no answer. Then his disciples came near and intreated him, saying, Dismiss this woman, for she crieth after us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And he in reply said, My mission is only to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>She nevertheless advanced, and prostrating herself before him, said, O my lord, help me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Whereupon he in reply said, It is not seemly to take the childrens bread and cast it to the dogs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And she said, True, Sir. Yet even the dogs eat of the crumbs which fall from their master's table.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus in reply said to her, O woman, great is thy faith; Be it to thee as thou desirest. And from that instant her daughter was healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>When Jesus left that place he came nigh to the sea of Galilee, and having ascended the mountain, he sat down there,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and great multitudes flocked to him, bringing with them the lame, the blind, the dumb, the cripple and many others, whom they laid at the feet of Jesus, and he healed them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>insomuch that the people beheld with amaze the dumb speaking, the cripple sound, the lame walking, and the blind seeing, and they glorified the God of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then Jesus called his disciples and said, I have compassion on the multitude, because they have attended me now three days, and have nothing to eat. I will not send them away fasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Perhaps they may faint on the road. Thereupon his disciples say to him, Whence can we get loaves enough, in a wilderness, to satisfy so great a multitude?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And Jesus saith to them, How many loaves have you? And they said, Seven, and a few small fishes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then commanding the multitude to recline on the ground,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>he took the seven loaves and the fishes, and having given thanks, he broke and gave to his disciples; and the disciples distributed to the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And when they had all eaten and were satisfied, there were carried off seven baskets full of the fragments left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Now they who had eaten were about four thousand men, besides women and children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Then having dismissed the multitude, he embarked and came to the coast of Magdala.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And the Pharisees and the Sadducees having come thither with a view to try him, desired that he would show them a sign from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whereupon he in reply said to them, When it is evening you say, It will be fair weather, for the sky is red:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and in the morning, there will be a storm today, for the sky is red and lowering. Hypocrites! you know how to distinguish the appearance of the sky, and can you not discern the signs of the times?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>An evil and adulterous generation demand a sign, but no sign shall be given them, save that of the prophet Jonas. So leaving them he departed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now his disciples, going to the other side, had forgotten to bring with them loaves of bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And Jesus said to them, Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the Sadducees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Whereupon they reasoned among themselves, saying, It is because we have not brought loaves with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And Jesus knowing this, said to them, Why do ye reason among yourselves, O ye of little faith, because you have not brought loaves?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Have you yet no reflection? Or do ye not remember the five loaves among the five thousand, and how many panniers you carried off;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>nor the seven loaves among the four thousand, and how many baskets you carried off?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>How is it that you do not understand that I did not speak to you of bread, when I cautioned you to beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the Sadducees?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then they understood that he did not caution them against the leaven of the bread, but against the doctrine of the Pharisees and Sadducees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When Jesus was going to Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, saying, Who do men say that I, the son of man, am?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And they said, Some say, John the Baptist; and some, Elias; and some Jeremias, or one of the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He saith to them, And who do ye say that I am?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Upon this Peter, in reply, said, Thou art The Christ, the son of the living God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Jesus answering, said to him, Happy art thou, Simon Barjona; for flesh and blood hath not revealed this to thee, but my father who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now I say to thee, Thou art named Peter, a rock, and upon this very rock I will build my church, and the gates of Hades shall not prevail against it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I will give thee the keys of the kingdom of the heavens; and whatsoever thou shall bind on the earth, will be bound in the heavens; and whatsoever thou shalt loose on the earth, will be loosed in the heavens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then he charged his disciples not to tell anyone that he, Jesus, is the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>From that time Jesus began to point out to his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem, and suffer many things from the elders, and chief priests and scribes, and be put to death, and raised again on the third day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon which Peter, taking him aside, began to check him, saying, Mercy on thee, O my Lord! This cannot befal thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But he, turning, said to Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan. Thou art an obstacle in my way. For thou hast not thy mind bent on the things of God; but on the things of those men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then Jesus said to his disciples if any one wisheth to follow me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For whoever wisheth to save his life shall lose it; and whoever shall lose his life for my sake, shall find it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For what will a man be profited, if he should gain the whole world, and be punished with the forfeit of his life? Or, what will not a man give as a ransom for his life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For the son of man will come in the glory of his father, with his angels, and will then render to every one according to his actions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Verily I say to you, there are some of them standing here who shall not taste death until they see the son of man coming in his kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after six days, Jesus taketh Peter, and James, and John, his brother, and bringeth them up privately to a high mountain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and was transfigured before them. His face shone like the sun: and his raiment became white as the light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And behold there appeared to them Moses and Elias, conversing with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon Peter, addressing Jesus, said, Master, it is well that we are here. if thou pleasest let us make here three booths, one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>While he was yet speaking, behold! a bright cloud overshadowed them; and lo! from the cloud, a voice, saying, This is my Son, the Beloved, in whom I am well pleased. Hear ye him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon hearing this the disciples fell on their face and were greatly affrighted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But Jesus came and touched them, and said, Arise, Be not afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And having lifted up their eyes they saw none but Jesus only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And as they were coming down from the mountain, Jesus charged them, saying, Tell no one what you have seen, until the son of man shall have risen from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then his disciples asked him, saying, Why then do the Scribes say, that Elias must come first?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus said to them, Elias indeed cometh first and is to finish and begin all anew.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now I say to you, Elias is already come and they did not know him, but have treated him as they pleased. In the same manner also the son of man will soon suffer by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then the disciples understood that he spake to them of John the Baptist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when they were come to the multitude, there came to him a man, who falling on his knees, said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>O sir, have pity on my son; for he is afflicted with an epilepsy, and suffereth grievously. For he often falleth into the fire and often into the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I brought him to thy disciples, but they could not cure him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And Jesus answering, said, O faithless and perverse generation! How long shall I be with you? How long shall I endure you? Bring him hither to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then Jesus rebuked the demon and it went out of him, and from that hour the child was cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then the disciples came to Jesus in private, and said, Why could not we cast it out?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And Jesus said to them, Because of your unbelief. For verily I say to you, If you have faith as a grain of mustard seed, you might say to that mountain, Remove hence to yonder place; and it would remove; and nothing would be impossible to you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but this kind of power goeth not forth, unless by prayer and fasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now while they remained in Galilee Jesus said to them, The son of man will soon be delivered into the hands of men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and they will put him to death; and on the third day he will be raised up. And they were exceedingly grieved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when they were come to Capernaum, the receivers of the assessments for the Temple came to Peter, and said, Doth your teacher pay the didrachm?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He saith, Yes. And when he came into the house, before he spake, Jesus said to him, What thinkest thou Simon? Of whom do the kings of the earth receive assessments? Of their own sons or of others?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Peter saith to him, Of others. Jesus saith to him, The sons then surely are free.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>However, that we may not offend them, go to the sea, and throw in a hook, and take the first fish that cometh up; and having opened its mouth thou wilt find a stater: take that and give it to them for me and thee.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>At that time the disciples came to Jesus, saying, Who is to be greatest in the kingdom of the heavens?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus, having called to him a little child, placed it in the midst of them</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and said, Verily I say to you, Unless you be changed, and be like children you shall never enter the kingdom of the heavens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whosoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, he is of higher dignity in the kingdom of the heavens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And whoever shall receive one such child in my name, receiveth me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But whoever shall occasion the stumbling of one of such little ones who believe in me, better were it for him that an upper millstone were hanged about his neck and that he were whelmed in the depth of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Alas, for the world because of these stumbling blocks, for these stumbling blocks must needs come: but alas for the man by whom the stumbling block cometh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>If then thy hand or thy foot occasioneth thy stumbling, cut them off and cast them from thee. It is better for thee to enter lame or maimed into life, than having two hands or two feet to be cast into the fire which is everlasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And if thine eye occasioneth thy stumbling, pluck it out and cast it from thee; it is better for thee to enter into life with but one eye, than having two eyes to be cast into the vale of that fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Take heed that you despise not one of these little ones; for I say to you, Their angels in heaven do continually behold the face of my father who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the son of man is come to save that which was lost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>What think you? If any man hath an hundred sheep, and one of them go astray, doth he not leave die ninety nine on the mountains, and go in quest of the stray?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And if he happen to find it, verily I say to you, he rejoiceth over it more than over the ninety nine which went not astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thus it is not the will of your father who is in heaven that one of these little ones should be lost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Wherefore if thy brother trespass against thee, go and expostulate with him when thou and he are alone. If he hearken to thee thou hast gained thy brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But if he will not hearken to thee, then take with thee one or two, that by the testimony of two or three witnesses everything may be ascertained;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And if he disregard them, tell the congregation; and if he disregard the congregation, let him be to thee as the heathen and the publican.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Verily I say to you, whatsoever ye shall bind on the earth will be bound in heaven; and whatsoever ye shall loose on the earth will be loosed in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Again I say to you, If two of you agree on the earth touching any thing which they may ask, it will be done for them by my father who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For where two or three are assembled for my name I am there in the midst of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Peter accosting him, said, Master, how often is my brother to trespass against me and I to forgive him? Till seven times?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, I do not say to thee seven times, but seventy times seven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>In this respect the reign of the heavens may be compared to a certain king who determined to settle accounts with his servants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And having begun to settle; there was one brought to him, who owed him ten thousand talents.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And as he had not wherewithal to pay; his lord ordered him and his wife and all that he had, to be sold and payment to be made.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The servant therefore falling prostrate before him, saith, Have patience with me, my lord, and I will pay thee all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And the lord of that servant, being moved with compassion, dismissed him and forgave him the debt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And as that servant was going out, he met one of his fellow servants who owed him a hundred deniars and seizing him by the throat, he said, Pay me what thou owest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>His fellow servant therefore falling at his feet, besought him, saying, Have patience with me and I will pay thee all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And he would not; but went and cast him into prison until he should pay the debt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When his fellow servants saw this they were deeply affected and went and told their lord all that was done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Thereupon his lord having called him in, saith to him, Thou wicked slave, I forgave thee all that debt at thy entreaty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>shouldst thou not then have had compassion on thy fellow servant as I had on thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>So his lord, being incensed, delivered him to the executioners of justice until he should pay all that was due to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Thus also will my heavenly father deal with you, if you do not from your hearts forgive, everyone the trespasses of his brother.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus had finished these discourses he departed from Galilee and came to the borders of Judea, on the bank of the Jordan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And great multitudes followed him, and he healed them there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the Pharisees came to him, and trying him said, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every fault?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>In reply to which he said to them, Have you not read that the Creator at the beginning made them a male and a female?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Moreover he said, For this cause a man is to leave his father and his mother, and cleave to his wife, and they two shall be one flesh;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>so that they are no longer two but one flesh. Therefore what God hath conjoined, let not man separate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They say to him, Why then did Moses command to give a bill of divorce and dismiss her?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He saith to them, Because of your intractable disposition Moses permitted you to put away your wives; but it was not so from the beginning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now I say to you, Whosoever shall put away his wife, except it be for whoredom and shall marry another, committeth adultery: and he who marrieth her who was put away committeth adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>His disciples say to him, If such be the case between the husband and wife, it is not expedient to marry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Whereupon he said to them, All men cannot admit this inference. But with respect to them to whom it is granted</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>(for there are some who have been eunuchs from their birth, and some have been made eunuchs by men, and there are some who have made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven) let him admit it, who can admit it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then children were brought to him that he might lay his hands on them and pray for them; and his disciples rebuked them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus said, Let the children alone, and do not hinder them to come to me; for of such is the kingdom of the heavens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when he had laid his hands on them he departed thence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And behold there came one who said to him, Good teacher, what good thing shall I do, that I may have an everlasting life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>In reply to which Jesus said to him, Why callest thou me good? There is none good but God only. But if thou desirest to enter into that life, keep the commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He saith to him, Which? And Jesus said, These: Thou shalt not commit murder; Thou shalt not commit adultery; Thou shalt not steal; Thou shall not bear false witness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Honour thy father and thy mother; and, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The youth said to him, All these I have kept from my childhood. What do I yet lack?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Jesus said to him, If thou wishest to be perfect, go, sell thy estate, and give to the poor; and thou shalt have treasure in heaven. Then come and follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon hearing this word, the youth went away sorrowful; for he had great possessions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to his disciples, Verily I say to you, With difficulty will a rich man enter the kingdom of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Again I say to you, It is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When his disciples heard this they were greatly astonished and said, Who then can be saved?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus looking earnestly at them said, With men this is impossible; but with God all things are possible.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then Peter addressing him said, Behold we have left all and followed thee, what then shall we have?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to him, Verily I say to you, With respect to you who have followed me, at the renovation, when the son of man shall sit on the throne of his glory, you also shall sit on twelve thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And everyone who hath forsaken houses, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or fields for the sake of my name, shall receive an hundred fold compensation. He shall indeed inherit an everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But many will be first who are last; and last, who are first.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For the reign of the heavens is like a householder who went out early in the morning to hire labourers for his vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And having agreed with some labourers for a deniar a day, he sent them to his vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And going out about the third hour he saw some standing in the market place, unemployed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and said to them, Go ye also to the vineyard and I will give you what is reasonable. So they went.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Again about the sixth and ninth hour he went out and did the same.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And having gone out about the eleventh hour, he found others standing unemployed, and saith to them, Why have you stood here all the day unemployed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They say to him, Because no one hath hired us. He saith to them, Go ye also to the vineyard and you shall receive what is reasonable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And in the evening the owner of the vineyard said to his steward, Call the labourers and pay them their wages, beginning with the last and ending with the first.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So they who had been hired at the eleventh hour, came and received even one a deniar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when the first hired came, they expected to receive more; but they also received everyone a deniar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when they received it, they murmured against the householder,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>saying, These last have worked but one hour, and thou hast made them equal to us, who have borne the burden, and the heat of the day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But he in reply said to one of them, Companion! I do thee no wrong. Didst thou not agree with me for a deniar:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>take what is thine and go thy way. It is my will to give this last as much as to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Is it not lawful for me to do what I please with mine own? Is thine eye evil because I am good?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So the last shall be first, and the first last. For there are many called, but few chosen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>As Jesus was going up to Jerusalem, he took the twelve disciples apart on the road and said to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Behold we are going up to Jerusalem, and the son of man will be delivered up to the chief priests and Scribes; and they will condemn him to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and deliver him up to the Gentiles to be mocked, and scourged, and crucified, and on the third day he will rise again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Then the mother of Zebedee's children came to him with her sons, and, prostrating herself, asked a favour of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whereupon he said to her, What is thy desire? She said to him, Grant that these two sons of mine may sit, one on thy right hand and the other on thy left in thy kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In reply to which Jesus said, You do not know what you ask. Can you drink the cup which I shall soon drink and be baptized with the baptism, with which I am baptized? They say to him, We can.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then Jesus saith to them, You will indeed drink my cup and be baptized with the baptism with which I am baptized: but to sit on my right hand, and on my left, is not mine to give, unless to them for whom it is prepared by my father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When the ten heard, they were moved with indignation against the two brothers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus having called them to him, said, You know that the chiefs of the nations exercise dominion over them; and they who are grandees exercise authority over them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>but it shall not be so among you. But whoever among you would wish to be great, let him be your attendant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And whoever among you would wish to be first, let him be your servant;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>even as the son of man came not to be waited on, but to wait, and to give his life a ransom for many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now when they were going from Jericho a great multitude followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And lo! two blind men who sat by the way side, hearing that Jesus was passing by, cried, saying, Have pity on us, O master, son of David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when the people reprimanded them that they might hold their peace, they cried the louder, saying, Have pity on us, O master, son of David.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Whereupon, Jesus, stopping, called them and said, What do you desire me to do for you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>They say to him, Sir! that our eyes may be opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And Jesus had compassion and touched their eyes; and instantly they received sight. And they followed him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when they approached Jerusalem and were come to Bethphage, near to the mount of olives, then Jesus sent two disciples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>saying to them, Go to that village which is over against you, and straightway you will find an ass tied and a colt with her. Loose her and bring them to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And if anyone say anything to you; say, The Lord hath need of them and will quickly send them back.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now all this was done, so that there was an accomplishment of what was spoken by the prophet, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Say to the daughter of Sion, Behold thy king cometh to thee, meek and mounted on an ass; even on a young colt the foal of an ass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So the disciples went, and having done as Jesus commanded them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>they brought the ass and the colt and threw their mantles on them, and set him thereon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the greater part of the multitude threw their mantles on the way, and some cut branches from the trees and strewed them in the way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the crowds that went before, and they who followed, shouted, saying, Hosannah to the son of David! Blessed he, who is coming in the name of the Lord! Hosannah in the highest!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And as he entered Jerusalem, all the city was in commotion, saying, Who is this?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the multitude said, This is Jesus the prophet, who is of Nazareth in Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And Jesus went into the temple of God and drove out all those who were selling and buying in the temple, and overturned the tables of the money changers and the stalls of them who sold doves,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and said to them, It is written, My house shall be called a house of prayer, but you have made it a den of robbers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then the blind and the lame came to him in the temple and he healed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>When the chief priests and the Scribes saw the wonders which he did, and the children shouting in the temple, and saying, Hosannah to the son of David, they were filled with indignation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and said to him, Hearest thou what these say? Jesus saith to them, Yes. Have you never read, From the mouth of babes and sucklings thou hast perfected praise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then leaving them he went out of the city to Bethany and lodged there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>In the morning, when he was coming to the city, he was hungry,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and seeing a fig tree near the way, he went to it and found nothing thereon but leaves. Whereupon he saith to it, Henceforward let no fruit ever grow on thee. And immediately the fig tree withered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When the disciples saw this they expressed astonishment, saying, How suddenly the fig tree is withered!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And Jesus answering, said to them, Verily I say to you, if you have faith, without wavering, you may do not only as much as is done to this fig tree; but if you should even say to that mountain, Be thou lifted up and thrown into the sea, it shall be done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And whatever you ask in prayer, with faith, you shall obtain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when he was come to the temple, the chief priests and the elders of the people came to him as he was teaching, and said, By what authority dost thou these things? And, Who gave thee this authority?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus saith to them, Let me also ask you a question, which if you answer me, I will tell you by what authority I do these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Whence was the baptism of John? From heaven, or of men? Upon this they reasoned among themselves, saying, if we say, From heaven, he will say, Why then did you not believe him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and if we say, Of men, we fear the people; for they all hold John as a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So in answer to Jesus, they said, We cannot tell. Thereupon Jesus said, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But what think you? A man had two sons. And coming to the first, he said, Son, go work today in my vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And he in reply said, I will not. But afterwards he repented and went. And coming to the second, he ordered him in like manner; and he in reply said, I will, sir; but did not go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Which of the two did the will of his father? They say to him, The first. Jesus saith to them, Verily I say to you, The publicans and the harlots lead the way for you to the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For John came to you in the way of righteousness, and you believed him not: but the publicans and the harlots believed him. And though you saw this, you did not afterwards repent and believe him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Hear another parable. There was a certain landlord who planted a vineyard and hedged it around, and dug therein a wine lake, and built a tower, and let it to tenants and went to a distant country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And when the fruit season approached, he sent his servants to the tenants to receive the fruits of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>But the tenants seizing his servants, beat one and killed another, and stoned another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Again he sent other servants in greater number than the first, and they treated them in the same manner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>At last he sent to them his son, saying, They will reverence my son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But when the tenants saw the son, they said among themselves, This is the heir. Come let us kill him and keep possession of his inheritance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>So, seizing him, they turned him out of the vineyard and slew him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Now when the lord of the vineyard shall come, what will he do to these tenants?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>They say to him, Wretches! he will put them to a wretched death: and his vineyard he will let to others; who will render him the fruits in their seasons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Jesus saith to them, Have you never read in the scriptures, The stone which the builders rejected was the very one for the head of the corner. This salvation was from the Lord, and it is wonderful in our eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Therefore I say to you, The kingdom of God shall be taken from you and given to a nation producing the fruits thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And he who falleth on that stone will be bruised, but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Now the chief priests and the Pharisees, when they heard his parables, knew that he spake of them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>but when they sought to seize him, they were afraid of the multitude, because they regarded him as a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So Jesus, continuing his discourse, addressed them again in parables, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The reign of the heavens may be compared to a temporal king, who made a marriage feast for his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And he sent his servants to call them who were invited to the wedding, but they would not come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Again he sent other servants, saying, Tell them who have been invited, Behold I have prepared my dinner. My bullocks and my fatlings are killed and all things are ready. Come to the wedding feast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But they turned away with indifference, one to his farm, and another to his merchandise</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and the rest seized his servants, insulted, and slew them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When the king heard this he was incensed, and sent forth his armies, and destroyed the murderers, and burned their city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then he saith to his servants, The wedding is indeed ready. but they who have been invited are unworthy;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Go ye therefor, to the highways, and invite to the wedding as many as you meet with.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Accordingly the servants went out to the highway and assembled all that they met, bad and good. And the wedding was plentifully supplied with guests.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when the king came in to see the guests, he saw there a man who had not on a wedding garment, and saith to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Companion, how camest thou hither without having on a wedding garment. And he was struck speechless.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then the king said to the attendants, Bind his hands and feet and carry him out and cast him into the outer darkness. Weeping and gnashing of teeth will be there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For there are many called, but few chosen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then the Pharisees went out and consulted how they might ensnare him by a discourse.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So they send to him their disciples with the Herodians, saying, Teacher, We know that thou art true and teachest the way of God truly, and carest for no one. For thou respectest not the persons of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Tell us therefore what thou thinkest. Is it lawful to pay tribute to Caesar, or not?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But Jesus, knowing their malice, said, Hypocrites! Why do ye try me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Shew me the tribute money. So they brought him a deniar,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>then he saith to them, Whose image and inscription is this?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They say to him, Caesar's. Then he saith to them, Render then to Caesar the things which are Caesar's; and to God, the things which are God's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon hearing this they were struck with surprise, and left him and went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>On the same day there came to him Sadducees, who say, There is no future state. And they asked him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>saying, Teacher, Moses said, If a man die, having no children, his brother shall marry his wife, and raise up seed for his brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now there were with us seven brothers. And the first married a wife and died; and having no children, he left his wife for his brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>In like manner also the second and the third, even to the seventh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And last of all, the woman also died:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>in the future state therefore, whose wife shall she be of the seven? For they all married her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus said to them, Ye err, not knowing the scriptures nor the power of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For in the future state, they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are as the angels of God in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But in respect to the revival of the dead. Have you not read what was spoken to you: by God, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaak, and the God of Jacob, God is not the God of the dead; but of the living.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>When the people heard this they were astonished at his manner of teaching.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Now when the Pharisees heard that he had silenced the Sadducees, they flocked about him for the same purpose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And one of them, an expounder of the law, with a view to 36 try him, asked him this question,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Teacher, which is the great commandment in the law?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>This is the first and great commandment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And the second is like it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>On these two commandments hang the whole law and the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Now while the Pharisees were together, Jesus asked them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>saying, What think ye concerning the Christ? Whose Son is he? They say to him, David's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>He saith to them, How then doth David by the spirit call him Lord; saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>The Lord said to my Lord, Sit at my right hand, until I make thine enemies thy footstool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>If then David calleth him Lord: how is he his son?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And none could answer him a word. Nor did any one presume from that day forward to ask him any more questions.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Jesus spake to the multitude and to his disciples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>saying, The Scribes and the Pharisees sit in Moses' chair.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Observe then and do whatever they enjoin you: but do not act as they do. For they say and do not practise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For they bind up heavy and insupportable burdens and lay them on men's shoulders: but they themselves will not move them with their finger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But all their works they do to be seen by men. For this they make their phylacteries broad, and enlarge the tufts of their mantles,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and love the uppermost places at entertainments; and the first seats in the synagogues;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and salutations in places of public resort; and to be called by men, Rabbi, Rabbi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But as for you, be ye not called Rabbi; for one is your teacher, namely the Christ. Now as for you all, ye are brethren,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and should call no one on earth your father, for one is your father, namely, he who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Neither be ye called leaders for one is your leader, namely the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Let then the greatest among you be your attendant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For who soever exalteth himself, shall be humbled, but he who humbleth himself, shall be exalted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now alas for you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you shut up the kingdom of the heavens against men. For you neither enter in yourselves, nor suffer them who are going in, to enter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Alas for you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you devour the houses of the widows; and for a pretext make long prayers. For this you shall be punished with greater severity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Alas for you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you traverse sea and land to make one proselyte; and when he is gained, you make him doubly more a child of hell, than yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Alas for you, blind guides, who say, to swear by the temple is not binding; but to swear by the gold of the temple is binding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Foolish and blind! which is greater? The gold? Or the temple which halloweth the gold?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And, to swear by the altar doth not bind; but to swear by the gift thereon is binding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Foolish and blind! which is greater? The gift? Or the altar which halloweth the gift?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He therefore who sweareth by the altar, sweareth by it and by all on it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And he who sweareth by the temple, sweareth by it and by him who dwelleth therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And he who sweareth by heaven, sweareth by the throne of God, and by him who sitteth upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Alas for you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you pay tithe of mint, and dill and cummin, and have neglected the weightier matters of the law; justice, mercy and fidelity. These you ought to have practised without omitting those.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Blind guides, you are skimming off the gnat, and swallowing the camel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Alas for you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you cleanse the outside of the cup and the plate; but on the inside they are full of rapine, and intemperance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Blind Pharisee, cleanse first what is within the cup, and the plate; so the outside will be clean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Alas for you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you are like whitened sepulchres. These indeed appear beautiful on the outside; but within they are full of dead men's bones, and of all Corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In like manner you also appear outwardly to men to be righteous; but you are inwardly full of hypocrisy and iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Alas for you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you build the sepulchres of the prophets and adorn the monuments of the righteous,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and say, If we had been in the days of our fathers we would not have been their accomplices in the blood of the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So you testify against yourselves that you are the sons of them who killed the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>As for you then, fill up the measure of your fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Serpents! brood of vipers! how can you escape the punishment of hell?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For this, behold I am about to send you prophets, wise men and Scribes: and some of them you will kill and crucify; and some of them you will scourge in your synagogues, and persecute from city to city;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>that upon you may come all the righteous blood shed upon the earth; from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zacharias, son of Barachias, whom ye slew between the temple and the altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Verily I say to you, All these things will come upon this generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>O Jerusalem! Jerusalem! thou that killest the prophets and stonest them who are sent to thee! how often have I desired to gather thy children even as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings; but you would not!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>behold this house of yours is left desolate</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>for you. For I say to you, Henceforth you shall not see me until you say, Blessed is he who is coming in the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Jesus went out, and as he was going from the temple, his disciples came to point out to him the buildings of the temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whereupon he said to them, See ye not all these? Verily I say to you, There shall not be left here one stone upon another, which shall not be pulled down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And as he was sitting on the mount of olives, his disciples came to him privately and said, Tell us, when will these things happen; and what will be the sign of thy coming and of the conclusion of this age?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus answering, said to them, Take heed that no one seduce you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For many will come in my name, saying, I am the Christ and will seduce many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>As you will soon hear of wars and rumours of wars, see that you be not troubled. For all these things must happen, but the end is not yet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For nation will rise against nation; and kingdom against kingdom. And there will be famines and pestilences and earthquakes in divers places.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now all these are the beginning of sorrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then they will deliver you up to affliction and put you to death; and you will be hated by all nations on the account of my name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And many will then be stumbled and will deliver up one another and hate one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And many false prophets will rise up and deceive many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And because iniquity will abound, the love of many will grow cold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But he who persevereth to the end shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The good news of the kingdom shall indeed be proclaimed throughout the whole world for a testimony to all the nations. And then will come the end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Therefore when you see the abomination of desolation, which was spoken of by Daniel the prophet, standing in a holy place, (reader attend!)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>then let them who are in Judea flee to the mountains:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and let not him who is on the house top go down, to carry away any thing out of the house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>nor him who is in the field turn back to take up his clothes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But alas for the women with child and for them who give suck in those days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Pray ye therefore that your flight may not be in the winter, nor on a sabbath day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For there will then be great affliction, such as hath not happened from the beginning of the world till now: no, nor ever shall be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Indeed if those days were not shortened, no flesh could escape. But for the sake of the chosen, those days will be shortened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>At that time if any say to you, Lo! the Christ is here! or there! believe it not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For false Christs and false prophets will rise up and give out great signs and wonders, so as to deceive, if it were possible, even the chosen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Behold I have forewarned you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Therefore if they say to you, Behold he is in the desert, go not out. Or, behold he is in the secret apartments! do not believe them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For as the lightning, which breaketh forth from the east, shineth even to the west, so will the coming of the son of man be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For wherever the carcass is, there will the eagles be assembled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now immediately after the tribulation of those days the sun will be darkened and the moon will not give her splendour; and the stars will fall from heaven, and the heavenly powers will be shaken. And then will appear the sign of the son of man in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And then, all the tribes of the land will mourn: and they shall see the son of man coming on the clouds of heaven, with power and great glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And he will send out his messengers with a loud sounding trumpet, and they will gather his chosen ones from the four winds; from one extremity of heaven to the other.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now learn this parable from that fig tree. When its branches become tender and put forth leaves, you know that the summer is near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So when you see all these things, know assuredly that he is near; at the door.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Verily I say to you, This generation shall not pass until all these things shall happen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The heaven and the earth shall fail; but my words shall not fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But with respect to the day and the season, that none knoweth, not even the angels of the heavens; none but my father only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For as the days of Noe were, so also will this coming of the son of man be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For as in those days, before the deluge, they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, till Noe entered the ark;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and they did not know till the flood came and swept them all away; so will this coming of the son of man be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Two men will then be in the field; the one is taken and the other left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Two women will be grinding at the mill, the one is taken and the other left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Watch therefore, because you know not at what season your lord cometh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>But this you know, that if the master of a family knew at what watch the thief would come, he would be upon guard and not suffer him to break into his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Be ye therefore ready prepared, because the son of man cometh at an hour you least expect.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Who is indeed the faithful and prudent servant, whom his lord hath set over his household to give them their food in due season.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Happy that servant, whom his lord when he cometh shall find thus employed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Verily I say to you, he will set him over all his estate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>But if that servant being wicked should say in his heart, My lord delayeth his coming;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>and begin to beat his fellow tenants, and to eat and to drink with drunkards;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>the lord of that servant will come on a day he least expecteth, and at an hour of which he is not aware</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>and will scourge him in the severest manner and assign him his portion with the hypocrites. Weeping and gnashing of teeth will be there.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now with respect to this, the reign of the heavens may be compared to ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And five of them were prudent and five foolish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They who were foolish took their lamps, but did not take oil with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But the prudent took oil in their vessels with their lamps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And while the bridegroom tarried they all became drowsy and fell asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And at midnight there was a cry, Behold the bridegroom is coming; Go out and meet him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then all the virgins arose and trimmed their lamps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the foolish said to the prudent, Give us some of your oil, for our lamps are going out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>In reply to which the prudent said, Perhaps there will not be enough for us and you. Therefore go rather to them who sell, and buy for yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And while they were going to buy, the bridegroom came, and they who were ready went in with him to the wedding, and the door was shut.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And after that the other virgins came, saying, Master, master, Open to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But he in reply, said, Verily I say to you, I do not know you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Watch therefore, because you do not know the day, nor the hour, when the son of man cometh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For he is like a man who, intending to travel, called his servants and committed to them his effects,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and to one gave five talents and to another two, and to another one; to every one according to his respective ability, and straightway set out on his journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then he who had received the five talents went and traded with them, and made five other talents;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and in like manner he who had received the two gained also other two;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>but he who received the one went and digged a hole in the ground and hid his master's money:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and after a long time the master of these servants cometh and reckoneth with them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>whereupon he who had received the five talents came and brought other five talents, saying, Sir, thou deliveredst to me five talents, here are besides them five other talents, which I have gained:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and his master said to him; Well done, good and faithful servant, thou hast been faithful in a small trust, I will give thee a much greater; enter into the joy of thy master:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>then he who had received the two talents came and said, Sir, thou deliveredst to me two talents, here are, besides them, two other talents, which I have gained:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>his master said to him, Well done, good and faithful servant, thou hast been faithful in a small trust, I will give thee a much greater, enter thou into the joy of thy master:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>then he, who had received the one talent, came and said, Sir, I knew that thou art a hard man, reaping where thou hast not sown, and gathering where thou didst not scatter; so,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>being afraid, I went and hid thy talent in the earth. Here it is. Thou hast what is thine own.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Thereupon his master said to him in reply, Malignant and slothful servant! Thou knowest that I reap where I did not sow, and gather where I did not scatter!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thou shouldst therefore have lodged my money with the bankers, that at my return I might have received mine own with interest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Take therefore the talent from him; and give it to him who hath the ten talents.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For to every one who improveth more shall be given, and he shall abound; but from him who improveth not, even what he hath shall be taken away:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and turn out this unprofitable servant into outer darkness; weeping and gnashing of teeth will be there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>So when the son of man shall come in his glory, and all the holy angels with him; he will then sit on the throne of his glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And before him shall be assembled all the nations. And he will separate them one from another, as a shepherd separateth the sheep from the goats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And he will place the sheep on the right hand and the goats on his left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then the king will say to them on his right, Come ye blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom which hath been prepared for you from the formation of the world:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>for I was hungry, and you gave me food; I was thirsty, and you gave me drink; I was a stranger, and you lodged me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>naked, and you clothed me; sick, and you took care of me; I was in prison, and you visited me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then the righteous will answer him, saying, Lord, when did we see thee hungry, and feed thee; or thirsty, and give thee drink?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>When saw we thee a stranger, and lodged thee; or naked, and clothed thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Or when saw we thee sick, or in prison, and came to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And the king in reply will say to them, Verily I say to you, Inasmuch as you have done this to one of these my brethren, even the least, you have done it to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then he will say to them on his left, Depart from me, ye cursed, into the fire which is everlasting; that prepared for the devil and his angels!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>For I was hungry, and you gave me no food; I was thirsty, and you gave me no drink;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>I was a stranger, and you did not lodge me; naked, and you did not clothe me; sick, and in prison, and you did not visit me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Then they also will answer him, saying, Lord, when did we see thee hungry, or thirsty, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and did not minister to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And he will answer them, saying, Verily I say to you, Inasmuch as you have not done this to any, the least of these, you have not done it to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>So these shall go to everlasting punishment and the righteous to an everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus had finished all these discourses, he said to his disciples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You know that two days hence is the passover, when the son of man is to be delivered up to be crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>At that time the chief priests, and the Scribes, and the elders of the people, were convened to the court of the high priest, whose name was Caiaphas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and were consulting how they might take Jesus by surprise and kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And they said, Not at the festival, that there may not be a tumult among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now when Jesus was at Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>there came to him a woman, having an alabaster box of precious balsam, which she poured on his head while he was at table.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>At seeing this, his disciples expressed indignation, saying, Why this profusion!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For this balsam might have been sold for a great sum, and given to the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus, knowing it, said to them, Why trouble ye the woman? For she hath done a good office for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For you have the poor always with you; but me you have not always.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For in pouring this balsam on my body, she hath done it to embalm me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Verily I say to you, In what part soever of the world these glad tidings shall be proclaimed, mention will also be made of what she hath done, for a memorial of her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then one of the twelve, named Judas Iscariot, went to the chief priests,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and said, What will you give me, and I will deliver him up to you. And they weighed to him thirty shekels of silver:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And from that time he watched an opportunity to deliver him up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now, on the first day of unleavened bread, his disciples came to Jesus, and said to him, Where wilt thou have us make preparation for thee to eat the passover?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And he said, Go to the city, to such a person, and say to him, The teacher saith, My time is near. At thy house I am about to celebrate the passover with my disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Accordingly the disciples did as Jesus commanded them, and prepared the passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the evening was come he placed himself at the table, with the twelve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And while they were eating, he said, Verily I say to you, One of you is to deliver me up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And they being very sorrowful, began every one of them to say to him, Master, am I?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Whereupon he answering, said, One who hath dipped his hand in the dish with me is to deliver me up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The son of man goeth indeed as it is written of him. But alas for that man by whom the son of man is delivered up. Good were it for that man if he had never been born.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Even Judas who was about to deliver him up, having taken occasion, said, Am I, Rabbi? He saith to him, As thou hast said.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now as they were eating, Jesus having taken the loaf and pronounced a blessing, broke and gave to the disciples, and said, Take, eat; This is my body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then having taken the cup and given thanks, he gave it to them, saying, Drink ye all of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For this is my blood; that of the new covenant; that shed for many, for the remission of sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now I say to you, I will not henceforth drink of the product of the vine; until the day when I shall drink it new with you in my father's kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And after the hymn they went out to the mount of olives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then Jesus saith to them, You will all be stumbled at me this night; for it is written, I will smite the shepherd and the sheep of the flock will be dispersed!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But after I am risen, I will go before you to Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Thereupon Peter addressing him, said, Though all should be stumbled at thee; as for me, I will never be stumbled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus said to him, Verily I say to thee, This very night, before cock crowing, thou wilt three times deny me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Peter saith to him, Though I should die with thee, I will not deny thee. And so said all the disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then Jesus goeth with them to a place called Gethsemane, and saith to the disciples, Stay here while I go yonder to pray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And having taken with him Peter, and the two sons of Zebedee, he began to be in an agony of grief and distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Whereupon he saith to them, My soul is overwhelmed with anguish 9 even to death. Stay here and watch with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Then, advancing a little further, he fell prostrate on his face, and prayed, saying, O my father, if it be possible, let this cup be removed from me. Nevertheless not as I would, but as thou wiliest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Then he cometh to the disciples, and finding them asleep, he saith to Peter, So, could you not watch one hour with me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Watch and pray, that you may not come to a trial. The spirit indeed is willing; but the flesh is weak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Again he went away the second time, and prayed, saying, O my father! If this cup cannot be removed from me, without my drinking it; thy will be done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then coming, he findeth them again sleeping; for their eyes were weighed down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>So, leaving them he withdrew again, and prayed a third time, to the same purpose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Then he cometh to these disciples of his, and saith to them, Are you still sleeping and taking repose? Behold the hour is come, and the son of man is delivered up into the hands of sinners.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Arise; let us go. Behold he who delivereth me up is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And while he was yet speaking, lo! Judas, one of the twelve, came, and with him a great multitude with swords and clubs, from the chief priests, and the elders of the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Now his betrayer had given them a sign, saying, The person I shall kiss is he; Secure him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>So coming directly up to Jesus, he said, Hail, Rabbi! and kissed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>And Jesus said to him, Companion! for what purpose art thou come? Then others, advancing, laid hands on Jesus, and held him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Upon which one of them who were with Jesus, stretching forth his hand, drew his sword, and smote the servant of the high priest, and cut off his ear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus saith to him, Return thy sword to its place. For are all who have taken a sword to perish by a sword?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Or dost thou think that I cannot now address ray father, who can send to my assistance, more than twelve legions of angels?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>How then would the scriptures be fulfilled, that thus it must be?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>At that instant Jesus was saying to the multitudes, Are you come out as against a rubber with swords and clubs, to take me? Day after day I sat before you teaching in the temple, and you did not lay hold on me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>But all this is done that the writings of the prophets may be confirmed. Then all the disciples forsook him and fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>And they who had hold of Jesus led him away to Caiaphas, the high priest, where the Scribes and the elders of the people were assembled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Now Peter followed him at a distance, even to the court of the high priest. And having gone in, he sat down with the attendants, to see the issue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>And the chief priests and the elders, even the whole Sanhedrim, sought false testimony against Jesus that they might put him to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>but found it not. Though many false witnesses came forward, they did not find it. At last two false witnesses came,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>who said, This man said, I can destroy the temple of God and in three days rebuild it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>Then the chief priest, standing up, said to him, Answerest thou nothing to what these testify against thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>But Jesus was silent. Then the chief priest addressing him, said, I adjure thee by the living God, that thou tell us whether thou art the Christ, the son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, It is as thou hast spoken. Moreover I say to you, Hereafter you shall see the son of man sitting at the right hand of that Power, and coming on the clouds of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>Upon this the high priest rent his clothes, saying, He hath blasphemed. What further need have we of witnesses? Behold you have now heard his blasphemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>What think ye? Thereupon they, answering, said, He is guilty of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>Then they spat in his face and struck him with their fists,68 and smote him with staves, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>Prophesy to us Christ. Who is he that smote thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>Now when Peter was sitting without, in the court, a servant maid came up to him and said, Thou also wast with Jesus the Galilean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>And he denied before them all, saying, I do not know what thou sayest</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>And as he was going out into the porch another maid saw him, and saith to them there, That man also was with Jesus the Nazarene.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>And he again denied, with an oath, I do not know the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="73">
      <content>And a little after, some byestanders came up and said to Peter, Thou also art certainly one of them, for thy speech discovereth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="74">
      <content>Then he began to curse and to swear, I do not know the man. And immediately a cock crowed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="75">
      <content>Whereupon Peter recollected the word which Jesus said to him, Before cockcrowing thou wilt three times deny me; and going out, he wept bitterly.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now early in the morning, all the chief priests and the elders of the people took counsel against Jesus to have him put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So, having bound him, they led him away and delivered him up to Pontius Pilate the governor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then Judas, who had delivered him up, finding that he was condemned, repented and carried back the thirty shekels of silver to the chief priests and the elders,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>saying, I have sinned in having betrayed innocent blood To which they replied, What is that to us? Look thou to that.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thereupon he threw down the money in the temple, and withdrew, and went and strangled himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the chief priests, taking the money, said; It is not lawful to put it into the holy treasury, seeing it is the price of blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So, having consulted together, they bought with it the pottor's field for the burial of strangers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore that field is ever since called the field of blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then was fulfilled that, which was spoken by the prophet Jeremias, saying, So I took the thirty pieces of silver, as the Lord commanded me. These being the price of him who was valued, whom some of the Israelites valued;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>these they gave for the potter's field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now when Jesus stood before the governor, the governor asked him, saying, Thou art the king of the Jews? And Jesus said to him, as thou hast said, I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But when he was accused by the chief priests and the elders, he made no reply.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Pilate said to him, Dost thou not hear what they testify against thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But he made no reply to any charge; so that the governor was greatly surprised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now at a festival it was customary for the governor to release to the people any one prisoner whom they desired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And they had then a noted prisoner named Barabbas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So when they were assembled, Pilate said to them, Whom do you desire me to release to you? Barabbas; or Jesus who is called Christ?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For he knew that out of envy they had delivered him up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And while he was sitting on the tribunal, his wife had sent to him, saying, Have nothing to do with that righteous person; for I have this day suffered much in a dream on his account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But the chief priests and the elders had prevailed on the people that they should demand Barabbas, and destroy Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So when the governor, addressing them, said, Which of the two do you desire me to release to you? They said, Barabbas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Pilate saith to them, What then shall I do with Jesus who is called Christ? They all say to him, Let him be crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thereupon the governor said, Why, what evil hath he done? But they with more vehemence cried, Let him be crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>When Pilate saw that he could not in the least prevail, but that a tumult rather was rising, he took water and washed his hands before the multitude, saying, I am clear from the blood of this innocent person. Look ye to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Upon which all the people, answering, said, His blood be upon us and upon our children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then he released to them Barabbas, and having scourged Jesus, delivered him up to be crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus to the pretorium, and assembled about him the whole cohort.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And having stripped him, they threw around him a scarlet military robe:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and having platted a crown of thorns, they put it on his head, and a reed in his right hand; and falling on their knees before him, they mocked him, saying, Hail king of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then, having spit in his face, they took the reed and struck him on the head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And when they had mocked him, they took off the robe, and put his own raiment on him, and led him out to be crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And as they were going out, they met a man of Cyrene, named Simon, and compelled him to carry the cross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And having come to a place called Golgotha, (the meaning of which is the place of a skull)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>they gave him to drink vinegar mingled with a bitter drug, which, when he tasted, he would not drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then, having crucified him, they parted his garments by lot, thus verifying what was spoken by the prophet, They parted my garments among them; and for my vesture they cast lots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And, sitting down, they guarded him there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Now over his head they had placed this inscription, denoting the charge against him, This is Jesus the king of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>At the same time two robbers were crucified with him, one on his right hand, and the other on his left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And they who passed by reviled him, shaking their heads,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and saying, Thou the demolisher of the temple and the rebuilder of it in three days, save thyself. If thou art the Son of God, come down from the cross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>In like manner also the chief priests, and the Scribes, and the elders, deriding him, said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>He saved others; cannot he save himself? If he be the king of Israel, let him now come down from the cross, and We will believe him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>He trusted in God; let him now deliver him, if he delighteth in him: for, he said, I am the Son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Nay, even the robbers, who were crucified with him, upbraided him in the same manner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Now from the sixth hour there was darkness over the whole land till the ninth hour:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And about the ninth hour Jesus cried, with a loud voice, saying, Eli, Eli, Lama, Sabachthani, that is, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Where upon some of them who stood there, hearing this, said, He calleth Elias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And immediately one of them ran, and having taken a spunge, soaked it with vinegar, and having fixed it to a reed, gave him to drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>But the rest said, Forbear, let us see, whether Elias will come to save him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>And Jesus, having cried again with a loud voice, expired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And lo! the veil of temple was rent in two from top to bottom; and the earth quaked and the rocks were rent</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>and the tombs were opened. And many bodies of saints, composed to rest, were awakened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>And, having come out of their tombs, after his resurrection, they went into the holy city and appeared to many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>When the centurion, and they who were with him guarding Jesus, observed the earthquake, and what had happened, they were greatly terrified, and said, This was certainly a son of a God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Now many women were there, looking on at a distance, who had accompanied Jesus from Galilee to wait upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Among whom were Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of the sons of Zebedee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>And in the evening there came a rich man of Arimathea, whose name was Joseph, and who himself was a disciple of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>This man having gone to Pilate had begged the body of Jesus; and Pilate had ordered the body to be given to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>So Joseph, having taken the body, wrapped it up in a clean sindon</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>and laid it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn in the rock. And having rolled a great stone to the entrance of the tomb, he went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>But Mary Magdalene and the other Mary continued sitting there over against the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>At the close of the day succeeding the preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees went in a body to Pilate,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>and said, Sir, we have recollected that this impostor, when alive, said, After three days I shall be raised up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>Give orders therefore that the sepulchre be secured till the third day. Perhaps his disciples may come by night, and steal him away, and tell the people, he is risen from the dead. So this last imposture will be worse than the first.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>Thereupon Pilate said to them, You have a guard. Go and secure it as you can.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>So they went and secured the sepulchre, sealing the stone and posting the guard.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the sabbath being over, at the dawn of the first day of the week, Mary Magdalene and the other Mary went to see the sepulchre;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and behold there was a great earthquake. For an angel of the Lord, having descended from heaven, came and rolled away the stone from the entrance, and sat upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>His countenance was like lightning, and his raiment white as snow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And for fear of him the guards trembled, and became as dead men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And the angel accosting the women, said, Be not ye terrified. For I know that you are seeking Jesus who was crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He is not here. For he is risen as he said. Come, see the place where the Lord lay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then go quickly and tell his disciples that he is risen from the dead. And lo he goeth before you to Galilee. There you shall see him. Behold, I have told you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Accordingly, having come out quickly from the tomb, with fear and great joy they ran to tell his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And as they were going to tell his disciples, lo! Jesus met them and said, Peace be to you. Whereupon, they coming near, took hold of his feet and worshipped him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Jesus saith to them, Be not afraid: go tell my brethren that they may go to Galilee; there they shall see me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now while they were going, behold some of the guard, having come to the city, told the chief priests all that had happened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whereupon they, with the elders, assembled and having held a council, they gave a large sum of money to the soldiers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>with this injunction, Say, His disciples came by night and stole him while we were asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And if this come to the governor's ears, we will appease him, and secure you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So they took the money, and did as they were taught. And this is the current report among the Jews even at this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now the eleven disciples went to Galilee, to the mountain whither Jesus ordered them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And some seeing him prostrated themselves before him, and some doubted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then Jesus came near and spoke to them, saying, All power in heaven and on earth is given to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Go therefore and make all the nations disciples, baptizing them to the Name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>teaching them to observe all that I commanded you. And lo! I am with you all the days to the conclusion of this age. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>