<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The beginning of the Gospel of Jesus Christ the Son of God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As it is written in the prophets, Behold I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare the way before thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>A voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare the way of the Lord; make the roads for him straight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>John came baptizing in the wilderness, and proclaiming a baptism of reformation, for a remission of sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And all the country of Judea and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, went out to him, and were all baptized by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now John's clothing was of camel's hair and he had a leathern girdle about his waist. And his food was locusts and wild honey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And he proclaimed saying, There is one coming after me, who is mightier than I, the latchet of whose sandals I am not worthy to stoop down and untie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I indeed have baptized you in water, but he will baptize you in a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And it came to pass in those days, that Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was baptized in the Jordan, by John,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>who immediately upon his coming up from the water, saw the heavens parted asunder, and the Spirit like a dove descending upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And there came a voice from the heavens, Thou art my Son, the Beloved, in whom I am well pleased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Presently after this the Spirit sendeth him forth into the wilderness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and he was there in the wilderness forty days, tempted by Satan, and was with the wild beasts; and the angels ministered to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And after John's imprisonment, Jesus went to Galilee, proclaiming the glad tidings of the reign of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and saying, The time is accomplished, and the reign of God is at hand. Reform and confide in this good news.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And as he was walking along the sea of Galilee, he saw Simon, and Andrew his brother, casting a drag net, into the sea; for they were fishermen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and Jesus said to them, Come with me and I will make you fishers of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thereupon they straightway left their nets and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And going thence a little further, he saw James, the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, who were in the vessel, mending the nets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And soon as he called them, they left their father Zebedee in the vessel, with the hired servants, and went after him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they come to Capernaum; and thenceforward on the sabbath days, he went to the synagogue and taught;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and they were astonished at his manner of teaching; for he taught as one having authority and not as the Scribes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now there was in their synagogue a man with an unclean spirit, and he cried aloud,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>saying, Forbear! what hast thou to do with us, Jesus of Nazareth? Art thou come to destroy us? I know who thou art; the Holy One of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus rebuked him, saying, Be silent and go out of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the unclean spirit, having convulsed the man, and screamed with a loud voice, went out of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>At which all were so amazed, that they asked one another, saying, What is this? What new teaching is this? For with authority he commandeth even the unclean spirits, and they obey him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And thenceforth his fame spread through all the region of Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Immediately on their going out of the synagogue they went to the house of Simon and Andrew, with James and John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And as Simon's mother in law was confined to her bed with a fever, they forthwith spake to him about her;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>whereupon he went to her, and taking hold of her hand, raised her up, and instantly the fever left her, and she waited on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And in the evening, when the sun was set, they brought to him all their sick, and those who were possessed by demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the whole city was assembled at the door.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And he healed many who were sick of various diseases, and cast out many demons; and he permitted not the demons to say they knew him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And in the morning, when the night was far advanced, he arose and went out, and retired to a solitary place, and there prayed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and Simon, and they who were with him, went in quest of him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and having found him they say to him, They are all seeking thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Whereupon he saith to them, Let us go to the neighbouring villages, that I may there also make proclamation, for I am come forth for that purpose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Accordingly he proceeded, proclaiming the news in their synagogues, through all Galilee, and casting out demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And there cometh to him a leper, who on his knees intreated him, saying, If thou wilt, thou canst cleanse me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And Jesus had compassion, and stretched forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will: be thou cleansed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And while he was speaking, the leprosy instantly left the man, and he was cleansed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then having restrained him, he sent him away immediately,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>saying to him, See thou say nothing to any one; but go, shew thyself to the priest, and offer for thy purification what Moses hath commanded, for a testimony to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>But when he went out he began to proclaim freely and publish the matter abroad, so that Jesus could no more go openly into a city, but continued without in solitary places, where people resorted to him from all quarters.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After some days he again entered Capernaum, and the report spread that he was in a house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and such multitudes presently flocked thither, that even the courts before the door could not contain them. And while he was speaking the word to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>some come to him bringing a paralytic, carried by four men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And not being able to come near to him by reason of the crowd, they drew back the covering over the place where he was, and having opened a passage they lowered down the couch on which the paralytic lay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon seeing their faith, Jesus saith to the paralytic, Son, thy sins are forgiven thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now there were some of the Scribes sitting there, and they were reasoning in their minds</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>What! Doth this man thus utter blasphemies! Who can forgive sins but God only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus, perceiving immediately by his spirit that they are thus reasoning in themselves, said to them, Why do ye reason thus in your hearts?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Which is easier, To say to the paralytic, Thy sins are forgiven thee; or to say, Arise, take up thy couch, and walk?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But that you may know that the son of man hath power on the earth to forgive sins, (he saith to the paralytic)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I say to thee, Arise, take up thy couch, and go to thy house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thereupon he arose immediately; and having taken up the couch, went out in the presence of them all. So that they were all amazed, and glorified God, saying, We never saw any thing like this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And he went out again to the sea side, and all the multitude came to him, and he taught them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now as he passed on he saw Levi, the son of Alpheus, sitting at the custom house, and saith to him, Follow me. Whereupon he arose and followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And it came to pass that when Jesus was at table, in this man's house, many publicans and sinners were at table, with Jesus and his disciples; for many of them followed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When the Scribes and the Pharisees saw him eating with these publicans and sinners, they said to his disciples, What! Doth he eat and drink with these publicans and sinners!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This being in the hearing of Jesus, he saith to them, They who are in health have no need of a physician; but they who are sick. I did not come to call righteous men, but sinners, to a reformation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now it was customary for the disciples of John, and those of the Pharisees, to fast. Therefore they come and say to him, Why do the disciples of John, and those of the Pharisees, fast;19 but thy disciples do not fast?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to them, Can the bridemen fast, while the bridegroom is with them? So long as they have the bridegroom with them, they cannot fast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But the days will come, when the bridegroom will be taken from them, and then they will fast in those days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>No one seweth a patch, of undressed cloth on an old garment, else the new patch teareth the old cloth, and the rent is made worse.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And no one putteth new wine into old leathern bottles; else the new wine bursteth the bottles. Thus the wine is spilled and the bottles are rendered useless. But new wine is to be put into new bottles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>At another time, as he was passing through corn fields, on the sabbath days, it happened that his disciples, as they passed along, began to pluck the ears.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Whereupon the Pharisees said to him, See! Why are they doing what is not lawful, on the sabbath days?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And he said to them, Did you never read what David did when he was in a strait; and he and his company were hungry?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>How he went to the house of God in the days of Abiathar, the high priest, and ate the presence loaves, which it is not lawful for any but the priests to eat, and gave thereof to his attendants?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Moreover he said to them, The sabbath was made for man, not man for the sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>So that the son of man is lord even of the sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when he again went to the synagogue, there was a man there who had a withered hand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and they watched him to see whether he would heal on the sabbath, that they might accuse him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thereupon he saith to the man who had the withered hand. Stand up in the midst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then he saith to them. Is h lawful to do good on the sabbath days, or to do evil? To save life, or to kill? But they were silent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then looking round on them with indignation, being grieved for the blindness of their mind, he saith to the man, Stretch forth thy hand. Accordingly he stretched it out, and his hand was restored whole as the other.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon this the Pharisees went out, and immediately held a consultation with the Herodians against him, how they might destroy him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Again 'Jesus withdrew with his disciples to the sea, and a great multitude followed him from Galilee, and from Judea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and from Jerusalem, and from Idumea, and from the banks of the Jordan. They also around Tyre and Sidon, having heard what he did, flocked to him in crowds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then he gave orders to his disciples that a boat should attend him, because of the multitude, that they might not throng him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For he healed many; so that they who had maladies, pressed in upon him to touch him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the unclean spirits; when they saw him, prostrated themselves before him, and cried out, saying, Thou art the Son of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>though he strictly charged them not to make him known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then he goeth up to the mountain, and calleth to him whom he would, and they went up to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And he appointed twelve, that they might be with him, and that he might send them to make proclamation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and to have power to cure diseases, and expel demons;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>namely, Simon, whom he surnamed Peter,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and James, the son of Zebedee, and John, the brother of James, (these he surnamed Boanerges, that is, sons of thunder)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James the son of Alpheus, and Thaddeus, and Simon the Chananite,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and Judas Iscariot, who delivered him up. Upon their going into a house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>a crowd again assembled, so that they could not so much as eat bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And when they who were just from it, heard, and were going out to restrain it, (for some said, He is distracted,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the Scribes who had come down from Jerusalem, said, He is possessed by Beelzebub, and by the prince of the demons he expelleth the demons;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus having called them to him, said to them in parables, How can Satan expel Satan?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If indeed a kingdom be divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and if a family be divided against itself, that family cannot subsist;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and if Satan is risen up against himself, and divided, he cannot subsist; but hath an end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>No one can enter the house of the strong, and plunder his goods, unless he first bind the strong one. Then indeed he may rifle his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Verily I say to you, All transgressions may be forgiven the sons of men, and what slanderous speeches soever they may utter,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>but whoever shall utter slanders against the Holy Spirit, hath not forgiveness in this age, but is liable to everlasting punishment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Because it was said he hath an unclean spirit,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>therefore his brethren, and his mother come, and having stood without, sent for him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>as the multitude sat around him. And when they said to him, Behold thy mother and thy brethren are Who had just come in from the crowd at the gate, without, inquiring for thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>he answered them, saying, Who is my mother? And who are my brethren?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then looking round on them who sat about him, he saith, Behold my mother and my brethren!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>For whosoever will do the will of God, the same is my brother, and sister, and mother.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when he began to teach again by the sea side, so great a multitude gathered about him, that he went on board the small vessel, and sat at sea, and all the multitude were on the sea shore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And he taught them many things in parables. and in his manner of teaching, said to them, Hearken!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Behold the sower went out to sow!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And it happened that as he was sowing, some fell on the highway, and the birds of the air came and devoured it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And some fell on rocky ground, where it had not much depth of soil; and it sprang up immediately, because it had not depth of soil,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but when the sun was up, it was scorched, and, for want of root, withered away:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and some fell among thorns, and the thorns sprang up and choked it, so that it yielded no fruit:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and some fell on good ground, which sprang up and yielded fruit, growing and thriving and bringing forth, some thirty, and some sixty, and some an hundred fold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then he said to them, Whoever hath ears to hear, let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when he was in private they who were about him. with the twelve, asked him the meaning of this parable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Whereupon he said to them, To you it is granted to know the secrets of the reign of God; but to those without, all these things are delivered in parables,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>so that seeing they see, though they may not perceive; and hearing they hear, though they may not understand. Perhaps they may turn, that their sins may be forgiven them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then he saith to them, Do ye not comprehend this parable? How then will you understand all the parables?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The sower soweth the word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now these are they by the way side, where the word is sown, who have no sooner heard, than Satan cometh, and taketh away the word which was sown in their hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And in like manner the rocky ground denoteth those, who, when they hear the word, receive it immediately with joy;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but not having it rooted in them, they are but temporary; so that when tribulation, or persecution cometh because of the word, they are instantly stumbled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And these are they sown among thorns, who hear the word,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but the cares of this world, and the delusion of riches, and inordinate desires of other things, crowd in and choke the word, so that it becometh unfruitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And these are they sown on good ground, who hear the word and receive it, and bring forth fruit, some, thirty; and some, sixty; and some, an hundred fold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then he said to them, Is a lamp brought to be put under the corn measure, or under the bed? Is it not that it may be set on a stand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For there is nothing hidden which shall not be discovered, nor any thing laid up in secret, but that it may be brought to light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If any one hath ears to hear, let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Moreover he said to them, Consider what you hear. With whatever measure you deal out, you shall receive; and to you who are attentive more shall be given.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For to him who improveth, more shall be given; but from him who improveth not, even what he hath shall be taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Again he said, The reign of God is as when a man soweth seed on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Whether he sleepeth or waketh, night and day, the seed groweth and increaseth, he knoweth not how.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For the earth of itself produceth first a blade, then an ear, then full grains in the ear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when the grain is ripe, he forthwith applieth the sickle, because the harvest is come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Again he said, To what may we compare the reign of God? Or by what similitude may we represent it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>It is like a grain of mustard seed, which, when it is sown in the ground, is one of the very smallest seeds there:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>but, being sown, it springeth up and becometh larger than all plants of the pulse kind, and shooteth out large branches, so that under its shade the birds of the air can find shelter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And with many such parables he spake the word to them as they were able to hear it:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>but without a parable he did not speak to them. And in private he explained all to his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the same day, in the evening, he saith to them. Let us cross over to the other side.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>So, leaving the multitude, they take him along with them as he was on board. And there were some other small vessels with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And there arose a violent storm of wind, and the waves beat into the vessel, so that it would soon be full.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Now he was in the stem, asleep on a pillow. And they awake him, and say, Teacher, carest thou not that we perish?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Thereupon he arose and rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, Peace, be still. And the wind ceased, and there was a great calm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Then he said to them, Why are you so much afraid. How is it that you have not faith?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And they were exceedingly terrified, and said one to another, Who in reality is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when they arrived at the other side, in the country of the Gaderenes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>just as he was stepping out of the vessel, there met him a man coming out from among the tombs, with an unclean spirit,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>who made his abode in the tombs, and whom no one could confine; no, not even with chains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For he had often been bound with fetters and chains; but he burst the chains and broke in pieces the fetters, so that none could tame him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And he was continually, night and day, on the mountains and in the tombs, screaming, and cutting himself with stones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But upon seeing Jesus at a distance, he ran, and prostrating himself,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>cried with a loud voice, saying, What hast thou to do with me, Jesus, son of the most high God? I conjure thee by God not to torment me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For he had said to him, Go out of the man, thou unclean spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then he asked him, What is thy name? And he answered, saying, My name is Legion; for we are many,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and earnestly intreated him not to send them out of that country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now there was there on the mountains, a great herd of swine feeding,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and all the demons besought him, saying, Send us to the swine that we may enter into them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And Jesus immediately permitted them. Whereupon the unclean spirits, having gone out, entered into the swine, and the herd rushed down a precipice into the sea, (now they were about two thousand) and were drowned in the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And they who fed the swine fled, and told the news in town and country. And the people came out to see what had happened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when they came to Jesus and saw the demoniac; him who had the legion, sitting, and clothed, and in his right mind, they were terrified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when the eye witnesses told them what was done to the demoniac, and respecting the swine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>they began to intreat him to withdraw from their territories.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And as he was going on board the vessel the late demoniac besought him that he might go with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But Jesus did not permit him, but saith to him, Go home to thy friends, and tell them what the Lord hath done for thee, and hath had compassion on thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So he departed, and began to proclaim in Decapolis all that Jesus had done for him. And they were all amazed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And when Jesus had repassed in the vessel to the other side, a great multitude gathered about him, and he continued by the sea side.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And behold there cometh to him one of the rulers of the synagogue, whose name was Jairus, who, upon seeing him, falleth at his feet</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and intreateth him earnestly, saying, My little daughter is at the point of death, pray come and lay thy hands on her that she may be cured, and she will live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>So Jesus went with him, followed by a great multitude which pressed about him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And a certain woman, who had been twelve years afflicted with an issue of blood,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and who had suffered much under many physicians, and spent all that she had, and instead of being any thing the better, rather grew worse,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>having heard of Jesus, came behind him, in the crowd, and touched his mantle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For she said, If I can but touch his clothes, I shall be cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And instantly the source of her disorder was dried up, and she felt in her body that she was cured of that disorder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus conscious of the power which had gone forth from him, turning about immediately, in the crowd, said, Who touched my clothes?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Upon which his disciples said to him, Thou seest how the crowd throng thee, and dost thou say, Who touched me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Still he looked round to see her who had done this,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>when the woman, knowing what had been done for her, came trembling with fear, and prostrating herself before him, told him the whole truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Whereupon he said to her, Daughter, thy faith hath cured thee. Go in peace, and continue cured of that disorder of thine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now while he was speaking, messengers came from the ruler's house, who said, Thy daughter is dead, why troublest thou the teacher any further?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Upon hearing this message delivered, Jesus immediately saith to the ruler of the synagogue,57 Be not afraid. Only believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then he permitted none to accompany him, but Peter and James, and John the brother of James.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And coming to the house of the ruler of the synagogue, and seeing a tumultuous crowd weeping and wailing immoderately,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>he saith to them, as he was going in, Why make ye this ado, and weep? The child is not dead, but asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Upon which they derided him. But he, having put them all out, taketh with him the father and mother of the child, and them who accompanied him, and goeth into the room where the child was laid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And, taking hold of the child's hand, he saith to her, Talitha cumi, the meaning of which is, damsel, I say to thee, Arise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And immediately the damsel arose and walked about; for she was twelve years old. Upon which they were struck with great astonishment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Then he strictly charged them that none should know this, and ordered something to be given her to eat.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Having left that place, he went to his own country, and his disciples accompany him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and on the sabbath day he began to teach in the synagogue. And many who heard were astonished, and said, Whence hath this man these things? And, What wisdom is this which is given him, that such miracles are done by his hands?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Is not this the carpenter, the son of Mary, and the brother of James, and Joses, and Judas, and Simon? And are not his sisters here with us? So they were stumbled at him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Upon which Jesus said to them, A prophet is not without honour, save in his own country, and among his kindred, and in his own family.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So he could not perform any miracle there, save that he laid his hands on a few sick persons and healed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And he expressed wonder at their unbelief. When he was going round the neighbouring villages, teaching,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>he calleth to him the twelve, and began to send them forth, by two and two, and gave them power over the unclean spirits;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and ordered them to take nothing for the journey, but only a staff; no scrip, no bread, no money in their purse;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>but to be shod with sandals; and not to put on two coats.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And he said to them, Wherever you enter a house, continue there till you leave that place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And whosoever will not receive you, nor hearken to you, when you depart thence shake off the dirt which is under your feet, as a testimony against them. Verily I say to you, the condition of Sodom and Gomorra will be more tolerable in a day of vengeance, than the condition of that city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So they went forth and proclaimed, that men should reform.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And they cast out many demons, and anointed with oil many who were sick, and healed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now when king Herod heard of him, (for his name was become famous) he said, John the baptizer is risen from the dead, and therefore these miracles are performed by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Some said, It is Elias; and others said, It is a prophet, or a person like one of the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But when Herod heard of him, he said, This is John, whom I beheaded. He is risen from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For Herod had sent and apprehended John, and confined him in prison, on account of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife, whom he had married.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For John had said to Herod, It is not lawful for thee to have thy brother's wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore Herodias was enraged at him, and wished to kill him, but could not;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for Herod revered John, knowing him to be a righteous and holy man; and he protected him, and did many things by his advice, and heard him with pleasure:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>At length a favourable opportunity occurred. When Herod, on his birth day, made an entertainment for the great officers of his court and army, and the chiefs of Galilee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and the daughter of this same Herodias came in and danced, and pleased Herod and his guests, the king said to the damsel, Ask of me what thou wilt, and I will give it thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>nay, he swore to her, Whatever thou shalt ask of me, I will give, even to the half of my kingdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Upon this she went out and said to her mother, What shall I ask? And she said, The head of John the baptist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>So coming in immediately with all haste to the king, she made her request, saying, I desire thee to give me forthwith, in a basin, the head of John the baptist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Though the king was much grieved, yet from a regard to his oaths, and his guests, he would not refuse her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So the king immediately despatched a sentinel with orders to bring the head of the baptist. And he went and beheaded him in the prison,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and brought his head in a basin, and gave it to the damsel: and the damsel gave it to her mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when his disciples heard this, they went and took up his body, and laid it in a sepulchre.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now the apostles come together again to Jesus, and when they had given him a full account both of what they had done, and what they had taught,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>he said to them, Come by yourselves privately, to a solitary place, and rest yourselves a little while. For there were so many coming and going that they had not leisure even to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>So they went away by themselves, in the vessel, to a solitary place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the multitudes saw them going, and many knew the place, and ran thither by land, in. crowds, from all the cities, and got there before them, and assembled to meet him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>When Jesus landed and saw a great multitude, he had compassion on them, because they were like sheep which have no shepherd; and he began to teach them many things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And the day being now far spent, his disciples came to him and said, This is a desert place, and the day is now far spent,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Dismiss them, that they may go to the neighbouring farms and villages, and buy themselves bread, for they have nothing to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And he in reply, said to them, Supply them ye yourselves. Thereupon they say to him, Must we go and buy bread to the amount of two hundred deniars for them to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>He saith to them, How many loaves have you? Go and see. And having examined, they say, Five, and two fishes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Then he ordered them to make all the people place themselves as at table on the grass, in several companies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Accordingly they arranged themselves in rows, by hundreds and by fifties.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then he took the five loaves and the two fishes, and having looked up to heaven, he pronounced a blessing. Then he broke the loaves, and gave to his disciples to set before them, and distributed the two fishes among them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And when they had all eaten, and were satisfied,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>there were carried away twelve panniers full of the fragments, and the remains of the fishes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Now they who had eaten of the loaves were about five thousand men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Immediately after this, he constrained his disciples to embark, and go before him to the other side, to Bethsaida; while he dismissed the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And when he had sent them away, he retired to the mountain to pray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And in the course of the evening the vessel was in the midst of the sea, and he all alone on the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And he saw them toiling at the oar; for the wind was contrary. And about the fourth watch of the night, he goeth to them, walking on the sea, and seemed inclined to pass them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>But they, seeing him walking on the sea, thought it was an apparition, and uttered a loud scream.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>For they all saw him, and were terrified. Whereupon he immediately spoke to them, saying, Take courage: it is I; be not afraid;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>and went on board to them. And the wind ceased. At which they were still more excessively astonished and expressed admiration.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>For they had not come to a right understanding by the loaves. For their understanding was callous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>And having crossed over, they came to the region of Genesaret, and put into port.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>And on their going out of the vessel the people knew him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>And, running through the whole country around, they began to bring the sick on beds, to every place where they heard he was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>And wherever he entered towns, or cities, or villages, they laid the sick in the streets, and begged that they might but touch the tuft of his mantle. And as many as touched were cured.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the Pharisees, and some of the Scribes who had come from Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>resort to him in a body, and seeing some of his disciples eating bread with unclean, that is with unwashen hands, they found fault.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the Pharisees, and all the Jews, holding the doctrine of the elders, do not eat with out washing the hands with the doubled fist:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and if they come from the market they do not eat without dipping them. And there are many other usages which they have adopted, such as the dipping of cups, and pots, and brass vessels, and couches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Therefore the Pharisees and the Scribes ask him, Why do not thy disciples walk according to the doctrines of the elders, but eat bread with unwashen hands?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In reply to which he said to them, Well did Esaias prophesy concerning you, hypocrites; as it is written, This people honour me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And in vain do they worship me, teaching doctrines, the commands of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For laying aside the commandment of God, you adhere to the doctrine of men; the dipping of cups, and drinking vessels, and many other things, of the like nature.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Indeed said he to them, You fairly annul the commandment of God to make room for this doctrine of yours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For Moses said, Honour thy father and thy mother; and, Let him who curseth father or mother be put to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But you say, If a man say to his father, or to his mother, Let that be Corban, (that is to say dedicated,) by which thou mightest be benefitted by me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>do not then permit him any more to do any thing for his father or his mother;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>thus annulling the word of God, by this doctrine of yours, which you have handed down. And thus you act in many other instances.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then having called to him the whole multitude he said to them, Hearken to me, all of you, and understand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>There is nothing from without, which by entering into a man can defile him; but the things which proceed from within him, are those which defile a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If any one hath ears to hear, let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when he withdrew from the multitude into a house, his disciples asked him concerning this parable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whereupon he saith to them, Are you also so void of understanding? Do you not perceive that nothing which entereth into a man from without can defile him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>because it doth not enter into the heart; but into the belly, and the of scouring of all meats passeth out into the sink?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But, said he, it is that which cometh out of a man, which defileth him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For from within, out of the heart of man, proceed those evil surmises, adulteries, fornications, murders,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>thefts, inordinate desires, malice, fraud, sensuality, envy, detraction, pride, foolishness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>All these are the evil things which come from within, and defile the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then he arose and went from that place to the confines of Tyre and Sidon. And having entered the house he desired that none should know. But he could not be concealed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For a woman, whose little daughter had an unclean spirit, having heard of him, came and fell at his feet</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>(now the woman was a Greek, a native of Syrophoenicia) and intreated him to expel the demon out of her daughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But Jesus said to her, Let the children first be satisfied; for it is not seemly to take the children's bread and cast it to the dogs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>To which she, in reply, said to him, True, sir; but still the dogs under the table eat the children's crumbs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Thereupon he said to her, For this saying, Go home. The demon is gone out of thy daughter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>So, going home, she found the demon was gone out, and her daughter lying on the bed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then, quitting the confines of Tyre and Sidon, he came again to the sea of Galilee, along the borders of Decapolis.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And they bring to him a man who was deaf, and had an impediment in his speech, and beseech him to lay his hands on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Whereupon he taketh him apart from the multitude, and put his fingers in his ears, and he spat, and touched his tongue;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then, looking up to heaven, he sighed, and said, Ephphatha, that is, Be opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And immediately his ears were opened, and his tongue loosed, and he spake distinctly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Though he commanded them not to tell any one, yet the more he enjoined them the more abundantly they proclaimed his miracles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And being struck with inexpressible amazement, said, He hath done all things well, he maketh the deaf hear, and the dumb speak.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In those days the multitude being very great, and having nothing to eat, Jesus called his disciples to him, and saith to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I have compassion on the multitude, because they have continued with me now three days and have nothing to eat;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and if I send them home fasting, they will faint by the way, for some of them have come from afar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon his disciples answered, Whence can they be supplied with bread here in the wilderness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And he asked them, How many loaves have you? And they said, Seven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then he ordered the multitude to place themselves on the ground. And having taken the seven loaves, and given thanks, he brake, and gave to his disciples to distribute, and they distributed to the multitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And they had a few small fishes. So, when he had pronounced a blessing, he ordered these also to be served up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when they had eaten, and were satisfied, the fragments which remained were carried off in seven baskets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now they who had eaten were about four thousand.0 And when he had dismissed them</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>he straightway embarked with his disciples, and went to the district of Dalmanutha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the Pharisees came out and began to dispute with him; and, in order to try him, desired of him a sign from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whereupon with a deep sigh, he saith, Why doth this generation demand a sign? Verily I say to you, There shall be no sign given to this generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So, leaving them, he embarked again, and went to the other side.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now his disciples had forgotten to take in bread, and they had only one loaf with them in the vessel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And he gave them a charge, saying, Take heed; beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the leaven of Herod.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thereupon they reasoned among themselves, saying, It is because we have not bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Jesus, perceiving this, saith to them, Why do you imagine that it is because you have not bread? Are you yet so void of sense and understanding? Have you hearts still callous?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Having eyes do you not see? And having ears do you not hear? And have you no memory?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When I brake the five loaves for the five thousand, how many panniers full of fragments did you carry off? They say to him, Twelve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when I brake the seven loaves for the four thousand, how many baskets full of fragments did you carry off? They said, Seven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then he said to them, How is it that you do not understand?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then he cometh to Bethsaida, and they bring a blind man to him, and intreat him to touch him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thereupon taking the blind man by the hand, he led him out of the village; and after spitting on his eyes, he laid his hands on him, and asked him if he seeth any thing?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And he looking up, said, I see the men like trees; walking about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then he laid his hands on his eyes again, and made him look up. And his sight was restored, and he saw them all clearly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then he sent him to his house, saying, Neither go to the village, nor tell any one in the village.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then Jesus went forth, with his disciples, to the villages of Caesarea-philippi. And by the way he asked his disciples, saying, who do men say that I am?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And they answered, John the Baptist: but some say, Elias; and others say, One of the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Then he saith to them, And who do you say that I am? Peter answering, saith to him, Thou art the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then he charged them to tell no one this concerning him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and began to inform them that the son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders, and chief priests, and scribes, and put to death, and after three days rise again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And he spake this so plainly, that Peter, taking him aside, began to rebuke him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Whereupon, turning about and looking on his disciples, he rebuked Peter, saying, Get thee behind me, Satan! For thou hast thy mind bent, not on the things of God, but on the things of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then, having called to him the multitude, with his disciples, he said to them, Whosoever hath a mind to come under my guidance, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>For whosoever would save his life, shall lose it; but whoever shall lose his life for the sake of me, and the glad tidings, he shall save it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For what will it profit a man, if he should gain the whole world, and forfeit his life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Or what will not a man give as a ransom for his life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For whoever shall be ashamed of me and of my words, in this adulterous and sinful generation, of him the son of man will be ashamed, when he cometh in the glory of his father, with his holy angels.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then he said to them, Verily I say to you, There are some of those standing here, who shall not taste death till they see the reign of God come with power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Six days after this, Jesus taketh Peter, and James, and John, and leadeth them up, privately by themselves, to a high mountain, and was transfigured in their presence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And his raiment became glittering white like snow, to such a degree as no fuller on earth could whiten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And there appeared to them Elias with Moses, who were conversing with Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Whereupon Peter, addressing Jesus, said, Rabbi, It is well that we are here. Let us make three booths, one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For he did not know what to say; for they were terrified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then there came a cloud which overshadowed them, and from the cloud came a voice, saying, This is my Son, the Beloved; hearken to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And instantly looking about, they saw no one anymore, but only Jesus with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And as they were coming down from the mountain, he strictly charged them not to tell anyone what they had seen, until the son of man is risen from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>This expression they laid hold on, questioning among themselves what this rising from the dead could mean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then they asked him, saying, Why do the Scribes say that Elias must first come?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>In reply to which, he said to them, Elias indeed having come first, finisheth and beginneth all anew, in a manner conformable to what is written of the son of man, that he may suffer many things, and be treated with contempt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But I say to you, that Elias hath actually come; and they have done to him what they pleased, as it is written of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And as he was coming to his disciples, he saw a great crowd about them, and the Scribes disputing with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And all the people when they saw him, were instantly struck with awe, and ran to salute him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then he asked the Scribes, About what are you disputing with them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And one of the multitude answering, said, O! Teacher, I brought to thee this my son, who hath a dumb spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And whenever it seizeth him, it convulseth him; and he foameth, and grindeth his teeth, and is shrivelled up. I spoke indeed to thy disciples to cast it out, but they could not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus, in reply to him, saith, O faithless generation! How long shall I be with you? How long am I to endure you! Bring him to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So he was brought to him. And soon as he saw Jesus, the spirit threw him into convulsions; and, falling on the ground, he rolled about and foamed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And Jesus asked his father, How long since this befel him? And he said, From his childhood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And oft times it hath cast him into fire, and into waters to destroy him. But if thou canst do anything, have compassion on us and help us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to him, With regard to this canst thou believe? All things are possible for him who believeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Upon which the father of the child immediately cried out, and with tears said, I do believe: Help, O sir, my unbelief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And when Jesus saw that the people were crowding upon him, he rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it, Thou dumb and deaf spirit, I command thee; Go out of him; and enter no more into him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and the demon having screamed, and severely convulsed him, went out. And he was like one dead. So that many said, He is dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But Jesus, taking him by the hand, raised him, and he stood up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And when he went into a house, his disciples asked him privately, Why could not we cast it out?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And he said to them, This kind of power can go forth by nothing but by prayer and fasting,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Having left that place, they travelled through Galilee, and he did not desire that any should know;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>for he was teaching his disciples. And he said to them, The son of man is about to be delivered up into the hands of men, and they will put him to death. And being put to death, he will rise again on the third day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But they did not comprehend the meaning of this, and were afraid to ask him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And when he came to Capernaum, and was in the house, he asked them. What was that, about which you were debating among yourselves on the road.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And they were silent. For on the road they had debated among themselves, Who should be greatest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then sitting down, he called the twelve, and saith to them, If any one desireth to be first, let him be last of all, and servant of all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then having taken a child, he placed it in the midst of them; and taking it in his arms, he said to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Whosoever shall receive one of such children on my account, receiveth me; and whoever shall receive me, receiveth him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then John addressed him, saying, Teacher, we saw one who doth not accompany us, casting out demons in thy name, and we forbade him, because he doth not accompany us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus said, Forbid him not, for there is no one who will do a miracle in my name, and be readily able to speak evil of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For whoever is not against us is for us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>For whosoever shall give you a cup of water to drink on my account, because you belong to Christ, verily I say to you, He shall not lose his reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And whoever shall cause one of these little ones, who believe in me, to stumble, better were it for him, that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and he cast into the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Therefore, if thy hand cause thee to fall, cut it off. It is better for thee to enter maimed into life, than having two hands, to go into hell, into the fire which is unextinguishable;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Where their worm dieth not; and the fire is not extinguished!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And if thy foot cause thee to fall, cut it off, it b better for thee to enter lame into life, than, having two feet, to be cast into hell, into the fire which is unextinguishable;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not extinguished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And if thine eye causeth thee to fall, pluck it out; it is better for thee to enter one eyed into the kingdom of God, than having two eyes, to be cast into the hell of that fire;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not extinguished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>For every one is to be salted for fire, as every sacrifice is to be salted with salt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Salt is good; but if the salt become saltless, with what can you season it? Have salt in yourselves, and maintain peace with one another.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Having departed thence, he cometh to the borders of Judea, through the plain of the Jordan. And multitudes again resort to him, and he, as usual, again taught them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the Pharisees came, and with a view to try him, asked him, is it lawful for a man to put away his wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon he, in reply, said to them, What hath Moses commanded you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And they said, Moses permitted to write a bill of divorce and to put away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>In answer to this, Jesus said to them, Because of your intractable disposition, Moses wrote this precept for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But from the beginning of the creation God made them a male and a female.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For this cause a man is to leave his father and mother and cleave to his wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And they two shall be one flesh. So that they are no longer two, but one flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Therefore what God hath conjoined, let not man separate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And when he was in the house, his disciples asked him again concerning this matter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Whereupon he saith to them, Whosoever shall put away his wife, and marry another, committeth adultery against her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And if a woman put away her husband, and marry another, she committeth adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then children were brought to him, that he might touch them; and his disciples rebuked those who brought them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But Jesus, observing this, expressed displeasure, and said to them, Suffer the children to come to me, and do not hinder the; for of such is the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Verily I say to you, Whosoever will not, like a child, receive the kingdom of God, he shall in no wise enter it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then, having taken them in his arms, he laid his hands on them, and blessed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And as he was setting out on his journey, one came running, and kneeling down before him, asked him, Good teacher, what shall I do that I may inherit an everlasting life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to him, Why callest thou me good? There is none good but God only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou knowest the commandments; thou shall not commit adultery, thou shalt not commit murder, thou shalt not steal, thou shalt not bear false testimony, thou shalt not defraud, honour thy father and thy mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He answering, said to him, Teacher, All these I have observed from my childhood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Jesus, looking stedfastly on him, loved him, and said to him, One thing is wanting to thee. Go sell what thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven. Then come, and having taken up the cross, follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>At this word, he was grieved and went away sorrowful, for he had great possessions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus, looking round, saith to his disciples, How difficult it is for them who have riches to enter into the kingdom of God!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>At these words of his, his disciples being astonished, Jesus, addressing them again, saith, Children, How difficult a thing it is for them who trust in riches to enter into the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>It is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>At this they were still more astonished, and said among themselves, Who then can be saved?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus, looking stedfastly on them, saith, With men it is impossible, but not with God. For with God all things are possible.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Upon this Peter took occasion to say to him, Behold we have forsaken all and followed thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>In reply to this, Jesus said, Verily I say to you, There is none who hath left house, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or fields, for the sake of me and the glad tidings,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>who shall not now, even in the present time, receive an hundred fold compensation for houses, and brothers, and sisters, and mothers, and children, and fields, as well as for persecutions and in the age to come, everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But many who are first, shall be last, and the last, first.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>When they were on the way up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was walking before them, they were seized with a horror, and followed him with fear. Whereupon1 Jesus, again taking the twelve aside, took occasion to tell them what would soon befal him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Behold, said he, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the son of man will be delivered up to the chief priests, and the Scribes; and they will condemn him to death, and deliver him up to the Gentiles,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>who will insult him, and scourge him, and spit upon him, and put him to death; and on the third day he will rise again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>When James 'and John, the sons of Zebedee, accosted him, saying, Teacher, we desire that thou wouldst do for us what we are going to ask;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>thereupon he said to them, What do you desire me to do for you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And they said to him, Grant us, that one of us may sit on thy right hand, and the other on thy left, in thy glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to them, You do not know what you are asking. Can you drink the cup which I am about to drink, and be baptized with the baptism with which I am about to be baptized?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>They said to him, we can. Then Jesus said to them, you shall indeed drink the cup which I am about to drink, and be baptized with the baptism, with which I am about to be baptized;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>but to sit on my right hand and on my left, is not mine to give, except to those for whom his prepared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Now the ten, when they heard this, began to express indignation in respect to James and John;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>but Jesus, having called them to him, said to them, You know that the rulers of the nations exercise lordship over them; and their grandees exercise authority over them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>but it shall not be so among you. But whoever would be great among you, let him be your attendant:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and whoever of you would be first, let him be the servant of all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>For the son of man did not come to be waited on, but to serve; and to give his life as a ransom for many,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Then they proceeded on to Jericho, and as he was going out of Jericho, with his disciples and a great multitude, blind Bartimeus, son of Timeus, was sitting by the way side, begging.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>And when he heard that it is Jesus, the Nazarene, he began to cry aloud, and say, Jesus, son of David, have pity on me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And many rebuked him, that he should hold his peace; but he cried the louder, Son of David, have pity on me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>There upon Jesus, stopping, ordered him to be called. So they call the blind man, Saying to him, Take courage; arise; he calleth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Upon which, throwing aside his mantle, he sprang up and came to Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And Jesus, addressing him, said, What dost thou desire me to do for thee? And the blind man said to him, Rabboni, that I may again receive sight:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to him, Go thy way. Thy faith hath cured thee. And instantly he recovered his sight, and followed Jesus in the way.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when they approach Jerusalem, being come as far as Bethphage and Bethany, near the mount of olives, he sendeth two of his disciples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and saith to them, Go to that village over against you, and just as you enter it, you will find a colt tied, on which no man ever rode. Loose it, and bring it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And if any one say, Why do ye this? Say, The master hath need of it, and will quickly send it back hither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So they went, and found the colt tied before the door, at a place where two ways met. And as they were loosing it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>some of the people standing there, said to them, What do you mean by untying the colt?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And they answered them as Jesus had ordered; upon which they let them go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So they brought the colt to Jesus; and when they had laid their mantles thereon, he sat upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And many spread their mantles on the way; 'and others cut sprigs from the trees, and strewed them in the way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And they who went before, and they who followed, cried, saying, Hosanna! Blessed he who is coming in the name of the Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Blessed the approaching reign of our father David! that coming in the name of the Lord, Hosanna, in the highest!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So Jesus entered Jerusalem, and into the temple, and when he had taken a survey of all, as it was now evening, he went out to Bethany with the twelve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And on the morrow, as they were coming out from Bethany, he was hungry,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and seeing a fig tree at a distance, full of leaves, he went to see if he could find any fruit on it (for the time to gather figs was not come) but going to it he found nothing but leaves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to it, Henceforth let no one ever eat fruit of thee. And his disciples heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then they came to Jerusalem, and Jesus, having entered the temple, began with turning out them who were buying and selling in the temple. And he overturned the tables of the money changers, and the stalls of them who sold doves,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and suffered no one to carry a vessel through the temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And he taught, saying, Is it not written, My house shall be called a house of prayer for all the nations; but you have made it a den of robbers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When the Scribes, and the chief priests heard this, they sought how to destroy him, for they were afraid of him, because all the people were astonished at his doctrine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now, when evening was come, he went out of the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And next morning, as they were passing by; they saw the fig tree dried up from the roots.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whereupon Peter, recollecting, saith to him, Rabbi, Behold the fig tree which thou cursedst, is quite dried up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus saith to them, Have faith in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For verily I say to you, If one should say to that mountain, Be thou lifted up and cast into the sea; and have no doubt in his mind, but believe that what he saith cometh to pass; whatever he may command shall be done for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Therefore I say to you, What things soever you ask when you pray, believe that you will receive, and you shall have them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But when you stand praying, if you have any ground of complaint against any one, forgive him; that your father who is in heaven may forgive you your trespasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For if you do not forgive, neither will your father, who is in heaven, forgive you your trespasses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then they come again to Jerusalem; and as he was walking in the temple, the chief priests, and the Scribes, and the elders, come to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and say to him, By what authority doest thou these things? And, Who hath given thee authority that thou shouldst do such things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Jesus, answering, said to them, I also will ask you one question. Answer me; and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Was the baptism of John from heaven or of men? Answer me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Upon this they reasoned among themselves, saying, If we say, From heaven; he will say, Why then did you not believe him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But if we say, From men; they feared the people; for all held John to be really a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>So they in reply; say to Jesus, We cannot tell. There upon Jesus answering, saith to them, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then he addressed them in parables, saying, A man planted a vineyard, and hedged it about, and dug a wine lake, and built a tower, and let it to tenants, and went to a distant country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And at the vintage season he sent a servant to the tenants, that he might receive from them some of the fruit of the vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But they, having seized him, beat him, and sent him away empty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Again he sent to them another servant; and him they attacked with stones, and wounded on the head, and sent back with disgrace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Again he sent another, whom they killed; and many others, some of whom they beat, and some they killed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore, at last, having an only son, his beloved, he sent him also to them, saying, They will reverence mv son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But the tenants said among themselves, This is the heir. Come; let us kill him; and the inheritance will be our own.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So having seized him, they killed him, and threw him out of the vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>What therefore will the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy these tenants, and give the vineyard to others.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Have you never read this portion of scripture, The stone which the builders rejected, was the very one for the head of the corner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This salvation was from the Lord, and is wonderful in our eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Upon this they sought to lay hold of him, but were afraid of the people. For they knew that he had spoken the parable against them. So they left him and went away,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and send to him some of the Pharisees, and the Herodians, to entrap him with a speech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when they came, they say to him, Teacher, we know that thou art true, and carest for no man. For thou respectest not the person of men, but teachest the way of God with truth. Is it lawful to pay tribute to Caesar? Or is it not?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Should we give? Or should we not give? But he, knowing their hypocrisy, said to them, Why do ye try me? Bring me a deniar, that I may see it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So they brought him one. Then he saith to them, Whose image and inscription is this? And they said, Caesar's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then Jesus, answering, said to them, Render to Caesar the things which are Caesar's; and to God, the things which are God's. And they expressed admiration at him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Then came to him the Sadducees, who say there is no revival of the dead. And they asked him, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Teacher, Moses hath written for us, that if any one's brother die, and leave a wife without leaving children, his brother should take his wife and raise up a seed for his brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now there were seven brothers, and the first took a wife, and died without leaving issue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then the second took her, and died, and he left no issue. And the same was the case with the third.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Indeed the seven married her, but left no issue. Last of all, the woman also died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>At the revival of the dead, therefore, when they rise again, whose wife will she be? for she hath been wife to the seven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus said to them, Are you not led into error because of your not knowing the scriptures, nor the power of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For when the dead rise again, they neither marry nor are given in marriage; but are as the angels in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now with respect to the dead, that they are raised, have you not read in the book of Moses, how God spake in the bush to him, saying, I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaak, and the God of Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He is not the God of the dead; but the God of the living. You are therefore led much astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then one of the Scribes who had heard them disputing, and knew that he had answered them properly, coming up, asked him, Which is the chief commandment of all?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus answered, This is the chief of all the commandments: Hear, O Israel, The Lord is our God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>the Lord is one: and thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thine understanding, and with all thy strength. This is the first commandment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And the second, resembling it, is this, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself. There is no other commandment greater than these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Upon this the Scribe said to him, right! Teacher! thou hast said truly that there is one God; and there is no other besides him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and to love him with the whole heart, and with the whole understanding, and with the whole soul, and with the whole strength; and to love one's neighbour as himself, is more than all the burnt offerings and the sacrifices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus observing that he had answered discreetly, said to him, Thou art not far from the kingdom of God. And, after that, no one ventured to ask him any questions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then Jesus, in the course of his teaching in the temple, said, How do the Scribes say, That the Christ is the son of David?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For David himself, by the Holy Spirit, said, The Lord said to my Lord, Sit at my right hand until I make thine enemies thy footstool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>If David then calleth him Lord, how is he his son? As the great multitude heard him with pleasure,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>he said to them in his manner of teaching, Beware of the Scribes, who are fond of walking in long robes, and of salutations in public places of resort,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and of the principal seats in the synagogues, and the uppermost places at entertainments</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>who devour the families of widows, and make long prayers for a disguise. Such shall receive greater condemnation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>As Jesus was sitting over against the treasury, he observed in what manner the multitude throw money into the treasury. And many being rich, threw in a great deal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>At length a poor widow came, and threw in two mites, which make a farthing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus, having called his disciples to him, saith to them, Verily I say to you, This poor widow hath thrown in more than all those who have thrown into the treasury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>For they have all contributed out of their superfluous store; but she, out of what she wanted for herself, hath thrown in all that she had; her whole living.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And as he was going out of the temple, one of his disciples saith to him, Teacher, see! what huge stones and stately buildings!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus answering, saith to him, Thou seest these great buildings? There shall not be left one stone on another which shall not be demolished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And as he was sitting on the mount of olives, over against the temple, Peter, and James, and John, and Andrew, asked him privately,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Tell us, when will these things happen? And what will be the sign of the impending accomplishment of all these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus, in answer to them, took occasion to say, Take heed that none seduce you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>for many will come in my name, saying, I am he; and will seduce many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now when you shall hear of wars and rumours of wars, be not alarmed; for this must happen; but the end is not yet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For nation will rise against nation; and kingdom against kingdom. And there will be earthquakes in divers places. And there will be famines and commotions. These are the beginnings of sorrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now look to yourselves. For they will deliver you up to councils and synagogues. You will be scourged and brought before governors and kings, for my sake, to bear testimony to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For the glad tidings must be first proclaimed to all the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But when they bring you to deliver you up, be not solicitous beforehand what to say; nor premeditate; but whatever shall be suggested to you on the occasion, speak that: for it is not you, who speak; but the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now brother will deliver up brother to death: and a father, a son: and children will rise up against parents, and cause them to be put to death:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and you will be hated by all men on account of my name. But he who persevereth to the end shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now when you see the abomination of desolation, which was spoken of by the prophet Daniel, erected where it ought not (Reader attend!) then let them who are in Judea flee to the mountains;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and let not him who is on the house top go down into the house, nor enter it to carry away any thing out of his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And let not him who is in the field turn back to take up his mantle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But alas! for the women who are with child; and for them who give suck in those days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Pray therefore that your flight may not be in winter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For in those days there will be such distress as hath not happened from the beginning of the creation, which God created, till now; nor ever shall be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And had not the Lord shortened those days, no flesh could escape. But for the sake of the chosen, whom he hath made choice of, he hath shortened those days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now, if at that time, anyone say to you, Lo! the Christ is here! or, Lo! he is there! believe it not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For false Christs and false prophets will rise up and give out signs and wonders to seduce, if possible, even the chosen ones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But be upon your guard. Lo! I have foretold you all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But in those days, after that distress, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will withhold her splendour,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and the stars of heaven will continue falling, and the powers which are in the heavens will be shaken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And then they shall see the son of man coming in clouds with great power and glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And then he will send his messengers and gather his chosen ones from the four winds from the remotest part of the earth to the remotest part of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now learn this parable from that fig tree: when its branch becometh tender and putteth forth leaves, you know that the summer is near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So when you see these things happen, know that he is near, at the door.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Verily I say to you, This generation shall not pass away until all these things are accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The heaven and the earth will fail, but my words shall not fail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But with respect to the day, and the season, that none knoweth; neither the angels who are in heaven, nor the son none but the father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Look, watch and pray; for you do not know when the time is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>As when a man was going to travel, on leaving his family and assigning to his servants their charge, even to even' one his work, he commanded the porter to watch;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>watch ye therefore; for you do not know when the master of the family cometh; whether in the evening, or at midnight, or at cockcrowing, or in the morning,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>lest coming unexpectedly, he find you asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Now what I say to you, I say to all, Watch.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now after two days was the passover, and the festival of unleavened bread. And the chief priests, and the Scribes were contriving how they might seize him by surprise, and put him to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And they said, Not at the festival; lest there be a tumult among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And he being at Bethany in the house of Simon the leper, while he was at table a woman came with an alabaster phial of balsam; of pure unadulterated spikenard, which is very costly, and shaking the phial, she poured out of it on his head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>At which some expressed indignation, saying, Why is this waste of the balsam?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For it might have been sold for more than three hundred deniars, and given to the poor. And as they were restraining her,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Jesus said, Let her alone. Why do ye trouble her? She hath done a good work for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For you have the poor always with you and can, when you please, do them good; but me you have not always.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>She hath done what she could. She hath come beforehand to anoint my body for its embalment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Verily I say to you, In whatever quarter of the world these glad tidings are proclaimed, what this woman hath done will be mentioned to her honour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon this, Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, went to the chief priests, in order to deliver him up to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And when they heard, they rejoiced exceedingly, and promised to give him money. So he sought a favourable opportunity to deliver him up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And on the first day of the festival of unleavened bread, the day when the paschal lamb was to be killed, his disciples said to him, Where wouldst thou have us go and prepare for thine eating the paschal lamb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thereupon he despatched two of his disciples, saying to them, Go to the city, and you will meet a man carrying a pitcher of water; follow him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And wherever he shall enter, say to the master of the house, The teacher saith, Where is the dining room in which I may eat the passover with my disciples?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And he will shew you a large upper room, ready furnished. Make preparation for us there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So the disciples went, and came to the city, and found as he had told them, and prepared the passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And in the evening he cometh with the twelve.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And as they were at table, and eating, Jesus said, Verily I say to you, One of you, who is eating with me, is to deliver me up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>At this they began to be sorrowful, and to say severally; one, Am I? And another, Am I?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And he answering, said to them, It is one of the twelve who is dipping with me in the dish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The son of man departeth indeed as it is written of him, but alas for that man by whom the son of man is delivered up. Good were it for that man, if he had never been born.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And, as they were eating, Jesus having taken a loaf and pronounced a blessing, broke and gave to his disciples, and said, Take; eat; this is my body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then having taken the cup, and given thanks, he gave to them and they all drank of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then he said to them, This is my blood; that of the new covenant; that shed for many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Verily I say to you, I will no more drink of the product of the vine, until the day when I shall drink it new in the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when they had sung a hymn, they went out to the mount of olives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And Jesus saith to them, This night you will all be stumbled at me. For it is written, will smite the shepherd and the sheep will be scattered.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But after I am risen, I will go before you to Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Hereupon Peter said to him, Though all should be stumbled, I will not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, Verily I say to thee, This very night before a cock crow twice, thou wilt three times deny me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But he with more vehemence said, Though I should die with thee, I will not deny thee. And all the rest said the same.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then they come to a place called Gethsemane, and he saith to his disciples, Stay here, till I pray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then he taketh with him Peter, and James and John, and being seized with agonizing horror and distress of mind,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>he saith to them, My soul is exceeding sorrowful even to death. Stay here and watch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then having advanced a little further, he prostrated himself on the ground, and prayed, that if it were possible this hour might pass from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And he said, Abba, father, all things are possible to thee. Take away this cup from me. Nevertheless not my will, but thine be done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then he cometh and findeth them asleep, and saith to Peter, Simon, art thou asleep? Couldst thou not watch one hour?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Watch and pray, that you may not come to a trial. The spirit is indeed willing; but the flesh is weak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Then going away again, he prayed, using the same words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And on returning, he found them again asleep. For their eyes were weighed down, and they did not know what to answer him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then he cometh the third time, and saith to them, Are you still asleep and taking rest? It is over. The hour is come. Behold the son of man is delivered into the hands of sinners.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Arise and let us go. Lo! he who delivereth me up is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And immediately, while he was still speaking, Judas, one of the twelve, cometh, and with him a great multitude, with swords and clubs, from the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Now he, who delivered him up, had given them a signal, saying, The person whom I will kiss, is he: seize him and carry him away securely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>So, when he came, having advanced directly up to Jesus, he saith, Rabbi, Rabbi, and kissed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Whereupon they laid their hands on him and held him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Then one of them who stood by, having drawn his sword, smote the servant of the chief priest, and cut off his ear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>And Jesus addressing them, said, Are you come out as against a robber, with swords and clubs, to take me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>I was daily amongst you in the temple, teaching you, and you did not arrest me. But the scriptures must be fulfilled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Then all forsook him, and fled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>But a certain youth followed him, having only a sindon wrapped about his naked body; and the young men laid hold on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Whereupon he let go the Sindon and fled from them naked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>And when they brought Jesus to the chief priest; all the chief priests, and the elders, and the Scribes, assembled with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Now Peter had followed him, at a distance, quite into the court of the chief priest, and sat there with the attendants, warming himself at the fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>And the chief priests and the whole Sanhedrim sought for evidence against Jesus, to put him to death, but found it not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>For many bore false witness against him, but their testimonies did not agree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>Then there arose some who falsely testified against him, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>We heard him say, I will destroy this temple made with hands, and in three days build another not made with hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>But neither in this did their testimony agree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>Then the chief priest, standing up in the midst, asked Jesus, saying, Answerest thou nothing? What sayest thou to what these testify against thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>But Jesus was silent, and made no reply. Then the chief priest interrogated him, and saith to him, Art thou the Christ, the son of the Blessed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said, I am. And you shall see the son of man seated on the right hand of that power, and coming with the clouds of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>Upon this, the chief priest rent his clothes, and said, What farther need have we of witnesses?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>You have heard this blasphemy. What think ye? And they all adjudged him to be liable to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>Then some began to spit upon him, and to cover his face, and buffet him, and say to him, Prophesy: when the attendants smote him on the cheek with their open hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>Now, Peter being in the court below, one of the maid servants of the chief priest cometh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>and seeing Peter warming himself, having viewed him narrowly, she saith, Thou also wast with Jesus, the Nazarene.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>Whereupon he denied, saying, I do not know, nor do I understand what thou sayest. Then he went out into the portico, and a cock crowed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>And the girl, seeing him again, began to say to the bye standers, that man is one of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>Hereupon he denied again. And a little while after, they who stood by, said to Peter, Thou art certainly one of them; for thou art a Galilean, and thy speech sheweth it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>Upon this, he began with imprecations and oaths to say, I do not know the man of whom you speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="72">
      <content>And a cock crowed a second time. Then Peter recollected what Jesus said to him, Before a cock crow twice, thou wilt three times deny me; and covering his head, he wept.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And early in the morning, the chief priests, with the elders, and the Scribes, even the whole Sanhedrim, having consulted together, bound Jesus, and led him away, and delivered him up to Pilate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And Pilate asked him, Thou art the king of the Jews? And he in reply, said to him, It is as thou sayst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Then the chief priests accused him of many things; but he made no answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Pilate asked him again, saying, Answerest thou nothing? Observe how many things they testify against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But Jesus still made no reply, so that Pilate was astonished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now at every festival he released to them any one prisoner whom they desired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And there was one Barabbas confined with his fellow insurgents, who in their insurrection had committed murder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So when the people with a loud clamour, began to demand what was usually granted to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Pilate addressing them, said, Is it your pleasure that I release to you the king of the Jews?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For he knew that out of envy the chief priests had delivered him up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But the chief priests instigated the populace to desire that he would rather release to them Barabbas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when Pilate addressing them again, said, What then do you wish me to do with him whom you call king of the Jews?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They again cried, Crucify him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then Pilate said to them, Why? What evil hath he done? But they cried more vehemently, Crucify him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Thereupon Pilate willing to satisfy the populace, released Barabbas to them, and having scourged Jesus, delivered him up to be crucified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then the soldiers led him away to the court called the praetorium, and having assembled the whole cohort,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>they arrayed him in purple, and platting a crown of thorns, they put it on his head,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and began with saluting him, Hail, king of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Then they smote him on the head with a reed, and spat upon him, and bowing their knees, made obeisance to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when they had mocked him they stripped him of the purple, and put his own clothes on him, and led him out to crucify him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And they compel one Simon, a Cyrenian, who was coming from the country, the father of Alexander and Rufus, to carry his cross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So they bring him to Golgotha (the meaning of which is, The place of a scull)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and offered him myrrhed wine to drink. But he did not take it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And when they had crucified him, they divided his garments into parcels, casting lots on them, to decide what each should take.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now it was the third hour when they nailed him to the cross:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and the inscription of the charge against him, which was written over him, was, The king of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And together with him they crucify two robbers, one on his right hand and the other on his left.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thus was the scripture fulfilled which saith, And he was numbered with transgressors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And they who passed by kept reviling him, shaking their heads, and saying, Ah! thou destroyer of the temple; and rebuilder of it in three days,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>save thyself, and come down from the cross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And in like manner the chief priests, and the Scribes, jesting with one another, said, He saved others, Cannot he save himself?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Let this Christ, this king of Israel, now come down from the cross that we may see and believe. Even they who were crucified with him, reviled him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But when the sixth hour was come, there was darkness over the whole land, until the ninth hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And at the ninth hour, Jesus cried with aloud voice, saying, Eloi, Eloi, Lama sabachthani which is, being interpreted, My God, my God, Why hast thou forsaken me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Which, when some of the bystanders heard, they said, Hark! he is calling Elias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Then one ran, and having filled a spunge with vinegar, and put it on a reed, offered him drink, saying, Let alone; let us see whether Elias cometh to take him down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Then Jesus, having uttered a loud cry, expired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Upon which the veil of the temple was rent in two, from top to bottom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And when the centurion who stood opposite to him, saw that he cried thus, and expired, he said, This man was certainly a son of a God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Now there were women looking on at a distance, among whom was Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the younger, and of Joses, and Salome;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>(these had attended him when he was in Galilee, and ministered to him) and many others who had come up with him to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And in the course of the evening, during preparation time (that is, the cessation from labour which is usual before the sabbath,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>came Joseph of Arimathea, an honourable senator, who himself also was expecting the reign of God; he had taken courage, and gone in to Pilate and begged the body of Jesus:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>upon which Pilate expressed wonder if he could be dead, and calling for the centurion, asked him, If he had been dead any time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And being informed by the centurion, he had granted the body to Joseph;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>and he, having bought a sindon, and taken Jesus down, wrapped him in the sindon and laid him in a sepulchre which was hewn out of a rock, and rolled a stone on the door of the sepulchre.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Now Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of Joses, saw where he was laid.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So when the sabbath was over, Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of James, and Salome, bought spices, that they might go and embalm him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And very early in the morning of the first day of the week, they come to the sepulchre. When the sun was rising;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and just as they were saying to one another, Who will roll away the stone for us from the door of the sepulchre,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>(for it was very large) upon looking up, they see that the stone hath been rolled away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And going into the sepulchre, they saw a youth sitting on the right side, clothed with a white robe, and they were terrified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon he said to them, Be not terrified. You are seeking Jesus, the Nazarene, who was crucified. He is risen. He is not here. Behold the place where they laid him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But go, tell his disciples, Peter in particular, that he goeth before you to Galilee. There you shall see him, as he said to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thereupon, having come out in haste, they ran from the sepulchre; but they were seized with such terror and consternation that they said nothing to any one, they were so frightened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now Jesus, having risen very early in the morning of the first day of the week, appeared first to Mary Magdalene, out of whom he had cast seven demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>She went and told his attendants who were mourning and weeping;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>but when they heard that he is alive, and was seen by her, they did not believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>After that, he appeared in another form, to two of them as they were walking into the country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Whereupon these came and told the rest; but they did not believe them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>At length he appeared to the eleven, when they were at table, and upbraided them for their incredulity and obstinacy, because they did not believe them who had seen him after his resurrection.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then he said to them, Go to all the world, and proclaim the glad tidings to all mankind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He who believeth, and is baptized, shall be saved; but he who disbelieveth shall be condemned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now these signs shall accompany them who believe; by my name they will expel demons; they will speak with new tongues:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>they will take up serpents: though they drink deadly poison, it shall not hurt them: upon sick persons they will lay their hands, and they shall recover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So after the Lord had spoken to them, he was taken up to heaven, and sat at the right hand of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and they went forth and proclaimed the tidings every where, the Lord co-operating with them, and confirming the word with those concomitant signs.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>