<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In the beginning was the Word; and the Word was with God; and the Word was God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He was in the beginning with God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>By him all things were made, and without him there was not made one single thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>What was in him was life, and this life was the light of men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and this light shineth in the darkness, and the darkness did not reach it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>There was a man sent from God: his name was John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>This man came as a witness to bear witness concerning this light, that by means of him all might believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He was not the light, but was to bear witness concerning the light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The light (the true light which enlighteneth every man) coming into the world</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>was in the world, and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He came to his own peculiar territories, and his own peculiar people did not receive him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But to as many as received him he granted the privilege of becoming children of God, even to them who believe in his name,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>who were born, not of bloods, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now the Word became incarnate, and dwelt as in a tent among us, and we beheld his glory; a glory as of an only begotten from the father. He was full of grace and truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Of him John testifieth when he cried, saying, This is he of whom I said, He who is coming after me is preferred before me, for he was before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And of his fulness we have all received even grace for grace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Because the law was given by Moses grace and truth came by Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>No one hath ever seen God. This only begotten son, who is in the bosom of the father, even he hath made him known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now this is the testimony of John: when the Jews of Jerusalem sent priests and Levites to ask him, Who art thou?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He frankly declared and did not deny, but frankly declared, I am not the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then they asked him, What then? Art thou Elias? And he said, I am not: art thou the prophet And he answered, No.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then they said to him, Who art thou? That we may give an answer to them who sent us: What sayest thou of thyself?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He said, I am The voice of one crying in the wilderness, Make straight the way of the Lord, as the prophet Esaias said.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now they who were sent were of the Pharisees.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then they asked him and said to him, Why then dost thou baptize, if thou art not the Christ, nor Elias, nor the prophet?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>John answered them saying, I baptize in water; but there is one in the midst of you, whom you know not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He is the person who is coming after me; who is preferred to me, the latchet of whose sandal I am not worthy to untie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>These things passed at Bethabara on the bank of the Jordan, where John was baptizing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The next day John seeth Jesus coming towards him, and saith, Behold the lamb of God, which taketh away the sin of the world!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>this is he of whom I said, After me cometh a man who hath been before me; for he existed before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>As for me, I did not know him; but to the end that he might be made manifest to Israel; for this purpose I came baptizing in water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Moreover John testified saying, I beheld the Spirit descending like a dove from heaven, and it remained upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Now for my part I did not know him; but he who sent me to baptize in water, even he said to me, On whomsoever thou shalt see the spirit descending and remaining on him, the same is he who baptizeth in a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Now I have Seen and testified that this is The Son Of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Again, on the next day, John was standing with two of his disciples,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>and having fixed his eyes intently on Jesus as he was walking, he saith, Behold the lamb of God!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>and the two disciples heard him speaking, and followed Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>When Jesus turned and saw them following him, he saith to them, What seek ye? And they said to him, Rabbi, (the meaning of which, when interpreted, is Teacher) where dost thou make thine abode?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>He saith to them, Come and see. They went and saw where he made his abode, and staid with him that day; for it was about the tenth hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who heard John and followed Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>He first findeth his brother Simon, and saith to him, We have found the Messias, (the meaning of which is the Christ) the anointed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and brought him to Jesus. And Jesus, having looked earnestly on him, said, Thou art Simon the son of Jonas. Thou shalt be called Cephas (the meaning of which is the same as that of Peter) a rock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>On the day following Jesus determined to set out for Galilee, and finding Philip, he saith to him, Come with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Now Philip was of Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Philip finding Nathaniel, saith to him, We have found him of whom Moses in the law, and the prophets have written, Jesus of Nazareth, the son of Joseph.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Upon which Nathaniel saith to him, Of Nazareth can there be any thing good! Philip saith to him, Come and see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Jesus saw Nathaniel coming to him and saith respecting him, Behold an Israelite indeed, in whom there is no guile!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Nathaniel saith to him, Whence knowest thou me? Jesus in reply said to him, Before Philip called thee, when thou wast under the fig tree, I saw thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>In answer to this, Nathaniel said to him, Rabbi, thou art the son of God. Thou art the king of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Jesus answered and said to him, Because I told thee, I saw thee under the fig tree, dost thou believe? Thou shalt see greater things than these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Then he saith to him, Verily, verily I say to you, Hereafter you shall see the heaven opened, and the angels of God ascending and descending on the son of man.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now on the third day there was a wedding at Cana of Galilee, and the mother of Jesus was there;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and Jesus and his disciples were invited to the wedding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the wine having fallen short, the mother of Jesus saith to him, They have no wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Woman, what hast thou to do with me? My hour is not yet come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>His mother saith to the waiters, Do whatever he shall bid you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now there were six water pots of stone, containing two or three measures apiece, placed there for the Jewish rites of purifying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Jesus saith to the waiters, Fill those water pots with water. And when they had filled them to the brim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>then he saith to them, Draw out now and carry some to the master of the feast. And when they had carried,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and the master of the feast had tasted the water which was made wine (now he did not know whence it was, but the waiters who had drawn off the water knew) the master of the feast calleth the bridegroom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and saith to him, Every man serveth up the good wine first, and when the guests have drunk plentifully, then that which is worse. Thou hast kept the good wine till now.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This at Cana, in Galilee, Jesus made the beginning of his miracles and manifested his glory, and his disciples believed on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>After this, he and his mother, and his brethren, and his disciples went down to Capernaum, but they did not stay there many days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For the passover of the Jews was nigh, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and found in the temple them who sold cattle, and sheep, and doves, and the changers of money seated;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and having made a whip of bulrushes, he drove them all out of the temple, with the sheep and cattle, and poured out the money of the changers, and overturned their tables,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and said to them who sold doves, Take these things hence. Make not the house of my father a house of merchandize.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then did his disciples remember that it was written, My zeal for thy house hath consumed me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Hereupon the Jews addressed him, and said, What sign dost thou shew us to justify thy doing these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>In reply to which Jesus said to them, Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Thereupon the Jews said, This temple was forty six years a building, and wilt thou raise it up in three days?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But he spake of the temple of his body:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>therefore, when he was risen from the dead, his disciples remembered that he had said this to them; and they believed the scriptures, and the word which Jesus had spoken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now while he was in Jerusalem at the passover, during the festival, many believed in his name when they saw the miracles which he did.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But Jesus did not trust himself to them, because he knew all men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And because he had no need that any one should testify of man, for he himself knew what was in man;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>there being a man of the sect of the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>when this man came to Jesus by night, and said to him, Rabbi, We know that thou art a teacher come from God; for no one can do the miracles which thou dost, unless God be with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Jesus answered and said to him, Verily, verily I say to thee, unless a man be born again, he cannot discern the reign of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Nicodemus saith to him, How can a man be born, when he is old? Can he enter a second time into his mother's womb and be born?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Jesus answered, Verily, verily I say to thee, unless a man be born of water and spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>That which is born of the flesh, is flesh; and that which is born of the spirit, is spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Wonder not at my telling thee, You must be born again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>That blast of wind bloweth where it pleaseth, and thou hearest the sound of it, but dost not know whence it cometh and whither it goeth. So is every one who is born of the spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Nicodemus answered, and said to him, How can these things be?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus said to him, Art thou the teacher of Israel, and knowest not these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Verily, verily I say to thee, We speak what we know, and testify what we have seen; yet you do not receive our testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If I have told you earthly things and you do not believe; how will you believe if I tell you heavenly things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>No one indeed hath ascended up into heaven, but he who came down from heaven, namely, the son of man who is in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, so must the son of man be lifted up,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>that whosoever believeth in him may not perish; but have everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten son, that whosoever believeth in him may not perish, but have everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For God did not send his son into the world to condemn the world; but that the world may be saved by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He who believeth in him will not be condemned; but he who believeth not, is condemned already; because he hath not believed in the name of the only begotten son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And this is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men loved darkness more than light, because their works were evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For whosoever doeth evil hateth the light, and doth not come to the light, that his deeds may not be detected.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But he who practiseth truth cometh to the light, that his works may be open to view, because they are the operations of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>After this, Jesus went with his disciples into the country of Judea, and spent some time with them there, and baptized.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And John also was baptizing at Enon, near Saleim, because there was much water there, and people used to come there and be baptized;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>for John was not yet thrown into prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>There was therefore a dispute between some of the disciples of John, and the Jews, respecting purification,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and they went to John, and said to him, Rabbi, he who was with thee on the bank of the Jordan, to whom thou didst bear testimony, behold he is baptizing, and all are flocking to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>In reply to which, John said, A man can receive nothing from heaven, unless it be given him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>You yourselves are witnesses for me that I said, I am not the Christ; but that I am sent before him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He is the bridegroom, who hath the bride. But the friend of the bridegroom, who standeth and heareth him, rejoiceth exceedingly on the account of the bridegroom's voice. This joy of mine therefore, is complete.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He must increase, but I must decrease.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The one coming from above, is above all. He who is of the earth is earthly, and speaketh of the earth. The one coming from heaven is above all,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and what he hath seen and heard, that he testifieth, yet none receiveth his testimony.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He who hath received his testimony, hath set his seal to this, That God is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For he whom God hath sent, speaketh the words of God; for God giveth him not the spirit by measure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The father loveth the son, and hath given all things into his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>He who believeth in the son, hath an everlasting life; but he who disbelieveth the son, shall not see life; but the wrath of God will abide on him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When the Lord, therefore, knew that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus is making and baptizing more disciples than John,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>(though it was not indeed Jesus himself, but his disciples who baptized)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>he left Judea and went again into Galilee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and as he must needs pass through Samaria,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore he cometh to a city of Samaria, called Sichar, near the piece of ground which Jacob gave to his son Joseph.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now Jacob's well was there. And as Jesus, wearied as he was with the journey, was sitting by the well, (it was about the sixth hour)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>a woman of Samaria came out to draw water. Jesus saith to her, Give me to drink;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>(for his disciples were gone to the city to buy food;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>thereupon the woman of Samaria saith to him, How is it that thou, being a Jew, askest drink of me, who am a woman of Samaria? (For the Jews have no friendly intercourse with the Samaritans.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus answered and said to her, If thou hadst known the bounty of God, and who it is who saith to thee, Give me to drink, thou wouldst have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The woman saith to him, Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the well is deep; whence then hast thou this living water?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Art thou greater than our father Jacob, who gave us this well, and drank thereof, himself, and his children, and his cattle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In reply to which, Jesus said to her, every one who drinketh of this water will thirst again;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but whosoever shall drink of the water which I will give him, will never thirst. But the water which I will give him, will be in him a fountain of water springing up for an everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The woman saith to him, O, sir, give me that water, that I may not thirst, nor come hither to draw.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Go, call thy husband and come hither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The woman in reply said, I have no husband. Jesus saith to her, Thou art right in saying, I have no husband:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for thou hast had five husbands; and he whom thou now hast, is not thy husband. In this thou hast spoken truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The woman saith to him, Sir, I perceive that thou art a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Our fathers have usually worshipped on this mountain; but you say, that at Jerusalem is the place where worship ought to be performed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Woman, believe me, the hour is coming when you will worship the Father, neither on this mountain, nor at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>You worship what you do not know. We worship what we do know: for salvation is of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>But the hour is coming; indeed is now come, when the true worshippers will worship the Father in spirit and truth. For such worshippers of him the Father seeketh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>God is Spirit; and they who worship him ought to worship him in spirit and truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The woman saith to him, I know that the Messias (he who is called the Christ) is coming. When he is come he will tell us all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, I who am speaking to thee am he.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>(Now at that instant his disciples came and wondered at his talking with the woman, yet none of them said, What seekest thou? Or why talkest thou with her?)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thereupon the woman left her pitcher, and went to the city, and saith to the men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Come, see a man who told me all that I ever did. Is this the Christ?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Therefore they of the city set out and were coming to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Now in the mean while his disciples entreated him, saying, Rabbi, eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But he said to them; I have meat to eat which you do not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>His disciples therefore said to one another, Hath any one brought him food?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus saith to them, It is my food to do the will of him who sent me, and to finish his work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Do you not say, Yet four months, and the harvest cometh. Behold I say to you, Lift up your eyes and view the fields; for they are already white for harvest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And he who reapeth receiveth wages, and gathereth fruit for an everlasting life, that he who soweth, and he who reapeth, may rejoice together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For herein is that saying verified, that one soweth, and another reapeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>I have sent you to reap that on which you bestowed no labour. Others have laboured and you have entered on their labours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now many of the Samaritans of that city believed in him, on the testimony of the woman who said, He told me all that I ever did.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Therefore, when these Samaritans came, they intreated him to tarry with them. So he stayed there two days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And many more believed, because of what he himself spake,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and they said to the woman, It is not now on account of thy talk that we believe; for we ourselves have heard and we know that he is indeed the Saviour of the world, the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Now after the two days he departed thence, and went to Galilee, but not directly to Nazareth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>for Jesus himself had testified that a prophet is not honoured in his native place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Therefore when he came to Galilee, the Galileans received him, having seen all that he had done at Jerusalem, during the festival. For they also went up to the festival.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Jesus therefore went again to Cana of Galilee, where he had made the water wine. And there was a certain officer of the king, whose son was sick at Capernaum.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>This person, upon hearing that Jesus was come from Judea to Galilee, went to him and intreated him to go down and cure his son; for he was at the point of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Jesus therefore said to him, Unless you see signs and wonders, can you not believe?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>The officer saith to him, Sir, Come down before my child die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, Go home: thy son liveth. And the man believed the word which Jesus spake to him, and went away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>And as he was going down, his servants met him and told him, saying, Thy son liveth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Whereupon he inquired of them at what hour he began to mend. And they told him, that yesterday, at seven o'clock, the fever left him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>So the father knew that it was the very time when Jesus said to him, Thy son liveth, and he and his whole family believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>This second miracle Jesus performed on his second coming from Judea to Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this there was a festival of the Jews, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now there is in Jerusalem at the sheep gate, a pool, which is called in Hebrew Bethesda, having five porticos,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>in which lay a great multitude of infirm persons, blind, lame, and withered, waiting for the moving of the water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For from time to time an angel came down into the pool and moved the water. He therefore, who went in first after this movement of the water, was cured of whatever disease he had.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now there was a certain man there who had been in his infirmity thirty eight years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Jesus seeing him lying there, and knowing that he had been in that condition now a long time, saith to him, Hast thou a desire to be healed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The infirm man answered him, Sir, I have no one to put me in the pool when the water is moved. And while I am going another steppeth down before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, Rise; take up thy couch and walk about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Upon which the man was instantly well, and took up his couch and walked about. Now there was a sabbath on that day;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>therefore the Jews said to him who was cured, It is a sabbath: It is not lawful for thee to carry the couch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He answered them, He who made me well, even he said to me, Take up thy couch and walk about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thereupon they asked him, Who is the man who said to thee, take up thy couch and walk about?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But he who was cured did not know who it was; for as there was a crowd in the place, Jesus had glided away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>After this Jesus findeth him in the temple, and said to him, Behold thou art made well. Sin no more, lest something worse befall thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The man went and told the Jews that it was Jesus who had cured him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And for this cause the Jews persecuted Jesus and sought to kill him, because he did these things on a sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus answered them, My Father worketh even now, and I also work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For this therefore the Jews sought the more to kill him, because he not only broke the sabbath, but called God peculiarly his father, likening himself to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Upon which Jesus addressed them, and said, Verily, verily I say to you, The son can of himself do nothing, unless indeed he see the Father doing it; for whatever things He doth, these the Son doth likewise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For the Father loveth the Son, and sheweth him all that he himself doth. And he will shew him greater works than these, that you may wonder.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For as the Father raiseth the dead and restoreth to life, so the Son restoreth to life, whom he pleaseth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For the Father judgeth no one, but hath committed the whole act of judging to his Son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>that all may honour the Son, as they honour the Father. He who honoureth not the Son, doth not honour the Father, who sent him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Verily, verily I say to you, He who heareth my word, and believeth on him who sent me, hath an everlasting life, and doth not incur condemnation, but hath passed from death to that life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Verily, verily I say to you, a time is coming, nay is now come, when the dead will hearken to the voice of the son of God, and they who hearken shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For as the Father hath life in himself, so he hath granted to the son to have life also in himself,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and hath also given him authority to execute judgment, because he is a son of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Wonder not at this; for a time is coming when all that are in the graves shall hearken to his voice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and come forth; they who have done good, to a resurrection of life, and they who have done evil, to a resurrection of condemnation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I can do nothing of myself. As I hear, I judge. And my judgment is just; for I do not seek mine own will, but the will of the Father who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>If I testify of myself my testimony is not true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>There is another who testifieth concerning me; and I know that the testimony which he giveth concerning me is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>You sent to John, and he gave a testimony to the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But as for me, I do not receive human testimony, but mention this that you may be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>He was the lighted and shining lamp; and for a while you were disposed to exult with joy at his light.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But I have a greater testimony than John's. For the works which my father hath given me to perform; these very works, which I do, testify concerning me, that the father hath sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Indeed the father who hath sent me hath himself given a testimony concerning me. You have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen a visible appearance of him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Indeed you have not his word abiding in you, because you do not believe him whom he hath sent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>You search the scriptures because you think you have by means of them everlasting life! Now these are the very writings which testify concerning me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>yet you will not come to me that you may have life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>I do not receive glory from men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>But I know you that you have not the love of God in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>I have come in my father's name and you do not receive me; if another come in his own name, him you will receive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>How can you believe while you court honour one from another, and do not seek the glory which is from God alone?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Do not imagine that I will accuse you to the father. There is one who is your accuser, namely, Moses, in whom you have trusted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>For if you had believed Moses, you would believe me; for he hath written concerning me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Now if you have not believed his writings, how will you believe my words?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After these things Jesus went away. On the coast of the sea, that of Galilee, that of Tiberias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he was also followed by a great multitude, because they saw the miracles which he performed on the diseased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And Jesus went up to the mountain, and sat down there with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now the passover, the festival of the Jews, was nigh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Jesus therefore lifting up his eyes, and seeing a great multitude coming to him, saith to Philip, Whence can we buy bread to feed these people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now this he said to try him, for he himself knew what he was going to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Philip answered him, Two hundred deniars would not purchase bread enough for every one of them to take a morsel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>One of his disciples, namely Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, saith to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>There is a lad here who hath five barley loaves, and two small fishes; but what are they among so many?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Jesus said, Cause the men to arrange themselves on the ground. Now there was much grass in the place. The men therefore, to the number of about five thousand, arranged themselves on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then Jesus took the loaves and having given thanks, distributed to the disciples; and the disciples distributed to them who were on the ground; and in like manner of the fishes, as much as they chose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And when they were satisfied, he saith to his disciples, Gather up the fragments which remain, that nothing may be lost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So they gathered, and with the fragments, which the people after eating had left of the five barley loaves, they filled twelve panniers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>When these men saw the miracle which Jesus had done, they said, This is certainly the prophet; He who is coming into the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Jesus therefore knowing that they were about to come and take him by force to make him king, withdrew again to the mountain himself alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And as the evening was coming on, his disciples went down to the sea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and having gone on board the vessel, they coasted along towards Capernaum. Darkness had now come on and Jesus had not come to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and the sea ran high by reason of the wind, which blew hard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So when they had rowed about twenty five or thirty furlongs, they saw Jesus walking on the sea, and approaching the vessel; and they were terrified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Whereupon he said to them, It is I; be not afraid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>They wished therefore to take him into the vessel; and immediately the vessel was at the land to which they were going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>On the day following the people who continued on the sea side, having seen that there was no vessel there besides that one in which his disciples had embarked, and that Jesus did not go on board the vessel with his disciples, but that his disciples had gone away alone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Other vessels however came from Tiberias, nigh to the place where they had eaten bread after the Lord gave thanks</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>when the people therefore saw that neither Jesus nor his disciples were there, they went on board these vessels and came to Capernaum, seeking Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and having found him on that coast of the sea, they said to him Rabbi, when didst thou come hither?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus in reply said to them, Verily, verily I say to you, You seek me; not because you have seen miracles; but because you have eaten of the loaves and were satisfied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Labour not to procure the food which perisheth, but the food which endureth for an everlasting life, which the son of man will give you; for him the Father, namely God, hath sealed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thereupon they said to him, What must we do that we may work the works of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Jesus answered and said to them, This is the work of God that you believe in him whom he hath sent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Then they said to him, What miracle dost thou perform that we may see and believe in thee? What workest thou?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Our fathers ate manna in the wilderness, as it is written, He gave them bread from heaven to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Upon this Jesus said to them, Verily, verily I say to you, Moses did not give you the bread from heaven; but my Father giveth you the true bread of heaven:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>for the bread of God is that which cometh down from heaven and giveth life to the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Thereupon they said to him, Master, give us evermore that bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them, I am the bread of that life. He who cometh to me, shall never hunger; and he who believeth in me, shall never thirst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But I have told you that though you have seen me, you do not believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>All that the Father giveth me, will come to me. And him who cometh to me I will not reject.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For I am come down from heaven not to do mine own will, but the will of him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And this is the will of the Father, who sent me that of all which he hath given me, I should lose nothing, but raise it up at the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And this is the will of him who sent me, that every one who seeth the son, and believeth in him, may have an everlasting life, and that I raise him up at the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The Jews then murmured at him, because he said, I am the bread which came down from heaven,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and they said, Is not this Jesus, the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? How then doth he say, I came down from heaven?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Therefore Jesus answered and said to them, Murmur not among yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>No one can come to me, unless the Father, who hath sent me, draw him. And as for me, I will raise him up at the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>It is written in the prophets, They shall be all taught of God. Every one therefore who hath heard and learned from the Father, cometh to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Not that any one hath seen the Father, save he only who is from God. He hath seen the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Verily, verily, I say to you, He who believeth in me, hath an everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>I am the bread of that life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Your fathers ate the manna in the wilderness, and died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Such is the bread which cometh down from heaven, that whoever shall eat of it shall not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>I am that living bread which came down from heaven. If any one eat of this bread he shall live forever. Now the bread which I will give is this flesh of mine, which I will give for the life of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Upon this the Jews debated among themselves, saying, How can this man give us his flesh to eat?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Therefore Jesus said to them, Verily, verily, I say to you, Unless you eat the flesh of the son of man, and drink his blood, you have no life in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>He who eateth my flesh and drinketh my blood, hath an everlasting life, and I will raise him up at the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>For this flesh of mine is food indeed; and this blood of mine is indeed drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>He who eateth my flesh, and drinketh my blood, abideth in me and I in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>As the living Father hath sent me, and I live by the Father; so he. who eateth me, even he will live by me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>This is the bread which is come down from heaven. Not as your fathers ate the manna and died. He who eateth this bread shall live forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>These things he said in a public assembly, as he was teaching at Capernaum.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>Many of his disciples, therefore, when they heard them, said, This is harsh doctrine, who can hearken to it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="61">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus knowing in himself that his disciples were murmuring at this, he said to them, Doth this offend you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="62">
      <content>What if you see the son of man ascending up where he was before.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="63">
      <content>It is the spirit which giveth life, the flesh profiteth nothing. The words which I speak to you are spirit, they are life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="64">
      <content>But there are some of you who do not believe; (for Jesus knew from the beginning who they are who do not believe, and who it is that will deliver him up)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="65">
      <content>and (said he) for this cause I said to you, that none can come to me unless it be given him by my Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="66">
      <content>From this time many of his disciples withdrew and walked no more with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="67">
      <content>therefore Jesus said to the twelve, Have you also a mind to go away?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="68">
      <content>Whereupon Simon Peter answered him, Master, to whom shall we go? Thou hast the words of an everlasting life,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="69">
      <content>and we believe and know that thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="70">
      <content>Jesus answered them, Have I not chosen you twelve? Yet one of you is a spy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="71">
      <content>Now he spake of Judas Iscariot, son of Simon; for he thought of delivering him up though he was one of the twelve.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this Jesus travelled about in Galilee, for he did not chuse to walk in Judea, because the Jews sought to kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now the Jews festival of tabernacles was near,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>therefore his brethren said to him, Depart hence and go to Judea that thy disciples may see the works which thou dost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For one who seeketh to be known publicly, doth any thing in secret. Since thou dost these things, shew thyself to the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>(For even his brethren did not believe in him.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus saith to them, My time is not yet come; but your time is always ready.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The world cannot hate you: but it hateth me, because I testify concerning it that its works are evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Go ye up to this festival. I am not yet going up to this festival, because my time is not yet fully come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And having said this, he continued in Galilee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But when his brethren were gone up, then he also went up to the festival, not publicly, but in a private manner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The Jews therefore sought him at the festival, and said, Where is he?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And there was much private dispute concerning him, among the people; for some said he is a good man; and others said, No; but he seduceth the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>No one, however, spoke openly of him, for fear of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But about the middle of the festival Jesus went up to the temple and taught.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Jews expressed astonishment, saying, How came this man acquainted with letters, having never had an education?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesus addressing them, said, This doctrine of mine is not mine, but his, who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If any man is disposed to do his will, he will know in respect to this doctrine, whether it is of God, or whether I speak from myself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He who speaketh from himself, seeketh his own glory; but he who seeketh the glory of him who sent him, is true, and in him there is no falsehood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Did not Moses give you the law? Yet none of you observeth the law. Why do you seek to kill me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The people answered and said, Thou art possessed by a demon; Who seeketh to kill thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>In reply to which Jesus said to them, I did one work and you all express wonder at it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Moses gave you the law of circumcision (not that it is from Moses, but from the patriarchs,) and you circumcise a man on a sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If a person receiveth circumcision on a sabbath, that the law of Moses may not be broken, are you angry with me because on a sabbath I cured a man whose whole body was diseased.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Judge not according to appearance, but judge righteous judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Upon this some of the inhabitants of Jerusalem said, Is not this he whom they seek to kill?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Yet behold he speaketh boldly, and they say nothing to him. Perhaps the rulers know indeed that he is really the Christ!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But we know whence this man is; but as for the Christ, when he cometh, no one knoweth whence he is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Hereupon, Jesus, as he was teaching in the temple, cried and said, Do you indeed both know me, and know whence I am? I have not come of myself. But he who hath sent me is true, Him you do not know;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>but I know him, because I am immediately from him, and he sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Upon this they sought to seize him, but no one laid his hand on him, because his hour was not yet come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Many of the people, however, believed in him and said, Will the Christ, when he cometh, do greater miracles than those which this man hath done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The Pharisees heard of the people's whispering such things concerning him; and the Pharisees and the chief priests sent officers to apprehend him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Jesus therefore said to them, Yet a little while I am with you. When I go away to him who sent me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>you will seek me but will not find me; and where I am you cannot come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Upon this the Jews said among themselves, Whither is he going, that we shall not find him? Is he going to the dispersed among the Greeks, to teach the Greeks?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>What is the meaning of this saying of his, You will seek me and will not find me, and where I am going you cannot come?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>It being now the last the great day of the festival, Jesus stood and cried, saying, If any one thirst, let him come to me and drink.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>He who believeth in me; as the scripture hath said, Out of his belly will flow streams of living water.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now this he said in reference to the spirit which they who believed in him were to receive; for a holy spirit was not yet received, because Jesus was not yet glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Hereupon many of the people, when they heard this saying, said, This is certainly the prophet,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Others said, This is the Christ. But others said', Doth the Christ come out of Galilee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Hath not the scripture said that the Christ cometh of the seed of David and from Bethlehem, the town whence David was?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>So there was a division among the people on his account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And some of them had a mind to seize him, but no one laid hands on him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>The officers therefore went to the chief priests and the Pharisees, who said to them, Why have you not brought him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>The officers replied, Never did a man speak like this man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Thereupon the Pharisees answered them, Are you also seduced?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Hath any of the chief priests believed in him, or any of the Pharisees?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>But this multitude, which know not the law, are accursed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Nicodemus, he who came to Jesus by night, and who was one of them, said to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Doth our law condemn the man without hearing him, and knowing what he hath done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>In reply to which, they said to him, Art thou also of Galilee? Search and see that a prophet of Galilee hath not been raised up. Then every one went to his own home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>As for Jesus, he went to the mount of olives,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and early in the morning he came, again to the temple, and all the people came to him. And when he had taken a seat, and was teaching them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>the Scribes and the Pharisees bring to him a woman caught in adultery; and, having set her in the midst,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>they say to him, Teacher, this woman was caught in the very act of adultery.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now Moses in the law hath commanded us that such be stoned. What therefore dost thou say?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This they said to try him, that they might have matter for accusing him. Thereupon Jesus stooped down and wrote with his finger on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And as they continued asking him, he raised himself up, and said to them, Let him among you who is without sin throw the first stone at her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then he stooped down again and wrote on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But they who heard, being convicted by their own conscience, went out, one by one, the eldest first, even to the last, and Jesus was left alone, and the woman standing in the midst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When Jesus raised himself up, and saw none but the woman, he said to her, Woman, where are thine accusers? Hath no one passed sentence on thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And she said, No one, Sir. Then Jesus said to her, Neither do I pass sentence on thee. Go and sin no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Jesus spake to them again, saying, I am the light of the world. He who floweth me will not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Hereupon the Pharisees said to him, Thou testifiest concerning thyself. This testimony of thine is not to be regarded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Jesus answered and said to them, Though I testify concerning myself, my testimony is to be regarded, because I know whence I came, and whither I am going. But as for you, you do not know whence I come, nor whither I am going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>You judge according to the flesh, I judge no one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Yet if I judge, my judgment is true, because I am not alone, but I and the Father who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now it is written in your law, that the testimony of two men is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I am one testifying concerning myself, and the Father who sent me testifieth concerning me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thereupon they said, Where is thy Father? Jesus replied, You neither know me nor my Father. If you had known me, you would have known my Father also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>These things Jesus spake in the treasury, as he was teaching in the temple; yet no one laid hands on him. Because his hour was not yet come;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>therefore Jesus said to them again, I am. going away, and you will seek me and die in your sins. Whither I go you cannot come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon this, the Jews said, Will he kill himself, that he saith, Whither I go you cannot come?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then he said to them, You are from below; I am from above. You are of this world; I am not of this world;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>therefore I said to you, You will die in your sins: for if you do not believe that I am, you will die in your sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Upon this they said to him, Who art thou? And Jesus said to them, I am what I told you at the beginning,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and am now telling you. I have many things to speak and to judge respecting you. He indeed who sent me is true, and I speak to the world what I have heard from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>They did not know that he was speaking to them of the Father;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>therefore Jesus said to them, When you have lifted up the son of man, then you will know who I am; and that I do nothing of myself; but speak these things as my Father taught me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He indeed who sent me is with me. The Father hath not left me alone, because I do always the things which are pleasing to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>While he was thus speaking many believed in him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>therefore to the Jews who believed in him Jesus said, If you continue steadily in this doctrine of mine, you are my disciples indeed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and you will know the truth, and the truth will make you free.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Some answered him, We are the seed of Abraham, and have never been in bondage to any one: how then dost thou say, Ye shall be made free.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>To them Jesus replied, Verily, verily, I say to you, Whosoever committeth sin is the slave of sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now the slave abideth not in the family forever; but the son abideth forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>If therefore the son shall make you free, you will be free indeed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>I know that you are Abraham's seed; but you seek to kill me, because my word continueth not in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>What I have seen with my Father, I speak; and what you have seen with your father you do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>They answered and said to him, Abraham is our father. Jesus saith to them, If ye were the children of Abraham, you would do the works of Abraham.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>But now you seek to kill me, a man who told you the truth which I heard from God. Abraham did not do this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>You do the works of your father. Hereupon they said to him, We were not born of fornication; we have one father, namely, God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them, If God were your father, you would love me; for I proceed and do come from God. For I have not come of myself, but he sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>Why do ye not understand what I say? It is because you cannot bear this doctrine of mine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>You are of your father the devil, and bent upon executing the desires of your father. He was a manslayer from the beginning, and did not abide in the truth. Because there is no truth in him, when he speaketh falsehood he speaketh what is. natural to him, for he is a liar, and the father of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>But as for me, because I speak the truth, you do not believe me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Which of you convicteth me of sin? Now, if I speak truth, why do you not believe me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>He who is of God doth, for this cause, hear the words of God: you do not hearken, because you are not of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Thereupon the Jews answered, and said to him, Are we not right in saying, Thou art a Samaritan, and possessed by a demon?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Jesus replied, I am not possessed by a demon, but I honour my Father, and you dishonour me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>As for me, I seek not mine own glory. There is one who seeketh it and judgeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Verily, verily, I say to you, If any one will keep this doctrine of mine, he shall never see death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Thereupon the Jews said to him, Now we know that thou art possessed by a demon. Abraham is dead and the prophets; yet thou sayest, I any one keep this doctrine of mine, he shall never taste death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>Art thou greater than our father Abraham who died? The prophets also died. Whom dost thou make thyself?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Jesus answered, If I glorify myself, this glory of mine is nothing. It is the Father who glorifieth me, of whom you say that he is your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Now you do not know him, but I know him; and if I should say, I do not know him, I would speak falsely like you. But I know him and keep his word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Your father Abraham was transported with a desire to see this day of mine, and he saw it, and was made glad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>Upon this the Jews said to him, Thou art not yet fifty years old, and hast thou seen Abraham?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>Jesus said to them, Verily, verily, I say to you, Before Abraham was, I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>Upon this they took up stones to throw at him. But Jesus concealed himself and went out of the temple, passing through the midst of them, and thus withdrew.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And as he was passing along he saw a man who was blind from his birth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>whereupon his disciples asked him, saying, Rabbi, who sinned this man, or his parents, that he should be born blind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Jesus answered, It was neither for any sin of this man, nor of his parents: but that the works of God may be manifested in him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I must work the works of him who sent me, while it is day. Night is coming, when no one can work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>While I am in the world, I am the light of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Having said this he spat on the ground, and made some clay with the spittle, and spread the clay on the blind man's eyes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and said to him, Go, wash them at the pool of Siloam (the meaning, of which is Sent.) So he went and washed them and returned seeing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Thereupon the neighbours, and they who had seen him before, when he was blind, said, Is not this he who used to sit begging?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Some said, It is he: and others said it is like him. He said, I am the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then they said to him, How were thine eyes opened?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>In reply to which he said, A man called Jesus made clay and anointed mine eyes, and said to me, Go to the pool of Siloam and wash them. So I went and washed them and got sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then they said to him, Where is he? He saith, I do not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>They brought to the Pharisees him who was formerly blind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now it was a sabbath when Jesus made the clay and opened his eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Therefore the Pharisees asked him again, how he got sight. And he said to them, He put clay on mine eyes, and I washed them and see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thereupon some of the Pharisees said; That man is not from God, because he doth not keep the sabbath. Others said, How can a sinful man do such miracles? So there was a dissention among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They say to the blind man again, What sayest thou of him for opening thine eyes? He said, He is a prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The Jews therefore did not believe in respect to him, that he had been blind and got sight, until they called the parents of him who had obtained sight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and asked them saying, Is this your son who you say was born blind? How then doth he now see?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In answer to which his parents said, We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But how he now seeth, we do not know: nor do we know who hath opened his eyes. He is of age; ask him; let him speak for himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>This his parents said, because they were afraid of the Jews; for the Jews had now agreed that if any one acknowledged Jesus to be the Christ, he should be excommunicated.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For this cause his parents said, He is of age; ask him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then they called a second time the man who had been blind, and said to him, Give glory to God. We know that this man is a sinner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Upon this he answered and said, If he be a sinner, I know not. One thing I know, that I was blind, and now I see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then they said to him again, What did he do to thee? How did he open thine eyes?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He answered them, I have told you already. Did you not hear? Why do you desire to hear it again? Have you indeed a mind to be his disciples?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Upon this they reviled him and said, Thou art a disciple of his; but as for us, we are disciples of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>We know that God spake to Moses; but as for this man, we know not whence he is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>In reply to this the man said to them, Why; in this there is something marvellous, that you do not know whence he is, though he hath opened mine eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Now we know that God hearkeneth not to sinners; but if any one be a worshipper of God, and do his will, to him he hearkeneth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>From the beginning of the world it was never heard that any one opened the eyes of one born blind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>If this man were not from God he could do nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>They answered and said to him, Thou wast altogether born in sin, and dost thou teach us? And they excommunicated him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Jesus heard that they had excommunicated him; and having met with him he said to him, Dost thou believe in the son of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>He answered and said, Who is he, Sir, that I may believe in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Jesus said to him, Thou indeed seest him, and it is he who is talking with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Whereupon he said, Lord, I believe, and worshipped him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Then Jesus said, I am come into this world for judgment that they who do not see may see, and that they who see may become blind;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and some of the Pharisees who were with him, when they heard this, said, Are we blind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Jesus said to them, If you were blind, you would not have had sin; but now you say, We see; therefore your sin remaineth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Verily, verily, I say to you, He who entereth not by the door into the fold of the sheep, but climbeth over some other way, is a thief and a robber:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>but he who goeth in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>To him the doorkeeper openeth and the sheep hearken to his voice; and he calleth his own sheep by name, and leadeth them out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when he hath brought out his own sheep, he goeth before them and his sheep follow him because they know his voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They will not follow a stranger, but will flee from him, because they do not know the voice of strangers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This parable Jesus spake to them, but they did not comprehend the meaning of what he said to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore Jesus said to them again, Verily, verily I say to you, I am the door of the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>All that have come in my stead, are thieves and robbers: but the sheep did not hearken to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I am the door. If any enter in by me, it shall be safe, and shall go in and out, and find pasture.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The thief cometh only to steal and to kill and to destroy. I am come that the sheep may have life and that they may have it superabundantly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I am the good shepherd. The good shepherd exposeth his life for the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But the hireling, who is not the shepherd, and to whom the sheep do not belong, when he seeth the wolf coming leaveth the sheep and fleeth; and the wolf seizeth some and scattereth the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The hireling fleeth because he is a hireling and careth not for the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I am the good shepherd and I know mine own sheep, and am known by them who are mine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>even as the father knoweth me, and I know the father; and I lay down my life for the sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now I have other sheep which are not of this fold. These also I must lead; they will hearken to my voice, and there shall be one flock and one shepherd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>On this account the father loveth me, because I lay down my life so that I may take it again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>No one forceth it from me; but I lay it down of myself. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again. This commission I have received from my father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Upon this there was another division among the Jews, on account of these sayings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And many of them said, He is possessed by a demon, and is mad, Why do you. hearken to him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Others said, These are not the words of a demoniac. Can a demon open the eyes of the blind?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When they were celebrating the dedication festival at Jerusalem, and it was stormy weather;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and Jesus was walking in the temple in Solomon's portico;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the Jews again came around him, and said to him, How long dost thou keep us in suspense? If thou art the Christ, tell us plainly:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Jesus answered them, I told you but you do not believe. The works which I do in my father's name these testify concerning me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But you do not believe, for you are not of my sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>My sheep, as I told you, hearken to my voice and I know them, and they follow me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and I give them everlasting life; and they shall never perish, nor shall any one wrest them out of my hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>My father who gave them to me, is greater than all, and none is able to wrest them out of my father's hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I and my father are one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Hereupon the Jews again took up stones to stone him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Jesus addressed them, I have shewn you many good works from my father, for which of those works would you stone me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>The Jews answered him saying, For a good work we are not about to stone thee, but for blasphemy, even because thou, being a man, makest thyself God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus answered them, Is it not written in your law I said you are Gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>If it stileth them gods to whom the word of God was addressed, (now the scripture cannot be set aside)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>do you say of me, whom the father hath consecrated and sent into the world, Thou blasphemest, because I said, I am the son of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>If I do not the works of my father, believe me not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But if I do; though you do not believe me, believe the works; that you may know and believe that the father is in me, and I in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Upon this they again sought to seize him. But he withdrew out of their hands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and went again to the bank of the Jordan; to the place where John baptized at first, and abode there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And many resorted to him and said, John indeed wrought no miracle; but all that John said respecting this man is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And many there believed in him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now one Lazarus, an inhabitant of Bethany, the town of Mary and her sister Martha, was sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>It was this Mary who anointed the Lord with balsam, after wiping his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The sisters, therefore sent to Jesus, saying, Sir, He whom thou lovest is sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Upon hearing this, Jesus said, This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that by it the son of God may be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Therefore though Jesus loved Martha and her sister, and Lazarus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>yet when he heard that he was, sick, he then stayed two days in the place where he was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And after that he saith to his disciples, Let us go again to Judea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The disciples say to him, Rabbi, very lately the Jews sought to stone thee, and art thou going thither again?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Jesus answered, Are there not twelve hours in the day? If any one walketh in the day he stumbleth not, because he seeth the light of this world:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but if any one walk in the night he stumbleth because there is no light in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thus he spake, and after that he saith to them, Our friend Lazarus is composed to rest; but I am going to wake him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thereupon his disciples said, Master, if he is composed to rest, he will recover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now Jesus spoke of his death; but they thought that he spoke of taking rest in sleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore Jesus then told them plainly, Lazarus is dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And on your account that you may believe, I am glad that I was not there. But let us go to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Upon this Thomas, who is called Didymus, said to his fellow disciples, Let us also go that we may die with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So when Jesus came, he found that he had now been four days in the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now Bethany was near Jerusalem, about fifteen furlongs off.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary, to comfort them on the death of their brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Therefore soon as Martha heard that Jesus is coming she went out to meet him; but Mary remained in the house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Martha therefore said to Jesus, Master, if thou hadst been here my brother would not have died;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>but still I know that whatever thou wilt ask of God, God will grant thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Thy brother shall rise again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Martha said to him, I know that he will rise again at the resurrection, at the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Jesus said to her, I am the resurrection and the life; he who believeth in me, though he may die, shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And none who liveth and believeth in me shall ever die. Believest thou this?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>She saith to him, Yes, Lord, I believe that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, the one coming into the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And having said this, she went and called her sister Mary privately, saying, The teacher is come and calleth for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>As soon as she heard, she riseth instantly and goeth to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now Jesus had not yet entered the village, but was at the place where Martha met him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When the Jews therefore who were in the house, and comforting her, saw that Mary arose hastily and went out, they followed her, saying, She is going to the tomb to weep there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>When Mary then was come to the place where Jesus was, upon seeing him she fell at his feet, saying to him, Lord, if thou hadst been here my brother would not have died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Therefore when Jesus saw her weeping, and the Jews also weeping who came with her, he restrained his spirit, and was troubled,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and said, Where have you laid him? They say to him, Master, Come and see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Jesus wept.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Upon this the Jews said, Behold! how he loved him!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And some of them said, Could not this man who opened the eyes of the blind have prevented his death?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then Jesus, again restraining himself, cometh to the tomb. Now it was a cave and a stone lay upon it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Jesus saith, Remove the stone. Martha, the sister of him who was dead, saith to him, Master, by this time the smell is offensive; for this is the fourth day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Did I not tell thee, if thou wouldst believe thou shouldst see the glory of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then they removed the stone from where the deceased lay. And Jesus lifted up his eyes and said, Father, I thank thee that thou hast heard me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Now I know that thou hearest me always; but I have said this for the sake of the people standing around, that they may believe that thou hast sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And having said this, he cried with a loud voice, Lazarus, Come forth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Whereupon he who had been dead came forth, bound hand and foot with grave clothes, and his face was wrapped in a napkin. Jesus saith to them, Loose him and let him go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Upon this many of the Jews who had come to Mary, when they saw what Jesus had done, believed in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>But some of them went to the Pharisees and told them what Jesus had done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Whereupon the chief priests and the Pharisees assembled the Sanhedrim, and said, What are we doing? Because this man doth many miracles,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>if we let him go on thus, all will believe in him, and the Romans will come and destroy both this place and this nation of ours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>And one of them, namely, Caiaphas, being chief priest that year, said to them, Are you totally ignorant,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>and do you not consider that it is better for us that one man die for the people than that the whole nation should perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Now this he said not merely of himself, but being high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus was soon to die for that nation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>and not for that nation only, but that he might gather into one body the children of God who were scattered abroad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>From that day therefore they consulted together that they might put him to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>For this reason Jesus walked no more publicly among the Jews, but went thence to the country near the wilderness, to a city called Ephraim, and continued there with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>Now the passover of the Jews was near, and many came up to Jerusalem from the country, before the passover, to purify themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>They therefore sought Jesus, and said to one another as they were standing in the temple, What think ye? Will he not come to this festival?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>Now the chief priests and the Pharisees had issued an order, that if any one knew where he is, he should give information, that they might apprehend him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Jesus therefore, six days before the passover, went to Bethany were Lazarus was, who had been dead, and whom he had raised from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And a supper was made for him there; and Martha waited, and Lazarus was one of them who were at table with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Mary then having taken a pound of the balsam of spikenard, unadulterated, very costly, anointed the feet of Jesus when she had wiped his feet with her hair. And the house was filled with the odour of the balsam.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Upon which one of the disciples, namely Judas Iscariot, son of Simon, who was about to deliver him up,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>said, Why was not this balsam sold for three hundred deniars, and given to the poor?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now this he said, not because he cared for the poor, but because he was a thief and had the purse and carried off what was put into it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Therefore Jesus said, Let her alone. She hath kept this for the day of preparing my body for burial,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>for you have the poor always with you; but me you have not always.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now a great number of the Jews knew that he was there, and had come, not on the account of Jesus only; but to see Lazarus, whom he had raised from the dead;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the chief priests therefore determined to put Lazarus also to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>because on his account many of the Jews withdrew and believed in Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>On the next day a great multitude who had come to the festival, hearing that Jesus is coming to Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>took branches of palm trees and went out to meet him, and cried, Hosanna! Blessed he, who is coming in the name of the Lord! The king of Israel!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now Jesus having found a young ass, was riding thereon, agreeably to what is written,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Fear not, daughter, of Sion! behold thy king cometh mounted on an ass's colt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>These things his disciples did not understand at the time; but when Jesus was glorified, then they remembered that these things were written concerning him; and that they had done them for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now because the multitude who were with him testified that he had called Lazarus from the tomb, and raised him, from the dead;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and on this account the multitude met him, because they heard that he had done this miracle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>therefore the Pharisees said among themselves, You see that you gain no advantage. Behold the world is gone after him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now among them who came up to worship at the festival, there were some Greeks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>These therefore came to Philip, who was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and asked him, saying, Sir, We wish to see Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Philip cometh and telleth Andrew. And Andrew and Philip tell Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Whereupon Jesus answered them, saying, The hour is come that the Son of man should be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Verily, verily I say to you, If the grain of wheat which falleth on the ground dieth not, it remaineth a single grain. But if it die, it bringeth forth much fruit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He who loveth his life, will lose it: but he who slighteth his life in this world, shall keep it for an everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>If any one would wait upon me, let him follow me; and where I am, there shall this attendant of mine also be. And if any one wait upon me my Father will reward him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now is my soul troubled. What then? Shall I say, Father save me from this hour? But for this cause I came to this hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Father, glorify thy name. Thereupon a voice came from heaven, I have glorified it, and I will glorify it again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The multitude therefore who were standing by, when they heard it, said, it thundered. Others said, An angel hath spoken to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Jesus answered and said, This voice hath not come for my sake, but for yours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Now is the judgment of this world. Now will the chieftain of this world be cast out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>As for me, when I am lifted up from the ground, I will draw all men to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>(Now this he said, signifying the death he should soon die.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>The multitude answered him, We have heard out of the law that The Christ remaineth forever. How then dost thou say, That the son of man must be lifted up? Who is this son of man?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Jesus therefore said to them, Yet a little while the light is with you. Walk while you have the light that the darkness may not overtake you; for he who walketh in darkness knoweth not where he is going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>while you have the light, believe in the light, that you may be children of light. Having said this, Jesus withdrew, and was concealed from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Now though he had performed so many miracles before them, they did not believe in him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>so that the word of the prophet Esaias was confirmed, which he spoke, Lord who hath believed our report, and to whom hath the arm of the Lord been revealed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>It was because they were not enabled to believe that in another place Esaias said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>He hath blinded their eyes, and stupified their hearts, so that they saw not with their eyes, nor understood with their heart, nor turned that I might heal them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>This Esaias said when he saw his glory and spake concerning him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Nevertheless when several of the chief's believed in him, but on account of the Pharisees did not acknowledge it, that they might not be excommunicated,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>(for they loved the praise of men, more than the praise of God)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>therefore Jesus raised his voice and said, He who believeth in me, believeth not merely in me, but in him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>And he who beholdeth me, beholdeth him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>I being light am come into the world, that whoever believeth in me may not remain in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Now if any one hear my words and believe not; it is not I who condemn him; for I did not come to condemn the world, but to save the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>He who slighteth me and receiveth not my words, hath that which condemneth him; the word which I have spoken, that will condemn him at the last day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>Because I have not spoken from myself, but the father who sent me hath himself given me a command what I should enjoin, and what I should speak,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>and I know that his commandment is everlasting life, therefore what I speak, I speak just as the father directed me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now before this festival of the passover, as Jesus knew that his time was come that he should remove from this world to the father, having loved his own who were in the world, he loved them to the last.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When they were at supper (the devil having already put it into the heart of Judas Iscariot son of Simon to deliver him up,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Jesus knowing that the father hath given all things into his hands, and that he had come forth from God, and is going to God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>riseth from the supper and layeth aside his upper garments, and having taken a towel and girded himself,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>he then poureth water into the basin and began to wash the feet of the disciples and wipe them with the towel, with which he was girded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He cometh therefore to Simon Peter. Whereupon Peter saith to him, Master, thou wash my feet!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Jesus answered and said to him, What I am doing thou dost not comprehend at present, but thou shalt know hereafter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Peter saith to him, Thou shalt never wash my feet. Jesus answered him, Unless I wash thee thou hast no portion with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Simon Peter saith to him; Master, not my feet only, but also the hands and the head.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, He who hath bathed needeth only to wash the feet, the rest of the body being clean. Now you are clean, but not all,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>(For he knew him who was delivering him up, therefore he said, You are not all clean.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So when he had washed their feet and put on his garments, having again taken his place at table, he said to them, Consider what I have done to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>You call me The teacher and the master; and you say right, for so I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If I then, the master and the teacher, have washed your feet, you ought to wash one another's feet;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>for I have set you an example, that you may do as I have done to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Verily, verily I say to you, The servant is not greater than his master; nor is a missionary greater than he who sent him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If you know these things, happy are you if you practise them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I do not speak of you all. I know whom I have chosen. But that the scripture may be fulfilled, He Who is eating bread with me hath lifted up his heel against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>This I tell you now before it happeneth, that when it cometh to pass you may believe me to be what I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Verily, verily I say to you, He who receiveth whomsoever I shall send, receiveth me; and he who receiveth me receiveth him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Having said this, Jesus was troubled in spirit and testified and said, Verily, verily I say to you, that one of you is to deliver me up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon this his disciples looked at one another, doubting of whom he spake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now one of the disciples, whom Jesus loved, was reclined at table next to Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Simon Peter therefore beckoned to him to ask who it might be of whom he spake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Thereupon he, bending back his head to Jesus breast, saith to him, Master, who is it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus answereth, It is he to whom I will give this morsel after I have dipped it. Then, having dipped the morsel, he giveth it to Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And, after the morsel, Satan then entered into him. Therefore Jesus said to him, What thou dost, do quickly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now none of them at table knew for what purpose he said this to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For some thought, as Judas had the purse, that Jesus is saying to him, Buy what we have need of for the festival, or that he should give something to the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He therefore, having received the morsel, went out immediately. Now it was night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>When he therefore was gone, Jesus saith, Now is the son of man glorified; and God is glorified by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>If God be glorified by him, God will also glorify him in himself. Indeed without delay he will glorify him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Children, yet a little while I am with you. You will seek me, and as I said to the Jews, whither I am going you cannot come, so I now say to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>A new commandment I give you, that you love one another. As I have loved you, that you also love one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>By this all men will know that you are my disciples, if you exercise mutual love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Simon Peter saith to him, Master, whither art thou going? Jesus answered him, Whither I am going thou canst not follow me now; but here after thou wilt follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Peter saith to him, Master, Why can not I follow thee now? I will lay down my life for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Jesus answered him, Thou wilt lay down thy life for me! Verily, verily, I say to thee, A cock will not crow till thou hast thrice denied me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Let not your hearts be troubled. Trust in God: trust also in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>In my Father's house there are many mansions. If there were not, would I have said to you, I am going to prepare a place for you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now when I have gone and prepared a place for you, I will come again and take you to myself, that where I am you may be also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now you know whither I am going and you know the way;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thomas saith to him, Master, We do not know whither thou art going, how then can we know the way?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, I am the way and the truth and the life. No one cometh to the father but by me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Had you known me, you would have known my Father also. But hence forth you know him and have seen him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Philip saith to him, Master shew us the Father, and it sufficeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, Am I so long a time with you, and hast thou not known me, Philip? He who hath seen me hath seen the Father: how then sayest thou, Shew us the Father?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Dost thou not believe that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? The words which I speak to you, I do not speak from myself. And it is the Father himself abiding in me who doth the works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Believe me that I am in the Father and that the Father is in me. At least believe me on account of the works themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Verily, verily, I say to you, He who believeth in me, even he shall do the works which I do; nay, works greater than these he shall do, because I am going to my Father,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and whatever you ask in my name, that I will do. That the Father may be glorified in the Son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>if you ask any thing in my name, I will do it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If you love me keep my commandments,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and I will ask the Father and he will give you another monitor, that he may continue with you forever,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>even the spirit of truth which the world cannot receive because it neither seeth him nor knoweth him. But you know him, because he abideth with you and will be in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I will not leave you orphans. I am coming to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Yet a little while and the world seeth me no more; but you see me. Because I live therefore you shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In that day you will know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He who hath my commandments and keepeth them; he. it is who loveth me. And he who loveth me will be loved by my Father, and I will love him and manifest myself to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Judas (not the Iscariot) saith to him, Master, How is it that thou wilt manifest thyself to us, and not to the world?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus in reply, said to him, If any one love me, he will keep my word and my Father will love him; and we will come to him and make an abode with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He who doth not love me, doth not keep my words. Now the word which you hear is not mine only, but the Fathers who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you, while I remain with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But the Monitor the Holy Spirit which the Father will send in my name, he will teach you all things and bring to your remembrance all that I have said to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Peace I leave with you. This peace of mine I give you. It is not as the world giveth that I give to you. Let not your heart be troubled nor dismayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>You have heard me say to you, I am going away and I am coming to you. If you love me, you would rejoice because I said, I am going to the Father: for my Father is greater than I.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now I have told you before it come to pass, that when it is come to pass you may believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I will not discourse much more with you, for the; chieftain of this world is coming, and hath nothing to do with me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>save only that the world may know that I love the Father and do as he commanded me. Arise; let us go hence.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I am the true vine, and my Father is the vine dresser.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Every branch in me which beareth not fruit, he loppeth off; and every branch which beareth fruit he cleaneth to make it more fruitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now you are clean through the word which I have spoken to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Abide in me, and I will abide in you. As the branch cannot bear fruit of itself unless it abide in the vine; so neither can you unless you continue in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I am the vine; you are the branches. He who continueth in me and I in him he it is who beareth much fruit. Because, separated from me, you can bear nothing:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>if any one continueth not in me he is thrown away as the branch is when it is withered. Such indeed are gathered and thrown into the fire and burned.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If you continue in me, and my words continue in you, ask what you will and it will be done for you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>by this my Father is glorified. That you may bear much fruit, you must be my disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As the Father hath loved me, so I have loved you. Continue ye in my love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If you keep my commandments, you shall continue in my love; as I have kept my Father's commandments and continue in his love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you that my joy may continue, and that your joy may be complete.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>This is my commandment, that you love one another as I have loved you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>No one hath greater love than this, that he would lay down his life for his friends.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>You are my friends, if you do what I command you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I no longer call you servants; because the servant doth not know what his master doth. But I have called you friends, because I have made known to you all that I heard from my Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>It was not you who chose me; but it was I who chose you, and placed you that you may go forth bearing fruit, and that your fruit may continue, that the Father may give you whatever you ask of him in my name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>These things I command you that you may love one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If the world hate you, consider that it hated me before you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>If ye were of the world, the world would love its own. Now because you are not of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Remember the word which I spake to you. The servant is not greater than his master. If they persecuted me, they will also persecute you. If they have kept my word, they will also keep yours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But all these things they will do to you on account of my name, because they do not know him who sent me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>If I had not come and spoken to them, they would not have had sin; but now they have no excuse for their sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He who hateth me, hateth my Father also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If I had not done among them works which no other did, they would not have had sin: but now, though they have seen, they have hated both me and my Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But by this is fulfilled the word which is written in their law, They hated me without cause.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now when the monitor whom I Will send to you from the Father, is come; the spirit of truth who proceedeth from the Father, he will testify concerning me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And as for you, bear ye witness also, because you have been with me from the beginning.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you that you may not be stumbled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>They will excommunicate you. Indeed a time is coming, when whosoever killeth you will think he doth an act of religious worship to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And these things they will do to you because they know neither the Father nor me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But I have spoken these things to you, that, when that time cometh, you may remember that I mentioned them to you. I did not tell you them from the beginning, because I was with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But now I am going to him who sent me, and none of you asketh me, Whither art thou going.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But because I have told you these things, sorrow hath filled your hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But, I tell you this truth, it is to your advantage that I go away: for if I do not go, the monitor will not come to you; but when I go I will send him to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when he is come, he will convince the world in respect to sin, and in respect to righteousness, and in respect to judgment</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>in respect to sin, because they do not believe in me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and in respect to righteousness because I go to my Father and you see me no more;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and in respect to judgment, because the prince of this world is judged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I have still many things to say to you, but you cannot bear them now.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But when he the spirit of truth, is come, he will lead you into all the truth; for he will not speak from himself, but will speak whatsoever he shall have heard, and will explain to you the train of events.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He will glorify me, for he will receive of mine, and communicate to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>All that the Father hath is mine; therefore I said, He will receive of mine, and communicate to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Yet a little while and you do not see me; and again a little while and you shall see me, because I am going to the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Upon this some of his disciples said to one another, What is this which he saith to us, A little while and you do not see me; and again a little while and you shall see me; and, because I am going to the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>They said therefore, What is this little while of which he speaketh? We do not comprehend what he saith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>As Jesus knew that they were desirous to ask him, therefore he said to them, Do ye inquire among yourselves concerning this, because I said, A little while, and you do not see me; and again a little while and you shall see me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Verily, verily, I say to you, You will weep and mourn; but the world will rejoice. You will be sorrowful; but your sorrow will be turned into joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>A woman in travail hath sorrow, because her time is come; but when the child is born, she no more remembereth her anguish, for joy that a man is born into the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So you at present are in grief; but I will see you again and your heart will be made joyful; and that joy of yours no one shall take from you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now in that day you will not ask me any thing. Verily, verily, I say to you, whatever you shall ask of the Father in my name, he will give you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Hitherto you have asked nothing in my name. Ask and ye shall receive, that your joy may be complete.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you in parables. But a time is coming when I will no more speak to you in parables, but with plainness of speech tell you respecting the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>In that day you will ask in my name, and I do not say to you that I will ask the Father for you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for the Father himself loveth you, because you have loved me and have believed that I came from God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>I came forth from the Father and am come into the world. Again I leave the world and am going to the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>His disciples say to him, Behold now thou speakest plainly and usest no parable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now we know that thou knowest all things, and hast no need that any should ask thee questions. By this we believe that thou camest forth from God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Jesus answered them, Do you now believe?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Behold the time is coming, indeed is now come, when you will be scattered every one to his own, and you will leave me alone; yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>These things I have spoken to you, that you may have peace in me. In this world you will have trouble; but take courage: I have overcome the world.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Having spoken this, Jesus raised his eyes to heaven, and said, Father the hour is come. Glorify thy son, that thy son may glorify thee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>that, as thou hast given him power over all flesh, he may, according to all that thou hast given him, give to these everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now this is the life everlasting that they may know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I have glorified thee on the earth; I have finished the work which thou gavest me to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now therefore, O Father, glorify thou me, with thyself, with that glory which I had in thy presence before the world was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I have made known thy name to the men whom thou gavest me out of the world. They were thine, and thou gavest them to me, and they have kept thy word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>They now know that all those things which thou gavest me, come from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Because I have given them the doctrines which thou gavest me, therefore they have received them, and know certainly that I came forth from thee; and believe that thou didst send me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I pray for them. I am not praying for the world, but for them whom thou gavest me. Because they are thine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and all things that are mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified by them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and am no longer in this world, but these are in this world, and I am coming to thee: Holy Father, keep in thy name them whom thou gavest me that they may be one as we are.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>While I was with them in the world, I kept them in thy name. Them whom thou gavest to me I have guarded, and none of them is lost, unless it be the son of perdition, so that the scripture is fulfilled;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>but I am now coming to thee, and I speak these things in this world, that they may have their joy in me completed in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have given them thy word, and the world hath hated them, because they are not of the world as I am not of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I do not ask thee to remove them out of the world, but to preserve them from the evil one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They are not of the world, as I am not of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Consecrate them for thy truth. The Word which is thine, is truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>As thou hast sent me into the world, so I have sent them into the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And for them I consecrate myself, that they may be consecrated for truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now I do not pray for these only, but for those also who shall by means of their word believe in me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>that all may be one as thou, Father, art in me and I in thee, that they also may be one in us that the world may believe that thou hast sent me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and that I have given them the glory which thou gavest me, that they may be one as we are one</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I in them and thou in me, that they may be taken into union, and that the world may know that thou hast sent me, and hast loved them as thou hast loved me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>O Father, with respect to them whom thou hast given me, my desire is that where I am, they may be with me, that they may behold my glory which thou hast given me, because thou lovedst me before the foundation of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Righteous Father, though the world did not know thee, I knew thee, and these have known that thou didst send me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I have made known thy name to them, and I will make it known, that the love with which thou hast loved me may be in them and I in them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When Jesus had thus spoken, he went out with his disciples to the bank of the brook Kedron, where there was a garden into which he went with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now Judas who delivered him up knew the place, because Jesus had often resorted thither with his disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Judas, therefore, having got the band of soldiers and under officers from the chief priests, and Pharisees, cometh thither with lanterns and torches and weapons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus, knowing all that were coming upon him, went forth and said to them, Whom do ye seek?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They answered him, Jesus the Nazarene. Jesus saith to them, I am he. Now Judas, who delivered him up, was with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>As soon then as he said to them, I am he, they drew back and fell on the ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He therefore asked them again, Whom do you seek? And when they answered, Jesus the Nazarene;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Jesus replied, I have told you that I am he. If therefore you seek me, let these go their way;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>that the word might be fulfilled which he spake, saying, Of them whom thou gavest me I have lost none.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon this Simon Peter, having a sword, drew it and smote the servant of the chief priest, and cut oft his right ear. Now the servant's name was. Malchus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thereupon Jesus said to Peter, Put up thy sword into the sheath. Must I not drink the cup which my Father hath given me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the band of soldiers, and the commander and the under officers of the Jews, took Jesus and bound him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and led him away, first to Annas, for he was the father in law of Caiaphas, who was chief priest that year.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now it was Caiaphas who in council said to the Jews, It was expedient that one man die for the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now Simon Peter, and another, disciple, followed Jesus. The other disciple was known to the chief priest, and went in with Jesus into the court of the chief priest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>but Peter stood at the gate without. The other disciple, therefore, who was known to the chief priest, went out and spoke to the portress, and brought in Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whereupon the girl, the portress, saith to Peter, Art not thou one of the disciples of that man? He saith, I am not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now the servants and the under officers stood by a fire which they had made, because it was cold, and were warming themselves; and Peter stood with them and was warming himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Meanwhile the chief priest asked Jesus concerning his disciples, and concerning his doctrine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Jesus answered him, I spake openly to the world, I taught always in the synagogues and in the temple, to which the Jews always resort. And I have spoken nothing in secret.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Why askest thou me? Ask them who heard what I spoke to them. Behold they know what I have said.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon his saying this, one of the under officers who stood by, gave Jesus a slap on the cheek, saying, Answerest thou the high priest so?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Jesus answered him, If I have spoken disrespectfully, testify concerning the disrespect: but if properly; why smitest thou me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now Annas had sent him bound to Caiaphas the chief priest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Still Simon Peter was standing warming himself; they therefore said to him, Art not thou also one of his disciples? He denied and said, I am not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>One of the servants of the chief priest, a kinsman of him whose ear Peter had cut off, said, Did I not see thee in the garden with him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thereupon Peter again denied, and immediately a cock crowed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>From Caiaphas they led Jesus away to the judgment hall of the Roman governor. Now it was early in the morning and they themselves did not go into the hall that they might not be polluted, but that they might eat the passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Pilate therefore came out to them and said, What accusation do you bring against this man?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>They in reply, said to him, If he were not a malefactor we would not have delivered him over to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Then Pilate said to them; Take him yourselves and judge him according to your law. Upon this the Jews said to him, It is not lawful for us to put any man to death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>so that the word was fulfilled which Jesus had spoken, signifying by what kind of death he was to die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then Pilate went again into the hall, and called Jesus and said to him, Thou art the king of the Jews?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Jesus answered him, Dost thou say this from thyself? Or have others told it thee concerning me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Pilate answered him, Am I a Jew? Thine own nation, even the chief priests, have delivered thee up to me. What hast thou done?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Jesus answered, My kingdom is not of this world. If my kingdom were of this world, my attendants would have fought to prevent my being delivered up to the Jews. But now my kingdom is not of this world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Thereupon Pilate said to him, Thou art a king then? Jesus answered, It is as thou sayest, I am a king. For this I was born, and for this I came into the world, to bear testimony for the truth. Every one who is of the truth hearkeneth to my voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Pilate saith to him, What is truth? And having said this, he went out again to the Jews, and saith to them, I find no fault in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Now you have a custom that I should release one to you at the passover. Is it your will therefore that I release to you the king of the Jews?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Upon this they all cried out again, saying, Not this man, but Barabbas. Now this Barabbas was a robber.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Pilate took Jesus and scourged him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and the soldiers having platted a crown of thorns, put it on his head and threw around him a purple robe,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and said, Hail! king of the Jews! When they gave him slaps on the cheek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Pilate went out again and saith to them, Behold I bring him out to you that you may know that I find no fault in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So Jesus came out wearing the crown of thorns and the purple robe. And Pilate saith to them, Behold the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Upon which when the chief priests, and the officers saw him, they cried, saying, Crucify him; crucify him. Pilate saith to them, Take him yourselves and crucify him; for I find no fault in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The Jews answered, We have a law; and by that law of ours he ought to die, because he hath pretended to be the son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now when Pilate heard this expression he was more alarmed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and went again into the judgment hall, and saith to Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus made him no answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then Pilate saith to him, Dost thou not speak to me? Knowest thou not, that I have power to crucify thee; and that I have power to release thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Jesus answered, Thou couldst have no power at all against me, if it were not given thee from above; therefore he who delivered me up to thee hath the greater sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>From this time Pilate sought to release him; but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou let this man go, thou art not Caesar's friend. Whoever maketh himself a king speaketh against Caesar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When Pilate therefore heard this speech, he brought out Jesus and sat down on the tribunal in a place called the pavement (in Hebrew Gabbatha.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>(It was now the paschal preparation day, and the sixth hour was drawing on,) and he saith to the Jews, Behold your king!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Whereupon they cried out, Away, away with him; crucify him. Pilate saith to them, Shall I crucify your king? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then he delivered him up to them to be crucified. So they took Jesus and led him away,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and he went out, carrying his cross, to the place called Sculls, (in Hebrew, Golgotha,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>where they crucified him, and two others with him; one on one side and the other on the other side, and Jesus in the middle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now Pilate had written a label and put it on the cross, and the writing was this, Jesus The Nazarine, The King Of The Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>This label therefore many of the Jews read; for the place where Jesus was crucified was near the city; and the inscription was in Hebrew and Greek and Latin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Wherefore the chief priests of the Jews said to Pilate, Write not The king of the Jews, but, that he said, I am the king of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Pilate answered, What I have written, I have written.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now when the soldiers had nailed Jesus to the cross, they took his garments and divided them into four parts, to every soldier a part. But as for the vest, as it was without seam, being woven from the top throughout,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>they said to one another, Let us not tear it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be, so that the scripture was fulfilled which saith, They parted my garments among them; and for my vesture they cast lots. These things the soldiers actually did.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now there stood by the cross of Jesus, his mother, and his mother's sister, Mary the wife of Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Jesus therefore seeing his mother, and the disciple whom he loved standing near, saith to his, mother, Woman, behold thy son!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then he saith to the disciple, Behold thy mother? And from that hour the disciple took her to his own home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>After this, Jesus, knowing that all things were now accomplished, that the scripture might be fulfilled, saith, I thirst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Upon which, as there was a vessel set full of vinegar, some having filled a sponge with vinegar put it on a stalk of hyssop and put it to his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>When Jesus had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished, and bowing his head, he expired.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Now that the bodies might not remain on the cross during the sabbath, therefore when it was preparation time (for that sabbath was a great day) the Jews besought Pilate that their legs might be broken and the bodies removed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The soldiers therefore came and broke the legs of the first and also of the other who had been crucified with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But when they came to Jesus, as they saw that he was already dead, they did not break his legs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But one of the soldiers with his spear pierced his side, and blood and water issued forth immediately.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now he who was an eye witness hath testified this. And his testimony is true, and Jesus himself knoweth that he speaketh the truth that you may believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For these things were done that the scripture might be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be broken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And again another scripture saith, They will look on him whom they have pierced.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>After this, Joseph of Arimathea, who was a disciple of Jesus, but for fear of the Jews, a concealed one, asked leave of Pilate to take away the body of Jesus, and Pilate granted it. He therefore came and took away the body of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And Nicodemus, he who formerly came to Jesus by night, came also with a mixture of myrrh and aloes, weighing about a hundred pounds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>So they took the body of Jesus and wrapped it up in linen swathings with the spices, according to the Jewish custom of embalming.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Now at the place where he was crucified there was a garden, and in the garden a new tomb, in which no one had ever been laid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Therefore on account of the preparation of the Jews, they laid Jesus there, because the tomb was nigh at hand.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now on the first day of the week, Mary Magdalene cometh to the tomb early in the morning, while there was still darkness, and she seeth the stone was taken away from the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Upon which she runneth and cometh to Simon Peter and the other disciple, whom Jesus loved, and saith to them, They have taken the master out of the tomb and we do not know where they have laid him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thereupon Peter set out with the other disciple, and they went to the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now they both ran together, but the other disciple out ran Peter and came first to the tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And having stooped down he seeth the linen swathings laid by; but did not go in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then cometh Simon Peter following him, and he went into the tomb and seeth the linen swathings laid by,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the napkin, which was on his head, not laid with the linen swathings, but folded up in a place by itself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the other disciple, who came first to the tomb, went in also and saw and believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For they did not yet know the scripture, that he was to rise from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore these disciples went their way home again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But Mary stood without, before the tomb, weeping. And as she wept, she stooped down to look into the tomb,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and seeth two angels robed in white, sitting one at the head and the other at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and they say to her, Woman why weepest thou? She saith to them, Because they have taken away my lord, and I know not where they have4 laid him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And, having said this, she turneth about and seeth Jesus standing, but did not know that it is Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Woman, why weepest thou? Whom art thou seeking? She, supposing him to be the gardener, saith to him, Sir, if thou hast taken him up; tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Mary! She turning saith to him, Rabboni, that is to say, Teacher.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Jesus saith to her, Cling not to me, for I have not yet ascended to my Father: But go to my brethren and tell them, I am about to ascend to my Father and to your Father, and to my God and your God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Mary Magdalene cometh and telleth the disciples that she hath seen the Lord, and that he spoke these things to her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>In the evening, on that same day, the first day of the week, the doors where the disciples assembled being shut for fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in the midst, and saith to them, Peace be to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And having said this, he shewed them his hands and his side, and the disciples were rejoiced at seeing the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then Jesus said to them again, Peace be to you. As the Father sent me so I send you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And having said this he breathed on them, and saith to them, Receive a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Whose sins soever you forgive, they are forgiven them, and whose sins soever you retain, they are retained.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now Thomas, one of the twelve, he who is called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The other disciples therefore said to him, We have seen the Lord. But he said to them, Unless I see in his hands the print of the nails; and put my finger into the print of the nails; and put this hand of mine into his side, I will not believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And after eight days, his disciples were again within, and Thomas with them. Jesus cometh, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst and said, Peace be to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then he saith to Thomas, Reach hither thy finger and behold my hands! and reach thy hand and put it in to my side; and be not an unbeliever, but a believer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And Thomas answered and said to him, My Lord and my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, Thomas, Because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed? Happy they who have not seen me and yet believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now Jesus performed many other miracles in the presence of his disciples, which are not written in this book.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But these are written that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that believing, you may have life by his name.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this Jesus shewed himself again to his disciples, by the sea of Tiberias, and in this manner he shewed himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Simon Peter, and Thomas called Didymus, and Nathaniel, who was of Cana in Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two other of his disciples, were together.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Simon Peter saith to them, I am going a fishing. They say to him, We will go with thee. They went and presently got aboard the vessel, and that night caught nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when it was morning Jesus stood on the shore, but the disciples did not know that it was Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then Jesus saith to them, Lads, have you any thing to eat? They answered him, No.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then he said to them, Cast the net on the right side of the vessel and you will find. So they cast, and now they were not able to draw it up, by reason of the multitude of fishes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Upon this that disciple whom Jesus loved saith to Peter, It is the Lord. Simon Peter therefore, upon hearing that it is the Lord, girded on his vest, for he was stript, and threw himself into the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But the other disciples came in the boat, (for they were not far from land, only about two hundred cubits) dragging the net with the fishes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As soon then as they came ashore, they see a fire of coals ready and a little fish on it, and a loaf of bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Jesus saith to them, Bring some of the fish you have now caught.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Simon Peter went and drew the net ashore full of large fishes, a hundred and fifty three. And though they were so many, the net was not torn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Jesus saith to them, Come to breakfast. Now none of the disciples ventured to ask him, Who art thou? knowing that it was the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then Jesus cometh and taketh the loaf and giveth to them, and the small fish likewise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>This was now the third time that Jesus appeared to these his disciples, after he was risen from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So when they had breakfasted, Jesus saith to Simon Peter, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me more than these? He saith to him, Yes, Lord, Thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith to him, Feed my lambs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Again he saith to him a second time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? He saith to him, Yes, Lord, thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith to him, Tend my sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He saith to him the third time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? Peter was grieved that he said to him, the third time, Lovest thou me, and he said to him, Lord thou knowest all things. Thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith to him, Feed my sheep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Verily, verily I say to thee, When thou wast young, thou didst gird thyself and walk where thou wouldst; but when thou shalt be old, thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another will gird thee and carry thee whither thou wouldst not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now this he said to him, signifying by what sort of a death he should glorify God. And having said this, Jesus saith to him, Follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now when Peter turned about and saw the disciple whom Jesus loved following, (even him who at the supper reclined on his breast and said, Master, who is he that is about to deliver thee up)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Peter seeing him, saith to Jesus, Lord, and this one, what in respect to him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Jesus saith to him, If I will that he stay till I come, what is that to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Follow thou me. This saying therefore went abroad among the brethren, that this disciple should not die. But Jesus did not say to him, he should not die; but, If I will that he stay till I come, what is that to thee?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>This is the disciple who testifieth concerning these things and hath written these things. And we know that his testimony is true.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>There are indeed many other things which Jesus did. With respect to them, if they were all committed to writing, one by one, even then I do not think that the world would cordially receive the books written. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>