<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Composed, O Theophilus, the former treatise concerning all that Jesus took occasion both to do and teach</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>till the day when he was taken up, after giving a charge by the Holy Spirit to the apostles whom he had chosen,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and to whom he had, after his suffering, shewn himself to be alive, by many proofs, during forty days appearing to them, and speaking of what concerned the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then assembling them together, he ordered them not to depart from Jerusalem, but to wait for the promise of the Father, which you have heard from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For John indeed baptized in water, but you shall be baptized in a Holy Spirit not many days hence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>When they therefore were come together they asked him, saying, Lord, art thou at this time about to restore the kingdom to Israel?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Whereupon he said to them, It is not for you to know times and seasons which the Father hath reserved in his own disposal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But you shall receive power when the Holy Spirit is come upon you; and you shall be witnesses for me in Jerusalem, and in all Judea, and Samaria, and to the remotest part of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And having said this, while they were beholding him he was taken up, and a cloud received him out of their sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And as they continued looking stedfastly up to heaven, while he was going, behold! two men stood near them, robed in white,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>who addressed them, saying, Men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up to heaven? This same Jesus who is taken up from you into heaven, will come in the same manner as you have seen him going to heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then they returned to Jerusalem from the mount called Olivet, which is near Jerusalem, a sabbath day's journey from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when they came in, they went up into the upper room, where Peter, and James, and John, and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bartholomew and Matthew, James, son of Alpheus, and Simon Zelotes, and Judas the brother of James, usually made their abode.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>These all continued with one mind in prayer and supplication, with the women, particularly Mary the mother of Jesus, and with his brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And in those days Peter rising up in the midst of the disciples, (the number of persons assembled being about one hundred and twenty)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>said, Men, brethren, It was necessary that this scripture should be fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit predicted, by the mouth of David, concerning Judas who was guide to them who laid hold on Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>because he was numbered with us, and had a part of this service allotted him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>(Now this man indeed had purchased! a field with the reward of his iniquity, and, falling on his face, had burst asunder, and all his bowels gushed out;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and this was so generally known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, that the field is called in their language, Akeldama, that is field of blood)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for it is written in the book of Psalms, Let his fold be desolate, and let there be no inhabitant therein. And, His office let another take;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>It is necessary therefore, that one of these men who have accompanied us, during all the time that the Lord Jesus came in and went out over us,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>beginning from the baptism of John to the day on which he was taken up from us, should be a witness with us of his resurrection.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So they set up two, Joseph called Barsabas, who was surnamed Justus, and Matthias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And having prayed, saying, Thou, O Lord, who knowest the hearts of all men, shew which of these two thou hast chosen</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>to take the share of this ministration and apostleship which Judas abandoned to go to his own place,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>they cast lots; and the lot fell on Matthias; and he was numbered with the eleven apostles.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now when the day of pentecost was fully come, they were all with one accord in the same place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And suddenly there came from heaven a sound as of a mighty rushing wind, which filled the whole house where they were sitting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And there appeared to them separate tongues, as of fire, and it settled on each of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And they were all filled with a holy spirit and began to speak in different languages, as the spirit gave them to make solemn addresses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now there were residing at Jerusalem Jews, devout men from every nation under heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So when this report spread, the multitude came together and were confounded. Because every one heard them speaking in his own peculiar dialect;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>therefore they were astonished and expressed their amazement, saying one to another, Behold! are not all these men who speak, Galileans?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>How then do we hear, every one in his own native tongue!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Parthians and Medes and Elamites and the inhabitants of Mesopotamia and Judea, and Capadocia, Pontus and Asia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Phrygia and Pamphilia, Egypt and the parts of Lybia about Gyrene, the Roman strangers also both Jews and Proselytes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Cretans and Arabs, we hear them speaking, in our own tongues, the wonderful dispensations of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So they were all amazed and in suspense, saying to one another, What can be the meaning of this?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But others scoffingly said, They are filled with sweet wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Whereupon Peter, as he was standing with the eleven, raised his voice and thus solemnly addressed them, Men of Judea and all ye inhabitants of Jerusalem, let this be made known to you; and listen attentively to my words:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>for these men are not drunk as you suppose; for it is but the third hour of the day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But this is what was spoken by the prophet Joel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And it shall come to pass in the last days, saith God, that I will pour out a portion of my spirit upon all flesh; and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy; and your young men shall see visions; and your old men shall dream dreams;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and upon my servants, and upon my handmaids, in those days I will pour out a portion of my spirit, and they shall prophesy:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and I will exhibit wonders in the heaven above, and signs on the earth beneath; blood and fire and smoky vapour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the coming of the great and illustrious day of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And it shall come to pass, that whoever will call on the name of the Lord shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Men of Israel hear these words Jesus the Nazarene, a man from God, pointed out to you by miracles and wonders and signs, which God performed by him among you, as you yourselves know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Him, being surrendered up by the determinate counsel and foreknowledge of God, you have taken; and by the hands of wicked men have crucified and slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Him God hath raised up, having loosed the bonds of death, as it was not possible that he could be holden by it:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>for concerning him David saith, I saw the Lord continually before me: because he is at my right hand that I may not be moved;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>therefore my heart was gladdened, and my tongue exulted with joy; and moreover my flesh also will dwell in hope,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>that thou wilt not leave my soul in the mansion of the dead, nor suffer thy Holy One to see corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Thou hast made known to me the ways of life. Thou with thy presence wilt fill me with joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Men, brethren, permit me to speak freely to you concerning the patriarch David, that he is both dead and buried; and his sepulchre is among us to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Being therefore a prophet, and knowing that God had sworn to him with an oath, that from the fruit of his loins he would, as far as regardeth the flesh, raise up the Christ to sit on his throne,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>he spoke prophetically of the resurrection of the Christ, that his soul was not left in the mansion of the dead, nor did his flesh see corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>This very Jesus God hath raised up, of which we all are witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Being therefore exalted at the right hand of God, and having received the promise of the Holy Spirit from the Father, he hath poured out this which you now see and hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For David did not ascend into the heavens; yet he saith, The Lord said to my lord, Sit at my right hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>until I make thine enemies thy footstool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Therefore let all the house of Israel know assuredly, that God hath made the same Jesus whom ye have crucified, Lord and Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Upon hearing this, they were pierced to the heart and said to Peter and the rest of the apostles, Men, brethren, What shall we do?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Thereupon Peter said to them, Repent and let every one of you be baptized to the remission of sins for the name of Jesus Christ, and you will receive the gift of the Holy Spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>For the promise is to you and to your children, and to all them afar off, whomsoever the Lord our God may invite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And with many other words he obtested and exhorted them, saying, Save yourselves from this depraved generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then they who gladly received his word were baptized, and about three thousand souls were that day added;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>and continued stedfast in the doctrine of the apostles and in the community, and in the breaking of the loaf, and in prayers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>and there was fear on every soul; and many wonders and signs were done by the apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>Now all they who believed were together, and had all things in common;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>and they sold their possessions and goods and distributed them to all, as any had need.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>And continuing daily with one accord in the temple, and breaking bread at home, they partook of food with joy and singleness of heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>praising God and having favour with all the people. And the Lord added daily to the congregation them who were cured.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now at the same time that Peter and John were going up2 to the temple at the hour of prayer, namely, at the ninth hour,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>there was a certain man carried up who had been lame from his birth, whom they laid daily at the gate of the temple, called Beauty-Gate, to ask alms of them who were going into the temple;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>who seeing Peter and John just about to enter the temple, begged to receive an alms.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon Peter and John having fixed their eyes on him, Peter said, Look on us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon which he looked earnestly at them, expecting to receive something from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then Peter said, Silver and gold I have none. But what I have, that I give thee. In the name of Jesus Christ the Nazarene, rise up and walk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Then having taken him by the right hand he raised him up. And instantly his feet and ankle bones were strengthened;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and leaping up, he stood; then walked and entered the temple with them, walking and leaping and praising God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>When all the people saw him walking and praising God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and recollected that he was the man who used to sit begging at the Beauty-gate of the temple, they were filled with wonder and astonishment at what had happened to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And while the lame man who was cured, kept hold of Peter and John, all the people in amaze crowded to them in the portico called Solomon's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now when Peter saw this he thus addressed the people. Men of Israel, why wonder ye at this? Or why do ye fix your eyes on us, as if we by our own power or piety had made this man walk?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The God of Abraham, and Isaak, and Jacob; the God of our fathers hath glorified his servant Jesus whom ye delivered up. Yes, you renounced him in the presence of Pilate, when he had determined to release him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>you indeed renounced the Holy One and the Just, and desired a murderer to be granted to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>You indeed killed him who is the conductor to life, whom God hath raised from the dead, of which we are witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now for the belief in his name, his name hath strengthened this man whom you see and know. Yes, the belief which is by him hath given this man this perfect soundness in the presence of you all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And now brethren, I know that it was through ignorance that both' you and your rulers acted thus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and that what God foretold by the mouth of all his prophets; That The Christ Should Suffer, he hath thus accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Repent therefore and return, that your sins may be blotted out, that seasons of refreshment may come from the presence of the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and that he may send him who hath been before hand proclaimed to you; namely, Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>whom the heaven must receive till the time of the consummation of all which God hath spoken by the mouth of all his holy prophets of old:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>for Moses indeed said to the fathers, The Lord your God will raise up for you from among your brethren a prophet like me. To him you must hearken according to all that he shall speak to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and whoever the person be who will not hearken to that prophet, he shall be cut off front among the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>All the prophets also from Samuel, even as many of the following ones as have spoken, have likewise foretold these days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>You are the children of the prophets and of the covenant which God made with our fathers, saying to Abraham And by thy seed all the families of the earth shall be blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>It is to you first that God, having raised up his son Jesus, hath sent him, blessing you, when you turn every one from his iniquities.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now while they were speaking to the people; the priests, and the captain of the temple, and the Sadducees,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>displeased at their teaching the people and promulgating by Jesus the resurrection from the dead, came on them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and laid hands on them, and put them in prison till the next day. For it was now evening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But many of those who heard the word believed. And the number of the men became about five thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And on the morrow their rulers, and elders, and Scribes at Jerusalem assembled,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>with Annas the chief priest, and Caiaphas, and John, and Alexander, and as many as were of the pontifical family;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and having set them in the midst, they asked by what power, or by what name, have you done this?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then Peter being filled with a holy spirit, said to them, Rulers of the people and elders of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>if we are this day examined for a good deed done to an infirm man, by what means he hath been healed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>be it known to you all, and to all the people of Israel, that by the name of Jesus Christ the Nazarene, whom ye crucified; whom God raised from the dead by him this man standeth before you, perfectly cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This is the stone that was rejected by you the builders, which was for the head of the corner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>This cure indeed is by no other, nor is there any other name under heaven given among men by which we can be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now when they saw the boldness of Peter and John, and found that they were illiterate men, and in private stations of life, they wondered; and recollected their having been with Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And seeing the man who was cured standing with them, they could make no reply.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So, having ordered them to withdraw from the Sanhedrim, they conferred among themselves,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>saying, What can we do with these men? For that a signal miracle hath indeed been done by them, is manifest to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and we cannot deny it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But that it may not spread farther among the people, let us severely threaten them not to speak any more for this name to any man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>So having called them in, they gave them this general charge, not to make solemn addresses, nor teach, for the name of that Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But Peter and John in reply to them, said, Whether it be right in the sight of God to hearken to you rather than to God, judge ye.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For we cannot but speak the things which we have seen and heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So, having further threatened them, they dismissed them, not finding how to punish them, because of the people who all glorified God for that which was done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For the man, upon whom this miracle of healing was performed, was above forty years old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So, being discharged, they went to their brethren and told them all that the chief priests and the elders had said to them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>which when they heard, they with one accord raised their voice to God and said, O Lord, thou art the God, who madest the heaven and the earth and the sea, and all that are therein,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>who by the mouth of thy servant David hast said, Why did nations rage, and tribes meditate vain things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The kings of the earth combined, and the chiefs assembled together against the Lord and against his Anointed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For indeed against thy holy Child Jesus whom thou hast anointed, both Herod and Pontius Pilate, with nations and the tribes of Israel, were gathered together,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>to do what thy hand and thy council had determinately marked out beforehand to be brought to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now with regard to present occurrences, look down, O Lord, on their threatenings, and enable thy servants to speak thy word with all freedom</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>when thou stretchest forth thy hand for healing; and signs and. wonders are done by the name of thy holy child, Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And while they were praying, the place in which they were assembled was shaken. And they were all filled with a Holy Spirit and spoke the word of God with boldness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now the whole body of the believers were of one heart and one soul. And no one said that any of his goods were his own; but all things were common among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And the apostles delivered with great power the testimony of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus. And there was great thankfulness among them all;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>for there was not one indigent person among them: for as many as were proprietors of lands or houses sold them and brought the prices of the things sold,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>which being laid at the apostles feet, distribution was made to every one according as any had need.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>In particular Joses, who by the apostles was surnamed Barnabas, the signification of which is Son of Consolation, a Levite, and by birth a Cyprian,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>having an estate, sold it and brought the money and laid it at the apostles feet.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But there was a certain man named Ananias, who with his wife Sapphira sold an estate</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and kept back a part of the price, his wife also being privy to it. And having brought a certain part he laid it at the feet of the apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Upon which Peter said, Ananias, Why hath Satan filled thy heart that thou shouldst lie to the Holy Spirit, and keep back a part of the price of the land?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>While it remained, did it not remain thine? And when sold it was still at thine own disposal. Why then hast thou determined this thing in thy heart? Thou hast not lied to men, but to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon hearing these words Ananias fell down and expired. And great fear came upon all who heard these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then the young men arose and having swathed him, they carried him out and buried him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And about the space of three hours after, his wife, not knowing what had happened, came in.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And Peter said to her, Tell me; did you sell the land for such a price? And she said, Yes, for so much.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thereupon Peter said to her, How is it that you have agreed to try the spirit of the Lord? Behold the feet of them, who have buried thy husband are at the door, and they will carry thee out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>At that instant she fell at his feet and expired. And the young men coming in found her dead. So they carried her out and buried her by her husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And great fear came upon all the congregation, and upon all that heard these things;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and by the hands of the apostles many signs and wonders were done among the people: Now they were all with one accord in Solomon's porch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and of the rest no one presumed to join himself to them, but the people magnified them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and believers in the Lord, multitudes both of men and women were more and more added</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>so that in every street they brought out the sick and laid them on beds and couches, that the shadow of Peter as he went along might overshadow some of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But when the multitude also of the cities around flocked to Jerusalem, bringing the sick and those who were tormented with unclean spirits, who were all cured;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>the chief priest rising up, and all his party; the sect of the Sadducees, they were filled with zeal,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and laid their hands on the apostles and put them in the common prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But during the night an angel of the Lord opened the doors of the prison; and having brought them out said,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Go, and having taken your station in the temple, speak to the people all the words of this life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Upon hearing this they went into the temple about break of day, and taught. Now when the chief priest was come with his party and had convened the Sanhedrim and all the elders of the children of Israel, they sent to the prison to have them brought up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But when the officers went and did not find them in the prison; they returned and made report,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>saying, We found indeed the prison shut with all safety, and the guards without standing before the door; but on opening we found no one within.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And while the priest and the captain of the temple and the chief priests, upon hearing these words, were doubting how this could be,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>there came one who told them, saying, Behold! the men whom you put in prison, are standing in the temple and teaching the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Then the captain went with the under officers and brought them, but without violence; for they were afraid of being stoned by the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And when they had brought them, and set them before the Sanhedrim, the chief priest asked them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>saying, Did we not strictly charge you not to teach for this name? Yet behold you have filled Jerusalem with this doctrine of yours and wish to bring that man's blood upon us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>In reply to which Peter and the apostles said, We must obey God rather than men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The God of our fathers hath raised up Jesus, whom ye slew, having caused him to be suspended on a cross</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>even him, a chief leader and a Saviour, God hath exalted at his right hand to give repentance to Israel and a remission of sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And we are his witnesses of these things, as is also the Holy Spirit which God hath granted to them who obey him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>At hearing this they were cut to the heart, and consulted to put them to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But there stood up a man in the Sanhedrim; a Pharisee named Gamaliel, a teacher of the law, in great esteem among all the people; and having moved that the apostles withdraw for a little while,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>he said to them, Men of Israel, take heed to yourselves how you proceed in regard to these men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For some time ago Theudas started up, saying that he was an. extraordinary person, to whom a number of men, about four hundred, joined themselves. He was destroyed, and all that put confidence in him were broken up and came to nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>After him started up Judas, the Galilean, in the days of the enrolment, and drew a great many people after him. He also perished, and all that put confidence in him were dispersed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Now therefore on this occasion I say to you, Forbear from meddling with these men, and let them alone: for if this counsel or this work be of men; it will moulder away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>But if it be of God you cannot annul it. Peradventure you may be found even fighting against God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>So to him they agreed: and having called in the apostles and scourged them, they charged them not to speak about the name of Jesus and dismissed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Thereupon they went from the presence of the Sanhedrim, rejoicing that they were counted worthy to suffer shame for his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And every day, both in the temple and at home, they ceased not to teach and publish the glad tidings, That Jesus is the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now in those days, the number of the disciples being multiplied, there was a murmuring of the Hellenists against the Hebrews that their widows were neglected in the daily distribution.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Wherefore the twelve having called together the multitude of the disciples said, It is not proper that we should leave the word of God to attend tables:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>look out therefore, brethren, from among yourselves seven men of good reputation, full of a holy spirit and wisdom, whom we may appoint to this office.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And as for us, we will continue in the constant exercise of prayer, and in the ministration of the word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And this speech pleased the whole multitude. So they chose Stephen, a man full of faith and a holy spirit, and Philip and Prochorus and Nicanor and Timon and Parmenias and Nicholas a proselyte of Antioch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>whom they set before the apostles, who having prayed, laid their hands on them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So the word of God spread, and the number of disciples was greatly multiplied in Jerusalem, and a great multitude of the priests became obedient to the faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now Stephen being full of faith and power performed miracles and great signs among the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and there arose some of the synagogue of the Libertini, as it was called, and of the Cyrenians and Alexandrians, and of those of Cilicia and Asia, who disputed with Stephen;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but not being able to withstand the wisdom and spirit with which he spoke,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>they suborned men to say, We heard him speak blasphemous words against Moses, and against God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And having stirred up the people and the elders and the Scribes, they came upon him and seized him, and brought him to the Sanhedrim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and set up false witnesses, who said, This man is incessantly speaking blasphemous words against this holy place and the law;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>for we heard him saying that Jesus the Nazarene will destroy this place and change the customs which Moses delivered to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And all who sat in the Sanhedrim, looking stedfastly at him, beheld his countenance, like the countenance of an angel.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then the chief priest said, Are these things so?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Upon which he said, Men, brethren and fathers hearken. The God of the glory appeared to our father Abraham, when he was in Mesopotamia, before he dwelt in Charran,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and said to him, Depart from this country of thine, and from thy kindred, and come to the land which I will shew thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon he went from the land of the Chaldees, and dwelt in Charran; and thence after his father died, God removed him to this land in which you now dwell,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but gave him no inheritance in it; not even a foot of land. He indeed promised that he would give it to him for a possession, even to his seed after him, though he then had no child.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And God spake thus; That his seed should sojourn in a strange land and be enslaved and afflicted: four hundred years:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the nation which they shall serve I will judge, said God, and after that they shall come out and serve me in this place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then he gave him the covenant of circumcision. So Abraham begat Isaak, and circumcised him on the eighth day, and Isaak begat Jacob; and Jacob, the twelve patriarchs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the patriarchs, being moved with envy, sold Joseph into Egypt. But God was with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and delivered him out of all his afflictions, and gave him favour and wisdom in the sight of Pharao king of Egypt, who appointed him ruler over Egypt, and all his household.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And there came a famine over all the land of Egypt and Chanaan. It was indeed a great affliction and our fathers found no sustenance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So when Jacob heard that there was corn in Egypt, he sent our fathers the first time;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and on their second going down Joseph made himself known to his brothers; and Joseph's kindred was made known to Pharao.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then Joseph sent for his father Jacob and all his kindred, amounting to threescore and fifteen souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>So Jacob went down to Egypt and died, he and our fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and were conveyed to Sychem, and deposited in the sepulchre which Abraham bought for a sum of money of the sons of Emmer the Sychemite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And as the time approached for accomplishing the promise which God had made with an oath to Abraham, the people increased and multiplied in Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>until another king arose, who knew not Joseph.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>This king, mischievously politic against our family, ill treated our fathers, causing their children to be ex posed that they might not be preserved alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>At this time Moses was born, who was exceeding beautiful, and was nursed up three months in his father's house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Being then exposed, Pharao's daughter took him up and had him nursed for her own son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians, and became mighty in council and in actions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when he was forty years old it came into his mind to visit his brethren, the children of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And seeing one of them injured, he defended him and avenged the injury by killing the Egyptian.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now he supposed that his brethren would understand that by his hand God was about to give them deliverance. But they understood not,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and on the next day when he shewed himself to them who were quarrelling and persuaded them to peace, saying, Men, you are brethren, Why do ye injure one another?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He who was doing his neighbour the injury thrust him away, saying, Who made thee a chief and a judge over us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Dost thou mean to kill me as thou didst the Egyptian yesterday?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>At this speech Moses fled and became a sojourner in the land of Madiam, where he became the father of two sons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And when forty years were completed, an angel of the Lord appeared to him in the wilderness at mount Sinai, in a flame of fire in a bush,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>which when Moses saw, he was astonished at the vision. And as he was going near to view it, there came a voice of the Lord to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>I am the God of thy fathers; the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaak, and the God of Jacob. Upon which Moses trembled and durst not view it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then the Lord said to him, Loose the sandals from thy feet, for the place where thou standest is holy ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>I have indeed seen the affliction of my people in Egypt, and have heard their groaning and am come down to deliver them. Now therefore come, I will send thee to Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>This Moses whom they rejected, saying, Who made thee a chief and a judge? this very person God sent as a chief and a deliverer by the hand of an angel who appeared to him in the bush</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>This person brought them out by performing wonders and signs in Egypt and at the Red sea, and in the wilderness, forty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>This is the very Moses who said to the children of Israel, The Lord your God will raise up for you, from among your brethren, a prophet like me, to him you are to hearken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>This is the person who was in the congregation in the wilderness, with the angel who spake to him at mount Sinai, and with our fathers; who received living oracles to give to us;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>to whom our fathers would not be obedient, but rejected him, when with their hearts they turned towards Egypt,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>saying to Aaron, Make gods for us to go before us; for as for this Moses who brought us out of the land of Egypt, we do not know what is become of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>So they made a calf in those days and brought a sacrifice for the idol, and rejoiced in the works of their own hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Therefore God turned and gave them up to worship the host of heaven. As it is written in the book of the Prophets, Have you, O house of Israel, offered to me burnt offerings and sacrifices, forty years in the wilderness?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>You have indeed taken up the tabernacle of Moloch and the star of your God Remphan; those types which you have made to worship them; therefore I will transport you beyond Babylon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>The tabernacle of the testimony was among our fathers in the wilderness, as he who spoke to Moses had ordered it to be made according to the pattern which he had seen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>This tabernacle, which our fathers with Joshua received and brought into the territory of the nations which God drove out from before our fathers, continued till the days of David;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>who found favour in the sight of God, and made it his petition to find a habitation for the God of Jacob.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>But it was Solomon who built a house for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>But the Most High dwelleth not in temples made with hands. As the prophet saith,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>The heaven is my throne, and the earth, my footstool. What sort of a house will you build for me? saith the Lord. And of what sort shall be the place of my rest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Did not my hands make all these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>O stiff necked and uncircumcised in heart and ears Ye do always resist the Holy Spirit. As your fathers did, so do ye.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Which of the prophets have not your fathers persecuted? Indeed they have slain them who prophesied concerning the coming of that Righteous one, of whom you have now become the betrayers and murderers:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>you who have received the law through ranks of angels, but have not kept it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>At hearing this they were cut to the heart and gnashed their teeth at him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>But he being full of a holy spirit, having his eyes fixed towards heaven, beheld the glory of God and Jesus standing at the right hand of God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>whereupon he said, Behold! I see the heavens opened and the Son of man standing at the right hand of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>At which they screamed aloud, and stopped their ears and rushed upon him with one accord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>And having driven him out of the city they stoned him. And the witnesses laid their mantles at the feet of a young man named Saul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="59">
      <content>and stoned Stephen, invoking and saying, Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="60">
      <content>Then he kneeled down and cried out with a loud voice, O! Lord, charge not this sin to their account; and having said this he fell asleep.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now Saul continued to express satisfaction at his death: and there was at that time a great persecution against the congregation which was at Jerusalem; and all, except the apostles, were scattered through the regions of Judea and Samaria.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>While devout men were carrying Stephen to the grave and making great lamentation for him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Saul was making havock of the congregation. Entering into houses and dragging out men and women, he committed them to prison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They, however, who were dispersed, went about proclaiming the glad tidings of the word;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and Philip having come to a city of Samaria, proclaimed to them the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the crowds with one accord attended to what were spoken by Philip, when they heard and saw the signal miracles which he performed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For unclean spirits, with which many were possessed, went out of them with loud outcries: and many paralytic and lame persons were cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And there was great joy in that city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now there was a certain man, named Simon, who had heretofore practised magical arts in that city and astonished the nation of Samaria, pretending that he was an extraordinary person,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>to whom all paid regard, from the least to the greatest, saying, This man is the great power of God. 11 To him indeed they paid regard because for a long time he had astonished them with his magical arts</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>But when they believed Philip's proclamation of the glad tidings concerning the kingdom of God and the name of Jesus Christ, they were baptized, both men and women.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And even Simon himself believed, and being baptized, he continued steadily with Philip. And seeing signs and great miracles done, he was astonished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now when the apostles who were at Jerusalem heard that Samaria had received the word of God, they sent to them Peter and John,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>who having gone down, prayed for them that they might receive a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For it had not yet fallen on any of them, and they were only baptized to the name of the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then they laid their hands on them and they received a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When Simon saw that by the laying on of the hands of the apostles the holy spirit was given, he offered them money,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>saying, Give me also this power, that on whomsoever I lay my hands he may receive a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Whereupon Peter said to him, let thy money with thee be for destruction! Because thou hast thought that this free gift of God may be purchased with money,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>thou hast no portion nor share in this matter, for thy heart is not right in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Repent therefore of this wickedness of thine; and beseech God, if indeed this thought of thy heart can be forgiven thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For I perceive that thou art for bitter gall and for a bond of iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>In reply to which Simon said, Pray ye to the Lord for me that none of these things which you have mentioned may come upon me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now when they had testified and spoken the word of the Lord, they set out on their return to Jerusalem, and communicated the glad tidings to many villages of the Samaritans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>In the mean while an angel of the Lord spoke to Philip, saying, Arise and go southward on the road which leadeth down from Jerusalem to Gaza, namely, the desert road.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So he arose and went. And lo! a man of Ethiopia, an eunuch, a grandee of Candace, the queen of the Ethiopians, who was her high treasurer, who had come to Jerusalem to worship,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and was on his return, was sitting in a chariot and reading the prophet Esaias.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And the Spirit said to Philip, Go near and keep close to that chariot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>So Philip ran close up and heard him reading the prophet Esaias. Whereupon he said, Dost thou understand what thou art reading?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>To which he replied, How can I unless some one guide me? Then he invited Philip to come up and take a seat with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now the passage of scripture which he was reading was this, He was led as a sheep to slaughter; and as a lamb before its shearer is dumb, so he openeth not his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>In his humiliation his legal trial is taken away. Who will declare his manner of life? Because his life is taken from the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And the eunuch addressing Philip, said, Of whom, I pray thee, doth the prophet say this? Of himself or of some other person?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Then Philip opened His mouth, and beginning with this scripture, told him the glad tidings of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And as they continued the journey, they came to a certain water. Whereupon the eunuch said, Behold! here is water. What hindereth my being baptized?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Philip said, If thou believest with thy whole heart, it may be done. To which he replied, I believe that Jesus Christ is the son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Then he ordered the chariot to stop. And they both went down into the water, both Philip and the eunuch; and he baptized him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And when they came up out of the water, the spirit of the Lord conveyed Philip away. And the eunuch saw him no more. For he proceeded on in his journey rejoicing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>and Philip was found at Azotus. And passing on he proclaimed the glad tidings in all the cities, till he came to Caesarea.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>As for Saul he was still breathing out threatening and slaughter against the disciples of the Lord. Having gone to the chief priest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he asked letters from him to the synagogues at Damascus, that if he should find any of this way, whether men or women, he might bring them bound to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But when he was on the road and drawing near to Damascus, suddenly a light from heaven shone around him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And having fallen on the ground, he heard a voice saying to him, Saul, Saul, Why persecutes! thou me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And he said, Who art thou, Lord? And the Lord said, I am Jesus, whom thou art persecuting. It is hurting thyself to kick against sharp pointed goads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whereupon he trembling and in amaze, said, Lord, What wouldst thou have me do? And the Lord said to him, Arise and go to the city and it will be told thee what thou must do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now the men who accompanied him were amazed, hearing indeed the sound, but seeing no one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then Saul arose from the earth. But as upon opening his eyes he saw nobody, they led him by the hand and brought him to Damascus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And he was three days without sight, and neither ate nor drank.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now there was in Damascus a certain disciple named Ananias, And to him the Lord said in a vision, Ananias! And he said, Lord, here I am.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then the Lord said to him, Arise and go to the street, which is called Straight street, and inquire at the house of Judas for Saul of Tarsus; for behold he is praying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and hath seen in a vision a man named Ananias, coming in and laying a hand on him that he may recover sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Upon which Ananias answered, Lord, I have heard from many concerning this man, how much evil he hath done to thy saints in Jerusalem;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and he is here with authority from the chief priests to bind all who invoke thy name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the Lord said to him, Go: for this person is a vessel which I have chosen to bear my name before nations and kings and the children of Israel. For</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I will shew him what he must suffer for my name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So Ananias went and entered the house, and having laid his hands on him, said, Brother Saul, The Lord, even Jesus who appeared to thee on the road as thou camest, hath sent me that thou mayst recover sight and be filled with a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Upon this there fell immediately from his eyes something like scales, and instantly he recovered sight. Then he arose and was baptized;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and having taken some food, he was strengthened. And Saul was some days with the brethren in Damascus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and forthwith, in the synagogues proclaimed Jesus that he is the son of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>At which all that heard were surprised, and said, Is not this he who made havoc of them at Jerusalem, who invoked that name, and came hither on purpose to carry such bound to the chief priests?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But Saul was strengthened more and more, and confounded the Jews who dwelt at Damascus, proving that this person is the C H R I S T .</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now when many days were fulfilled, the Jews conspired to kill him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and Saul was apprized of their plot. As they were watching the gates day and night to murder him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>the disciples took him by night and let him down over the wall, lowering him in a basket.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when Saul came to Jerusalem and tried to associate with the disciples, they were all afraid of him, not believing that he was a disciple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>But Barnabas took him and brought him to the apostles, and told them, how he had on the road seen the Lord, who had spoken to him; and how he had spoken boldly in Damascus in the name of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>So he was with them coming in and going out at Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and speaking boldly in the name of the Lord Jesus. He spoke also and disputed with the Hellenists, and they attempted to kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But when the brethren knew this they brought him down to Caesarea, and sent him on to Tarsus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Now then the congregations throughout all Judea and Galilee, and Samaria, were enjoying peace. Being built up and walking in the fear of the Lord, and the consolation of the holy spirit, they were multiplied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And it came to pass that as Peter was passing through all, he came down also to the saints who dwelt at Lydda</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>and found there a man, named Aeneas, who was paralytic, and had been confined to his bed eight years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And Peter said to him, Aeneas, Jesus, The Christ, cureth thee. Arise and make thy bed. And he arose immediately.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And all the inhabitants of Lydda and Sarona saw him, and turned to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Now there was at Joppa a certain disciple named Tabitha (the signification of which in Greek, is Dorcas a Roe.) This woman abounded in good works and in acts of charity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And at this time she fell sick and died. And when they had washed her, they laid her out in an upper room.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And as Lydda was near Joppa, the disciples, hearing that Peter was there, sent two men to him, intreating him to come to them without delay.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Accordingly Peter arose and went with them. And when he came they took him up to the upper room. And all the widows stood by him, weeping and shewing the tunicks and mantles which Dorcas had made while she was with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Then Peter, having put them all out, kneeled down and prayed, and turning to the body, he said, Tabitha, arise. Upon which she opened her eyes, and seeing Peter, sat up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Then Peter giving her his hand, helped her up, and having called the saints and the widows, presented her alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And this was known throughout all Joppa, and many believed in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And after this he continued many days at Joppa with one Simon, a tanner.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now there was at Caesarea a certain man named Cornelius, a centurion of that called the Italian cohort.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He was pious, and feared God with all his household, and did many acts of benevolence to the people, and prayed to God continually.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>About the ninth hour of the day, he saw plainly in a vision, an angel of God coming in to him and saying to him, Cornelius!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Upon which he having fixed his eyes on him, and being terrified, said, Lord! what is it? Then the angel said to him, Thy prayers and thine acts of benevolence have ascended for a memorial before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now therefore send men to Joppa and call for Simon who is surnamed Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He lodgeth with one Simon, a tanner, whose house is by the sea side. He will tell thee what thou must do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So when the angel who spoke to him was gone, Cornelius called two of his household servants and a devout soldier of them who waited on him continually,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and having related to them the whole affair, he sent them to Joppa.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And on the next day while they were on their journey and approaching towards the city, Peter went up on the house top to pray, about the sixth hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now he had become hungry and wished to take some refreshment; and while it was preparing he fell into a trance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and saw the heaven opened, and a kind of vessel coming down to him, like a great sheet tied by the four corners, and let down to the earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>in which were all sorts of four footed beasts of the earth, namely, the wild beasts and the reptiles, and the birds of the air.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And there came a voice to him, Rise Peter; Kill And Eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Whereupon Peter said, By no means, Lord. For I have never eaten any thing common or unclean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And a voice said to him a second time, What God hath cleansed call not thou that common.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And this was done thrice, and then the vessel was again taken up into heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And while Peter was in great doubt, what this vision which he had seen could mean, behold the men who were sent by Cornelius, having inquired out Simon's house, stood at the gate,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and calling, asked, Doth Simon who is surnamed Peter, lodge here?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And while Peter was pondering on the vision, the spirit said to him, Behold there are three men inquiring for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Arise therefore, get thee down and go with them, without any cavilling, for I have sent them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So Peter went down to the men who were sent to him from Cornelius, and said, Behold I am he for whom you are inquiring. What is the cause of your coming?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>They said, Cornelius, a centurion, a righteous man, and one who feareth God, and is approved by the testimony of the whole Jewish nation, hath been divinely warned by a holy angel to send for thee to his house and receive instruction from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Peter therefore, having invited them in, entertained them hospitably, and on the morrow he set out with them. And some of the brethren who were of Joppa accompanied him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And on the day following they arrived at Caesarea, Now Cornelius was waiting for them, having called together his kinsmen and intimate friends.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And as Peter was coming in, Cornelius met him, and prostrating himself at his feet, made obeisance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But Peter raised him up, saying, Rise up: I am but a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Then conversing with him he went in, and finding many assembled</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>he said to them, You know unlawful it is for a man who is a Jew, to associate with or go to one of another nation: but God hath shewn me, that I am not to call any man common or unclean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For this cause, when I was sent for, I came without any hesitation. I ask therefore on what account you have sent for me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Thereupon Cornelius said, Four days ago I was fasting till this hour, and at the ninth hour praying in my house. And lo! a man stood before me in splendid attire,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and said, Cornelius, thy prayer is heard, and thine acts of benevolence are remembered before God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>send therefore to Joppa for Simon who is surnamed Peter. He lodgeth at the house of Simon, a tanner, by the sea side. He will come and speak to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Therefore I sent to thee immediately and thou hast done well in coming. Now therefore we are all here in the presence of God, to hear all that God hath given thee in charge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then Peter opened his mouth and said, Of a truth I perceive that God is not a respecter of persons;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>but in every nation he who feareth him and worketh righteousness is acceptable to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>According to the word which he sent to the children of Israel, when he published the glad tidings of peace by Jesus Christ, He is Lord of all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>You know the affair which is spread through all Judea, taking its rise from Galilee after the baptism which John proclaimed respecting Jesus; him from Nazareth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>how God anointed him with a holy spirit and power. Him who went about doing good, and healing all who were oppressed by the devil; for God was with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and we are witnesses of all that he did both in the country of the Jews, and in Jerusalem; Him, whom they slew, suspending him on a cross</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>even him God raised up the third day, and granted him to become manifest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>not to all the people, but to witnesses who were preappointed by God; to us who have eaten, and drunk with him after he arose from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And he commanded us to proclaim to the people and testify that he is the one determinately pointed out by God to be the judge of the living and the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>To him all the prophets bear witness, that every one who believeth in him, shall receive remission of sins by his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>While Peter was yet speaking these words the holy spirit fell on all them who heard this word.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Whereupon all the circumcised believers who had come with Peter were astonished that the gift of the holy spirit was poured out upon the Gentiles also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>For they heard them speaking in divers languages and magnifying God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>Then Peter addressed them saying, Can any one on any account forbid water, that these should not be baptized who have received the holy spirit in the same manner as even we did?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>So he ordered them to be baptized in the name of the Lord. Then they intreated him to stay some days.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now the apostles and the brethren who were in Judea heard that the Gentiles also had received the word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>So when Peter went up to Jerusalem, they of the circumcision cavilled at him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>saying, Thou hast gone to men who are uncircumcised, and hast eaten with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thereupon Peter stated to them the whole affair in order from the beginning, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I was praying in the city Joppa, and in a trance I saw a vision, a kind of vessel coming down, like a great sheet let down by the four corners, out of heaven, and it came close to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>On which when I fixed mine eyes, I observed and saw the four footed beasts of the earth, namely the wild beasts and the reptiles, and the birds of the air;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and I heard a voice saying to me, Rise, Peter; kill and eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But I said, By no means, Lord; For nothing common or unclean hath ever entered my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thereupon a voice from heaven addressed me a second time, saying, What God hath cleansed, call not thou that common.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now this was done three times, then all were drawn up again into heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And lo! at that instant three men arrived at the house where I was, who were sent to me from Caesarea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the spirit commanded me to go with them without any scruple. Now there went with me these six brethren. And when we came to the house of the man,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>he told us how he had seen in his house, the angel standing and saying to him, Send men to Joppa for Simon, surnamed Peter,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>who will dictate to the matters by which thou and all thy household shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when I had begun to speak, the holy spirit fell upon them as it did upon us at the beginning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then I remembered the word of the Lord how he said, John indeed baptized in water, but ye shall be baptized in a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If then God granted the same free gift to them as to us, who believed in the Lord Jesus Christ, who was I, that I should obstruct God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Having heard this they acquiesced and glorified God, saying, God hath then indeed granted to the Gentiles repentance unto life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now they who had been dispersed by reason of the distress which arose about Stephen, had travelled as far as Phoenicia and Cyprus and Antioch, speaking the word to none but Jews only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But there were some of them, men of Cyprus and Cyrene, who went into Antioch and spoke to the Greeks, proclaiming the glad tidings of the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the hand of the Lord was with them, and a great number believed and turned to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When the report of this reached the ears of the congregation which was at Jerusalem, they sent forth Barnabas to go as far as Antioch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And when he came and saw the grace of God, he was filled with joy and exhorted them all to adhere to the Lord with a firm determination of heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Because he was a good man and full of a holy spirit and faith, therefore a considerable multitude was added to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Upon which Barnabas went to Tarsus to seek. Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And having found him he brought him to Antioch. And for a whole year they assembled with this congregation, and taught a considerable multitude. And the disciples at Antioch first got the name of Christians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And in those days there came down prophets from Jerusalem to Antioch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And one of them named Agabus rising up signified by the spirit that there would very soon be a great famine throughout the whole inhabited land, which accordingly came to pass in the days of Claudius Caesar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Whereupon the disciples determined, every one according to his ability to send relief to the brethren who dwelt in Judea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And. this they did, sending it to the elders by the hands of Barnabas and Saul.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now about that time Herod the king stretched forth his hands to afflict some of the congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and slew with the sword James the brother of John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And as he saw that this pleased the Jews, he proceeded to apprehend Peter also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But as this was during the days of unleavened bread, when he had apprehended him he put him in prison, committing him to the custody of four quaternions of soldiers, intending to bring him out to the people after the passover.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So Peter was kept in prison; and there was earnest prayer to God made for him by the congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And when Herod was about to bring him forth, on that very night, as Peter was sleeping between two soldiers, being bound with two chains; and the guards before the door were keeping watch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>behold an angel of the Lord suddenly appeared, and a light shone in the prison. And touching Peter's side he roused him up, saying, Arise quickly. Upon which his chains dropped from his hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the angel said to him, Gird thyself and put on thy sandals; and when he had done so, then he saith to him, Throw thy mantle around thee and follow me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So going out, he followed him, but did not know that what was done by the angel was real, but thought he saw a vision.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And having passed the first and second guard, they came to the iron gate leading into the city, which opened to them of its own accord. So, going out, they proceeded on through one street, and suddenly the angel left him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then Peter coming to himself, said, Now I know certainly that the Lord hath sent his angel and delivered me out of the hand of Herod, and from all the expectation of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then, upon recollection, he went to the house of Mary the mother of John, surnamed Mark, where many were assembled and praying.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when Peter knocked at the door of the gateway, a servant maid named Rhoda, went to inquire who was there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But knowing Peter's voice, she, for joy, did not open the gate, but ran and told that Peter was at the gate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Upon which they said to her, Thou art mad. But she confidently affirmed that it was certainly so: then they said, It is his angel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>As Peter continued knocking, they opened the gate, and upon seeing him, were extremely surprised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But he having beckoned to them with his hand to be silent, related to them how the Lord had brought him out of prison, and said, Tell this to James and the brethren. Then departing, he went to another place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now as soon as it was day there was no small disturbance among the soldiers, What was become of Peter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And Herod having caused search to be made for him, and not finding him, after examining the guards, he ordered them to be led away to execution. Then departing from Judea, he went down to Caesarea and resided there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now Herod was meditating a war against the Tyrians and Sidonians; but they with one accord waited on him, and having made Blastus the king's chamberlain their friend, they sued for peace, because their country was subsisted by that of the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And on a set day Herod arrayed in robes of state and seated on the throne, made a speech to them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>upon which the people shouted, It is the voice of a god and not of a man!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And instantly an angel of the Lord smote him, because he gave not God the glory. And being gnawed by worms he died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Still the word of God increased and was multiplied;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and Barnabas and Saul, having fully performed their service, had returned from Jerusalem, taking with them John who was surnamed Mark.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now there was in the congregation at Antioch, certain prophets and teachers, namely, Barnabas and Symeon called Niger, and Lucius the Cyrenian, and Manaem, who had been brought up with Herod the tetrarch, and Saul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And whilst they were ministering to the Lord, and fasting, the holy spirit said, Set apart for me Barnabas and Saul, for the work to which I have called them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>So having fasted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they dismissed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They then being sent forth by the holy spirit, went down to Seleucia, and thence sailed to Cyprus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And arriving at Salamis, they proclaimed the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews. And they had John for their attendant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And having traversed the island till they came to Paphos, they found there a magian, a false prophet, a Jew whose name was Barjesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He was with the proconsul Sergius Paulus, a man of understanding, who had sent for Barnabas and Saul, and desired to hear the word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But Elymas the Magian, (for thus his name is translated) set himself against them, endeavouring to divert the proconsul from the belief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Upon which Saul, who is also called Paul, being filled with a holy spirit, and having his eyes fixed upon him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>said, O! full of all deceit and of all wickedness, son of the devil, enemy of all righteousness; wilt thou not cease to pervert the right ways of the Lord!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now therefore behold the hand of the Lord is upon thee, and thou shall be blind and shall not see the sun for a season. And instantly there fell upon him a mist and darkness. And groping about he sought some to lead him by the hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then the proconsul, upon seeing what was done, believed, being struck with awe at the doctrine concerning the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now Paul and his company, having taken their departure from Paphos, came to Perga in Pamphylia; but John having withdrawn from them, returned to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>They, however, went on from Perga and came to Antioch, in Pisidia, and going into the synagogue on the sabbath day, they sat down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And after the reading of the law and the prophets, the rulers of the synagogue sent to them, saying, Men, brethren, if you have any word of consolation to the people, deliver it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Whereupon Paul stood up and beckoning with his hand for attention, said, Men of Israel and ye who fear God, hearken!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The God of the people Israel chose our fathers and exalted the people when they sojourned in the land of Egypt, and with an uplifted arm brought them out of it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and for the space of about forty years bore with their behaviour in the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And having destroyed seven nations in the land of Chanaan, he distributed their land among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And after these things, which took up about four hundred and fifty years, he gave them judges till Samuel the prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But from that time they desired a king, and God gave them Saul, the son of Kis, a man of the tribe of Benjamin, Forty years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Then having removed him, he raised up for them David to be king, to whom he gave this testimony, I have found David the son of Jesse, a man according to my heart, who will execute all my orders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Of his seed God hath, according to promise, raised up for Israel a saviour, namely Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>before whose appearance John proclaimed a baptism of reformation to all the people of Israel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And as John was fulfilling his course, he said, I am not he whom you suppose me to be; but behold he is coming after me, the latchet of whose shoe I am not worthy to untie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Men, brethren, children of the race of Abraham, and those among you, who fear God, to you the word of this salvation is sent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For the inhabitants of Jerusalem and their chiefs, not knowing him, have indeed by condemning him fulfilled the words of the prophets which are read every sabbath day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Though they found no cause of death, they demanded of Pilate that he should be executed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when they had accomplished all that was written concerning him, he was taken down from the cross and laid in a tomb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But God raised him from the dead,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and for many days he appeared to them who came up with him from Galilee to Jerusalem. They are his witnesses to the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And we proclaim to you the glad tidings with respect to the promise made to the fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>That God hath fulfilled it to us their children by raising up Jesus, even as it is written in the second psalm, Thou art my son, this day I have begotten thee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and that he hath raised him from the dead never more to return to corruption, as he said, I will give you the gracious promises to David which are faithful:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>and therefore, in another place, he saith, Thou wilt not suffer thy holy one to see corruption!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For David indeed, having in his generation answered the purpose of God, went to rest and was laid with his fathers, and saw corruption;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>but he whom God raised up did not see corruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Be it known therefore to you, Men, brethren, that by this person remission of sins is proclaimed to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>and that by him every one who believeth is acquitted from all those sins, from which you Could not be acquitted by the law of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Take heed therefore that what is said in the prophets may not come upon you</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>Behold ye despisers, and express your amaze and vanish. For I am working a work in your days, which you will not believe, though one tell you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>And on their going out of the synagogue of the Jews, the Gentiles intreated that these things might be spoken to them, in the interim till the next sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>And when the synagogue broke up, many of the Jews and of the devout proselytes followed Paul and Barnabas, who spoke to them and exhorted them to persevere in the grace of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>And on the next sabbath almost the whole city was assembled to hear the word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>But when the Jews saw the crowds they were filled with zeal and contradicted what was spoken by Paul; contradicting and reviling.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>Whereupon Paul and Barnabas with great freedom of speech said, It was necessary that the word of God should be first spoken to you. But since you reject it, and judge yourselves unworthy of this everlasting life, behold we turn to the Gentiles</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>for thus the Lord hath commanded us, I have set thee for the light of nations, that thou mayst be for salvation to the remotest parts of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>Upon hearing this, the Gentiles rejoiced and glorified the word of the Lord; and as many as were fitly disposed for everlasting life, believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>And the word of the Lord spread through that whole region.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>But the Jews stirred up the devout women, even such as were women of rank, and the leading men of the city, and raised a persecution against Paul and Barnabas, and expelled them out of their territories.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Upon which they having shaken off the dust of their feet against them, went to Iconium.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>Now the disciples were filled with joy and a holy spirit,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and at Iconium they went in the same manner to the synagogue of the Jews, and spoke so that a great number both of Jews and Greeks believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>But the disbelieving Jews stirred up and disaffected the minds of the Gentiles against the brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They, however, staid there a considerable time, speaking boldly for the Lord who gave attestation to the word of his grace, and granted signs and miracles to be done by their hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So the multitude of the city were divided, some siding with the Jews, and some with the apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But as a violent attempt was going to be made, both by the Gentiles and Jews, with their chiefs, to assault and stone them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>they having intelligence of it, fled to the cities of Lycaonia; to Lystra and Derbe, and the region around;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and proclaimed the glad tidings there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now at Lystra there sat a man who had no use of his feet, being a cripple from his birth, who had never walked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>This man was listening to Paul speaking, who fixing his eyes upon him, and perceiving that he had faith to be healed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>said with a loud voice, Stand upright on thy feet. Upon which he leaped up and walked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When the people saw what Paul had done, they lifted up their voice, and, in the Lycaonian dialect, said, The Gods are come down to us in the likeness of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they called Barnabas, Jupiter: and Paul, Mercury; because he was the chief speaker.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the priests of Jupiter's temple which was before their city, brought bulls with garlands to the gates, and together with the multitude, desired to offer a sacrifice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But the apostles Barnabas and Paul, hearing of this, rent their clothes and ran in among the crowd, crying out</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and saying, Men, why do ye these things? We are only frail mortals like yourselves, proclaiming to you to turn from these vanities to the living God, who made the heaven and the earth, and the sea, and all the things which are therein;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>who in the ages past suffered all the nations to walk in their own ways,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>though at the same time he did not fail to give an evidence of himself, by conferring favours, giving us rain from heaven and fruitful seasons, filling our hearts with food and gladness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And with such speeches as these, they, with difficulty, restrained the people from offering them a sacrifice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But there came thither some Jews from Antioch and Iconium, who, having gained over the populace and stoned Paul, dragged him out of the city, supposing him dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But while the disciples were around him, he arose and went into the city. And on the morrow he departed with Barnabas to Derbe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And when they had proclaimed the glad tidings in that city, and made a considerable number of disciples, they returned to Lystra, and Iconium, and Antioch,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>establishing and confirming the souls of the disciples, and exhorting them to continue in the faith. And because we must enter into the kingdom of God through many afflictions;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>they therefore appointed elders for them in every congregation, and having fasted and prayed, they recommended them to the Lord in whom they believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Then passing through Pisidia, they came to Pamphilia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And having spoken the word in Perga, they went down to Attalia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and thence sailed to Antioch, from which place they had been delivered up to the grace of God, for the work which they had now accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And on their arrival they assembled the congregation and told them all that God had done with them; and that he had opened the door of faith for the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now when they had continued there a considerable time with the disciples,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>there came down from Judea some persons who taught the brethren, Unless you be circumcised after the manner of Moses, you cannot be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Whereupon, as there arose a dissention, and Paul and Barnabas had no small debate with them, they determined that Paul and Barnabas, and some from among themselves, should go up to the apostles and elders at Jerusalem, about this question.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>They therefore, being forwarded on their journey by the congregation, passed through Phoenicia and Samaria; and by declaring fully the conversion of the Gentiles, they gave great joy to all the brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when they arrived at Jerusalem they were well received by the congregation, particularly by the apostles and elders, and they gave an account of all that God had done by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thereupon some of the sect of the Pharisees who believed, rose up and said, that it was necessary to circumcise those, and order them to keep the law of Moses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the apostles and elders were convened to deliberate on this matter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And after much debate, Peter arose, and said to them, Men, brethren, you know that a good while ago, God made choice among us that by my mouth the Gentiles should hear the word of these glad tidings and believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And God who knoweth the heart, bare witness for them, giving them the holy spirit in the same manner as he did to us;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and made no distinction between us and them, purifying their hearts by belief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now therefore why do ye try God, to put upon the neck of the disciples, a yoke which neither our fathers nor we are able to bear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>but we trust that we shall be saved by the favour of the Lord Jesus Christ, in the same manner as they do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Upon this the multitude were silent and heard Barnabas and Paul, relating all the signs and wonders which God hath done among the Gentiles by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when they had done speaking, James answered and said, Men, brethren, hearken to me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Simeon hath related how God first looked down on the Gentiles, to take from among them a people for his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And with this the words of the prophets agree, as it is written.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>After this I will return and rebuild the tabernacle of David which hath fallen. I will rebuild those parts of it which have fallen to decay, and those parts of it which have been demolished, and raise it up again,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>that the rest of mankind may seek the Lord; even all the nations who are called by my name, saith the Lord who doth all these things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>To God all his works are known from eternity;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>therefore it is my judgement not to disquiet those of the Gentiles who turn to God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but to enjoin them to abstain from the pollutions of idols, and fornication, and what is strangled, and blood,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>because from generations of old Moses hath in every city them who preach him, being read in the synagogue every sabbath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>It was then determined by the apostles and elders, when they with the whole congregation had chosen chief men from among them, to send with Paul and Barnabas to Antioch, Judas, who is surnamed Barsabas, and Silas, leading men among the brethren,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>by whom they wrote the following letter. The apostles and the elders and the brethren, to the brethren from among the Gentiles in Antioch, and Syria and Cilicia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>greeting. As we have heard that some who went out from among us have troubled you with discourses, unsettling your minds, saying, You must be circumcised and keep the law, though we gave them no such injunction,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>we being all of one mind determined that after making a choice, we would send men to you with our beloved Barnabas and Paul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>men who have hazarded their lives for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>we have therefore sent Judas and Silas, who by word of mouth will tell you the same things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For it hath seemed good to the holy spirit and to us to lay upon you, over and above the things absolutely necessary, no more burden than these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>To abstain from things offered to idols, and blood, and what is strangled, and fornication, from which you will do well to keep yourselves. Farewell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>So they being despatched came to Antioch and assembling the multitude, delivered the letter,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>and when they had read it, they rejoiced for the consolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And as Judas and Silas were themselves also teachers, they with many discourses exhorted the brethren, and established them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And having tarried some time they had leave to depart with peace from the brethren to the apostles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But Silas thought proper to continue there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Paul also, and Barnabas, continued at Antioch, teaching and publishing with many others the glad tidings of the word of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And after some days Paul said to Barnabas, Let us, I pray thee, return and visit our brethren in every city where we have published the word of the Lord, to see how they do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And Barnabas advised to take along with them, John surnamed Mark.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But Paul did not think it proper to take along with them one who had quitted them in Pamphylia, and had not gone with them to the work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>There was therefore a sharp dispute, so that they separated one from the other. And Barnabas took Mark and sailed to Cyprus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>As for Paul, having chosen Silas and being commended by the brethren to the favour of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>he set out and passed through Syria and Cilicia, establishing the congregations</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and then went down to Derbe and Lystra. And behold there was there a certain disciple, named Timothy, whose mother was a believing Jewess, but his father was a Greek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He was well spoken of by the brethren in Lystra and Iconium.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>This man Paul wished to go with him. So he took and circumcised him because of the Jews who were in those places, for they all knew that his father was a Greek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And as they passed through the cities they delivered to their keeping the determinations of the apostles and elders who were at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So the congregations were established in the faith, and grew daily more and more numerous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now when they had passed through Phrygia and Galatia, (having been restrained by the holy spirit from speaking the word in Asia proper)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>coming towards Mysia, they attempted to go to Bithynia, but the spirit did not permit them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So passing by Mysia, they went down to Troas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And a vision appeared to Paul in the night; it was a certain man, a Macedonian, standing and intreating him, and saying, Cross over to Macedonia and help us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore as he saw this vision, we immediately endeavoured to go to Macedonia, concluding from it, that the Lord called us to publish the glad tidings to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So, embarking at Troas, we sailed directly to Samothracia, and the next day to Neapolis,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and thence to Philippi, which is a city of the first district of Macedonia, a Roman colony. And in this city we continued several days,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and on the sabbath day we went out of the city to the river side, where there was an established place of prayer, and sat down and spoke to the women who had assembled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And a certain woman, named Lydia, a dealer in purple, of the city of Thyatira, a worshipper of God, was listening. The Lord had opened her heart to attend to the things which were spoken by Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And when she and her household were baptized, she intreated us saying, If you have judged me to be faithful to the Lord come and lodge at my house. So she prevailed upon us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And it came to pass, as we were going to the oratory, we were met by a certain female slave who had a spirit of Python, and who brought her masters much gain by divining.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This girl, following Paul and us, cried, saying, These men are the servants of the most high God. They are telling us the way of salvation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And this she did for many days. At length Paul, being troubled, turned and said to the spirit, I command thee, in the name of Jesus Christ, to go out of her. And at that instant it went out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When her masters saw that the hope of their gain was gone, they laid hold of Paul and Silas and dragged them to the forum, before the magistrates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And having set them before the generals of the army, they said, These men, being Jews, trouble this city of ours exceedingly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and teach customs which it is not lawful for us, who are Romans to receive or practise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon this the populace rose up together against them; and the generals ordered them to be stript and beaten with rods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And having inflicted on them many stripe's, they committed them to prison, charging the jailor to keep them safely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He having received such a charge, thrust them into the inner prison, and secured their feet in the stocks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And about midnight Paul and Silas, having prayed, sung a hymn to God; and the prisoners heard them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And suddenly there was a great earthquake, so that the foundations of the prison were shaken, and all the doors were instantly opened,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and the fetters of all dropped off. Upon which the jailor awaking, and seeing the doors of the prison open, drew his sword and was just going to kill himself, thinking that the prisoners had escaped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But Paul cried with a loud voice, saying, Do thyself no harm, for we are all here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Thereupon, calling for lights, he ran in, and being in a tremour, prostrated himself before Paul and Silas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and having brought them out, said, O sirs, What must I do to be saved?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And they said, Believe in the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be saved, thou and thy household.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Then they spoke the word of the Lord to him, and to all that were in his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And he taking them that very hour of the night, washed their stripes; and he and all his family were immediately baptized.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Then conducting them up to his house, he spread a table and rejoiced with all his family for having believed in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And in the course of the day the generals sent the lictors, saying, Dismiss those men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>When the jailor made this report to Paul, The generals have sent that you may be discharged; now, therefore, depart and go in peace;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Paul said to them, Having scourged us publicly without a trial, men who are Roman citizens, they have cast us into prison, and now discharge us privately!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>No. Let them come themselves and take us out. When the lictors reported these words to the generals, they were terrified, hearing that they are Romans. So</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>they came and comforted them, and having taken them out, intreated them to leave the city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Now when they came out of prison, they went to Lydia's where seeing the brethren, they comforted them and departed;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>and passing through Amphipolis and Apollonia, they came to Thessalonica, where there was a synagogue of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And according to his custom, Paul went in among them; and for three sabbaths discoursed to them from the scriptures,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>opening and stating that the Christ was to suffer and rise from the dead, and that this Jesus whom I announce to you is The Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And some of them were convinced, and associated with Paul and Silas; and a great multitude of the devout Greeks; and of women of distinction not a few.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But the disbelieving Jews, affecting zeal, and collecting some ill disposed men of the lowest class, raised a mob and set the city in an uproar; and besetting Jason's house sought to bring them out to the people;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but not finding them, they dragged Jason and some brethren before the magistrates of the city, crying out, Those men who have turned the world upside down, are come here also;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and Jason hath harboured them, though they all act contrary to the decrees of Caesar, saying, There is another king, one Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>So they alarmed the multitude and the magistrates, who heard these things;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and these having taken security of Jason and the rest, dismissed them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now the brethren had immediately sent away Paul and Silas by night to Berea, where being arrived, they went into the synagogue of the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now these were of a more generous disposition than those of Thessalonica. They received the word with all readiness, daily examining the scriptures whether these things were so,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and accordingly many of them believed, and of the Grecian women of rank, and of the men not a few.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But when the Jews of Thessalonica knew that the word of God was proclaimed by Paul at Berea, they came thither also and set the populace in a ferment;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>upon which the brethren immediately sent away Paul towards the sea. But Silas and Timothy continued there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now they who attended Paul conducted him to Athens, and having received his orders for Silas and Timothy to come to him with all speed, they departed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And while Paul was waiting for them at Athens, his spirit within him was greatly troubled, when he saw the city overspread with idols.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore he discoursed in the synagogue to the Jews and proselytes, and in the forum daily to them who met him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And while some of the epicurean and stoic philosophers were conferring with him, some said, What would this retailer of scraps say? And others, He appeareth to be a proclaimer of strange deities. Because he proclaimed the glad tidings of Jesus and the resurrection,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>therefore they took hold of him and brought him to the Areopagus, saying, May we know what this new doctrine is which is spoken by thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For thou bringest some strange things to our ears. We wish therefore to know what these things mean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now all the Athenians, and the foreigners who reside among them, spent their leisure time in nothing else but in telling and hearing news.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Paul then being placed in the midst of the Areopagus, said, Men of Athens, I perceive from every thing I see, that you are exceedingly addicted to the worship of demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For as I passed along and beheld the objects and instruments of your devotion, I found an altar with this inscription, To The Unknown God. Him, therefore whom you worship without knowing him, I announce to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He is the God who made the world and all the things which are therein. He is the Lord of heaven and earth. He dwelleth not in temples made with hands;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>nor is he served by the hands of men, as needing any thing. He is the giver of life and breath, and of all things, to all,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and hath made of one blood the whole nation of men to inhabit the whole face of the earth, having marked out times previously arranged in order, and the boundaries of their habitation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for them to seek the Lord if haply they might feel, and find him, though he indeed is not far from any one of us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For in him we live and are moved and exist; as some also of your own poets have said, For we his offspring are.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Being therefore the offspring of God, we ought not to imagine the Deity to be like gold, or silver, or stone, wrought by the art and contrivance of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>God indeed having overlooked the ages of this ignorance; now maketh proclamation to all men every where to reform,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>because he hath appointed a day in which he will judge the world righteously, by a man whom he hath pointed out: of which he hath given assurance to all men, by raising him. from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>When they heard of the resurrection of the dead, some made a jest of it; and some said we will hear thee again on this subject.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>On which Paul went out from among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>But some men of rank adhered to him and believed, among whom was Dionysius, a member of the Areopagus; also a woman of rank, named Damaris, and others with them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this Paul departed from Athens and went to Corinth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>where finding a certain Jew, named Aquilas, a native of Pontus, who had lately come from Italy with his wife Priscilla, because Claudius had commanded all the Jews to depart out of Rome, he went to them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and being of the same trade, lived and wrought with them; for they were tentmakers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And every sabbath day he discoursed in the synagogue, and conciliated the affections both of Jews and Greeks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But when Silas and Timothy were arrived from Macedonia, Paul was enrapt by the spirit, testifying to the Jews that Jesus is The Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And upon their setting themselves against this, and using abusive language, he shook his garments, and said to them, Your blood is on your own head. I am clear. Henceforth I will go to the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So having left them, he went to the house of a certain person named Justus, a worshipper of God, whose house was adjoining to the synagogue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now Crispus, the ruler of the synagogue, with all his household, believed in the Lord: and many of the Corinthians, when they heard, believed and were baptized.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And in a vision by night, the Lord said to Paul, Be not afraid, but speak, and keep not silence;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for I am with thee; and no one shall set upon thee to hurt thee: for I have much people in this city.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So he continued there a year and six months, teaching among them the word of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now when Gallio was proconsul of Achaia, the Jews with one accord rose against Paul and brought him to the tribunal,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>saying, This person persuadeth men to worship God, contrary to the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when Paul was about to open his mouth, Gallio said to the Jews, If it were indeed some act of injustice or malicious villainy, I could with reason, O Jews, bear with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But if it is a question about a word, or names, or your law, you may look to it yourselves; for I will not be a judge of such matters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So he drove them from the tribunal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Then all the Greeks took Sosthenes the ruler of the synagogue, and beat him before the tribunal. But Gallio did not concern himself in the affair.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>After this Paul having continued there a considerable time longer, took leave of the brethren and sailed to Syria, and with him Priscilla and Aquilas, having shaved his head at Cenchrea, for he had a vow:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and touching at Ephesus he left them there. He indeed having gone to the synagogue discoursed to the Jews;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but though they requested him to tarry longer with them he would not consent,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but took his leave of them, saying, I must by all means keep the ensuing festival at Jerusalem. But I will come back to you again, if God permit. So, sailing from Ephesus</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>he arrived at Casarea; and having gone up and saluted the congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>he went down to Antioch where he spent some time, and then departed and passed successively through Galatia and Phrygia, establishing all the disciples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>In the mean while a certain Jew named Apollos, born at Alexandria, an eloquent man, had come to Ephesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>This man being well versed in the scriptures, had been instructed in the way of the Lord, and being fervent in spirit, he spoke and expounded accurately the passages concerning the Lord, being acquainted only with the baptism of John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And when he began to speak boldly in the synagogue, Aquilas and Priscilla, having heard him, took him home and explained to him more accurately the way of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And as he was desirous to go to Achaia, the brethren encouraged him and wrote to the disciples to receive him. And being arrived there he by his gift greatly assisted them who had believed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>for he strenuously confuted the Jews in public, shewing by the scriptures that Jesus is The Christ.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now while Apollos was at Corinth, Paul having passed through the upper provinces came to Ephesus, where finding2 certain disciples</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>he said to them, Did you receive a holy spirit when you believed? Upon which they said to him, We have not so much as heard that a holy spirit is received.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>There upon he said to them, To what then were ye baptized? And they said, To the baptism of John.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Then Paul said, John indeed baptized the baptism of reformation, telling the people that they should believe in one coming after him, namely in Jesus The Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Upon hearing this they were baptized to the name of the Lord Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and Paul having laid his hands on them, the holy spirit came upon them and they spoke with tongues and prophesied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now they were in all about twelve men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now having gone to the synagogue he spoke boldly for three months, reasoning and recommending the things concerning the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But as some were stubborn disbelievers and continued to revile the way before the multitude, he withdrew from them and separated the disciples, discoursing daily in the school of one Tyrannus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And this he continued to do for the space of two years, so that all the inhabitants of Asia, both Jews and Greeks, heard the word of the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And God wrought extraordinary miracles by the hands of Paul,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>so that handkerchiefs and aprons were carried from his body to them who were sick, and the diseases were removed from them, and evil spirits went out of them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Upon this some of the strolling Jewish exorcists attempted to name the name of the Lord Jesus, over them who had these evil spirits, saying, We adjure you by that Jesus whom Paul proclaimeth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now there were seven sons of one Sceva, a Jewish chief priest, who did this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Upon which the evil spirit in reply said, Jesus I know, and I have some knowledge of Paul: but who are ye?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Then the man, in whom was the evil spirit, springing upon them, and getting a mastery over them, prevailed against them so that they fled out of his house naked and wounded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And this was known to all, both Jews and Greeks, who dwelt at Ephesus; and fear fell upon them all. And the name of the Lord Jesus was magnified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And many of them who believed came and confessed, and made a public acknowledgment of their deeds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And several of them having practised magical arts, brought their books and burned them publicly, the value of them by computation amounting to fifty thousand pieces of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>So powerfully did the word of the Lord increase and prevail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now when these things were accomplished, Paul resolved in his mind, after passing through Macedonia and Achaia to go to Jerusalem, saying, after I have been there, I must also see Rome.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So having sent forward two of them who attended him, namely Timothy and Erastus, into Macedonia, he himself tarried some time in Asia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And during that time there was a considerable disturbance about this way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For one Demetrius, a silversmith, a maker of silver shrines of Diana, kept in employ a great number of artists;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and having assembled these and the workmen of like occupation, he said, Men, you know that on this manufacture dependeth our maintenance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And you see and hear that not only in Ephesus, but almost throughout all Asia, this Paul by his persuasion hath perverted a vast multitude, saying that they which are made with hands, are not gods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So that not only this occupation of ours is in danger of being brought into disrepute; but the temple also of the great goddess Diana, of being set at naught; and her majesty destroyed, whom all Asia and the world worshippeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Upon hearing this and being full of rage they shouted, saying, Great is Diana of the Ephesians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And the whole city was filled with confusion. And they rushed with one accord into the theatre, dragging along with them Gaius and Aristarchus, men of Macedonia, Paul's fellow travellers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Upon this Paul had a mind to go to the people, but the disciples did not permit him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And some of the chiefs of Asia also, who were his friends, sent to him and advised him not to venture into the theatre.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now some cried one thing; and some, another. For the congregation was in the utmost confusion, and the greater part did not know for what particular purpose they had convened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But when they had thrust Alexander out of the crowd, the Jews pushing him forward, and Alexander waving his hand wished to make a defence to the people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>they knowing that he was a Jew, there was, for about two hours, one continued shout from all, crying out, Great is Diana of the Ephesians.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>At length the recorder having stilled the crowd, said, Men of Ephesus, who is there who doth not know that the city of the Ephesians is a humble devotee of the great goddess Diana, and of the image which fell from Jupiter?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Since these things are incontestable you ought to be quiet, and to do nothing rashly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>For you have brought hither these men, who have neither violated things sacred, nor reviled your goddess.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>If now Demetrius and his fellow craftsmen have an action against any one, the courts are open and there are proconsuls to judge: let them bring their suits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And if you seek any thing in respect to other matters, let it be discussed in a legal assembly of the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>For we indeed are in danger of being called in question for this day's riot, there being no cause which we can assign for this tumultuous concourse. 41 Having said this, he dismissed the assembly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now this tumult being over, Paul sent for the disciples, and having embraced them, he set out to go to Macedonia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And when he had gone through those parts, and comforted them with many a discourse, he came to Greece,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>where having spent three months, as an ambush was laid for him by the Jews just as he was on the point of embarking for Syria, he thought it advisable to return through Macedonia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And there accompanied him to Asia, Sopater the Berean; and of the Thessalonians, Aristarchus and Secundus; and Gains, of Derbe; and Timothy; and the Asiatics, Tychicus, and Trophimus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>These having gone before, waited for us at Troas;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And we, after the days of unleavened bread, set sail from Philippi, and in five days came to them at Troas, where we staid seven days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And on the first day of the week when the disciples assembled to break bread, Paul, being about to depart on the morrow, discoursed with them, and lengthened out the discourse till midnight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now in the upper room where they were assembled, there were many lamps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And a certain young man named Eutychus, who was sitting in an open window, bending backwards in a deep sleep, was, while Paul was continuing his discourse, bent quite back with the sleep, and fell from the third story, and was taken up dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But Paul going down, threw himself upon him, and taking him in his arms, said, Be not troubled, for his life is in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then going up again, and having broken bread and eaten, he conversed with them a considerable time, even till break of day, and so departed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now when they brought up the lad alive and were not a little comforted,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>we went before to the ship and sailed to Assos where we were to take in Paul. For so he had ordered, intending himself to go by land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when he met us at Assos we took him in and came to Mitylene.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And sailing thence we came the next day over against Chios, and on the day following reached Samos. And after stopping at Trogyllium, we came the next day to Miletus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For Paul had determined to sail by Ephesus, that he might not spend time in Asia, for he was earnestly desirous, if it were possible for him, to be at Jerusalem on the day of Pentecost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>So from Miletus he sent to Ephesus, and called hither the elders of the congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And when they came to him, he said to them, You know how from my first coming into Asia, I have been with you all the time,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>serving the Lord with all humility, and with many tears and trials which befel me by the insidious practices of the Jews;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>how I have never shrunk from those things which are advantageous; from announcing to you and teaching you publicly and privately,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>attesting both to Jews and Greeks the turning of the mind to God, and the belief in our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now behold I am going up to Jerusalem, bound by the spirit, not knowing the things which shall befal me there,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>save only that the Holy spirit testifieth in every city, saying, That bonds and afflictions await me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But I make no account of any of these, nor is this life of mine so much my concern as to finish with joy my course; even the office which I have received from the Lord Jesus, to testify the glad tidings of the favour of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And now behold I know that all you among whom I have gone proclaiming the reign of God, shall no more see my face;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>therefore I testify to you this day that I am clear from the blood of all men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For I have not shrunk from declaring to you the whole counsel of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Take heed therefore to yourselves and to the whole flock among which the holy spirit hath made you overseers to tend the congregation of God which he hath purchased with his own blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For this I know, that after my departure there will enter in among you grievous wolves, not sparing the flock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Yes, even from among yourselves men will start up, speaking perverse things to draw the disciples after them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Watch therefore, remembering that for the space of three years I did not cease, night nor day, with tears to warn every one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And now with regard to these things I recommend you, brethren, to God and to the word of his grace, who is able to build you up and to give you an inheritance among all who are sanctified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>I have coveted no man's silver or gold, or raiment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Even you yourselves know that these very hands have ministered to my wants, and to the supply of them who were with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>On all occasions I have suggested to you that you ought thus to labour, and support the indigent, and to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, that he said, It is a greater happiness to give, than to receive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And when he had thus spoken, he kneeled down with them all and prayed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And there was great weeping among them all; and they fell upon Paul's neck and kissed him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>being more particularly afflicted at his having said, that they should see his face no more.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then they conducted him to the ship; and soon as we were parted from them and clear of the land, keeping a straight course we came to Coos, and the next day to Rhodes, and thence to Patara;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>where finding a vessel bound to Phoenicia, we went aboard and set sail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And coming in sight of Cyprus, and leaving it on the left, we sailed for Syria and arrived at Tyre; for the ship was to land her cargo there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And having by diligent inquiry found out the disciples, we staid there seven days. Some of these told Paul by the spirit not to go up to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But when these days were ended, we set out on our departure, they, with women and children, all attending us out of the city, and kneeling down on the sea shore, we prayed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>then having saluted each other, we embarked, and they returned home.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when we had finished the voyage from Tyre, we landed at Ptolemais, and having saluted the brethren, staid with them one day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And on the morrow we who were Paul's company, departed and came to Caesarea, and going to the house of Philip the evangelist, who was one of the seven, we abode with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now he had four virgin daughters who were prophetesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And after we had been there several days, there came down from Judea a prophet named Agabus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>who coming to us and taking Paul's girdle, bound his own hands and feet and said, Thus saith the holy spirit, So will the Jews at Jerusalem bind the man, whose girdle this is, and deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Upon hearing this both we and they of that place in treated him not to go up to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But Paul answered, Why make ye this ado, weeping and breaking my heart? As for me, I am ready, not only to be bound, but even to die at Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So, as he could not be prevailed on, we acquiesced, saying, The will of the Lord be done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And after those days we got ready and went up to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And some of the disciples came with us from Csesarea and brought us to one Mnason, a Cyprian, an old disciple, with whom we were to lodge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now when we arrived at Jerusalem, the brethren received us with joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And on the day following Paul went with us to James. And when all the elders were come,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>he saluted them and gave them a particular account of all that God had done among the Gentiles by his ministry;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>which when they heard, they glorified the Lord, and said to him, Thou seest, brother, how many myriads there are of believing Jews, and they are all zealous observers of the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now they have been informed concerning thee, that thou teachest all the Jews who are among the Gentiles to abandon Moses, telling them not to circumcise their children, nor walk in the established rites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>What then is to be done? At all events the multitude must needs assemble; for they will hear that thou art come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Do this then which we tell thee: there are four men with us who have a vow upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Take these and purify thyself with them, and be at charges for them that they may shave their heads; and that all may know that there is nothing in those things of which they have been told concerning thee; but that thou thyself walkest regularly, keeping the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now with respect to the Gentiles who have believed, we have sent them our decision; that they are not to observe such things, but only to abstain from what is offered to idols, and from blood, and from what is strangled, and from fornication.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>So Paul took the men, and the next day being purified with them he went into the temple, announcing the full term of the days of the purification, even to the time when the offering for each of them was to be made;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>but as the seven days were to be completed, the Jews from Asia, having seen him in the temple, threw all the multitude into confusion, and laid hands on him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>crying out, Men of Israel help; This is the man who is continually teaching all men every where against the people and the law and this very place; and moreover he hath brought Greeks into the temple and defiled this holy place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>(For they had before seen Trophimus, the Ephesian, in the city with him, and imagined that Paul had brought him into the temple.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Upon this the whole city was moved, and there was a concourse of the people; and laying hold on Paul they dragged him out of the temple, and immediately the gates were shut.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And while they were seeking to kill him, a report came to the commander of the cohort that all Jerusalem Was in commotion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Upon which he instantly took soldiers and centurions and ran in among them. And when they saw the commander and the soldiers, they left off beating Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Then the commander drew near and arrested him, and ordered him to be bound with two chains, and demanded who he was and what he had done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And as some in the crowd cried one thing, and some another, and he could not know the certainty by reason of the tumult, he ordered him to be brought into the castle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And when he was on the stairs it happened that Paul was carried up by the soldiers, on account of the violence of the crowd.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>For the multitude of the people followed, crying, Away with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>So, when Paul was just about to enter the castle, he said to the commander, May I be favoured with a word to thee? Upon which he said, Canst thou speak Greek?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>Art thou not the Egyptian who some time ago raised an insurrection, and led out into the wilderness four thousand of the assassins?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>Thereupon Paul said, I am indeed a Jew of Tarsus, in Cilicia, a citizen of no inconsiderable city, I intreat thee therefore, permit me to speak to the people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>And on his giving permission, Paul standing on the stairs waved his hand to the people; and a great silence taking place, he addressed them in the Hebrew dialect, saying,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>brethren and fathers, hear my defence which I now make to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>(And when they heard that he spoke to them in the Hebrew dialect, they were the more silent, whereupon he said,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I indeed am a Jew, born at Tarsus, in Cilicia, but brought up in this city, instructed accurately at the feet of Gamaliel in the law of our fathers, being a zealous worshipper of God as you all are at this day;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>one who persecuted this sect to death, binding and delivering into custody both men and women,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>as even the chief priest and the whole Sanhedrim can witness for me; from whom when I had received letters to the brethren at Damascus, I went with a design to bring those also who were there, in chains to Jerusalem, that they might be punished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But it came to pass that when I was on the journey and drawing near to Damascus, about mid-day, a great light from heaven suddenly flashed around me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Upon which I fell to the ground, and I heard a voice saving to me, Saul, Saul, Why persecutest thou me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And I answered, Lord, who art thou? And he said to me, I am Jesus the Nazarene, whom thou art persecuting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now they who were with me saw indeed the light and were terrified, but did not hear the voice of him who spake to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then I said, Lord, what am I to do? And the Lord said to me, Arise and go to Damascus, and there thou shall be told of all that is appointed for thee to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But as I could not see, by reason of the glory of that light, being led by them who were with me, I went to Damascus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>where one Ananias, a devout man according to the law, in high repute with all the Jewish inhabitants,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>came to me, and standing near me, said, Brother Saul, look up. And that instant I looked up upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Then he said, The God of our fathers hath prepared thee to know his will and to see the righteous one, and to hear a voice from his mouth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>that thou mayst be a witness for him to all men of what thou hast seen and heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now therefore why delayest thou? Arise, baptize and wash thee from thy sins, calling upon the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And it came to pass when I returned to Jerusalem and was praying in the temple, that I fell into a trance</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and saw him saying to me, Make haste and depart speedily out of Jerusalem; for they will not receive thy testimony concerning me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Whereupon I said, Lord, they know that I am one who imprisoned and scourged in the synagogues them who believed in thee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and when the blood of thy witness Stephen was shed, I was standing by and gladly consenting to the slaughter of him, and watching the clothes of them who were killing him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And he said to me, Depart, for I will send thee to far distant nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Now till that Word they had continued listening to him; then they raised their voice saying, Away with such a one from the earth, for it is not fit that he should live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And as they continued to cry aloud and were casting off their mantles and throwing dust in the air,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>the commander ordered him to be brought into the castle and examined by scourging that he might know for what cause they raised such an outcry against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But while they were straining him with thongs, Paul said to the centurion who stood by, Is it lawful for you to scourge a man who is a Roman, and hath not had a trial.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Upon hearing this the centurion went to the commander and told him, saying, Consider what thou art about to do; for this man is a Roman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thereupon the commander came and said to him, Tell me. Art thou a Roman? And he said, Yes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The commander replied, I bought that right of citizenship with a large sum. And Paul said, I had it by birth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>They therefore who were going to put him to the question, departed from him immediately. And the commander was afraid, knowing that he was a Roman, and that he had been tying him up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And on the next morning, as he was desirous to know certainly what it was of which he was accused by the Jews, he loosed him from the chains and ordered the chief priests and their whole Sanhedrim to meet; and having brought Paul down he set him before them.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Paul having fixed his eyes on the Sanhedrim said, Men, brethren, I have conducted myself with an entire good conscience as a subject of God even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Upon which the chief priest Ananias ordered them who stood by him to smite him on the mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Whereupon Paul said to him, God is about to smite thee, thou whited wall! Dost thou sit to judge according to the law, and in defiance of the law order me to be smitten?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Upon this the bystanders said. Dost thou revile the chief priest of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And Paul said. Brethren, I was not aware that he is chief priest: for it is written, Thou shalt not speak evil of the ruler of thy people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Paul then perceiving that the one part were Sadducees; and the other Pharisees, cried aloud in the Sanhedrim, Men, brethren, I am a Pharisee, a son of a Pharisee. For a hope even of a resurrection of the dead I am now to be judged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And on his saying this there arose a dissention between the Pharisees and the Sadducees, and the multitude was divided.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For the Sadducees say, There is no resurrection nor any angel nor spirit; but the Pharisees acknowledge both.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And there was a great clamour. And the Scribes, siding with the Pharisees, arose and contended, saying, We find nothing amiss in this man. If a spirit or an angel hath spoken to him, let us not fight against God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And as the tumult increased, the commander, apprehensive that Paul might be torn in pieces by them, ordered the army to march down and take him from among them and bring him into the castle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now the night following, the Lord standing by him said, Paul be of good courage; for as thou hast testified concerning me at Jerusalem, so thou must bear witness at Rome also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And in the course of the day some of the Jews, having entered into a conspiracy, bound themselves by the solemn Anathema, saying they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And there were more than forty who took this oath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and who went to the chief priests and elders and said, We have bound ourselves by the solemn Anathema not to taste any thing till we have slain Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now therefore do you with the Sanhedrim make application to the commander that he may bring him down to you to morrow, as being about to examine his affair more minutely. And as for us, before he come near, we are prepared to kill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But Paul's sister's son hearing of the plot, went to the castle and being admitted told Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whereupon Paul called one of the centurions and said, Introduce this young man to the commander, for he hath something to tell him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He therefore took him along and conducting him to the commander said, Paul the prisoner called me to him, and desired me to introduce to thee this young man who hath something to tell thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thereupon the commander took him by the hand, and retiring to a private place asked, What is it that thou hast to tell me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And he said, The Jews have agreed to request thee to bring down Paul to morrow to the Sanhedrim, under a pretence of making some more minute inquiry concerning him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but be not prevailed on by them; for there are more than forty men of them in ambush, who have bound themselves by a solemn anathema not to eat nor drink, till they have killed him, and they are now ready, expecting this promise from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon this the commander dismissed the young man with this charge, Tell no one that thou hast given me this information.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then calling two of the centurions he said, Get ready two hundred soldiers to go to Caesarea, and seventy horsemen, and two hundred spearmen, by the third hour of the night</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and provide beasts that they may mount Paul and conduct him safe to Felix the general.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Then he wrote a letter of which this is a copy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Claudius Lysias to his excellency general Felix, health and happiness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>This man was seized by the Jews and just upon the point of being slain by them, when I came with the army and rescued him. Having learned that he is a Roman</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and being desirous to know the crime of which they accused him, I took him down to their Sanhedrim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and found that he was accused of matters touching questions of their law, but had done nothing that deserved death or imprisonment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But receiving intelligence of a plot against the man, which the Jews were in act to execute, I have sent him to thee and directed his accusers to lay before thee their charges against him. Farewell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The soldiers therefore, pursuant to their orders, took Paul and conducted him that night to Antipatris</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and on the morrow returned to the castle leaving the horse to go on with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>These on their arrival at Caesarea delivered the letter to the general and presented Paul to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And when the general had read the letter, he asked him of what province he was. And being informed that he was of Cilicia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>I will hear thee, said he, when thy accusers are also come. And he ordered him to be kept in Herod's praetorium.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after five days the chief priest, Ananias, came down with the elders and one Tertullus, an orator, and laid before the general an accusation against Paul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And he being called up, Tertullus began the accusation, saying, As we enjoy great peace by thy means, and from thy prudent administration great benefits result to this nation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>we on all occasions and every where acknowledge this, most excellent Felix, with all gratitude.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But that I may not further trouble thee, I beseech thee to hear us in brief with thy usual indulgence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For having found this man to be a pest and a mover of sedition, among all the Jews, through the whole empire, and a ringleader of the sect of the Nazarenes,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and who attempted to profane even the temple, we apprehended him, and would have judged him according to our law;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>but Lysias the commander coming with a strong force, took him out of our hands</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and ordered his accusers to come to thee. By examining the man himself thou canst gain a full knowledge of all these things of which we accuse him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the Jews gave assent, affirming that these things were so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In answer to this, when the general beckoned to him to speak, Paul replied. Knowing that thou hast been for many years a judge to this nation, I enter upon my defence with the more cheerfulness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>as thou canst know that it is not more than twelve days since I went up to worship at Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And they neither found me disputing with any man in the temple; nor raising sedition among the people, either in the synagogues or in the city:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>nor can they prove any of the things which they now lay to my charge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But this I confess to thee, that after the way which they call a sect, I worship the God of our fathers, believing all the institutes of the law and the writings of the prophets;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>having a confidence in God, which they themselves also entertain, that there will be a resurrection of the dead, both of the just and the unjust;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and with this I exercise myself to have a conscience void of offence before God and men continually.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now after many years I went to bring contributions for my nation and religious offerings;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>in which services some Jews from Asia found me purified in the temple, without crowd or tumult.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Those ought to have been present before thee, and to bring their accusation, if they had, any against me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Or let these men themselves say whether, when I stood before the Sanhedrim, they found any crime in me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>unless it be for this single expression which I uttered while standing among them, That for the resurrection of the dead I am this day to be judged by you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When Felix heard these things he put them off, saying, Having gained a more accurate knowledge of the things respecting this way when Lysias the commander comes down, I will inquire fully into your business.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And he gave orders to the centurion that Paul be kept in custody, not closely confined; and that none of his friends be hindered from assisting him or coming to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And after some days Felix came with his wife Drusilla, who was a Jewess, and sent for Paul and heard him concerning the faith in Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And while Paul was discoursing concerning justice and temperance, and the judgment to come, Felix, being terrified, said, Go thy way for the present, and when I find a convenient time I will send for thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>hoping withal that money would be given him by Paul that he might discharge him, and for this cause he sent for him the oftener, and conversed with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>After two years however Felix was succeeded by Portius Festus, and being desirous to ingratiate himself with the Jews, Felix left Paul bound.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore when Festus came to the government and three days after went up from Caesarea to Jerusalem,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>the chief priests and the principal men of the Jews laid before him an information against Paul</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and earnestly intreated him to favour them so far as to send for him to Jerusalem; (they having laid an ambush to kill him on the road.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whereupon Festus replied, that Paul was in custody at Caesarea and that he himself would shortly set out thither.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Therefore, said he, Let the chief men among you go down with me; and if there be any thing criminal in the man, let them accuse him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>So when he had tarried among them more than ten days he went down to Caesarea, and on the morrow taking his seat on the tribunal he ordered Paul to be brought.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when he appeared, the Jews who had come down from Jerusalem stood around and brought many heavy accusations against Paul, which they could not prove.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>To which when Paul replied, Neither against the law of the Jews, nor against the temple, nor against Caesar, have I committed any offence,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Festus willing to gratify the Jews addressed Paul saying, Wilt thou go up to Jerusalem, and be judged there before me concerning these things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Upon which Paul said, I stand at Caesar's judgment seat, where I ought to be judged. To the Jews I have done no wrong, as thou thyself well knowest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If indeed I am guilty, or have committed any capital crime, I do not deprecate death: but if the charges which they bring against me be groundless, no man can give me up to gratify them. I appeal to Caesar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Then Festus, having conferred with his council, replied, Thou hast appealed to Caesar. To Caesar thou shall go.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Some days after, king Agrippa and Bernice came down to Caesarea to pay their respects to Festus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and as they spent many days there Festus stated Paul's case to the king, saying, There is a man who was left a prisoner by Felix,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>concerning whom, when I was at Jerusalem, the chief priests and the elders of the Jews laid an information, soliciting judgment against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>To whom I made answer that it is not customary with the Romans to give up any man to destruction, till he who is accused is confronted with his accusers, and hath an opportunity to make a defence respecting the charge:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore when they came hither, I without any delay ascended the tribunal the next day, and ordered the man to be brought up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Against whom, when the accusers stood up, they advanced no charge of such things as I expected,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but objected against him some disputed points relative to their peculiar mode of worship, and respecting one Jesus who had died, whom Paul affirmed to be alive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And as I was at a loss how to decide in such a case, I asked him, if he would go to Jerusalem and be tried there respecting these matters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But Paul having appealed that his cause should be referred to the cognisance of the Emperor, I ordered him to be kept in custody, till I can send him to Caesar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Upon which Agrippa said to Festus, I could wish myself to hear the man. Tomorrow then, said he, thou shalt hear him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>On the morrow therefore, when Agrippa and Bernice were come with a numerous splendid retinue and had entered the hall of audience, with the commanders of cohorts and the principal men of the city, at the command of Festus, Paul was brought.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And Festus said, King Agrippa, and all you who are here present with us, You see this man, about whom the whole body of the Jews have made application to me, both at Jerusalem and in this place, crying out that he ought not to live any longer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But as for me, finding that he had done nothing which deserved death, and he himself having appealed to the Emperor, I have determined to send him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Now as I have nothing certain to write to my master concerning him; I have therefore brought him out before you and especially before thee, king Agrippa, that after this examination, I may have something to write.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For to me it seemeth absurd to send a prisoner without specifying the charge against him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then Agrippa said to Paul, Thou art permitted to speak for thyself. Upon which Paul stretched forth his hand and made this defence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Touching all the things of which I am accused by the Jews, I think myself happy, O king Agrippa, that I am this day to make my defence before thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>specially skilled as thou art in all the Jewish customs and controversies; therefore I beseech thee to hear me patiently.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>My course of life; that from my youth; that which from the beginning was led among my own nation at Jerusalem, is known to all the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They have a prior knowledge of me from an early period, if they would testify, that according to the strictest sect of our religion I lived a Pharisee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And now I stand arraigned for a hope of the promise which God made to our fathers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and which our twelve tribes, by their continual services night and day, hope to obtain: for which hope, O king Agrippa, I am accused by the Jews.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>It is deemed among you somewhat incredible that God raiseth the dead;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>as for me I indeed myself thought that I ought to do many things in opposition to the name of Jesus the Nazarene.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And this I did at Jerusalem: and many of the saints I shut up in prison, having received this authority from the chief priests. And when they were put to death, I gave assent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And in all the synagogues many a time did I, by torments, urge them to blaspheme. And being transported to madness against them, I pursued them even to foreign cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>With which views when I was going to Damascus, with authority, and a commission which I had from the chief priests,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>in the middle of the day, on the road, I saw, O king, a light from heaven, exceeding the brightness of the sun, flashing around me and them who were accompanying me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And when we had all fallen to the ground, I heard a voice speaking to me and in the Hebrew dialect, saying, Saul, Saul, why persecutes thou me? It is hurting thyself to kick against sharp pointed goads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And I said, Lord, who art thou? And he said, I am Jesus, whom thou art persecuting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But arise, and stand on thy feet; for I have appeared to thee for this purpose, to appoint thee a minister and a witness of the things which thou hast seen, and of the things for which I will appear to thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>delivering thee from the people and the nations to which I now send thee</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>to open their eyes, that they may turn from darkness to light and from the power of satan to God, that they may receive a remission of sins and an inheritance among them who are sanctified by the belief in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>From that time, O king Agrippa, I was not disobedient to the heavenly vision,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but made proclamation first to them at Damascus, then at Jerusalem and throughout all the country of Judea, and to the nations, to reform and turn to God, performing works worthy of the change of mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For these things the Jews seized me in the temple, and attempted to kill me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Having therefore obtained help from God, I have continued to this day, testifying both to small and great, saying nothing but what the prophets have said were to come to pass; particularly Moses,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>that the Christ should suffer, that he the first of a resurrection from the dead is to proclaim light to the people and the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>While Paul was thus making his defence, Festus said with a loud voice, Paul thou art distracted. Those many writings whirl thee to madness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>To which he replied, I am not mad, most noble Festus; but am speaking the words of truth and soberness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For the king is acquainted with these things, to whom therefore I speak with freedom. For I am persuaded that none of these things have escaped his notice. For this hath not been done in a corner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Thou, O king Agrippa, believest the prophets? I know that thou believest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Upon this Agrippa said to Paul, Thou almost persuadest me to become a Christian.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And Paul said, I would to God, that not only thou, but also all who hear me this day, were both almost and altogether such as I am, except these chains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And as he was saying this, the king rose up, and the general and Bernice and they who sat with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And as they were withdrawing, they conferred with each other, saying, This man hath done nothing that deserveth death or chains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And Agrippa said to Festus, This man might have been set at liberty if he had not appealed to Caesar.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>So, as it was determined that we should sail to Italy, they delivered Paul and some other prisoners, to a certain centurion, named Julius, of the Augustan cohort.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And having embarked in a vessel of Adramyttium, we set sail, intending to coast along the shores of Asia, Aristarchus a Macedonian of Thessalonica being with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And on the next day we touched at Sidon, where Julius, who treated Paul with great humanity, suffered him to go to his friends and enjoy the benefit of their care.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Having taken our departure from this place we sailed close under Cyprus, because the winds were contrary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And traversing the sea over against Cilicia and Pamphylia, we came to Myra of Lycia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>where the centurion met with a ship of Alexandria, bound for Italy, and put us on board it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And sailing slowly for several days and having hardly got over against Cnidus, the wind not favouring us, we sailed close under Crete over against Salmone;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and weathering this with much ado came to a place called Fair-haven, near to which is the city Lasea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Much time being spent and the navigation now dangerous (for it was now after the fast,) Paul gave them warning,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>saying to them, Sirs, I perceive that this voyage will be attended with damage and no small risk, not only of the vessel and cargo, but also of our lives.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But the centurion paid greater regard to the pilot and the master of the vessel than to what Paul said.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And as the harbour was not convenient for a winter station, the greater part advised to depart thence and try to reach Phenice; a port in Crete looking south west and north west, to winter there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>So a gentle breeze springing up from the south. they, confident of gaining their point, weighed anchor and sailed close along Crete.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But not long after there arose against it a tempestuous wind, which is called Euroclydon,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and the vessel being hurried away and not able to look up to the wind, we were forced to let her drive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And running close under a little island called Clauda, we had much ado to secure the boat:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Having hoisted this in they used helps, undergirding the ship. And fearing lest they should run on the quicksands, they lowered the sail and so were driven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But as we were exceedingly tossed by the tempest, they on the next day threw overboard some of the cargo.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And on the third day we with our own hands threw overboard the tackling of the ship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now as neither sun nor stars appeared for several days, and the tempest still bore hard upon us, all hopes of escaping were at last taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And there being then a great abstinence from food, Paul standing in the midst of them said, Sirs, you ought to have hearkened to me and not sailed from Crete and incurred this damage and risk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>However, for the present, I exhort you to be of good courage, for there will be no loss of any life among you, but of the ship only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For an angel of God, whose I am, and whom I serve, stood by me last night,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and said, Fear not, Paul. Thou must appear before Caesar; and lo! God hath given thee all them who are sailing with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Therefore take courage, sirs: for I have a confidence in God that the result will be just as it hath been told me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>But we must be shipwrecked on some island.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So when the fourteenth night was come, while we were driving about in the Adriatic sea, about midnight, the sailors suspected that they were approaching some land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And upon sounding they found twenty fathoms. And proceeding a little further they sounded again, and found fifteen fathoms.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So fearing lest they should run ashore among rocks, they dropped four anchors from the stern and wished for day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But the sailors seeking to flee from the ship, and having hoisted out the boat under a pretence of carrying out anchors from the bow,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Paul said to the centurion and the soldiers, Unless those continue in the ship, you cannot be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Upon this the soldiers cut the ropes of the boat and let it go adrift.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And while day was coming on, Paul advised them all to take some refreshment, saying, Longing for this fourteenth day you continue fasting, having taken nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Therefore I intreat you to take refreshment, for this is conducive to your safety: for not a hair shall fall from the head of any of you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And having said this he took bread, and gave thanks to God in the presence of them all, and having broken it began to eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>And they all became cheerful and also took nourishment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>Now we in the ship were in all two hundred and seventy six souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>And when they had satisfied themselves with food, they lightened the vessel, throwing out the corn into the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>And when it was day they did not know the land; but they observed a creek convenient for landing, into which they determined, if possible, to force the ship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>So having got rid of the anchors, leaving them in the sea, and at the same time loosing the bands of the rudder and hoisting the mainsail to the wind, they pressed towards the shore.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>And coming to a place where two currents met, they ran the ship aground. And the prow stuck fast and remained immoveable; but the stern was broken to pieces by the force of the waves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>It was now the counsel of the soldiers to kill the prisoners, lest any should swim away and escape.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>But the centurion desirous to save Paul prevented their design and ordered those who could swim to throw themselves out first and get to land;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>and the rest, some on planks, and some on pieces of the vessel: and so it came to pass that all got safe to land.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And having escaped, they then knew that the island was called Melita.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now the barbarians treated us with uncommon humanity; for having kindled a fire they took us all to it, because of the3 present rain, and because of the cold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And as Paul having gathered a bundle of sticks was laying them on the fire, a viper coming out from the heat, fastened on his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When the barbarians saw the venomous creature hanging to his hand they said to one another, This man is certainly a murderer whom vengeance suffereth not to live, though he hath escaped from the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>He indeed shaked off the venomous creature into the fire, and suffered no harm;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but they expected that he would swell or fall dead suddenly. But when they had waited a considerable time and saw no mishap befal him, they changed their minds and said, He is a god.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now in the neighbourhood of that place lay the estate of the chief man of the island, whose name was Publius, who took us to his house and entertained us kindly three days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And it happened that the father of Publius being seized with a fever and a dysentery, was confined to his bed, to whom Paul went in and having prayed, laid his hands on him, and cured him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>This therefore being done, the rest in the island who had diseases came and were cured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Therefore they honoured us with many honours and at our departure put on board such things as were necessary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now after three months we embarked on board a ship of Alexandria which had for its ensign Castor and Pollux, and which had wintered in that island.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And being conveyed to Syracuse we staid there three days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thence we came round and touched at Regium; and after one day, the south wind springing up, we on the second day arrived at Puteoli,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>where we met with brethren and were intreated to stay with them seven days and then set out for Rome,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>from which place the brethren, having heard of us, came, some to Appii-forum and some to Tres-tabernae to meet us. And when Paul saw them he gave thanks to God and took courage.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when we arrived at Rome the centurion delivered the prisoners to the prefect. But Paul was permitted to be at a private lodging, with the soldier who guarded him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And it came to pass after three days that Paul sent for them who were the chief men of the Jews, and when assembled he said to them, Men, brethren, though I have done nothing against the people, or the customs of our fathers, I was delivered up a prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>These when they examined me, would have set me at liberty, because I had done nothing that deserved death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But the Jews opposing this, I was forced to appeal to Caesar, not that I have any thing to lay to the charge of my nation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For this cause, therefore, I have sent for you that I might see you and speak with you. For on account of the hope of Israel, I am bound with this chain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>To this they replied, We have neither received any letters concerning thee from Judea, nor hath any of the brethren who have arrived, related or spoken any harm of thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But we should be glad to hear what thou thinkest; for with respect to this sect we know that it is every where spoken against.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>So having set him a day, they came to him at his lodging, in greater numbers; to whom he explained the kingdom of God, testifying and endeavouring to reconcile them to the things concerning Jesus, from the law of Moses and the prophets, from morning till evening.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And some indeed were reconciled by what were spoken, and some disbelieved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And being at variance among themselves they broke up, upon Paul's saying one word, that the holy spirit had spoken well to our fathers by the prophet Esaias,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>saying, Go and say to the people, Hearing you shall hear, though you may not understand; and seeing you shall see, though you may not perceive;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for the heart of this people is callous, and their ears are dull of hearing, and they have shut their eyes, that for a while they may not see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their hearts, and turn that I may heal them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Be it known therefore to you, that this salvation of God is sent to the Gentiles, and they will hearken to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And when he had said this the Jews departed, debating warmly among themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And Paul continued two whole years in his own hired house, and received all that came to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>proclaiming the reign of God, and teaching the things concerning the Lord Jesus Christ with all freedom and without restraint.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>