<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, a called apostle, set apart for the gospel of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>which he promised heretofore by his prophets in the Holy Scriptures</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>concerning his son, (him who was of a seed of David with respect to flesh</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>him who was determinately marked out as son of God by a power, according to a spirit of holiness, of rising up from the dead,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>namely Jesus Christ, our Lord, by whom we have received favour and an apostolical mission, that for his name there may be an obedience of faith among all the nations,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>among which you indeed are called ones of Jesus Christ</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>to all who are at Rome, beloved of God, called and consecrated; favour be to you, and peace from God our father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>In the first place, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that your belief is celebrated throughout the whole world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For God, whom I serve with my spirit in the gospel of his son, is my witness how incessantly I make mention of you, intreating always in my prayers</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>that by the will of God I may at length have some how a favourable opportunity to come to you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For I long to see you that I may impart to you some spiritual gift for your establishment,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>that is, to partake of consolation among you by the faith which is mutually in us, both yours and my own.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now, brethren, I would not have you ignorant that I have hitherto been hindered, though I have often heretofore purposed to come to you, that I might have some fruit among you even as among the other nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I am a debtor both to Greeks and barbarians, to both the learned and the unlearned,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>so that as far as it rests with me, I am ready to publish the glad tidings to you also who are at Rome.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For I am not ashamed of the gospel of the Christ; for it is the power of God for salvation to every one who believeth, to the Jew in the first place, and also to the Greek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For by it there is revealed a justification of God's appointment because of belief, that we may believe. As it is written, But the just shall live because of belief:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of the men, who by unrighteousness repress truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because that which is to be known of God is manifest among them, for God hath manifested it to them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for his invisible attributes, both his eternal power and divine majesty, being thought upon, are from the creation of the world clearly discoverable by the things made, so that they are without excuse</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>because when they knew God, they did not glorify him as God, nor give him thanks, but became vain by their ill- grounded reasonings, and their foolish heart was darkened;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>pretending to be wise, they became fools,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and changed the glory of the incorruptible God for an image representing coruptible man, and birds, and four footed beasts, and reptiles;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>therefore God delivered them up, by the desires of their own hearts, to impurity, that by themselves their own bodies might be dishonoured.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>They changed the truth of God for a falsity, and worshipped and served the creature, and not the creator who is blessed forever, Amen:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>therefore God gave them up to infamous passions; for even their women perverted the instinct of nature;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and in like manner the males also leaving the sex, were inflamed with desires towards each other, which they most shamefully indulged, men with men, and received in themselves the retribution which was justly due to their error.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And as they did not search out God to have constantly a due sense of him, God gave them up to an undiscerning mind to do things unseemly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>filled as they were with all manner of injustice, lewdness, maliciousness, covetousness, mischief, being full of envy, murder, contention, fraud, evil habits; being whisperers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>backbiters, haters of God, insulters of men, insolent, boastful, inventors of evils, disobedient to parents,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>without understanding, covenant breakers, void of natural affection, implacable, unmerciful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Some having recognised God's law, That they who do such things deserve death, not only do the same things themselves, but have even a complacency in them who commit them;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>therefore thou art inexcusable, O man, whosoever thou art, who judgest another: for in the act of judging another thou condemnest thyself. For thou the judger dost the same things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now we know that the judgment of God is according to truth against them who commit such things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And dost thou imagine, O man, who judgest them who commit such things and dost the same thyself, that thou shall escape the judgment of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Or dost thou contemn the riches of his gentleness and forbearance and long suffering, not considering that the gentleness of God is leading thee to a reformation?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Indeed according to this obduracy, and impenitent heart of thine thou art treasuring up for thyself wrath against a day of the wrath and of the revelation of the righteous judgment of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>who will render to every one according to his works</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>to them who by perseverance in well-doing, seek for glory and honour, and incorruption he will grant everlasting life;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but for them who are contentious and disobedient to the truth and in subjection to unrighteousness, there will be indignation and wrath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>tribulation and anguish, upon every soul of man who doth evil, of the Jew first, and also of the Greek;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but glory and honour and peace, for every one who doth good; for the Jew first, and also for the Greek.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For with God there is no respect of persons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For as many as have sinned without law, shall without law perish, and as many as have sinned, being under law shall be judged by law, on the day when, according to my gospel, God will judge the secrets of men by Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For it is not the hearers of the law who are righteous in the sight of God, but the doers of the law will be justified;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>for when the Gentiles who have not law do by nature the duties required by the law, these not having law are a law to themselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>By the joint testimony of their conscience, and by their debates one with another, whether accusing or defending, they shew the matter of the law written in their hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>(See verse 12)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Behold thou art called a Jew, and thou restest on the law and gloriest in God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and knowest his will, and triest things which differ, being instructed out of the law,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and hast a confidence that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light to them who are in darkness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>an instructor of the ignorant, a teacher of babes, having the form of the knowledge and of the truth in the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Thou therefore who teachest another, dost thou not teach thyself? Thou who proclaimest not to steal, dost thou steal?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thou who sayest, Commit not adultery', dost thou commit adultery? Thou who abominatest idols, dost thou violate things sacred?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Thou who gloriest in a law, dost thou by the breach of that law dishonour God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For as it is written, On your account the name of God is blasphemed among the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For circumcision is indeed profitable if thou performest the law. But if thou art a transgressor of the law thy circumcision is become uncircumcision.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>If then the uncircumcision keep the moral precepts of the law, shall not such a one's uncircumcision be accounted circumcision?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And may not the uncircumcision which in a state of nature performeth the law, judge thee who being under a written law and circumcision art a transgressor of law?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For he is not a Jew, who is one outwardly; nor is that circumcision, which is barely in the flesh:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>but he, who is a Jew inwardly, whose circumcision is that of the heart; spiritually not literally, whose praise is not from men, but from God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>What then is the superior privilege of the Jew, or what the advantage of circumcision?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Much every way. First indeed that they were intrusted with the oracles of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Well! what if some have been unfaithful? Shall their unfaithfulness make void the faithfulness of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>No, by no means. Yea, let God be true, though every man be a liar, as it is written, So that thou must be justified in thy acts and must overcome when thou art judged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>If then our unrighteousness established the righteousness of God, what shall we say, Is not God unjust who taketh vengeance? I speak as a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>No, by no means. In that case, how shall God judge the world?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For if by my falsehood the truth of God hath abounded to his glory, why am I yet condemned as a sinner?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And will you, (as we are calumniated and as some affirm that we) say, that we should do evil that good may come, you whose condemnation is just?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>What preference then have we? None at all. For we have before charged both Jews and Greeks with being all under sin;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>as it is written, There is none righteous, no, not one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>There is none who hath understanding. There is none who seeketh God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>They are all gone aside; They are all together become vile; There is none who doth good; no, not one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Their throat is an open sepulchre. With their tongues they practised deceit. The poison of asps is under the lips of them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Their feet are swift to shed blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Destruction and misery are in their ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And the way of peace they did not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>There is no fear of God before their eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now we know that what things soever the law saith, it saith to them who are under the law, that every mouth may be stopped, and the whole world stand convicted before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Because no flesh can be justified before him by works of law; for by law there is a knowledge of sin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>now therefore, independency of law, there is made manifest a justification of God's appointment, attested by the law and the prophets</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>even a justification, of God's appointment, by faith in Jesus Christ, for all and upon all who believe; for there is no distinction;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>for all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>They are justified freely by his grace through the redemption which is by Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>whom God heretofore exhibited as a mercy seat by faith in his blood, that, on account of the remission of past sins, during the forbearance of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>it might be an indication of this justification of his, pointing to a display of this justification of his at this time, in order to shew this, That he is just and the justifier of him who is a believer in Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Where then is this boasting? It is excluded. By what law? By that of works? No; but by a law of belief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>We conclude therefore that man is justified by belief independent of works of law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Is God the God of Jews only? Is he not also the God of the Gentiles? Yes, of Gentiles also:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>since it is one and the same God who will justify circumcision because of belief and uncircumcision by the same belief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Do we then by this belief make law void? No, by no means: on the contrary we establish law.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>What then shall we say that our father Abraham obtained in regard to the flesh?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for if Abraham was justified because of works he hath matter of boasting. But he hath not before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For what saith the scripture, And Abraham believed God and it was reckoned to him for righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now to him who worketh the reward is not reckoned a favour, but a debt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But to him who doth not work, but believeth in him who acquitteth the ungodly, his belief is placed to account for righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>As David also saith in respect to the happiness of the man to whose account God placeth righteousness without works,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Happy they whose iniquities are forgiven; And whose sins are covered:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Happy the man to whose account the Lord will not charge sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now with respect to this happiness, doth it come upon the circumcision only, or upon the uncircumcision also? For we say that the believing was reckoned to Abraham for righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>How then was it reckoned to him? When he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not when in circumcision; but when in uncircumcision;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and he received the sign of circumcision as a seal of the righteousness of that belief, which he had in uncircumcision, that he might be a father of all who believe when in a state of uncircumcision, in order that this righteousness may be reckoned to them also</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and a father of circumcision to them who are not only circumcised, but who also walk in the footsteps of that belief of our father Abraham, which he had during uncircumcision.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For the promise that he should be heir of the world was not made to Abraham or his seed, during law, but during the righteousness of belief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For if they who are under law are heirs, the believing is made void, and the promise rendered of no effect.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For the law operateth to produce wrath; for where there is no law, there is no transgression.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore the promise is because of faith, that it may be matter of favour to this extent, that it may be firm to the whole seed; not only to that under the law, but to that of the faith of Abraham,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>who; as it is written, I have made thee a father of many nations, is the father of us all in the sight of him in whom he believed; namely God who reanimateth the dead, and calleth up things not yet in existence as if actually existing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Against hope he believed with a hope that he should become father of many nations according to what was said, So shall thy seed be,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and far from being weak in faith, he did not consider his own body now become dead, he being then in his hundredth year; nor the deadness of Sarah's womb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He disputed not against the promise of God by unbelief; but was strong in faith, giving glory to God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and being fully persuaded that he was able to perform what he had promised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Therefore it was reckoned to him for righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now it was not written merely for his sake, that it was reckoned to him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>but for our sakes also to whom it will now be reckoned, namely to such as believe in him who hath raised from the dead Jesus our Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>who was delivered up for our offences and raised again for our justification.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore being justified because of belief, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>through whom we have, by this belief, obtained access to this favour in which we stand and boast in a hope of the glory of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And not only so, but we boast also in our tribulations, as we know that tribulation operateth to produce patience;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and patience, a proof; and proof, a hope;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and this hope will not shame us, because the love of God is diffused through our hearts by a Holy Spirit, which is given us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For while we were yet without strength, Christ In due time died for the ungodly:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for scarcely will any one die for a just man; though perhaps for the good some one may even flare to die:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but God confirmeth his love for us, because while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Much more therefore shall we, being now acquitted by his blood, be saved by him from the wrath;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For if we, when enemies, were reconciled to God by the death of his son, much more shall we, being reconciled, be saved by his life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And not only so. but we also boast in God. through out Lord Jesus Christ, by whom we have now obtained this reconciliation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>on this account; as sin entered into this world by one man, and death by sin, and so death for which all sinned passed through unto all men:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for there was sin in the world until the law: now sin is not placed to account where there is no law;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over them who had not sinned after the likeness of the transgression of Adam, who is a type of him who was to come:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but the free gift is not as the transgression; for if for the transgression of the one, the many died; much more hath the favour of God, and the free gift by the favour of the other man, Jesus Christ, superabounded to the many:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>nor is this free gift as in the case when one sinned? for the sentence was a condemnation for one offence, but the</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>free gift is an acquittal from many transgressions. For if for the offence of the one, death reigned by that one; much more shall they who receive the superabundance of this favour and of the free gift of this acquittal, reign in life by the other, namely Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore as by one transgression there was a sentence of condemnation for all men; so by one acquittal there is an adjudication of life for all men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For as by the disobedience of the one man, the many were ranked as sinners, so also by the obedience of the other man, the many will be ranked as righteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now the law came in a little way, so that transgression abounded, but where sin abounded, favour superabounded,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>that as sin had reigned by death, so favour might reign by means' of a justification for everlasting life, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin that favour may abound?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>No, by no means. With respect to us who have died to sin, how can we any more live therein?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Do you not know that as many of us as have been baptized to Christ Jesus, have been baptized to his death?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>We have therefore been buried with him by that baptism to his death, that as Christ was raised from the dead by the glory of the Father, so we also may walk in newness of life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For if we are grafts, we are made so by the similitude of his death, but by that of his resurrection we shall actually be so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This we know, that our old man was crucified with him that the body of sin may be stopped from operating, in order that we may no longer be slaves to sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For he who is dead, is delivered from sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now if we have died with Christ, we believe that we shall live with him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>as we know that Christ, being raised from the dead, dieth no more. Death hath no more a mastery over him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For inasmuch as he died for sin, he died once for all; but as he liveth, he liveth for God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>So likewise reckon ye yourselves to be dead to sin, but alive for God in Christ Jesus our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore let not sin reign in your mortal body, so as by the appetites thereof to serve sin;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>nor deliver up your members to sin as instruments of unrighteousness; but deliver yourselves up to God, as brought to life from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness for God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For sin is not to have dominion over you, as you are not under the law, but under favour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>What then: shall we sin because we are not under law, but under favour? No, by no means.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Do you not know that to whatsoever you deliver yourselves up as servants at command, you are the slaves of that which you obey, whether it be of sin for death; or of obedience for righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But thanks be to God, that though you were slaves of sin, yet from the heart you have conformed to the mould of doctrine in which you were cast,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and being freed from sin, have become servants of righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>(I speak in the language of human affairs because of the weakness of your flesh,) for as you yielded up your members to iniquity, as slavish instruments of uncleanness and all manner of iniquity, so now yield up your members as servants to righteousness for sanctification.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For when you were servants of sin; when you were at a loose from righteousness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>what fruit therefore had you then from those things of which you are now ashamed? For the end of them is death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But being now set free from sin and become servants of God, you have your fruit to holiness, and in the end, everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For die wages of sin is death; but the free gift of God is everlasting life by Christ Jesus our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Or do not you, brethren, know (for I now speak to them who know law) that the law hath dominion over man as long as it liveth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For the married woman is by law bound to her husband while he is alive. But if the husband die, a stop is put to the operation of the law of the husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore if she marry another man while her husband is alive, she will get the name of an adulteress; but if her husband die, she is free from the law so as not to be an adulteress by becoming another man's wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>So you also, my brethren, are become dead to the law by means of the body of the Christ, that you may be for another, who is raised from the dead, that we may bring forth fruit to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For when we were in the flesh, the sinful passions, which subsisted under the law, exerted their energy in our members to bring forth fruit to death:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but we are now set free from the law by the death of that by which we were holden, so that we may serve with a new spirit, and not by the old letter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>What shall we say then? Is the law sin? No, by no means. Indeed I should not have known sin, had it not been for the law. For I should not have known covetousness, had not the law said, Thou shall not covet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But sin having got an advantage by the commandment, wrought in me all manner of desire. For without law sin is dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now as for me, I for a while was alive without law, but when the commandment came, sin revived and I died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>So I found the commandment which was for life, to be for death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For sin having got an advantage by the commandment, seduced me, and by it slew me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So that the law is indeed holy, and the commandment is holy, just and good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Hath that then which is good been death to me? No, by no means. But sin, so that it appeared to be sin, continued working death for me by that which is good, so that sin appeared to be sin in the highest degree by the commandment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For we know that the law is spiritual, but as for me, I being carnal, am sold to sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For what I am doing I do not allow; for that which I approve, I do not perform; but what I hate, that I do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now if I do that which I do not approve, I assent to the law that it is good:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and it is now not I myself, who do this, but sin which dwelleth in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, good doth not dwell. For to will is present with me, but the performance of what is good, I do not find.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For the good which I approve, I do not perform; but evil which I disapprove, this I do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now if I do that which I myself disapprove; it is no more I myself who do it; but sin which dwelleth in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I find then this law for me, that when I would do good, evil is close to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For in the inner man I am delighted with the law of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>but I perceive another law in my members warring against the law of my mind and making me a captive to the law of sin which is in my members.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Wretched man that I am! who will deliver me from this deathful body?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>I thank God that through Jesus Christ our Lord, (do I then myself with the mind serve the law of God, but with the flesh the law of sin?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>There is then no condemnation now to them who are in Christ Jesus and who walk not after the flesh, but after the spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For the law of the spirit of the life in Christ Jesus hath freed me from the law of sin and death;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>for as it was out of the power of the law to do this, inasmuch as it was weak through the flesh, God having sent his own son in a likeness of sinful flesh, and to be a sin offering, hath condemned this sin in the flesh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that the morality of the law might be confirmed by us who walk not after flesh, but after spirit:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>for they who are followers of flesh have their minds bent on the things of the flesh; but the followers of spirit, on the things of the spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For the bent of the flesh is death; but the bent of the spirit is life and peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Because the bent of the flesh is enmity to God, (for it is not in subjection to the law of God, nor indeed can be,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>they therefore who are in a carnal state cannot please God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But you are not in a carnal state, but in a spiritual state, if indeed the spirit of God dwelleth in you. But if any one hath not the spirit of Christ, he is none of his.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But if Christ be in you, the body indeed is dead because of sin, but the spirit is alive, because of a justification;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and if the spirit of him who raised up Jesus from the dead dwelleth in you, he who hath raised up the Christ from the dead will quicken even those dead bodies of yours by his spirit which dwelleth in you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore we, brethren, are not debtors to the flesh, that we should live according to the flesh;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for if you live according to the flesh, you are dying; but if you by the spirit mortify the deeds of the body, you shall live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For as many as are led by the spirit of God, are sons of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For you have not received a spirit of bondage again to fear; but you have received a spirit of adoption, by which we cry, Abba, Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>This very spirit beareth joint witness with our spirit that we are children of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and if children, then heirs; heirs indeed of God, and joint heirs with Christ if we suffer with him so that with him we may also be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be set against that glory which is about to be revealed for us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For the earnest expectation of mankind is waiting for the manifestation of the children of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For to vanity this creation was subjected, not as a voluntary agent, but by him who subjected it to a hope</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>that this very creation shall be freed from the slavery of this corruption, that it may enjoy the glorious liberty of the children of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For we know that this whole creation are groaning together, and even till now are all in pain as a woman in travail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Nay, even they who have the first fruits of the spirit, even we ourselves are groaning within ourselves, waiting for an adoption the redemption of this body of ours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For to this hope we have escaped. Now hope which is attained, is not hope; for why should one hope for that which he enjoyeth. 25 But if we hope for what we do not enjoy, we wait for it with patience,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and in such a manner as the spirit joineth in helping our infirmities: for we do not know what we should pray for as we ought, but the spirit itself intercedeth for us with groans which cannot be expressed in words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And he who searcheth the hearts knoweth the bent of the spirit, that it pleadeth for saints according to the will of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And we know that all things are working together for good to them who love God; to them who according to a previous purpose are now actually called.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For those whom he foreknew, even these he marked out beforehand to be of a form the same as that of the image of his son, that he might be a first born among many brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And those whom he marked out beforehand he actually called, and those whom he called, even these he acquitted, and those whom he acquitted even these he glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>What then shall we say to these things? If God is for us, who can be against us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>He who spared not his own son but delivered him up for us all, how will he not also with him freely grant us all things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Who shall lodge an accusation against them whom God hath chosen? God who acquitteth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>who is he who shall condemn? Christ who died? Rather indeed who is raised up, who is actually at the right hand of God, and who maketh intercession for us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Who shall separate us from the love of the Christ? Shall tribulation or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>(As it is written, For thy sake we are killed all the day long, And accounted as sheep for slaughter.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>We indeed in all these things are more than conquerors by means of him who hath loved us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>For I am persuaded that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>nor height, nor depth, nor any other created being shall be able to separate us from the love of God which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I speak the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience, with a holy spirit, bearing joint witness for me</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>that I have great grief and incessant sorrow in my heart</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>(for I even I myself wished the followers of Christ to be devoted to destruction,) for my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>who are Israelites, to whom belonged the adoption and the glory, and the covenants, and the civil government, and the religious service, and the promises;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>whose ancestors were the patriarchs, and from whom, with regard to flesh, the Christ is descended who is over all, God blessed forever. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>It is not however to be supposed that the word of God hath failed. For with regard to all the descendants of Israel, they are not Israel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>nor are they all children, because they are of the race of Abraham; but in Isaak a seed shall be called for thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>That is to say, It is not the children of the flesh who are the children of God; but the children of the promise are reckoned for seed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For this is the word of the promise. About this time twelve month I will come and Sarah shall have a son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And not only so but the same was the case with Rebecca, when she was with child of twins by one man, namely, our father Isaak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the children being not yet born, nor having done any thing good or evil that the purpose might rest on the choice of God, not in consideration of works, but of his call,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>it was said to her, The elder shall serve the younger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>As it is written: Jacob I have loved and Esau I have slighted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>What then shall we say? Is there injustice with God? No by no means.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For to Moses he saith, I will have mercy on whomsoever I please to have mercy'? and I will have compassion on whomsoever I please to compassionate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore it is not of him who willeth, nor of him who runneth, but of God, who sheweth mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For the scripture saith to Pharaoh, I have raised thee up for this purpose that by thee I may display my power; and that my name may be celebrated throughout all the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Well then, he sheweth mercy to whom he pleaseth, and hardeneth whom he pleaseth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>wilt thou then say to me, Why doth he yet find fault, for who hath resisted his will?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But who art thou, O man, who enterest into a dispute with God? Shall the thing formed say to him who formed it, Why hast thou made me thus?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Hath not the potter power over the clay to make, out of the same lump, one vessel for honour, and another for dishonour?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>What if God willing to manifest his wrath and make known his power, did with much long suffering, bear with the vessels of wrath fitted for destruction,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>to the end that he might make known the riches of his glory on the vessels of mercy which he had previously prepared for glory</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>even us whom he hath called not only from among the Jews, but also from among the Gentiles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>As he actually saith by Hosea, I will call them my people who are not my people; and I will call her beloved, who was not beloved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And it shall come to pass that in the place where it was said to them, You are not my people, they shall there be called children of the7 living God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Esaias also crieth concerning Israel, Though the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, this remnant shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>For he is closing an account and making a deduction with saving goodness. Because the Lord will make with the land a reckoning from which a deduction is made,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>therefore as Esaias said. Had not the Lord of hosts left us a seed, we must have been like Sodom and become like Gomorrah.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>What then are we to infer? That the Gentiles who did not pursue righteousness, attained righteousness, but it was a righteousness because of belief;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>but Israel pursuing a law of righteousness did not come up to the law of righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Why?) Because they sought it not from belief; but as if attainable by works of law. For they stumbled at the stumbling stone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>As it is written, Behold I lay in Sion a stone of stumbling and a rock of offence. And whosoever believeth in him shall not be shamed.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Brethren, the earnest desire of my heart and my supplication to God for Israel is, that they may be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For I bear them witness that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For being ignorant of the righteousness of God's appointment, and seeking to establish a righteousness of their own, they did not submit themselves to God's righteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For Christ is the end of the law for righteousness to every one who believeth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For Moses describeth the righteousness which is from the law, thus; The man who doth these things shall live thereby;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but the righteousness because of believing speaketh in this manner: Say not in thy heart, Who will ascend up to heaven (that is to bring Christ down);</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>or who will go down to the abyss (that is to bring up Christ from the dead)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But what doth it say? The matter is near thee, in thy mouth and in thy heart. That is, the matter of this belief, which we proclaim,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>That if thou wilt acknowledge with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and believe with thy heart that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For with the heart man believeth for righteousness, and with the mouth acknowledgment is made for salvation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the scripture saith, Whosoever believeth in him shall not be shamed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For there is no distinction of Jew and Greek; for he is Lord of all, abounding in riches for all who call upon him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For whosoever will call on the name of the Lord shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? And how shall they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? And how shall they hear without a proclaimer?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and how shall they proclaim, unless they be sent? As it is written, How beautiful are the feet of them who proclaim the joyful message of peace? who proclaim the glad tidings of good things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>But all have not duly hearkened to the good news, for Esaias saith, Lord, who hath believed this report of ours.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The believing is indeed because of hearing, and what they heard is by the order of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But I say, Have they not heard? What! Is their sound then gone forth to every land; and their doctrines to the limits of the world?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But I say, Hath not Israel known? First Moses saith, I will provoke you by what is not a nation, By a foolish nation I will vex you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But Esaias is more explicit, and saith, I was found by them who sought me not, I became manifest to them who inquired not for me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>But concerning Israel he saith, I have stretched out my hands all the day long to a disobedient and gainsaying people.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I say then, Hath God utterly rejected his people? No, by no means. For even I myself am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>God hath not utterly rejected his people whom he heretofore acknowledged. Do you not know by Elias what the scripture saith? When he is pleading with God against Israel, saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Lord, they have slain thy prophets and demolished thine altars; and I alone am left, and they seek my life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>What doth the divine oracle say to him? I have reserved for myself seven thousand men who have not bowed a knee to Baal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>In like manner, therefore, at this present time there is a remnant according to a choice of favour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now if it be by favour, it is no more in consideration of works, since in this case the favour be no favour: but if it be in consideration of works it is no more of favour, otherwise the work is no work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>What is the inference? That which Israel sought he did not obtain; but the chosen obtained it and the rest were blinded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>As it is written, God hath given them a spirit of stupefaction, eyes not to see and ears not to hear even to this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And David saith, Let their table be for a snare and for a trap, and for a stumbling block, and for a retribution to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Let their eyes be darkened that they may not see, And bow down their neck continually.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I say then, Did they stumble that they might fall? No, by no means. But on this lapse of theirs the Gentiles have this salvation to provoke them to emulation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now if this lapse of theirs is the riches of the world and the diminution of them is the riches of the Gentiles, how much more will their fulness be!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>(For I tell you, Gentiles, inasmuch as I am the apostle of the Gentiles, I honour my office,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>if I can any how excite to emulation them who are my flesh and save some of them).</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For if the casting of them off is the reconcilement of the world, what must the taking of them back be, but life from the dead?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now if that portion which is set apart from an offering is holy, so will the mass be. And if the root is holy, so are the branches:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And if some of the branches are broken off, and thou being a wild olive art ingrafted among them and become a partaker of the root and fatness of the olive tree,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>boast not against the branches. But if thou boast remember that thou dost not support the root, but the root supporteth thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou wilt say then, The branches were broken off, that I might be ingraffed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Well! They were broken off for their disbelief, and thou standest for thy belief. Be not high minded; but fear;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For if God spared not the natural branches, perhaps he may not spare thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Behold then the kindness and the severity of God: severity against them indeed who have fallen, and kindness to thee if thou continue in that kindness, otherwise thou also wilt be cut off.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And with respect to them, if they continue not in their disbelief, they shall be ingraffed. For God is able to ingraff them again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For if thou hast been cut from a natural wild olive tree, and contrary to nature graffed on a good olive tree; how much more shall they that are natural branches be graffed on their own olive tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For, that you, brethren, may not have too high an opinion of your selves, I would not have you ignorant of this secret, That a partial blindness hath come upon Israel until the fulness of the Gentiles shall have come in,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and then at length all Israel shall be saved. As it is written For the sake of Sion the Deliverer will come And turn away ungodliness from Jacob:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And this shall be my covenant with them When I take away their sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>With respect to these glad tidings, they are enemies on your account; but with respect to the choice, they are beloved on account of the fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>For the favours and choice of God are not reversed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For as you for a while rebelled against God, but have now obtained mercy at their rebellion;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>so they also have now rebelled at the mercy shewn to you, that they also may be objects of mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For God hath shut all up for disobedience that he may have mercy on all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>O the depth of the riches, and of the wisdom, and of the knowledge of God! How unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways not to be traced out!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>For who hath known the mind of the Lord? Or who hath been his counsellor?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Or who hath first given to him, that in return he may receive a recompense?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Because of him, and by him, and for him are all things; to him be the glory forever, Amen;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>therefore I exhort you, brethren, by the mercies of God, to present your bodies a living, holy, acceptable sacrifice to God as your rational, religious service;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and be not conformed to this world; but transformed by the renewal of your mind, that you may know experimentally what the will of God is, which is good and acceptable and perfect.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For by virtue of the favour which is granted to me, I charge every one who is among you not to have an overweening opinion of himself, but to bend his thoughts to the attaining of a sober and modest demeanour, as God hath distributed a portion of faith to every one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For as we have many members in one body, and all the members have not the same office;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>so we being many are one body in Christ, but individually members of one another,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and employed in exercising free gifts, according to the favour conferred on us, different as they are, if prophesy, in conformity to that belief;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>if a ministerial office, in that office; and if one is a teacher, in teaching;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the exhorter in exhortation; let him who giveth do it with sincerity; him who superintendeth, with assiduity; him who sheweth mercy, with cheerfulness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let love be unfeigned: abhor what is evil; adhere closely to what is good;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>in brotherly love be tenderly affectionate one to another: in honour prefer one another;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>in business be not slothful: Be fervent in spirit; constant in serving the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>joyful in hope; patient in tribulation; stedfastly persevering in prayer;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>administering to the wants of the saints; cultivating hospitality:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Bless them who persecute you; bless and curse not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Set your hearts on this with respect to each other; to rejoice with them who rejoice, and to weep with them who weep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Set not your minds on high things, but accommodate yourselves to things which are low. Be not wise in your own conceits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Render to none evil for evil. Be provident in regard to things good in the sight of all men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If possible, that is, as far as in your power, be at peace with all men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Beloved, avenge not yourselves, but give place to the wrath; for it is written, Vengeance is mine; I will requite, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Therefore if thine enemy hunger feed him; if he be thirsty, give him drink; for by doing so thou wilt use the means to melt him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Be not overcome by evil; but overcome evil with good.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Let every soul be subject to the ruling powers; for there is no power but from God. The powers in being are arranged by God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>so that he who setteth himself against the power resisteth the arrangement of God; and they who resist shall receive for themselves condemnation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the rulers are not a terror to good works but to evil. Dost thou then wish not to dread the power? Do that which is good and thou shall have praise from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For it is a minister of God for good to thee. But if thou dost evil, be in dread; for it wieldeth not the sword in vain. For it is a minister of God, an avenger to execute wrath on him who doth evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Therefore it is necessary to submit to government, not only on account of punishment, but also for conscience's sake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Indeed on this account you pay taxes, because there are ministers of God continually employed for this very purpose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Render therefore to all their dues; tribute to whom tribute; custom to whom custom; reverence to whom reverence; honour to whom honour is due.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Owe no one any thing, save this, to love one another: for he who loveth others hath fulfilled the law:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>for this: Thou shalt not commit adultery; Thou shall not murder; Thou shalt not steal; Thou shalt not bear false witness; Thou shall not covet; and whatever other commandment there be, is summed up in this commandment, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>This love worketh no evil to one's neighbour: This love therefore is the fulfilling of the law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Furthermore, as we know the season, that it is now high time for us to rouse from sleep, for our deliverance is nearer now than when we first believed:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The night is far spent; the day is drawing on; let us therefore put off the works of darkness, and put on the armour of light;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and let us walk as in day light, in a becoming manner; not in revels and drunken debauches; not in dalliance and wantonness; not in strife and envy;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>but put on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh to fulfil its desires.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Receive into fellowship him who is weak in the faith, without regard to differences of opinions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>One indeed believeth that he may eat all things; another who is weak eateth vegetables.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Let not him, who eateth despise him who doth not eat. And let not him who doth not eat, judge him who eateth. For God hath taken him into his family,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>who art thou who judgest another's servant. To his own master he standeth or falleth. But he shall stand, for God is able to establish him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>One indeed judgeth one day above another; another esteemeth every day alike. Let every one be fully persuaded in his own mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He who regardeth the day, regardeth it for the Lord; and he who regardeth not the day, refraineth from regarding it, for the Lord. He who eateth, eateth for the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he who eateth not, refraineth from eating, for the Lord, and he giveth God thanks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For none of us liveth to himself, nor doth any die to himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For whether we live, we live to the Lord; and if we die, we die to the Lord; so that whether we live or die, we are the Lord's.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For to this end Christ died and rose and lived again, that he might be Lord both of the dead and the living.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Why then judgest thou thy brother, or why despisest thou thy brother? For we shall all stand before the judgment seat of the Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For it is written, As I live, saith the Lord, to me every knee shall bow, and every tongue shall give praise to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Since every one of us then shall give an account of himself to God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>let us therefore no more judge one another, but rather come to this determination, not to lay a stumbling block in the way of a brother, nor give any occasion of offence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I know and am fully assured by the Lord Jesus; that nothing is of itself unclean. But to him who thinketh any thing unclean, to him it is unclean.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now if on account of thy food thy brother is grieved, thou no longer walkest According to love. Destroy not by thy food him for whom Christ died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let not therefore the good which you enjoy be ill spoken of.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For the reign of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness and peace and joy in a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For he who serveth the Christ in these things is acceptable to God and approved by men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Let us then pursue those things which tend to peace and mutual edification.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Do not for the sake of food destroy the work of God. All things indeed are pure; but they are an evil to a man who eateth for a stumbling block.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>It is good not to eat flesh, nor drink wine, nor any thing by which thy brother falleth, or stumbleth, or is made weak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thou hast a belief; exercise it at home by thyself before God. Happy he who upon a strict examination doth not condemn himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now he who maketh distinctions is condemned if he eateth, because he eateth not with belief; and every thing which is not according to belief is a sin.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>We then who are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Let every one of us please his neighbour as far as is good for edification.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For even the Christ did not consult his own gratification, but as it is written, The reproaches of them who reproached thee fell upon me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For whatever was written heretofore, was written for our instruction, that we by patience and the consolation of the scripture may have hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now may the God of this patience and of this consolation grant you to have your minds mutually bent on this very thing after the example of Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>that you may unanimously, with one voice, glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Therefore receive one another into fellowship, even as the Christ received us into his family, for the glory of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now I say that, for the truth of God, Jesus Christ became the minister of circumcision, to confirm the promises made to the fathers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and that the Gentiles are to glorify God for his mercy. As it is written, For this cause I will praise thee among the nations and sing to thy name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And again it is said, Rejoice, O nations, with his people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And again, Praise the Lord, all ye nations: Praise him, all ye people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>also, And again Esaias saith, There shall be the root of Jesse, even he who riseth up to rule nations; in him nations will put their trust.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now may the God of this trust fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that you may abound in this trust by virtue of a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now as for me, I am persuaded, my brethren, with respect to you, that you yourselves are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge and able to instruct one another;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>nevertheless I have written to you, brethren, with more boldness, partly as your remembrancer, because of the favour which God hath granted me,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>that I should be a ministering servant of Jesus Christ to the Gentiles, and employed in the holy service of dispensing the glad tidings of God, that the offering of the Gentiles may be accepted, being hallowed by a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Therefore I have matter of boasting in Christ Jesus with respect to the things pertaining to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For I will not presume to mention any thing, save what Christ hath wrought by me for the obedience of the Gentiles, both in profession and practice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>by virtue of signs and wonders, by the power of the spirit of God; so that from Jerusalem and the country around even to Illyricum, I have confirmed the glad tidings of the Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>(yet when thus ambitious to publish the glad tidings) not where Christ was named, that I might not build on another's foundation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>but as it is written, They to whom no publication was made concerning him, shall see, and they who have not heard, will attentively consider.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Therefore, though I have been many times hindered from coming to you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>yet having now no further scope in these parts, and having had, for many years, a strong desire to visit you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>I will, when I take a journey to Spain, come to you. For I hope to see you on my way, and to be forwarded thither by you, when I shall have first been in some degree satisfied with your company.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But now I am going to Jerusalem as an almoner to the saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For Macedonia and Achaia have been pleased to make a contribution for the poor saints in Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For they have been pleased! Indeed they are their debtors. For if the Gentiles have partaken of their spiritual things, they ought to minister to them with temporal things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Having therefore performed this business, and secured to them this contribution, I will come to you in my way to Spain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And I know that when I come to you, I shall come with a fulness of the blessing of the glad tidings of the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Now I beseech you, brethren, by our Lord Jesus Christ and by the love of the spirit, to join with me in earnest supplications to God, for me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>that I may be delivered from the unbelievers in Judea; and that this service of mine, which carrieth me to Jerusalem, may be acceptable to the saints,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>that I may come to you with joy, by the will of God, and refresh myself with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I recommend to you Phebe our sister, who is an almoner of the congregation at Cenchrea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>that you may receive her in the Lord in a manner becoming the saints, and afford her such assistance as her business may require: for she indeed hath assisted many, particularly myself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Salute Priscilla and Aquilas my fellow labourers in Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>who for my life exposed their own; to whom not only I, but all the Gentile congregations also, owe thanks.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Salute also the congregation at their house. Salute my beloved Epenetus, who is the first fruits of Achaia for Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Salute Mary, who hath taken a great deal of pains on our account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Salute Andronicus and Junias, my kinsmen and my fellow prisoners. They are in high repute among the apostles, and were in Christ before me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Salute Amplias, who is my beloved in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Salute Urbanus, our fellow labourer in Christ, and Stachys, who is my beloved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Salute Appelles, who is approved in Christ. Salute those who are of the household of Aristobulus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Salute Herodian, my kinsman. Salute those of the household of Narcissus, who are in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Salute Tryphena and Tryphosa, who have laboured in the Lord. Salute the beloved Persis, who hath laboured much in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Salute Rufus, the chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Ermas, Patrobas, Herme, and the brethren with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Salute Philologus, and Julias, and Nereus, and his sister, and Olympus, and all the saints with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Salute one another with a holy kiss. The congregation of Christ salute you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now I exhort you, brethren, to mark them who make the divisions and the stumbling blocks contrary to the doctrine which you have learned; and avoid them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For such men do not serve our Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly. And by their fawning speeches and flattering forms of address, they deceive the hearts of the innocent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For your obedience is come abroad to all; I therefore rejoice on your account, and wish you to be indeed wise for good, and without any mixture of evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the God of peace will soon bruise satan under your feet. The favour of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Timothy, my fellow labourer, and Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater, my kinsmen, salute you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>I, Tertius, the writer of this letter, salute you in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Gaius, who entertaineth me and the whole congregation, saluteth you. Erastus, the chamberlain of the city, saluteth you: so doth Quartus the brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The favour of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now to him who is able to establish you according to my glad tidings and the proclamation of Jesus Christ; according to the disclosure of a secret which was concealed in times of old,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>but which is now laid open, and by prophetic writings made known to all the nations, according to an order of the everlasting God, for the obedience of belief</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>to the only wise God be the glory forever, through Jesus Christ. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>