<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, called to be an apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, and Sosthenes the brother,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to the congregation of God which is at Corinth; to them who are hallowed by Christ Jesus; called to be holy, together with all those in every place who invoke the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, both their Lord and ours:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>favour be to you, and peace from God our father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I thank my God always with respect to you, for the favour of God which is granted you by Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>that in every thing you have been enriched by him with all doctrine and with all knowledge,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>in the same manner as the testimony of Christ was confirmed among you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>so that you are not deficient in any gift during your waiting for the full manifestation of our Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>who will confirm you to the end, exempt from accusation in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>God is faithful by whom you have been called to a fellowship in his son, Jesus Christ our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And I intreat you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you all speak the same thing, and that there be no divisions among you, but that you be perfectly united in the same mind and in the same sentiment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For I am informed respecting you, my brethren, by some of Chloe's family, that there are contentions among you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I mean this, that every one of you saith, I am for Paul; and I am for Apollos; and I for Cephas; and I for Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Is the Christ divided? Was Paul crucified for you? Or were you baptized to the name of Paul?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I thank God that I baptized none of you, except Crispus and Gaius,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>that none might say that I baptized to my own name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I baptized also the household of Stephanas. I do not recollect that I baptized any other.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For Christ did not send me to baptize, but to proclaim the glad tidings, not with wisdom of speech, that the cross of the Christ might not be rendered useless.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For this doctrine (the doctrine of the cross) is foolishness to them who perish; but to us who are saved it is the power of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise and abolish the understanding of the prudent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Where is the wise? Where the scribe? Where the disputer of this age? Hath not God shewn the wisdom of this world to be folly?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For when, amidst the wisdom of God, the world did not, by means of that wisdom, know God; it pleased God by the foolishness of this proclamation to save them who believe;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>so when the Jews demand a sign and the Greeks seek wisdom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>as for us, we proclaim a crucified Christ; to the Jews indeed a stumbling block, and to the Greeks foolishness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>but to them who are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God and the wisdom of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>because this foolish thing of God is wiser than men, and this weak thing of God is stronger than men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For observe, brethren, this call of you, that there are not many wise after the flesh, not many mighty, not many of illustrious birth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>but God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to put to shame the wise; and the weak things of the world God hath made choice of to put to shame the strong</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and the ignoble of this world, and those of no account, God hath chosen; nay, the very nothings, to put a stop to the operation of the things which are,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>that no flesh might boast in his presence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And it is owing to him that you are in Christ Jesus, who hath been made to us wisdom from God, namely, righteousness, and sanctification, and redemption,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>so that as it is written, Let him who boasteth boast in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now as for me, brethren, when I came to you, I did not come with a pomp of language or of wisdom, announcing to you the testimony of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for I determined to know nothing among you but Jesus Christ, even that crucified person; and</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>with regard to myself, I was among you in weakness and in fear, and in great trembling;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and my discourse and my proclamation was not with persuasive words of human wisdom, but with a demonstration of spirit and power,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>that your belief might not be by the wisdom of men, but by the power of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>We, however, speak wisdom among them who are perfect, but a wisdom not of this age, nor of the chiefs of this age to whose operations a stop is put;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>but we speak a mysterious wisdom of God that hidden (wisdom) which God determinately marked out for the benefit of the ages, to our glory</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>which none of the chiefs of this age knew (for had they known it they would not have crucified the Lord of the glory)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>things indeed, which as it is written, Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, nor the heart of man conceived; which God hath prepared for them who love him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and which God hath revealed to us by his spirit. For this spirit searcheth all things, even the depths of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For who of mankind knoweth the things of a man, but only the spirit of the man which is in him? So no one knoweth the things of God, but the spirit of God only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now we have not received the spirit of this world, but the spirit which is from God, that we may know the things which God hath freely granted to us;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>which things we indeed speak, not in set words of human wisdom, but in the dictated words of a holy spirit, explaining spiritual things by spiritual words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Now an animal man receiveth not those dictates of the spirit of God; for they are foolishness to him, and he cannot know them, because they are to be spiritually examined;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but the spiritual man examineth all things, and is himself examined by no man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For who hath known the mind of the Lord? Who can instruct him? As for us we have the mind of Christ.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now with regard to myself, I could not, brethren, speak to you as spiritual, but as carnal men, as babes in Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I fed you with milk, and not with strong food, because you were not arrived at strength; nor are you indeed yet strong, even now.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For you are yet carnal; for while there is among you envy and strife and divisions, are you not carnal and walking in the ways of man?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For when one saith, I am for Paul; and another, I am for Apollos, are you not carnal?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who then is Paul? And who is Apollos? Are they any thing but mere dispensers of another's bounty, by whose means you have believed? Even as the Lord hath given to each,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the increase.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>So that neither the planter nor the waterer is any thing; it is God only who giveth growth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now he who planteth and he who watereth are all one; and each shall receive his peculiar reward according to his peculiar labour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For we are fellow labourers belonging to God; you are God's field; you are his building.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>According to the favour of God granted to me, I, like a skilful architect, have laid a foundation, and another buildeth upon it. But let every one take heed how he buildeth thereon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For no one can lay any other foundation than that which is laid, which is Jesus The Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now if upon this foundation any one buildeth gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, stubble;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>the work of every one will be made manifest; for the day will shew it: Because it is revealed with fire, therefore the fire will prove every one's work of what sort it is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>If any one's work which he hath built upon it, shall stand the test, he will receive a reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If any one's work be consumed he will lose that; but he shall himself be saved but so as through fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Do you not know that you are a temple of God, and that the spirit of God dwelleth in you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If any one corrupt the temple of God, him God will destroy; for the temple of God is holy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Whosoever you are, let no one deceive himself. If am one among you seemeth to be wise in this age, let him become a fool that he may become wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God: for it is written, He entangleth the wise in their craft.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And again, The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wise that they are vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>So let no one boast in men; for all things are yours:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>whether Paul. or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come, all are yours,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and you are Christ's and Christ is God's.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In this manner let a man reckon us, as servants of Christ and stewards of divine mysteries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now that, which is principally required in a steward, is, that he be found faithful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>To me indeed it is a matter of very small concern, to be tried by you or by human process; nay, I will not be my own judge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For though I am not conscious to myself of an' thing amiss, yet even in that case I am not justified; but he who trieth me is the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So pass no judgment prematurely, until the Lord come, who will bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and expose to view the counsels of the hearts, and then the praise for every one will be from God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now, brethren, I have transferred these things by a figure to myself and Apollos, for your sakes, that by us you may learn not to have your minds bent upon any thing above what is written; that you may not any of you be puffed up</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for one teacher against another. For who distinguisheth thee? Or what hast thou, which thou didst not receive? Now if thou hast received, why boastest thou as if thou hadst not received?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>You are now full! you are now rich! you have now reigned without us. I wish indeed that you did reign, that we also might reign with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For it seems as if God had exhibited us, the apostles, last on the stage as devoted to death since we are made a spectacle to the world, both to angels and men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>We are fools on the account of Christ; but you are prudent in Christ: We are weak; but you are strong: you are honourable; but we are despised:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Even at this very moment we are hungry and thirsty and naked and buffeted, and are wandering about and weary,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>working with our own hands. Being reviled we give good words; being persecuted we suffer patiently;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>being defamed we exhort. We are become as it were the expiatory sacrifices of the world; the refuse of all things until now.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I do not write these things to shame you, but am admonishing you as my beloved children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For though you may have ten thousand guides in Christ, yet you have not many fathers; for by means of the glad tidings I am your father in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Therefore I intreat you to be imitators of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For this cause I have sent to you Timothy, who is my beloved son, and faithful in the Lord, who will remind you of my ways; those in Christ, as I am every where teaching in every congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now some are puffed up as if I would not come to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but I will come to you quickly, if it be the Lord's will, and I will know not the word, but the power of them who are puffed up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For the reign of God is not in word but in power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>What do you chuse? that I should come to you with a rod, or with love and a spirit of meekness?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>It is currently reported that there is among you an act of lewdness, and of such a sort as is not named among the nations, so that one hath his father's wife:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And you are puffed up! Why did you not rather mourn, in order that he who hath done such a deed might be removed from among you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For I indeed, absent as I am in the body, but present in the spirit, have already determined as if I were present, with regard to him who hath done this,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, when you and my spirit are assembled with the power of the Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>to deliver such a one over to satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This boasting of yours is unbecoming. Do you not know that a little leaven leaveneth the whole mixture?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Purge out therefore the old leaven that you may be a new mass as you are unleavened. For Christ our Paschal lamb is indeed slain for us,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>so that we should keep the festival, not with old leaven, nor with the leaven of wickedness and malignity; but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I wrote to you in that letter not to associate with fornicators,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>not including in general the fornicators of this world, nor those who are immoderate in their desires, or rapacious, or idolaters; since in that case you must needs have gone out of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But this is what I now write to you, that if any one named a brother, be a fornicator, or one who gratifieth immoderate desires, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, you are not to associate; no, nor eat with such a one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For what have I to do with passing sentence on those who are without? Is not this the case? On those within you are to pass sentence,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and God will pass sentence on those without. Therefore remove the wicked person from among yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Dare any of you having a controversy with another submit it to a trial before the unrighteous, and not before the saints?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Do you not know that the saints are to judge the world? If then the world is to be judged by you, are you unworthy to judge petty causes?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Do you not know that we shall judge angels? Can we not then things which concern this life?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>If you therefore have controversies relating to affairs of this life, do you appoint those to be judges who are held in no esteem by the congregation?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>To your shame I say, is it so that there is not among you a wise man; not so much as one who can determine a cause between brethren;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but brother goeth to law with brother and that before unbelievers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now, then, it is indeed a disparagement to you that you have law suits among yourselves. Why do you not rather suffer wrong? Why do you not rather suffer loss?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Instead of this you yourselves do wrong, and defraud even your brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Do you not know that the unjust shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived; neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor the voluptuous, nor sodomites,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>nor thieves, nor such as indulge inordinate desires, nor drunkards, nor railers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now such some of you were; but, you have washed yourselves; but you are hallowed, but you are acquitted by the name of the Lord Jesus and by the spirit of our God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Are all things lawful for me! All things however are not expedient. Are all things lawful for me! I however will not be a slave to any thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Meats are for the belly, and the belly for meats! But God will put a stop to the operation of both; But as for the body, it is not for fornication, but for the Lord; and the Lord for the body:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And as God hath raised up the Lord, he will by his power raise up you also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Do you not know that your bodies are members 'of Christ? Shall I then take the members of the Christ, and make them members of a harlot? Surely no.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Do you not know that he who is joined to the harlot is one body with her? For the scripture saith, They two shall be one flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now he who is joined to the Lord is one spirit with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Flee fornication. Every other sin, which a man committeth, is without the body; but he who committeth whoredom sinneth against his own body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Do you not know that your body is a temple of a holy spirit in you, which you have from God? Indeed you are not your own;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for you have been bought with a price. Therefore glorify God with your body and with your spirit which are his.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now with respect to those matters about which you wrote to me, it is well for a man not to marry:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>but to avoid fornication let every man have his own wife; and every woman her own husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Let the husband render due benevolence to the wife; and in like manner the wife to the husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The wife hath not the power over her own body; but the husband: And in like manner the husband hath not the power over his own body; but the wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Withdraw not from each other, unless by mutual consent for a time, that you may devote yourselves to fasting and prayer. Then come together again that satan may not tempt you through your incontinence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now this I say by way of counsel, not of command;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for I wish all men to be as I myself am. But every one hath his peculiar gift from God, some of one kind; and some, of another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I say then to unmarried men and to widows, it is well for them if they continue as I do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But if they have not the gift of continency, let them marry; for it is better to marry than to burn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And to them who are married I give this injunction; not I but the Lord: That a wife separate not herself from her husband;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>but if she hath actually separated, let her continue unmarried, or be reconciled to her husband; and that a husband put not away a wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And to the rest I say, not the Lord; if any brother hath an unbelieving wife, and she is well satisfied to live with him, let him not divorce her:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and if any woman hath an unbelieving husband, and he is well satisfied to live with her, let her not divorce him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For the unbelieving husband is hallowed by the wife, and the unbelieving wife is hallowed by the husband; else your children would be unclean; whereas they are now holy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But if the unbelieving withdraw; let him or her withdraw, the brother or the sister is not in such cases enslaved: But God hath called us to peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For how knowest thou, O wife, but thou mayst save thy husband? Or how knowest thou, O husband, but thou mayst save thy wife?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But as God hath distributed to every one; as the Lord hath called every one, so let him walk. And thus I enjoin in all the congregations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Hath any one been called, being circumcised, let him not become uncircumcised. Hath any been called in a state of uncircumcision, let him not be circumcised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The circumcision is nothing, and the uncircumcision is nothing, in comparison with keeping the commandments of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>In whatever state any one hath been called, in that let him abide.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Hast thou been called being a slave, let it not give thee concern. But if thou canst be made free, chuse that rather.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For he who is called by the Lord, being a slave, is the Lord's freedman; and in like manner he who is called being free, is the vassal of Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>You have been bought with a price, become not slaves of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Brethren, in whatever state any one hath been called, in that let him continue with God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now with respect to the virgins, I have no commandment of the Lord; but I give an opinion as one who hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be faithful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I think then this to be good on account of the impending distress; that it is well for a man to be as he is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Art thou bound to a wife? seek not to be disengaged: Art thou disengaged from a wife, seek not a wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But if thou shouldst actually marry, thou hast not sinned; and if the virgin marry she hath not sinned. But such will have affliction in the flesh: But I spare you</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>and say this, brethren, that the time with regard to what remaineth, is shortened, so that they who have wives should be as if they had them not;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and they who weep, as if they wept not; and they who rejoice, as if they rejoiced not; and they who buy, as not possessing; and they</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>who use this world, as not using it immoderately. For the scenery of this world is shifting;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and I wish you to be free from anxious cares. He who is unmarried careth for the things of the Lord how he may please the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>but he who is married careth for the things of the world, how he may please his wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>There is the like difference between the wife and the virgin. The unmarried careth for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and spirit; but she who is married careth for the things of the world, how she may please her husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Now this I say for your own benefit, not with a view to lay a snare for you; but for that which is becoming and best adapted to a steady, uninterrupted adherence to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But if any man thinketh that he bringeth reproach on his virgin; if she be past the prime, this then should be the rule, What she willeth, let him do, he doth not sin; let them marry:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>but whoever hath come to a. fixed determination in his heart, using no constraint, but hath power with respect to his own will and hath determined in his heart to keep his virgin, he doth well.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>So that he who giveth in marriage doth well, but he who giveth not in marriage doth better.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>A wife is bound by law as long as her husband liveth; but if her husband die; she is at liberty to many whom she will; only in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>But she is happier, if she continue as she is. This is my opinion, and I think I have a spirit of God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now with regard to the things offered to idols, we know that we all have knowledge. (This knowledge puffeth up; but love edifieth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>If then any one thinketh that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But if any one loveth God by him he is acknowledged.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Therefore in respect to the eating of things offered to idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world: and that there is no other God but one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>for though there are nominal gods both in heaven and on earth, as there are many gods and many lords;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>yet to us there is but one God, the father of all, of whom are all things and we for him; and one Lord Jesus Christ, by whom are all things and we by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But all have not this knowledge; and some, with the consciousness of regard for the idol, even to this time eat meat as sacrificed to an idol; and their conscience being weak is defiled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now food doth not recommend us to God. For if we eat we are not the better; nor are we the worse if we do not eat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But take heed that this liberty of yours do not prove a stumbling block to the weak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For if one seeth thee who hast knowledge seated at table in an idol temple, will not the conscience of him who is weak be emboldened to eat the idol sacrifice?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And shall the weak brother, for whom Christ died, be destroyed for thy knowledge?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When you sin thus against the brethren and wound their weak conscience, you sin against Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Wherefore if meat cause my brother to stumble, I will never eat flesh that I may not cause my brother to stumble.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Am not I an apostle? Am not I free? Have not I seen Jesus Christ our Lord? Are not you my work in the Lord?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>If to others I am not an apostle, yet surely I am to you. For your being in the Lord is the seal of my apostleship.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>My answer to them who examine me is this</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Have we not a power to eat and drink?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Have we not a power to take along with us a sister, wife as well as the other apostles, and the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Or are I only and Barnabas excluded from the privilege of not working?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Who goeth to war any time at his own expenses? Who planteth a vineyard and eateth not of the fruit thereof? Who feedeth a flock and doth not eat of the milk of that flock?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Do I say these things according to the custom of human affairs? Doth not the law say the same?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For in the law of Moses it is written, Thou shalt not muzzle an ox treading out corn: Is God solicitous for oxen?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Or doth he not unquestionably say this for our sake? For us indeed it was written, because he who plougheth ought to plough in hope; and he who thresheth in hope ought to partake of his hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If we have sown for you spiritual things is it a great matter if we reap your carnal things?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If others exercise this power over you, may not we rather? But we have not made use of this power; but endure all things that we may not give any obstruction to the glad tidings of the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Do you not know that they who prepare the sacrifice eat of the sacrifice? They who attend on the altar partake with the altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So also the Lord hath ordered for them who proclaim the glad tidings, that they should live by the glad tidings</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>But as for me I have not made use of any of these privileges nor have I written these things that they should be a rule for me. For it were better for me to die than that any should deprive me of what is my boast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For though I publish the glad tidings I have no cause of boasting; for I am under an obligation and woe is for me if I do not publish the glad tiding</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>for if I do this willingly, I have a reward; but if against my will I have been intrusted with an office, what then is the reward for me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>In this case, when proclaiming the glad tiding I will make the glad tidings of the Christ so far unexpensive, not to use to the utmost the privilege which I have by the glad tidings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For being free from all men, I have made myself a slave to all that I may gain the more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>To the Jews I became as a Jew that I might gain the Jews: to them under law, as if I were under law, that I might gain those under law:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>to them without law, as if I were without law (not as without law to God, but under a law to Christ) that I might gain those with out law:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>To the weak I became as weak, that I might gain the weak; to all those I have become all this that I may save all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And this I do in consequence of the glad tidings that I may be a joint sharer thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Do you not know that they who run a race, all run; but one only rcceiveth the prize? In this manner run ye, that you may obtain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Now, every one who is to contend in the public games is temperate in all things. They indeed do this that they may obtain a corruptible crown. But we to obtain one that is incorruptible.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For my part, therefore, I run in this manner, not as if I were running unseen: I fight, not as if I were beating the air;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>but I buffet my body and subdue it, lest having proclaimed the glad tidings to others I myself should be disapproved.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Moreover, I would not, brethren, have you ignorant that our fathers were all under the cloud, and that they all passed through the sea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and were all baptized to Moses in the cloud and in the sea;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and did all eat the same spiritual food;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and did all drink of the same spiritual drink, for they drank from a spiritual rock accompanying them; now that rock was the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But with the greater part of them God was not well pleased; for they were overthrown in the wilderness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now these things were examples for us, that we may not lust after evil things as they did.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Be not ye then idolaters as some of them were; as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink and rose up to play:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Nor let us commit fornication as some of them did, and there fell in one day twenty three thousand:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>nor let us try the Christ as some indeed of them did, and were destroyed by serpents:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>nor murmur ye, as some of them murmured and were destroyed by the destroyer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now all these things came upon them for examples, and were written for the instruction of us on whom the ends of the ages have met.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>So let him who thinketh that he standeth, take heed that he do not fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>No trial hath come upon you but such as is common to man; and God is faithful, and will not suffer you to be tried above your strength, but will with the trial make a way to escape, that you may be able to bear it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Therefore, my beloved, flee from idolatry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I speak to you as men of understanding; judge ye what I say</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not a fellowship in the blood of the Christ? The loaf which we break, is it not a Fellowship in the body of the Christ?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Because it is one loaf, we being many are one body, for we ail partake of this one loaf.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Consider Israel according to the flesh; are not they who eat the sacrifices, partakers in common of the altar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>What then, do I say that an idol is any thing? or that what is sacrificed to an idol is any thing?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>No. I only say, that what the nations sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons and not to God. Now, I would not have you to be partakers in the worship of the demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>You cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons. You cannot partake of the table of the Lord and of the table of demons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Are we provoking the Lord to jealousy? Are we stronger than he?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>All things are lawful for me. All things however are not expedient, All things are lawful for me. All things however do not edify.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Let none seek barely his own interest, but every one that of his neighbour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Eat whatever is sold in the shambles, asking no questions for conscience sake;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>for the earth is the Lord's and the fulness thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And if any of the disbelievers invite you to an entertainment, and you chuse to go, eat whatever is set before you, asking no questions for conscience sake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>But if any one say to you, This was sacrificed to an idol, eat not of it for the sake of him who gave the information; and for conscience sake; for the earth is the Lord's and the fulness thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>When I say conscience I do not mean one's own, but the conscience of the other.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>But why is my liberty to be judged by another's conscience? And if I partake with thankfulness, why am I ill spoken of for what I give thanks?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Whether then you eat or drink, or whatever you do, do all to the glory of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Conduct yourselves so as to give no offence to Jews or Greeks, or the congregation of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>even as I do. In all things I please all men, not studying barely my own interest, but that of the many, that they may be saved.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Be ye imitators of me as I am of Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Now, I praise you, brethren, that in all things you are mindful of me and hold fast the doctrines as I delivered them to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and I wish you to know that the Christ is the head of every man; and that the head of woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Every man praying or prophesying with his head covered dishonoureth his head;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and every woman praying or prophesying with the head uncovered dishonoureth her head; for it is the same as if she were shaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For if a woman is not veiled, let her be shorn. But if it be shameful for a woman to be shorn or shaved, let her be veiled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For man indeed ought not to have his head covered, he being an image and a glory of God; but woman is a glory of man;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>for man was not made of woman; but woman of man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Nor was man created for the woman; but woman for the man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The woman, therefore, ought to have a covering on the head, because of the messengers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Nevertheless, man is not without woman, nor woman without man in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For as the woman was of the man, so also the man is by the woman; and all things are of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Judge for yourselves. Is it becoming for a woman unveiled to pray to God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Doth not nature itself teach you that if a man hath long hair, it is a shame to him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but if a woman hath long hair it is a glory to her; because the hair is given her for a veil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If any one, however, is disposed to be contentious, neither we nor the congregations have any such custom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But in regard to this which I am about to mention I do not commend you, because you meet together not for the better but for the worse.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For in the first place, on your assembling together in the congregation, I hear that there are divisions among you; and I partly believe it:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>for there must be sects among you, that the approved among you may become manifest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When you therefore assemble together, it is not to eat the Lord's supper;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>for every one at eating taketh first his own supper, so one indeed is hungry and another is plentifully fed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>What? have you not houses for eating and drinking? Or do you despise the congregation of God, and expose to shame them who have not? What must I say to you? Shall I commend you for this? I do not commend you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For I received from the Lord this which I delivered to you, that the Lord Jesus on the night in which he was delivered up, took a loaf,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and having given thanks, broke it, and said, Take, eat; this is my body which is broken for you. Do this in commemoration of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And in like manner, the cup also, after supper, saying, This cup is the new covenant by my blood. Do this, as often as you drink it, in commemoration of me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For as often as you eat this loaf, and drink this cup, you proclaim the death of the Lord, until he come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>So that whosoever shall eat this loaf or drink this cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner, he will be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Now, let a man examine himself, and in this manner eat of that loaf and drink of that cup;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>for he who eateth and drinketh in an unworthy manner, eateth and drinketh a judgment for himself, not distinguishing the body of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>For this cause many among you are weakly and sick, and many are falling asleep.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For if we distinguish ourselves, should we not be judged?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And being judged, we are corrected by the Lord, that we may not be condemned with the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Wherefore, my brethren, when you assemble to eat, wait for one another;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>and if any one is hungry let him eat at home, that you may not come together for judgment. And the rest I will set in order when I come.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now, brethren, I would not have you ignorant with respect to the spiritual gifts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You know that you were Gentiles carried away to dumb idols just as you were led.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Therefore I certify to you that none speaking by a spirit of God saith that Jesus is an Anathema; and that none can say that Jesus is the Lord, but by a holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now, there are diversities of gifts, but the same spirit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and there are diversities of offices, but the same Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and there are diversities of energies, but it is the same God who by his inward operation worketh all these effects in all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now, this manifestation of the spirit is given to every one for that which is profitable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For to one is given, by the spirit, a word of wisdom; and to another, a word of knowledge according to the same spirit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and to another, faith, by the same spirit; and to another, gifts of healing, by the same spirit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and to another, mighty powers of working miracles; and to another, the gift of prophecy; and to another, that of discerning spirits; and to another, divers languages; and to another, the interpretation of languages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now, it is one and the same spirit who effecteth all these, distributing his own as he pleaseth, to every one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one body, being many, are one body; so also is the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For by one spirit we are all baptized to one body, whether we were Jews or Greeks, slaves, or freemen; and have all been made to drink to one spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For the body is not one member, but many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>If the foot should say, Because I am not a hand, I am not of the body, is it therefore not of the body?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And if the ear should say, Because I am not an eye, I am not of the body, is it therefore not of the body?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>If the whole body were eye, where would, be the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where would be the smelling?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But now God hath placed the members, every one of them, in the body, as it hath pleased him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>But if they were all one member, where would be the body?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now they indeed are many members, yet one body:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and the eye cannot say to the hand, I have no need of thee: nor can the head say to the feet, I have no need of you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>On the contrary, those members of the body which seem to be the weakest are more especially necessary;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and on those which we think the more dishonourable parts of the body we bestow the more abundant honour: and the uncomely parts of us have more abundant finery,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>of which the comely parts have no need. God indeed hath formed the symmetry of the body, giving more abundant honour to the part which wanteth it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>that there may be no schisms in the body, but that the members may have mutual concern for one another;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>so that if one member suffereth, all the rest suffer with it; and if one member is honoured, all the rest rejoice with it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Now with regard to you, ye are a body of Christ, even individual members,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>whom God hath placed in the congregation; first, apostles, secondly, prophets, thirdly, teachers, then miraculous powers, then gifts of healing, helps, governments, different languages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Are all apostles? Are all prophets? Are all teachers? Have all miraculous powers?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Have all the gifts of healing? Do all speak divers languages? Are all interpreters?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>But you are ambitious of those gifts which are of superior excellence. Well, I am going to point out to you a way still more excellent.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, if I have not love, I am but a sounding brass or a tinkling cymbal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and though I have a gift of prophesy and understand all the mysteries and all this knowledge; and though I have all that faith, so as to remove mountains; if I have not love, I am nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And though I distribute all my substance to feed the poor, and deliver up my body to be burned, if I have not love, it profiteth me nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Love is long suffering; it aboundeth in kindness. Love is not envious. Love is not insolent: it is not puffed up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>It doth not behave itself unbecomingly. It is not self interested. It is not easily provoked. It placeth not the evil to account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>It rejoiceth not in iniquity, but shareth in the joys of truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>It beareth all things. It believeth all things. It hopeth all things. It endureth all things patiently.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Love never faileth. But as for prophecies, they will be out of use. As for languages, they will cease: As for science, it will be done away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For we now know in part and prophesy in part,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but when perfection is come, there will a stop be put to that which is in part.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When I was a child, I spake as a child, I thought as a child, I reasoned as a child; but when I became a man, I put a stop to childish things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For we now by means of a mirrour see a representation of things; but we shall then see face to face. I now know in part; but I shall then know as I am known.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now then these three, faith, hope and love, will remain; but love is the greatest of the three.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Be zealous then in the pursuit of this love, and aspire after spiritual gifts, but chiefly that you may prophesy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For he who speaketh in a strange language, speaketh not to men but to God: for none understandeth; and with a spirit he speaketh mysteries.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But he who prophesieth, speaketh to men edification, and exhortation, and consolation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He who speaketh in an unknown tongue edifieth himself; but he who prophesieth, edifieth a congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now I wish you all to speak with tongues; but much rather that you should prophesy: For he who prophesieth is greater than he who speaketh with tongues, unless some one interpret, that the congregation may be edified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For instance, should I, brethren, come to you, speaking with tongues, what shall I profit you, unless I explain to you what I say, be it either a revelation, or science, or a prophecy, or a doctrine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>In like manner with regard to inanimate things which give a sound, whether pipe or kithara, unless they produce distinct notes, how can it be known what that is, which is played on the pipe or kithara.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For if even a trumpet give an undistinguishable sound who will prepare himself for battle?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So also with regard to you, unless you utter with the tongue a discourse of a clear signification, how can that which is spoken be known? You will be indeed talking to the air.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Let there be ever so many kinds of sounds in the world, and none of them without signification,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>if I do not know the meaning of the sound I shall be to the speaker a barbarian, and he who speaketh will be the same to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Such also is the case with you. Since you then are ambitious of spiritual gifts, seek to abound in such as tend to the improvement of the congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Let him therefore who speaketh in an unknown tongue, pray that he may interpret.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For if I pray in an unknown tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my understanding is unfruitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>What then is to be done? I am to pray with the spirit and to pray with the understanding also. I am to sing with the spirit, and to sing with the understanding also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Otherwise if thou bless with the spirit, how can he who occupieth the place of the unlearned say Amen at thy giving thanks, when he knoweth not what thou sayest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Thou indeed givest thanks well, but the other is not edified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I thank my God, I speak with tongues more than you all;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but in a congregation I would rather speak five words with my understanding that I may instruct others, than ten thousand words in an unknown tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Brethren, be not children in your understandings; but be infants in malice; and in your understandings full grown men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>It is written in the law, By men of strange tongues and with strange lips I will speak to this people; yet for all this they will not hearken to me, saith the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>So that these strange tongues are for a sign, not for them who believe; but for unbelievers. But prophesying is not for unbelievers, but for them who believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>If therefore the whole congregation assemble and all speak with unknown tongues, and there should come in any uninstructed persons or unbelievers, would they not say that you are raving?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But if all prophesy, and any unbeliever or uninstructed person come in, he is convicted by all; examined by all;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and thus the secrets of his heart are laid open, and so, falling on his face, he will worship God, declaring that God is indeed among you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>What then, brethren, is to be done? When you come together every one of you hath a psalm; hath a doctrine; hath a strange tongue; hath a revelation; hath an interpretation; let all be for edification;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>and if any one speak in an unknown tongue, let him speak as by two, or at the most three; and in parts, and let one interpret:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>but if there be no interpreter, let him be silent in a congregation, and speak to himself and to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>And let two or three prophets speak, and let the rest deliberate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And if a revelation be made to another who is sitting, let the first have become silent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>For you can all prophesy, one by one, that all may learn, and all be comforted,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>And the spirits of prophets are subject to prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>For God is not a God of confusion, but of peace, As in all the congregations of the saints</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>let your women be silent in these congregations: for they are not permitted to talk, but to be in subjection, as the law also saith:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And if they wish to learn any thing let them ask their husbands at home. For it is shameful for women to talk in a congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Did the word of God go forth from you? or did it come to you only?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>If any one be, in reality, a prophet, or a spiritual man, let him acknowledge that what I write to you are the commandments of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>But if any one doth not know this, let him continue ignorant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>So then, brethren, be ambitious of prophesying, and prohibit not the speaking with tongues.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>Let all things be done in a becoming and orderly manner.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I now, brethren, remind you in what terms I proclaimed the gospel which I proclaimed to you, and which you received, and in which you have continued,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and by which also you are saved, if you strictly adhere to it, unless indeed you believed in vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For I delivered to you, as one of the principal things, that which I actually received, that Christ died for our sins, according to the scriptures;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and that he was buried; and that he was raised up the third day according to the scriptures;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and that he was seen by Cephas, then, by the twelve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>after that he was seen by above five hundred brethren at once, of whom the greater number are even now alive, but some indeed are composed to rest;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>after that he was seen by James, then by all the apostles;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and, last of all, he was seen also by me, who am as it were one born out of due time;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>for I am the very least of the apostles, and am not worthy to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the congregation of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>But by the favour of God I am what I am; and this favour of his which reached me was not fruitless; but I have laboured more than they all; yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Whether therefore I or they laboured, thus do we proclaim, and thus you have believed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now, if Christ be proclaimed, that he hath been raised from the dead, how do some among you say that there is no resurrection of the dead?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If there is indeed no resurrection of the dead, then Christ is not raised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And if Christ hath not been raised, our proclamation is vain, and your belief is also vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And we are found to be actually false witnesses of God; because we have testified concerning God, that he hath raised the Christ, whom he hath not raised, if indeed the dead are not raised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For if the dead are not raised, then Christ was not raised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And if Christ hath not been raised, your belief is vain; you are still in your sins;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and consequently they, who have been composed to rest in Christ, have perished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>If we have hope in Christ in this life only, we, of all men, are most to be pitied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But now Christ hath been raised from the dead. He was the first fruits of them who have been composed to rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For since by man came death, by man also cometh a resurrection of the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For as by Adam all die, so by the Christ all shall be brought to life:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>but every one in his proper order; Christ the first fruits; then they who belong to Christ, at his coming:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>then the end, when he shall deliver up the kingdom to God the father, when he shall have put a stop to all empire and all authority, and all power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For he must reign until he hath put all the enemies under his feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The last enemy, death, is to be destroyed:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>for he hath put all under his feet. But when it is said, That all are subjected; it is evident that there is an exception of him who subjected the all to him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>and when the all are subjected to him, then will the Son himself also be subjected to him who subjected the all to him that God may be the all in all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>This being the case what will they do who are baptized for the dead? If they who are altogether dead are not raised up, why are they then baptized for the dead?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>and why are we every hour incurring danger</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>I dying daily? I swear by that boasting of yours (meaning that which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>if I as a man had fought with beasts at Ephesus, what advantage is that to me if the dead are not raised up? Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Be not led astray; good morals are debauched by talk profane.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Be righteously sober and sin not. For some have not a knowledge of God. I say this to your shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>But a certain person will say, How are the dead raised, and with what sort of a body do they come?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>Simpleton! that which thou thyself sowest is not quickened unless it dieth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="37">
      <content>And as to what thou sowest, thou sowest not the body which is to be, but a bare grain, for instance, of wheat, or of any other seeds:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="38">
      <content>and God giveth it a body as it hath pleased him, and to every of the seeds its own peculiar body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="39">
      <content>All flesh is not of the same sort; but there is one sort of flesh peculiar to men; another to beasts, and another to fishes, and another to birds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="40">
      <content>There are also celestial bodies, and terrestrial bodies. But the glory of the celestial is of one sort, and the glory of the terrestrial, of another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="41">
      <content>The glory of the sun is of one kind; and the glory of the moon, of another; and the glory of the stars is different: One star differeth from another in glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="42">
      <content>Thus it is also with respect to the resurrection of the dead. That which is sown, is sown in corruption; it is raised in incorruption;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="43">
      <content>it is sown in dishonour; it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness; it is raised in power:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="44">
      <content>it is sown an animal body; it is raised a spiritual body. There is an animal body; and there is a spiritual body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="45">
      <content>Thus also it is written, The first man Adam was made a living soul. The latter Adam is a quickening spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="46">
      <content>The spiritual was not first, but the animal; then the spiritual.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="47">
      <content>The first man from the earth was earthy; the second man is the Lord from heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="48">
      <content>As the earthy was, such also are they who are earthy. And as the heavenly is, such shall they be who are heavenly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="49">
      <content>And as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="50">
      <content>Now this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God; nor can corruption inherit incorruption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="51">
      <content>Behold I tell you a secret: We shall not all be composed to rest; but we shall all be changed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="52">
      <content>in a moment in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trumpet, for it will sound, and the dead will be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="53">
      <content>For this corruptible must put on incorruptibility; and this mortal must put on immortality.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="54">
      <content>Now when this corruptible shall have put on incorruptibility; and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then will be brought to pass the word which is written, Death is completely swallowed up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="55">
      <content>O death where is thy sting? Where thy victory, O grave?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="56">
      <content>Sin is indeed the sting of death; And the law is the strength of sin:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="57">
      <content>But thanks be to God who gives us the victory Through our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="58">
      <content>So then, my beloved brethren, be ye stedfast, immoveable, abounding always in the work of the Lord, for as much as you know that your labour in the Lord is not in vain.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now, with respect to the collection which is for the saints, as I have directed in the congregations of Galatia, so do ye also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Every first day of the week, let every one of you lay by him, and put into a common treasury, what he can conveniently; that when I come there may be no collection then made.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when I come, whomsoever you approve, them I will despatch with letters to carry your bounty to Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And if it be thought proper that I myself should go, they shall go with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now I will come to you when I have passed through Macedonia, (for I am going through Macedonia)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and perhaps I may continue with you some time, or even spend the winter, that you may forward me on in whatever journey I may take.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For I do not wish to see you now on my way, but hope to spend some time with you, if the Lord permit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But I will stay at Ephesus until the pentecost,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>for a great and effectual door is opened for me, though there are many opposers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now when Timothy comes to you, see that he be with you without fear; for he worketh the work of the Lord, as I myself do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Therefore let none despise him; but forward him on in peace, that he may come to me; for I wait for him with the brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now with respect to Apollos the brother, I importuned him much to go to you with the brethren. Though upon the whole it was not his will to go now, yet he will go when there shall be a favourable opportunity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Watch; stand firm in the faith; acquit yourselves like men; be strong;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>let all your affairs be transacted with love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And I intreat you, brethren, (you know the household of Stephanas, that it is the first fruits of Achaia, and that they have addicted themselves to the service of the saints;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>that you submit yourselves to such, and to every fellow worker and labourer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now I rejoice at the coming of Stephanas, and Fortunatus, and Achaicus, because they have supplied to the full what was wanting on your part.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For they have quieted my spirit as well as yours. Have regard therefore to such as these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The congregations of Asia salute you. Aquilas, and Priscilla; and the congregation at their house, salute you with much affection in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>All the brethren salute you. Salute ye one another with a holy kiss.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The salutation of me Paul with my own hand</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>If any one loveth not the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be an Anathema. Maranatha.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The favour of the Lord Jesus Christ be with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>