<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, to the saints; to them who are at Ephesus and faithful in Christ Jesus:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Favour be to you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who hath blessed us with every spiritual blessing; with the heavenly things in Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>as he chose us in him before the5 foundation of the world, that we might be holy and blameless before him in love;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>having before hand determinately pointed us out for an adoption into the number of children by Jesus Christ for himself, according to the good pleasure of his will;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>for the praise of the glory of that favour of his with which he made us objects of favour in the Beloved;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>by whom we have this redemption by his blood; the forgiveness of our sins according to the richness of his grace</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>in which he hath abounded for us</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>having with all wisdom and care made known to us this secret of his will, according to that good pleasure of his, which he previously purposed in himself,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for the dispensation of the fulness of times, to bring all things again under one head in Christ, both those in heaven and those on earth; even in him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>by whom we, (having been previously marked out in a determinate manner, according to the purpose of him who effecteth all things according to the counsel of his will) were made his inheritance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>to the end that we who first trusted in the Christ might be for the praise of his glory;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and by whom you also, when you heard the word of this truth, the glad tidings of this salvation of yours; by whom you indeed, when you believed, were sealed with the spirit of the promise</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>(that holy spirit which is an earnest of the inheritance of us; for the complete redemption of the purchase) for the praise of his glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For this cause, having heard of the faith which you have in the Lord Jesus, and of your love for all the saints,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I do not cease to give thanks for you, making mention of you in my prayers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of the glory, would give you a spirit of wisdom and revelation in the acknowledgment of him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>that He would enlighten the eyes of your understanding, that you may see what the hope of this invitation of his is; and what the riches of the glory of this inheritance of his, in the saints;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and what the exceeding greatness of this power of his for us who believe, corresponding to the energy of the strength of that power</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>of his which he exerted in the Christ: Having raised Him from the dead, he set him at his right hand, in the heavenly kingdom,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>far above all principality and power, and might, and dominion, and every name which is named, not only in this age but in that to come;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and put all things under his feet, and constituted him head over all for the congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>which is his body; the fulness of him who filleth all in all.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And with respect to you, when you were dead in those trespasses, and those sins,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>in which you formerly walked according to the course of this world; according to the prince of the power of the air, that spirit which is now working powerfully in the children of disobedience;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>among whom when we also were all formerly leading our lives in the desires of our flesh, executing the dictates of the flesh, and the imaginations, and were naturally children of wrath even as the rest;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>then God, who is rich in mercy, on the account of the great love with which he loved us,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>even when we were dead in those trespasses, did bring us to life with the Christ, (by grace you are saved)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and did raise us up, and place us with him in the heavenly kingdom in Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>in order that he might, in the ages which are to come, display the immense riches of his favour by kindness to us in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For by grace you are saved by means of this belief. And even this is not of yourselves; it is the gift of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>It is not because of works; so that no one can boast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For we are his workmanship, fitted by Christ Jesus for good works, for which God had before prepared us that we might walk therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Wherefore remember that you were formerly the nations in flesh, those denominated uncircumcision by the nominal circumcision made with hands, in flesh</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>that you were at that time without Christ; aliens from the commonwealth of Israel, and strangers to the covenants of the promise, having no hope, and being without God in the world:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>but now by Christ Jesus, you, who were formerly far off, are brought near by the blood of the Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>for he is our peace. He it is, who hath made both one, and who hath demolished the partition wall,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>having; by his flesh put a stop to the enmity; the law of the commandments contained in positive injunctions; that he might frame the two anew, in himself, into one new man, making peace;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and reconcile them both in one body, to God by means of the cross, having by that slain the enmity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And being come he hath proclaimed the glad tidings of peace to you who were far off, and to them who were near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Because through him we both have access to the father by one spirit,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>you therefore are no longer strangers, and pilgrims, but fellow citizens of the saints, and of the household of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself being the corner stone,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>by whom the whole building being united in symmetry is to grow up to a holy temple in the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>by whom you also are builded up together with them by the spirit, for an habitation of God.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For this cause, with regard to me Paul the prisoner of the Christ, Jesus, for you the nations;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>inasmuch as you have heard of the dispensation of the favour of God granted to me for you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>that he hath by a revelation made known to me this secret (as I have briefly written above,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>by the bare reading of which you may perceive my knowledge in this secret of the Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>which in former generations was not made known to the children of men as it hath now been revealed to his holy apostles and prophets by the spirit,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>That the nations are coheirs, and a joint body, and joint partakers of that promise of his in the Christ by means of the gospel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>of which I was made a minister according to the free gift of God's favour which was granted to me; according to the energy of his power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>To me, who am less than the least of all the saints, this favour was granted to proclaim among the nations the unsearchable riches of the Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and to enlighten all men with respect to the dispensation of this secret, which God who created all things by Jesus Christ had hidden from the ages,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>in order that the manifold wisdom of God might now be made known to the principalities and the powers in the heavenly kingdom, by means of the congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>according to the predisposition of the ages which he made by Christ Jesus our Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>by whom we have this freedom of speech, and this access with confidence, by this belief in him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>therefore I pray you not to be dejected at these afflictions of mine for you. It is for your glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For this cause I bend my knees to the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>of whom the whole family in heaven and on earth is named,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>that he would, according to the riches of his glory, grant you to be strengthened by his spirit for the inner man,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>that, by means of this belief, the Christ may dwell in your hearts; that you being rooted and grounded in love,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>may be able to comprehend, with all the saints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and to know the love of the Christ which surpasseth that knowledge; that you may be filled with all the fulness of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now to him who is able to do infinitely above all that we can ask or conceive, according to that power which is operative in us</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>to him be the glory in the congregation, by Christ Jesus, through all the generations of the age of the ages. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I, therefore, the prisoner for the Lord, beseech you to walk worthy of the call with which you have been called,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>with all humility and meekness; with long suffering, bearing with one another in love;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and endeavouring to preserve the unity of the spirit by the bond of peace;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>to be one body and one spirit: as you have indeed been called to one hope of your call.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>There is one Lord, one belief, one baptism,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in you all;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and to every one of us there hath been granted in due measure the favour of the free gift of the Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Therefore it is said, Having ascended on high, he hath led captivity captive, and he hath given gifts to men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Now this expression, He ascended what doth it infer, but that he had first descended into the lower parts of the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He who descended is the same who ascended far above all the heavens, that he might fill all;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and he hath given some to be apostles, and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some pastors, and teachers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>for the fitting up of the saints; for the work of distribution; for the building up of the body of the Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>until we all come up to the unity of the belief and of the knowledge of the son of God; to perfect manhood to a measure of the stature of the fulness of the Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>that we may no longer be infants, tossed like waves, and whirled about by every wind of doctrine, by the cheating sleight of men, by a skill in the art of deceiving:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but that maintaining truth with love, we may grow up in all respects for him, who is the head, the Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>from whom the whole body being fitly framed together and cemented, provision is made by means of the supply of every joint, according to the proportionate operative power of every part, for an increase of the body; for building itself up in love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>This therefore I say and testify in the Lord, that you no more walk, as the rest of the nations do, in the vanity of their mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>They having their understandings darkened, being alienated from the life of God because of the ignorance which is in them, by reason of the blindness of their heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>have without remorse abandoned themselves to the commission of every uncleanness with inordinate desire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But you have not thus learned the Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>inasmuch as you have heard him and been taught by him, as the truth is in Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>with respect to your former course of life, to put off the old man, which is corrupted by deceitful desires,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and to be renewed in the spirit of your mind;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and to put on the new man, which in a conformity to God is created in righteousness and the holiness of truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Wherefore, putting away all falsehood, speak truth, every one to his neighbour. Because we are members one of another,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>are you excited to anger? Do not therefore sin. Let not the sun go down on your wrath,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>nor give the devil an opportunity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Let the stealer steal no more; but rather labour, and procure honestly with the work of his hands, that he may have wherewithal to relieve the needy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Let no corrupt discourse proceed out of your mouth; nothing but what is good for edification, of such utility as to be a benefit to the hearers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>And grieve not the holy spirit of God by which you have been sealed for the day of redemption.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Let all bitterness, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and detraction, be banished from among you, with malice of every sort;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>and be kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, forgiving one another. And as God hath in Christ forgiven you,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>be ye therefore imitators of God as beloved children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And walk in love, even as the Christ loved us, and delivered himself up for us, as an3 offering and a sacrifice to God for a sweet smelling savour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And let not fornication, nor uncleanness of any sort, nor inordinate desire, be so much as named among you, as becometh saints;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>nor obscenity, nor foolish talking, nor jesting about things which are unbecoming; but rather thanksgiving.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For this you know that no fornicator, nor unclean person, nor lewd libertine, who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the kingdom of the Christ and God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let no one deceive you with vain discourses; for on the account of these things the wrath of God is coining on these children of disobedience,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>be not ye8 therefore partakers with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For you were formerly darkness, but being now a light in the Lord, walk as children of light</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>(for the fruit of this light consists of goodness and righteousness and truth of every sort)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>proving what is well pleasing to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather reprove them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>for as to the things done by them in secret, it is shameful even to mention them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>But all these reprehensible things are exposed to view by the light. For it is light which exposeth every thing to view;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>therefore it is said, Awake thou who sleepest and arise from the dead and the Christ will shine upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Take heed therefore how circumspectly you walk, not as unwise, but as wise,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>redeeming the time. Because these are evil days,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore be not without understanding, but intelligent with regard to what is the will of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And be not intoxicated with wine in which there is debauchery, but be filled with the spirit</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>when: you are speaking to one another, when with psalms and hymns and spiritual songs you are singing and making melody with your hearts to the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and give thanks on all occasions for all things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ to the God and Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Be subject to one another in the fear of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Wives, be subject to your husbands as to the Lord;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>because the husband is the head of the wife, even as the Christ is the head of the congregation. He indeed is the saviour of the body;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>but as the congregation is subject to the Christ, so let wives be to their husbands in every thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Husbands love your wives, even as the Christ loved the congregation, and gave himself up for it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>that having purified it with the bath of the water, he might hallow it; indeed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>that he might present it to himself as the glorious congregation, having neither spot, nor wrinkle, nor any defect whatever; but that it may be holy and without blemish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In the same manner husbands ought to love their wives as their own bodies. He who loveth his wife, loveth himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Now no one ever hated his own flesh, but nourisheth and cherisheth it, even as the Lord doth the congregation,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>because we are members of his body; of his flesh and of his bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Instead of this, a man will leave his father and mother and cleave to his wife, and they two will be one flesh,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>this is the great mystery, I mean in regard to Christ and the congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>However with regard to you individually, let every one love his wife as himself, and let the wife reverence her husband.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Children, obey your parents in the Lord; for this is right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Honour thy father and mother (this is the first commandment with a promise)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayst live long on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And you, parents, exasperate not your children, but educate them with the discipline and admonition of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Servants, obey them who are your masters according to the flesh, with fear and trembling, in the sincerity of your hearts, as you do the Christ</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>not with eye-service as men pleasers, but as servants of the Christ, doing the will of God from the heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>performing service with good will, as to the Lord and not to men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>knowing that whatever good any one doth, the Lord will reward him for it, whether he be a bondman or freeman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And you, masters, observe the same conduct towards them, abating your threats, knowing that you yourselves have a master in heaven, and that with him there is no respect of persons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord and in the power of his might.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Put on the complete armour of God, that you may be able to withstand the wiles of the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Because our conflict is not barely with flesh and blood, but against the principalities and the powers; against the rulers of this dark age, against the spiritual assaults of the wickedness in the heavenly dispensation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>take up therefore the complete armour of God, that you may be able to make resistance in the evil day, and having put a stop to them all, to maintain your ground.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Stand, therefore, having your loins girded with truth, and having on the breast plate of righteousness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and your feet shod with the preparation of the glad tidings of peace,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>covering all with the shield of faith with which you will be able to extinguish all the fiery darts of the evil one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Take also the helmet of salvation, and the sword o? the spirit, that is the word of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>in every prayer and supplication, always praying with the spirit (being for this purpose in a continual state of watchfulness and prayer) for all the saints</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>particularly for me, that to me a word may be given, that with the opening of my mouth, and with freedom am plainness of speech, I may make known the secret of the glad tidings,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for which I am performing the office of an ambassador in a chain, that in this situation I may speak boldly as I ought to speak.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Now that you may know the state of my affairs, and what I am doing, Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, will give you a particular account,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>as I have sent him for this very purpose, that you may know the state of our affairs, and that he may comfort your hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Peace to the brethren and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>this favour be with all them who love our Lord Jesus Christ without any mixture of Corruption. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>