<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul and Timothy, servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus, to them who are at Philippi, with overseers and deacons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>favour be to you and peace from God our father, and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I thank my God at every mention of you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>always, in ever prayer of mine for you all, making such supplication with joy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>for your contribution for the glad tidings; having from the first day till now</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>the same confidence, that he who hath begun a good work in you will continue completing it until the day of Jesus Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>as it is just for me to be thus affected towards you all, because you have me in your heart; and in my bonds and in the defence and support of the glad tidings you all continue to be fellow sharers with me of this favour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For God be my witness how tenderly I love you all with the affection of Jesus Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and this I pray that your love may abound still more and more, in knowledge and all discernment,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>that you may prove the things which differ; that you may be sincere and inoffensive till the day of Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>filled with fruits of righteousness, which are by means of Jesus Christ, for the glory and praise of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now I wish you, brethren, to know that what hath happened to me hath rather conduced to the furtherance of the</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>gospel; so that in the whole imperial palace, and all other places, my bonds are well known to be for Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and a greater number of the brethren in the Lord are emboldened by my bonds to venture to speak the word with more freedom and intrepidity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Some indeed proclaim the Christ out of envy and contention, but others do it out of good will</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>the former for the sake of strife proclaim the Christ not in a pure manner, thinking to add affliction to my bonds;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but the latter for love, knowing that I am set for the defence of the gospel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>What then? Still in every way, whether in pretence or in truth, Christ is proclaimed. At this therefore I rejoice and will rejoice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For I know that this will issue in my deliverance, through your supplications and a supply of the spirit of Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>according to my earnest expectation and hope that I shall in no wise be ashamed; but that in the most open manner, as always so now, Christ shall be magnified in my body, either by life or by death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But whether the living in flesh is for me a fruit of labour, and what I should chuse, I do not know.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For I am strained between the two, having a desire to depart and to be with Christ which is by far the best;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>but to abide in the flesh is more needful on your account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And being confident of this, I know that I shall abide and continue some time with you all for your furtherance and joy in the faith;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>that by me your glorying in Christ Jesus may abound, by means of my being present with you again.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Only conduct yourselves in a manner becoming the glad tidings of the Christ, that whether I come and see you, or if absent I may hear this of you, that you are stedfast in one spirit, and that without being in the least daunted by your opposers, you contend unanimously for the belief of the gospel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>which is to them indeed a manifestation of destruction, but to you, of salvation. Now with respect to this from God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>because this hath been granted to you for Christ, not only to believe in him but also to suffer for him and you are engaged in the same conflict as that in which you saw me and now hear that I am engaged,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>if therefore there be any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any participation of spirit, if any compassion and tender mercies,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>complete my joy. In order that you may be like minded, exercising the same love, having your souls knit together, your minds bent on the one thing</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>upon nothing out of a spirit of contention or vain glory, but in lowliness of mind esteeming one another better than yourselves,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>look not every one to his own interests, but every one of you to the interests also of others.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For let this temper of mind be in you which was in Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>who being in the form of God did not think it robbery to be like God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>but he emptied himself; having taken the form of a servant, being in the likeness of men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself and became obedient to death, even the death of a cross;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>wherefore God highly exalted him, and granted him a name which is above every name,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>that in the name of Jesus every knee should bend, of those in heaven, and of those on earth, and of those beneath the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory of God the father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore, as you, my beloved, have always been obedient, not only when I was present, but now much more when I am absent, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for it is God who is working in you both the will and the power to act.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For this good pleasure do you all things without murmurings and surmises,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>that you may be blameless and sincere, spotless children of God in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation, amongst whom shine ye forth as lights in the world,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>displaying the word of life, that I may have matter of boasting for the day of Christ, that I did not run in vain, nor labour in vain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but can if I am even poured out as a libation on the sacrifice and service of your belief, rejoice and congratulate with you all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For the same cause then rejoice ye also and congratulate with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Now I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy very soon to you, that I may be refreshed by knowing the state of your affairs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For I have none of a like disposition who will sincerely interest himself in your concerns.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For all are seeking their own things, not the things of the Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But of him you know this proof, that as a son serveth a father, he hath served with me for the gospel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Him therefore I hope to send as soon as I see the issue of my affairs here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And I have a confidence in the Lord that I myself shall come very soon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But I have thought it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus my brother, and fellow labourer and fellow soldier, and your missionary and agent to supply my want;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>as he hath been longing for you all, and is much distressed because you heard that he was sick.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For he was indeed sick, nigh to death; but God had pity on him, and not on him only, but also on me, that I might not have sorrow on sorrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>I have therefore sent him with the greater despatch, that upon seeing him again you may rejoice, and that I may be less sorrowful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Receive him then in the Lord with all joy and hold such in high esteem</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>because he was on the brink of death, for the work of the Christ, having exposed his life that he might supply the want of your religious service for me.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. To write to you the same things is not troublesome to me; and to you it is safe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Beware of the dogs; beware of the evil workers; beware of the concision;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>for we are the circumcision, who serve God in spirit, and glory in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Though, with regard to my having a confidence even in flesh, if any other thinketh that he hath a confidence in flesh, I have greater pretensions</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>circumcision performed on the eighth day; a descent from Israel; of the tribe of Benjamin; a Hebrew of Hebrews; with respect to the law, a Pharisee;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>with respect to zeal, a persecutor of the congregation; with respect to righteousness which is by law, blameless;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>yet what were gain to me these I have counted refuse on account of the Christ</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>nay more, I do therefore indeed count all things but refuse, on account of the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, for whom I have given up all and account them but dregs, that I may gain Christ</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and be found in him, not having for my righteousness, that which is of the law, but that which is by a belief in Christ; that which is of God; a righteousness for this belief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>That I may know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings, I have conformed myself to his death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>that I may somehow arrive at the resurrection of the dead</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>not that I have already received, or am yet made perfect, but I continue the pursuit, that I may lay hold that for which I have been laid hold on by the Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Brethren, I do not reckon myself to have laid hold on it, but one thing I do, forgetting the things which are behind, and intent on the things before,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I press forward to the mark, for the prize of the call of God from above by Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Let as many of us therefore as are full grown, have our minds bent on this; and if any of you are otherwise minded, when God shall reveal this to you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>(over and above the advance which we have made by walking by this rule, by minding this itself)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>be ye, brethren, imitators of me, and keep your eyes fixed on those who walk thus, as you have us for an example.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For many walk of whom I have frequently told you, and now tell you with tears, that they are enemies of the cross of Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Their end is destruction; their God is their belly; and their glory is their shame. Their minds are bent on earthly things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But we are citizens of heaven, from which we earnestly expect a saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>who will transform the body of this our humble state, that it may be made conformable to his glorious body, according to the energy of his power to subject all to himself.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Wherefore, my brethren, my beloved, and much longed for! my joy and my crown! stand thus stedfast in the Lord, my beloved!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I beseech Euodia, and I beseech Syntiche, to be of one mind in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I intreat thee also, my faithful colleague, assist them; for they were fellow labourers of mine in the gospel, with Clement in particular, and the rest of mv fellow labourers whose names are in the book of life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Rejoice in the Lord always. Again, I say, rejoice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Let your meekness be known to all men. The Lord is at hand:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Be anxious about nothing; but on all occasions, by prayer and supplication with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known to God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and the peace of God, which surpasseth all understanding, will keep your hearts and your minds safe in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Finally, brethren, whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are venerable, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are friendly, whatsoever things are reputable, if there be any virtue, and if there be any praise, think of these things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and practise what you have learned, and received, and heard, and seen in me; and the God of peace be with you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now I was greatly rejoiced in the Lord that now at length you revived your care for me, for whom you indeed were concerned, but had not an opportunity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Not that I speak with regard to want; for I have learned, in whatever circumstances I am, to be contented.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I know how to be brought low; and I know how to abound: in every respect, and in all things, I have been initiated into the mysteries of feeding plentifully, and suffering hunger; of abounding, and being in want.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I can undergo all things through Christ who strengthened me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Notwithstanding this you did well in assisting me in my distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now you, Philippians, yourselves know, that at the beginning of the glad tidings when I was departing from Macedonia, no congregation communicated with me in respect to giving and receiving, but you only</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>that when I was at Thessalonica you sent once and again to supply my want.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Not that I desire a gift, but I wish for the fruit which aboundeth to your account.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now I have all things and abound. I am fully supplied, having received your presents by Epaphroditus, a fragrant odour, a sacrifice acceptable, well pleasing to God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And my God will supply all your wants, according to his riches in glory in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now to our God and father be the glory for the ages of the ages. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Salute every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren with me salute you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>All the saints salute you, they especially who are of Caesar's household.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The favour of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>