<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, and Timothy the brother,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to the holy and faithful brethren in Christ at Colosse: favour be to you, and peace, from God our father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>We give thanks to the God and father of our Lord Jesus Christ, always praying for you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>(having heard of your belief in Christ Jesus, and of your love for all the saints)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>on account of the hope laid up for you in the heavens, of which you heard before by the true word of the gospel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>which is come to you as it hath also to all the world, and is bringing forth fruit, as it doth among you, from the day you heard and acknowledged the favour of God in truth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>as you learned it from Epaphras our dear fellow servant, who is for you a faithful minister of the Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and the person who informed us of your love in spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For this cause, we indeed, from the day we heard of it do not cease praying for you, and requesting, in order that you may be filled, in respect to the acknowledgment of his will</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>with all wisdom and spiritual understanding, that you may walk worthy of the Lord, to all well pleasing. By every good work we bear fruit, and grow up for the acknowledgment of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>being strengthened with all might according to the power of his glory for all patience and long suffering we with joy</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>give thanks to the Father who hath fitted us for a portion of the inheritance of the saints in light;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>who hath delivered us from the power of darkness, and removed us into the kingdom of his beloved son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>by whom we have this redemption, even the remission of our sins by the blood of him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>who is an image of the invisible God, a first born of the whole creation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Because all the things which are in the heavens and which are on the earth were created by him, the visible and the invisible, whether thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers, they were all created by him, and for him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore he is before all, and they are all kept in consistence by him,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and he is the head of the body, namely of the congregation. He who is the beginning is a first born from the dead that in all things he might be pre-eminent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Because all the plenitude was pleased to dwell in him, and by him to reconcile all to himself,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>he having by the blood of his cross; by himself, brought them to be at peace, (whether they be the things on earth or the things in heaven,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>hath now therefore brought you, who were for a time alienated, and enemies in your minds by wicked works, to a state of reconcilement</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>by the body of his flesh by his death, to present you holy and without blemish, and exempt from accusation in his sight,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>provided you continue in this belief, grounded and settled, and are not moved away from the hope of the glad tidings which you have heard, which have been proclaimed to this whole creation under heaven, of which I Paul was made a minister.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now I rejoice in these sufferings of mine for you, and am in my turn making up in my flesh the remainders of the sufferings of the Christ, for his body, namely, the congregation</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>of which I was made a minister, according to the dispensation of God which was committed to me for you, to confirm the word of God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>the mystery which was hidden from the ages and from the generations, but is now manifested to his saints;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>to whom God hath been pleased to make known the riches of the glory of this mystery among the nations: namely Christ in you the hope of Glory,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>whom we proclaim, admonishing every man, and teaching every man with all wisdom; that we may present every one a full grown man in Christ Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>for which I indeed labour, and struggle with all my might, according to that energy of his which operateth in me with power.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For I wish you to know what a great struggle I have for you, and for them in Laodicea, and as many as have not seen me in person,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>that, they being knit together in love, their hearts may be comforted, even to all the riches of the full assurance of this knowledge; to the acknowledgement of the mystery of the God and Father and the Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>in which are hid all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Now I say this in order that none may deceive you with enticing discourse;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>for though I am absent in person, yet in spirit I am present with you, rejoicing and beholding the regularity of your conduct and the stedfastness of your belief in Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>As you therefore have received the Christ Jesus for your Lord, walk in him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>rooted and built up in him, and firmly established in this belief, as you have been taught; abounding in it with thankfulness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Be on your guard, that none may make a prey of you by their philosophy and vain deceit, according to the tradition of men, according to the elements of the world, and not according to Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Because all the plenitude of the deity resideth substantially in him, 10 therefore you are complete in him who is the head of all principality and power;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>in whom also you have been circumcised with a circumcision made without hands; with the putting off of the body of the sins of the flesh; with the circumcision of the Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>having been buried with him in that baptism in which also you were raised with him by your belief in the mighty power of God, who raised him from the dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When you were dead in the trespasses and the uncircumcision of your flesh he raised you to life with him. Having freely forgiven you all those trespasses</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>having blotted out the hand-writing which was against us by the ordinances; that which was adverse to us he removed out of the way; having nailed this to the cross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>having divested himself of the principalities and the powers, he exposed them to public view- when he triumphed over them on it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let none therefore judge you in respect to eating or drinking, or in respect to a festival, or a new moon, or sabbaths,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>which are a shadow of the things to come. And with respect to the body of the Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>let no one deprive you of the prize; however delighted he may be with an affected humility and the religion of angels, prying into matters which he hath not seen, being vainly puffed up by his fleshly mind,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and not adhering to the head, from which the whole body, being by means of joints and ligaments supplied and knit together, is to receive the divine increase.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>If you, then, have died with the Christ from the elements of the world, why are you, as if you were living in the world, troubled with these dogmas,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Touch not; taste not; handle not;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>which all tend to corruption by this improper use according to the injunctions and doctrines of those men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>These indeed have a show of wisdom in will-worship and humility and self denial. Are they not in some estimation for the gratification of the flesh?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Since you then have been raised up with the Christ, seek the things which are above; where the Christ is seated at the right hand of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Set your affections on the things above and not on the things of this earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For you have died, and your life is hid with the Christ in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When the Christ, our life, shall appear, then shall you also appear with him in glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Mortify, therefore, with regard to your members which are on earth, fornication, uncleanness, inordinate passions, wicked desire, and that licentiousness, which is idolatry,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>on the account of which things the wrath of God is coming on the children of disobedience,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and in which even you yourselves walked formerly when you lived among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But now lay ye aside also all these things, anger, wrath, malice, detraction, obscene discourse out of your mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Lie not one to another. Having put off the old man, with his deeds,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and put on the new man, which is renewed for knowledge after the image of him who created it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>where there is not Greek and Jew, circumcision and uncircumcision, barbarian, scythian, bondman, freeman, but the all, and in all, Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>put on therefore as chosen of God, holy and beloved, bowels of tender mercies, gentleness, humility, meekness, long suffering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>bearing with one another, and forgiving one another. If any one hath a cause of complaint against another; as the Christ hath freely forgiven you, so do ye.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And over all these put on love which is the band of this perfection;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and let the peace of God, to which you have been called in one body, rule in your hearts; and be ye grateful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let the word of the Christ dwell richly in you with all wisdom, when you teach and admonish one another; when with psalms and hymns and spiritual songs you sing gratefully to the Lord with your heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Indeed whatever you do in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to the God and Father by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Wives, be submissive to your own husbands, as is fit in the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Husbands, love your wives and be not imbittered against them</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Children, obey your parents in all things, for this is well pleasing to the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Fathers, exasperate not your children, lest they be discouraged</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Servants, obey in all respects them who are your masters according to the flesh; not with eye-service as men pleasers, but with singleness of heart, fearing God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and whatever you do, do it heartily as for the Lord, and not for men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>knowing that you will receive from the Lord the reward of the inheritance; for you are serving the Lord Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and he who doth wrong shall receive according to the wrong he hath done. There is no respect of persons.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Masters, render to your servants what is just and equitable; knowing that you have a master in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Continue in the constant exercise of prayer, watching there in with thanksgiving;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>praying at the same time for us also, that God would open for us the door of the word, that we may declare the mystery of the Christ (for which I indeed am in. bonds)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that I may publish it in the manner ought to do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Walk in wisdom towards them who are without, redeeming the time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let your conversation be always with courteousness, seasoned with salt, with a knowledge how you ought to answer every one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>With regard to my affairs, you will receive full information from Tychicus, the beloved brother, and faithful minister, and fellow servant in the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>whom I have sent to you for this very purpose, that he may know your situation and comfort your hearts;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>together with Onesimus, the faithful and beloved brother, who is one of you. They will inform you of the state of all things here.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Aristarchus, my fellow prisoner, saluteth you. So doth Marcus the nephew of Barnabas, concerning whom you have received letters of recommendation, If he come to you, receive him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Jesus also, who is called Justus, saluteth you. These are the only persons of the circumcision who are my fellow labourers for the kingdom of God. These have been a comfort to me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Epaphras who is one of you, a servant of Christ, saluteth you, always in his prayers making the most fervent supplications for you, that you may stand perfect and confirmed in all the will of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For I bear him witness that he hath a great zeal for you, and for those of Laodicea and Hierapolis.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Luke the physician, the beloved, saluteth you: so doth Demas.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Salute the brethren at Laodicea, particularly Nymphas and the congregation at his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when this letter hath been read among you cause it to be read also in the congregation of the Laodiceans; and read ye that from Laodicea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And say to Archippus, Be careful to discharge the office which thou hast received from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The salutation of me Paul with my own hand. Remember my bonds. The favour be with you. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>