<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, and Silvanus, and Timothy, to the congregation of the Thessalonians in God the father and the Lord Jesus Christ: Favour be to you, and peace, from God our father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>We give thanks to God always for you all, making mention of you in our prayers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>remembering incessantly the work of your belief, and the labour of your love, and the perseverance of your hope in our Lord Jesus Christ, in the sight of our God and Father;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>knowing, brethren beloved of God, the choice made of you</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>that our glad tidings did not come to you in word only, but with power, and with a holy spirit, and with much assurance. As you knew what manner of persons we were among you</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>for your sakes, you indeed became imitators of us, and of the Lord, having embraced the word in much affliction, with the joy of a holy spirit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>so that you became patterns for all the believers in Macedonia and Achaia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For from you the word of the Lord hath been sounded forth, not only in Macedonia and Achaia; but, in every place, your belief in God is spread to such a degree, as rendereth it unnecessary for us to say any thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For they themselves relate concerning us what an entrance we had among you; and how you turned to God from the idols, to serve the living and true God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and to wait for his son from heaven, whom he raised from the dead, namely Jesus, who delivered! us from the wrath to come</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>For you, brethren, yourselves know that entrance of ours among you, that it was not in vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Though we indeed had suffered before, and had been treated injuriously, as you know, at Philippi; we had the courage, by the help of our God, to declare to you the glad tidings of God with much earnestness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For our exhortation did not proceed from error, nor from impurity; nor was it with deceit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>but as we had been approved by God to be entrusted with the glad tidings, so we speak, not as pleasing men, but God who trieth our hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For never did we at any time use flattering words, as you know; nor a pretext for covetousness, God is witness;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>nor were we seeking human glory either from you or from others. We might have appeared with weight as Christ's apostles;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>but we were gentle among you. Our affectionate regard for you being such, as that with which a nursing mother would cherish her own children,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>we were willing to impart to you not only the glad tidings of God, but even our own lives, because you were dear to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>For you, brethren, remember our labour and our toil: for working day and night that we might not be burthensome to any of you, we proclaimed to you the glad tidings of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>You are witnesses, and God is witness, how holy, how just, how irreproachable our behaviour was to you who believed</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>how, as you know, we exhorted every one of you, as a father would his children,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>exhorting you, and comforting you, and testifying that you should walk worthy of God who inviteth you to his kingdom and glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>On this account also we give thanks to God continually, because, when you received from us this message of God, you embraced it, not as a word of men, but, as it really is, a word of God, which operateth with powerful effect in you who believe.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For you, brethren, became imitators of the congregations of God which are in Judea in Christ Jesus. Because you suffered from your countrymen the same treatment as they did from the Jews</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>(from those indeed who slew the Lord Jesus, and their own prophets, and persecuted us, and who please not God, and are in opposition to all men,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>hindering us from speaking to the nations that they may be saved; thus, filling up the measure of their sins continually: but the wrath is at last coming upon them,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>therefore we brethren, being torn from you for a short time in person, not in heart, did the more earnestly endeavour to see your face. Having therefore a longing desire,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>we wished to come to you, (particularly I Paul) once and again, but Satan obstructed us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For what is our hope, or will be our joy, or crown of rejoicing? Will it not be you in the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ at his coming?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For you are our glory and our joy.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Wherefore not being able to bear any longer, we acquiesced in being left alone in Athens,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and sent Timothy our brother, and a minister of God, and our fellow labourer in the glad tidings of the Christ, to establish you and comfort you concerning your belief;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>that none of you might be staggered by those afflictions. For you yourselves know that we are destined for this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>For when we were with you, we told you beforehand that we should soon be afflicted, as it hath actually come to pass, and you know;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>therefore not being able to bear any longer, I sent to know your faith, for fear the tempter might have tempted you, and our labour be in vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But Timothy having now come to us from you, and brought us the good news of your belief and love, and that you have always a good remembrance of us, earnestly desiring to see us, as we do to see you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>we therefore, brethren, under all our affliction and distress are comforted in respect to you, by your faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now because we live if you continue stedfast in the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>what thanks then can we render to God respecting you, for all the joy with which we rejoice on your account, in the presence of our God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>day and night supplicating in the most earnest; manner to see your face and to complete the remainders of! your belief!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>now may he himself, our God and father, and our Lord Jesus Christ, direct our way to you!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and may the Lord cause you to increase and abound in love for one another and for all men, (as we do for you)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>so as to establish your hearts unblameable in holiness, in the presence of our God and Father, at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ with all his holy ones.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Wherefore, as to what remaineth, we beseech you brethren, and exhort you, by the Lord Jesus, that as you have received from us how you ought to walk and please God, you would abound more and more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For you know what instructions we gave you by the Lord Jesus:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>for this is the will of God even your sanctification, that you abstain from fornication;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that every one of you know how to use his own vessel in sanctification and honour;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>not in lustful indulgence, like the nations which know not God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>not overreaching and injuring his brother in this matter; for the Lord is the avenger of all such things, as we told you before and testified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For God hath not called us for uncleanness, but to sanctification.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He therefore who rejecteth these instructions rejecteth not man, but God, even him who hath given us his holy spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>In respect to brotherly love you have no need of our writing to you, for you yourselves are taught of God to love one another,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and this indeed you practise to all the brethren, through all Macedonia; but we beseech you, brethren, to abound therein more and more;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and to make it your ambition to live quietly, and to mind your own business, and work with your own hands, as we charged you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>that your walk may appear orderly to the world, and that you may be in want of nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Now I would not, brethren, have you ignorant in respect to them who are composed to rest, that you may not be afflicted with grief, like others who have no hope.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again, so should we also, that God will, by the agency of Jesus, bring with him them who are composed to rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For this we tell you by a word of the Lord, that we the living who are left till the coming of the Lord shall not anticipate them who are laid to rest</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>that the Lord himself, with an authoritative command, with the voice of an archangel, and with the trumpet of God, will descend from heaven, and the dead in Christ shall be raised first;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>afterwards we who are left alive shall, together with them, be conveyed in clouds to meet the Lord in the air. And so we shall be forever with the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Therefore comfort one another with these words.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Now, in respect to the times and the seasons, you brethren, have no need of our writing to you;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for you yourselves know very well that the day of the Lord cometh as a thief at night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For whilst they are saying, there is peace and safety, sudden destruction is then upon them, like the pangs of a woman in travail, and they cannot escape.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But you, brethren, are not in darkness, that this day should break upon you at unawares as a thief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>You are all children of light and children of the day. We are not of night, nor of darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Therefore let us not sleep as others do; but let us watch and be sober.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For they who sleep, sleep at night; and they who get drunk are drunk at night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But as we are of the day, let us be sober, arming ourselves with the breastplate of faith and love, and for a helmet with the hope of salvation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Because God hath not stationed us for wrath, but to obtain salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>who died for us, that whether we wake or sleep we may live with him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>therefore comfort one another, and edify one another, as indeed you do.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now we intreat you, brethren, to consider them who labour among you, and preside over you in the Lord, and instruct you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and esteem them very highly in love on account of their work. Be at peace among yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And we exhort you, brethren; admonish the disorderly; comfort the desponding; support the weak; exercise forbearance towards all;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>see that none return evil for evil to any one; but on all occasions do all the good you can, both to one another and to all men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Be always cheerful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Pray without ceasing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Render thanks for every thing; for this is the will of God in Christ Jesus for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Quench not the spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Despise not prophesyings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Prove all things and adhere to what is good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Abstain from every appearance of evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And may the God of this peace himself sanctify you entirely! And may the whole of you: the spirit and the soul, and the body, be preserved blameless to the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He who calleth you is faithful, and will do this.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Brethren, pray for us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Salute all the brethren with a holy kiss.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>I adjure you by the Lord that this letter be read to all the holy brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The favour of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>