<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ, by the will of God, according to the promise of life which is by Christ Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to Timothy, my genuine son by belief, be favour, mercy, peace from God our father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>As I entreated thee, when I was going to Macedonia, to continue at Ephesus; that thou mightest charge certain persons not to teach a different doctrine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>nor pay attention to fables and endless genealogies, which rather promote disputes than the godly edification, which is by faith:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now the end of that charge is love, from a pure heart, and good conscience, and an unfeigned belief;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>from which some having swerved, have turned aside to vain discourse,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>desiring to be teachers of the law. not understanding what they say, nor about what they are so positive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>We know indeed that the law is good, if one use it as a law,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>considering this, that law is not enacted for a righteous man, but for the lawless and refractory; for the impious and sinful; for the immoral and profane; for murderers of fathers and murderers of mothers; for homicides,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>fornicators, sodomites, enslavers of men, liars, perjured persons, and whatever else is contrary to the wholesome doctrine</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>according to the glorious glad tidings of the blessed God with which I have been intrusted,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and am thankful to Christ Jesus our Lord who qualified me; for his counting me faithful, putting into office me</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>who was before a reviler, and a persecutor, and an outrageous offender: but I obtained mercy because I acted ignorantly, in unbelief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And this favour of our Lord superabounded with faith and love which is by Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>This is a faithful word and worthy of all acceptation, That Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners of whom I am a chief;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>but I obtained mercy for this purpose, that Jesus Christ might display the utmost forbearance in me, a chief, for an example to them who should afterwards trust in him for everlasting life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now to the king of the ages; the incorruptible, invisible, only wise God, be honour and glory, for the ages of the ages. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>This charge I commit to thee, son Timothy, according to the preceding gifts of prophesying conferred on thee, that by them thou mayst carry on this good warfare,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>having faith and a good conscience, which last some having discarded, they have, in respect to the faith, suffered shipwreck,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>of which number are Hymeneus and Alexander, whom I have delivered over to satan, that they may learn not to blaspheme.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I therefore exhort thee first of all, that supplications, prayers, intercessions, thanksgivings, be made for all men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for kings and all who are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life with all piety and honesty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>for this is good and acceptable in the sight of God our saviour,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>who willeth all men to be saved, and to come to an acknowledgment of truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For there is one God, and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>who gave himself as a ransom for all; as the testimony for his own times;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>for which I have been appointed a herald and an apostle, (I speak the truth in Christ, I do not lie) a teacher of nations in belief and truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I therefore give it in charge that the men pray in every place, lifting up holy hands, without wrath and surmise:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>in like manner also, that the women adorn themselves in comely apparel, with bashful modesty; not with curls, or gold, or pearls, or costly array;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>but with good works, as it becometh women who profess a reverence for God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Let women learn in quietness with all submission.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For I do not allow a woman to teach or to usurp authority over man, but to be in quietness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For Adam was formed first, then Eve;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and Adam was not deceived: but the woman being deceived was in transgression,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but to be saved by the child birth, if they continue in faith and love and sanctification, with a sober mind.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>This is a faithful word. If any one desireth the office of an overseer, he desireth a good work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The overseer therefore ought to be blameless, the husband of one wife, sober, discreet, well behaved, hospitable, qualified to teach,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>not addicted to wine, no striker, not attached to sordid gain, but of a gentle disposition, not quarrelsome, not a lover of money,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>one who presideth well over his own household, having his children in due subordination, with all gravity,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>(for if one doth not know how to preside over his own household, how can he take care of the congregation of God;)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>not one newly converted, lest, being lifted up with pride, he fall into the condemnation of the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He ought also to have a good character from those without, that he may not fall into reproach and the snare of the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Almoners in like manner should be grave, not double tongued, not addicted to much wine, not attached to sordid gain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>holding the mystery of the faith with a pure conscience;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and let even such be first tried, then, if found blameless, let them exercise the office of almoners.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Women in like manner should be grave, not addicted to slander, sober, faithful in all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let almoners be the husbands of one wife, presiding well over their children and their own households;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for they who discharge the office of an almoner well, acquire for themselves an honourable rank, and much freedom of speech in the faith which is in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>These things I write to thee, hoping to come to thee in a little time;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but if I be delayed, that thou mayest know how thou oughtest to conduct thyself in the house of God, that is in the congregation of the living God. The pillar and firm support of the truth is</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>(and unquestionably great is the mystery of this religion,) God hath been manifested in flesh, justified by spirit, hath appeared to messengers, been proclaimed among nations, believed on in the world, taken up in glory.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But the spirit saith expressly that in latter times some will apostatise from this belief, giving heed to seducing spirits, and doctrines concerning demons,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>through the hypocrisy of liars, who have their own conscience seared,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>forbidding marriage, and enjoining an abstinence from meats which God hath created to be partaken of with thankfulness by the faithful, and by them who are convinced of this truth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>that every thing which God created is good, and nothing to be rejected; for when taken with thankfulness</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>it is sanctified by the permission of God and prayer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>By suggesting these things to the brethren thou wilt be a good minister of Jesus Christ, nourished by the words of this belief, and this good doctrine, which thou hast followed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But as for vain and groundless fables, reject them, and exercise thyself for godliness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For bodily exercise is of little service, but this godliness is profitable for all things, having a promise of the present life and of that to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>This is a faithful word and worthy of all acceptation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>for it is for this that we both labour and suffer reproach, because we have trusted in the living God, who is the saviour of all men, especially of the faithful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Announce these things and teach them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let none despise thy youth; but be thou a pattern to the faithful in doctrine, in behaviour, in love, in spirit, in fidelity, in purity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Until I come apply thyself to reading, to exhortation, to teaching.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Neglect not the gift which is in thee, which was given thee by prophesy with the laying on of the hands of the assembled elders.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Meditate on these things; be intent upon them. That thy improvement in all things may be manifest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>take heed to thyself and to thy doctrine; continue in them: for by doing this thou wilt save thyself and them who hearken to thee.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Rebuke not an aged man with sharpness; but admonish him as a father; young men, as brothers;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>aged women, as Mothers; young women, as sisters, with all purity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Honour widows who are widows indeed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But if any widow hath children, or grand children; let these first learn to respect their own household, and to make suitable returns to their parents; for this is good and acceptable in the sight of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now she, who being really a widow and desolate, hath trusted in God, will continue in her supplications and prayers night and day;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>but she, who indulgeth herself in sensuality, is dead, though she liveth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Announce these things, that they may be irreprehensible.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now if any one doth not provide for his own, and especially for those of his family, he hath renounced his belief, and is worse than an infidel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let no widow under sixty years old be put on the list, Having been the wife of one man,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>is she eminent for good works? Hath she brought up children? Hath she exercised hospitality? Hath she washed the feet of the saints? Hath she assisted the afflicted? Hath she been assiduous to perform every good work?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>As for young widows, reject them; for when they become impatient of the restraints of the Christ, they will wish to marry,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>incurring blame for having violated their former engagement.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Add to this, that, being idle, they learn to ramble from house to house, and are not only idle, but are indeed tatlers, and intermedlers, speaking tilings which are unbecoming.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>My decision therefore is, that the younger widows marry, bear children, govern their families, give no advantage, no occasion of reproach to the adversary.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For some have already turned aside after satan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If any believer of either sex hath widows, let him or her relieve them, and let not the congregation be burdened, that they may relieve them who are really widows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Let the elders who preside well be accounted worthy of double honour, especially they who labour in word and doctrine;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>for the scripture saith, Thou shalt not muzzle an ox treading out corn, and, The labourer is worthy of wages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Receive not an accusation against an elder, but on the testimony of two or three witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Them, who sin, rebuke before all, that others may fear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I charge thee before the God and Lord Jesus Christ, and the chosen angels, to observe these things without prejudging, and to do nothing by partiality.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Lay hands upon no one hastily, nor be a partaker in the sins of others. Keep thyself pure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Discontinue the drinking of water, and take a little wine on account of thy stomach, and thy frequent indisposition.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The sins of some are so notorious that they go before them to judgment. Some indeed they follow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>In like manner also the good works of some are open and manifest; and such as are otherwise cannot be hid.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Let as many as are under a yoke of bondage account their masters worthy of all honour, that the name of God, and this doctrine, may not be reviled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And let not those who have believing masters disregard them because they are brethren, but serve them the more, because they who receive the good service are believers, and beloved. Teach these things, and enforce them by exhortation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>If any one teacheth otherwise, and doth not attend to the wholesome words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the doctrine according to godliness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>he is puffed up, knowing nothing, but raving upon questions and debates about words, from which proceed envy, contention, abusive language, evil suspicions,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>preposterous studies of men whose minds are corrupt and devoid of truth, who suppose this religion to be a matter of gain. From such withdraw thyself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now this religion, with contentment, is a great gain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For we brought nothing into this world; and it is evident that we can carry nothing out of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Having then food and raiment let us be content with these.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But they who determine to be rich, fall headlong into temptation, and a snare, and into many foolish and hurtful desires, which plunge men into ruin and destruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For the love of money is the root of all evil; to gratify which, some have wandered from the faith, and pierced themselves through with many sorrows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But thou, man of God, shun these things and pursue righteousness, godliness, faith, love, patience, gentleness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Maintain the good combat of faith. Lay hold on the life everlasting to which thou hast been invited, and of which thou hast made a good profession before many witnesses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I charge thee in the presence of God, who giveth life to all, and of Christ Jesus who witnessed before Pontius Pilate the good confession,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>to keep thyself, in respect to this command, unspotted, irreprehensible, until the appearance of our Lord Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>which, in his own proper times will be displayed by him, who is the blessed and only potentate, the king of kings and the lord of lords,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>who alone hath immortality, who inhabiteth light inaccessible, whom no man hath seen, or can see, to whom be honour and everlasting dominion. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Charge them who are rich in this present state not to be high minded; not to trust in uncertain riches, but in the living God who imparteth to us richly all things for enjoyment;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>to be beneficent; to be rich in good works, ready to distribute; willing to communicate,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>laying up for themselves a good deposit for the time to come, that they may obtain the life everlasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>O Timothy keep this deposit, avoiding the profane empty declamations, and the antitheses of that falsely called science,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>which some making a profession of, have, in respect to this belief, wandered from the mark. The favor be with thee. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>