<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to Timothy, a beloved son, be favour, mercy, peace from God our Father, and Christ Jesus our Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I thank God, whom I serve from my forefathers with a pure conscience, that I have so uninterruptedly the remembrance of thee in my prayers, night and day,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>earnestly desiring (when I call to mind thy tears) to see thee that I may be filled with joy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>recollecting that unfeigned belief in thee, which dwelt first in thy grand mother Lois and thy mother Eunice, and I am persuaded is in thee also:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>for which cause I remind thee to kindle up that gift of God which is in thee by the laying on of my hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For God hath not given us a spirit of cowardice, but of power, and love, and a sound mind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Be not therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me who am a prisoner on his account; but share with me in affliction for the glad tidings, according to the power of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>who hath saved us, and called us with a holy invitation, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose, and the favour which was granted to us in Christ Jesus, before the times composed of ages,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and which hath now been manifested by the appearance of our Saviour Jesus Christ, who hath put a stop to the operations of death, and hath brought life and incorruption to light by the glad tidings,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>for which I have been appointed a herald, and an apostle, and a teacher of nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For which cause also I suffer these things, but am not ashamed; for I know in whom I have trusted, and am persuaded, that he is able to keep that which I have deposited with him till that day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Use the form of sound words, which thou hast heard from me, with faith and the love in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Keep that good deposit by means of a holy spirit which dwelleth in us. This thou knowest,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>that all the Asiatics have withdrawn from me, of whom are Phygellus and Hermogenes'</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The Lord grant mercy to the household of Onesiphorus, because he often refreshed me and was not ashamed of this chain of mine;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>but when he was at Rome, sought me out diligently and found me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The Lord grant him to find mercy from the Lord in that day! Indeed, on how many occasions he ministered to me at Ephesus, thou thyself knowest very well.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Do thou, therefore, my son, strengthen thyself with the favour which is in Christ Jesus;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and what thou hast heard from me, in the presence of many witnesses, commit thou to faithful men, who will be able to teach others.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Do thou therefore endure hardships as a good soldier of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>No one going to war entangleth himself with worldly affairs, that he may please him who hath inlisted him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And if a man combateth in the public games, he is not crowned, unless he combat according' to the rules prescribed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The husbandman must labour before he partaketh of the fruits. 7 Consider what I say,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>and may the Lord grant thee understanding in all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Remember Jesus Christ, of the seed of David, raised from the dead according to these glad tidings of mine</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>for which I suffer even to bonds, as a malefactor; but the word of God is not bound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For this Cause I bear all things patiently for the sake of the chosen, that they also may obtain that salvation which is by Christ Jesus, with everlasting glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>This is a faithful word. For if we have died with him, we shall also live with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If we suffer, we shall indeed reign with him. If we deny him, he will deny us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>If we are unfaithful, he will continue faithful; he cannot deny himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Bring these things to remembrance, giving a solemn charge in the presence of the Lord not to dispute about words. It answereth no useful purpose. It tendeth to the subversion of the hearers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Study diligently to present thyself approved before God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed; handling rightly the word of truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And repress those profane empty declamations; for they will proceed on to farther impiety;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and like a gangrene the word of these men will spread, of whom are Hymeneus and Philetus,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>who have swerved from the truth, saying that the resurrection is already past; and subvert the belief of some.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Nevertheless the foundation of God standeth firm, having this inscription: The Lord knoweth them who are his; and Let every one who nameth the name of Christ depart from iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Now, in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and silver, but also of wood and potter's clay; and some indeed for honourable uses and some for meaner purposes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>If any one therefore purify himself from these he will be a vessel for honour, set apart and suitable for the master, ready prepared for every good work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Fly then the passions of youth and pursue righteousness, fidelity, love, peace with them who invoke the Lord with a pure heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And avoid foolish and ignorant debates, knowing that they generate strifes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now, the servant of the Lord ought not to be at strife; but ought to be gentle towards all, ready to teach, patient of ills,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>with meekness instructing opposers: perhaps God may grant them a change of mind so as to acknowledge the truth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>and they who have been captivated by the devil for his pleasure, may rouse and escape from his snare.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But know this, that in the last days there will be grievous times.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For the men will be selfish, avaricious, vain, haughty, addicted to slander, disobedient to parents, ungrateful, unholy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>void of natural affection, perfidious, false accusers, intemperate, fierce, destitute of love for goodness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with conceit, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>having a form of religion but denying the power of it. From such turn away;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>for of such sort are they who insinuate themselves into families, and lead captive weak women laden with sin, led aside by various lusts,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>always learning, but never able to come to a knowledge of truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so do these men withstand the truth, having their minds corrupted, being, with respect to this belief, such as cannot stand the test</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But they shall not advance much further; for the folly of these shall be exposed to the world, as that of those was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now as for thee, thou hast traced accurately my doctrine, my manner of life, my purpose, my belief, my long suffering, my love, my patience,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>my persecutions, my sufferings, what befell me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra; what persecutions I endured: but out of them all the Lord delivered me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Indeed all who wish to live holy in Christ Jesus will be persecuted,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and wicked men and impostors will grow worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But as for thee, continue thou in what thou hast learned; and in the belief of which thou hast been confirmed, knowing from whom thou hast learned them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and that, from thy childhood, thou hast known the holy scriptures, which are able to make thee wise for salvation by trusting in Christ Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>All scripture, given by divine inspiration, is indeed profitable for doctrine, for conviction, for reformation, for instruction in righteousness,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>that the man of God may be complete, thoroughly fitted for every good work.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I therefore charge thee in the presence of the God, and the Lord Jesus Christ, who is about to judge living and dead at his glorious appearance and reign,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>proclaim the word; be intent thereon, in season and out of season; convince, rebuke, exhort with all long suffering and doctrine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For a time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine: But when they have an itch of hearing they will, according to their own desires, heap up for themselves teachers,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>who will turn their attention from the truth, and they will be turned aside to fables.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Be thou therefore watchful on all occasions. Endure hardships: perform the work of a publisher of the glad tidings. Discharge thy ministerial office completely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For I am now about to be poured out as a libation; and the time of my departure is at hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>I have maintained the good combat. I have finished the course; I have kept the faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>As to what remaineth, there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, will give me on that day, not only to me, but to all who have loved his glorious appearance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Use all diligence to come to me quickly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For Demas, from a love for this world, hath forsaken me, and is gone to Thessalonica; Crescens, to Galatia; Titus, to Dalmatia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Luke alone is with me. Take Mark and bring him with thee; for he is useful to me for attendance,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>as I have sent Tychicus to Ephesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>When thou comest, bring the cloak which I left with Carpus at Troas, and the books, especially the parchments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Alexander the coppersmith hath lodged many false accusations against me. Let the Lord reward him according to his works:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Be thou on thy guard against him, for he greatly withstood our words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>At my first defence no one attended; but all forsook me. May this not be charged to their account!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But the Lord stood by me and strengthened me, that the proclamation might be made completely by me, and that all the nations might hear it. And I was delivered out of the mouth of a lion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the Lord will deliver me from every evil work, and save me for his heavenly kingdom. To him be the glory, for the ages of the ages. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Salute Priscas and Aquilas, and the household of Onesiphorus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Erastus staid at Corinth; and I left Trophimus sick at Miletus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Endeavour to come to me before winter. Eubulus, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren, salute thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The Lord Jesus Christ be with thy spirit. The favour be with you. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>