<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, to the twelve tribes who are dispersed abroad, Greeting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Count it, my brethren, all joy when you fall into divers trials,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>knowing that the trial of your faith operateth to produce patience.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Let patience then have a full effect, that you may be perfect and complete, deficient in nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And if any of you wanteth wisdom, let him ask it of God, who giveth to all liberally and upbraideth not; and it will be given him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But let him ask with faith, without wavering, for he who wavereth is like a wave of the sea, raised by the wind and tossed about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Let not therefore such a man think that he shall receive any thing from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>A man unsteady in his mind, is unstable in all his ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let the brother who is in low circumstances glory in his exaltation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and him who is rich, in his humiliation, because he shall pass away like a flower of the grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the sun riseth with its scorching heat, and withereth the blade, and the flower thereof failleth, and its beautiful appearance is gone. Just so will the rich man be blasted in his pursuits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Happy the man, who endureth a trial! because having stood the test, he will receive the crown of life, which the Lord hath promised to them who love him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Let no one when tempted say, I am tempted of God. For God cannot be tempted by evil, neither doth he tempt any one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But every one is tempted by his own desire, when allured and ensnared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In that case desire having conceived, bringeth forth sin, and sin, when grown up, produceth death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Be not led astray, my beloved brethren:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Every good donation, and every perfect gift, is from above, and cometh down from the father of lights, with whom there is no change, nor shadow of turning. 18 Of his own will he hath impregnated us with a word of truth, that we may be a kind of first fruits of his creatures.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Therefore, my beloved brethren, let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>for the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Therefore having thrown off all the filth and scum of wickedness, receive with meekness the implanted word which is able to save your souls;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and be doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving yourselves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>For if any one is a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like a man viewing his natural face in a glass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For having viewed himself, and gone away, he instantly forgot what manner of person he was.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>But whosoever hath looked carefully into the perfect law of this liberty, and continued therein; he being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of work, shall by his doing be happy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>If any one among you thinketh to be religious without bridling his tongue, he is but deceiving his heart. Such a one's religion is vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Pure and undefiled religion in the sight of our God and father is this, to take the oversight and care of orphans and widows in their distress, and to keep one's self unspotted from the world.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Do not, my brethren, exercise this belief of our glorious Lord Jesus Christ in partial regards for persons.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For if there should come into your assembly a man in splendid dress, having his fingers adorned with gold rings; and there should come in also a poor man in mean apparel;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and you should pay respect to the man in the splendid dress, and say to him, sit thou here in an honourable place; and say to the poor man, stand thou there; or, sit here below my footstool:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>have you not actually made distinctions among yourselves, and become ill principled judges?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Hearken, my beloved brethren, hath not God chosen the poor of this world to be rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom, which he hath promised to them who love him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But you have treated the poor with disdain. Do not the rich domineer over you? Do they not drag you to tribunals?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Do they not revile that honourable name by which you are called?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>If you fulfil a law which, according to the scripture, is indeed a royal one, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself, you do well:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>but if you have respect of persons, you commit sin, and are by that law convicted as transgressors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For whosoever is to keep the whole law and shall fail in one point, is guilty of all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For it having said, Thou shalt not commit adultery, hath also said, Thou shalt not murder. Now, if thou shall not commit adultery, but shalt commit murder, thou art become a transgressor of law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Thus speak and act thus, as you are to be judged by a law of liberty;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>for the sentence of judgment shall be without mercy for him who hath not exercised mercy, though mercy glorieth over a sentence of judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>What is the advantage, my brethren, though one should say he hath belief, when he hath not works? Can that belief save him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Suppose a brother or a sister be naked, or in want of daily food,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and one of you should say to them, go in peace: be warmed, and be fed to the full; and you do not give them the things necessary for the body, is this any advantage?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Just so it is in respect to this belief, if it hath not works; being by itself it is dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>One indeed may say, thou hast belief, and I have works. Shew me thy belief by thy works. As for me, I will shew thee my belief by my works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Thou believest that there is one God. Thou dost well. The demons also believe and tremble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But wouldst thou, vain man, know that belief without works is dead?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Was not Abraham, our father, justified by works when he offered up his son Isaak on the altar?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Thou seest that his belief co-operated with his works, and by his works his belief was perfected.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the scripture was fulfilled, which saith, Abraham believed God and it was reckoned to him for righteousness; and he was called the friend of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>You see then that a man is justified by works, and not by belief only.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>In like manner also, was not Rahab the harlot justified by works, having secreted the messengers, and sent them out another way?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For as the body without spirit is dead, so belief without works is dead also.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Be not, my brethren, many teachers; as you know that we shall receive a severer sentence;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for in many instances we all offend. If any one offend not in discourse he is a perfect man, and able to bridle in the whole body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Behold we put bits in the mouths of horses to make them obey us, and we manage their whole body.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Behold ships also, how large soever they be, though driven by hard gales are managed by a very small helm, and kept to the course which the pilot in tendeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>So also the tongue is a very small member, yet it boasteth great things. See what a great pile of wood a little fire kindleth to a flame!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Now, the tongue is a fire, the leader of iniquity; the tongue is set among the members, staining the whole body, and setting the wheel of nature in a blaze, when it is itself set in a blaze by hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For all kinds of beasts, and birds, and reptiles, and fishes, are subdued and have been subdued by man;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But the tongue of man none can subdue. It is an ungovernable monster: it is full of deadly poison.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>With it we bless our God and father; and with it we curse men, who are made after the image of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Out of the same mouth proceed blessing and cursing. These things, my brethren, ought not to be so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Doth the fountain send forth sweet water and bitter out of the same opening? 12 Can a fig-tree, my brethren, produce olives? Or the vine, figs? So no fountain can yield salt Water and fresh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Whoever among you is a man of wisdom and knowledge, let him, by a virtuous course of life, shew his works with the meekness of wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But if you have bitter zeal, and strife in your heart, do not boast and lie against the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>This is not the wisdom which cometh down from above; but that which is of an earthly, sensual, and devilish nature.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For where there is a zeal with strife, there will be confusion, and every thing which is bad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now the wisdom which cometh from above, is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, easily to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocrisy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And the fruit of this righteousness is peaceably sown by them who cultivate peace.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Whence come wars and fightings among you? Is it not from this; from those sensual appetites of yours which are at war in your members?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>You covet and use not. You kill, and envy, and cannot enjoy. You fight, and wage war, and do not possess, because you do not ask.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>You ask and do not receive, because you ask amiss, that you may lavish on your sensual appetites.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Ye adulterers and adulteresses! do you not know that the friendship of this world is enmity against God? Whoever therefore wisheth to be a friend of the world is adjudged an enemy of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Do you think that the scripture speaketh in vain? Doth the spirit which dwelt in us excite desire to envy?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>It granteth indeed a greater favour, therefore it saith, God resisteth the proud, and granteth favour to the humble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Submit yourselves therefore to God. Resist the devil and he will flee from you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Draw near to God and he will draw near to you. Cleanse your hands, ye sinners; and purify your hearts, ye double minded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Be afflicted and mourn and weep. Let your laughter be turned into grief; and your joy into con fusion of face.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord and he will exalt you. Speak not, brethren, against one another. He who speaketh against a brother, and judgeth his brother, speaketh against law, and judgeth law. Now if thou judgest law, thou art not a doer of law, but a judge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>There is but one judge: the lawgiver, who is able to save and destroy; who art thou who judgest another?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Come, now, ye who say, Today or tomorrow we will go to this or that city, and spend a year there, and traffic, and get gain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>when you do not know what will be the result of tomorrow. For what is your life? For it is a vapour which appeareth for a little while and then vanisheth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Instead of your saying, If it be the Lord's will, and we shall live, we will do this or that,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>you now boast of your arrogant projects. All such boasting is evil. Therefore to know what is good and not do it, is a sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Come, now, ye rich; weep, and raise a mournful cry for the miseries which are coming upon you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Your riches are corrupted, and your garments are moth eaten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Your gold and your silver are covered with rust; and the rust of them will be a witness against you, and corrode your flesh like fire. You have heaped up treasure in the last days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Behold the wages of the labourers who have reaped your fields, which you have withholden, raise a cry; and the outcries of these reapers have reached the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>You have lived luxuriously on the earth. You have indulged voluptuousness. You have pampered your hearts, as on a day of public feasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>You have condemned you have murdered the just one. Is he not setting himself in array against you?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Wherefore be ye, brethren, patient till the coming of the Lord. Behold the husbandman expecteth the precious fruits of the earth, waiting for them with patience, until it hath received the former and the latter rain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Wait ye also with patience. Strengthen your hearts, because the coming of the Lord is near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Repine not, brethren, against one another, that you may not be condemned. Behold the judge is at the door.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For an example of enduring adversity, and of long suffering, take, my brethren, the prophets who have spoken in the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Behold we call those sufferers happy. You have heard of the patience of Job, and have seen the Lord's termination? that the Lord is full of compassion and tender mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now above all things, my brethren, swear not, either by heaven, or by the earth, or by any other oath; but let your yes, be yes; and your no, no; that you may not fall under condemnation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Is any one among you afflicted, let him pray. Is any one cheerful, let him sing praises.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Is any among you sick, let him send for the elders of the congregation, and let them pray over him, having anointed him with oil in the name of the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the prayer of this faith will cure the sick, and the Lord will raise him up. And though he may have committed sin, he will be forgiven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Confess your faults to one another, and pray for one another, that you may be healed. The prayer of a righteous man under the divine impulse is very powerful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Elias was a man frail and mortal like ourselves. In one prayer he prayed that it might not rain, and it did not rain on the land during three years and six months.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And he prayed again, and the heaven gave rain, and the land bloomed with its productions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Brethren, if any among you hath wandered from the truth and another hath brought him back,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>let him know that he who hath brought back a sinner from the error of his way, shall save a soul from death, and cover a multitude of sins.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>