<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the sojourners of the dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia and Bithynia,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>whom God the Father, according to his predetermination hath chosen, that by a sanctification of spirit they may obey, and be sprinkled with the blood of Jesus Christ; favour be to you, and may peace be multiplied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who, according to his abundant mercy, hath regenerated us to a lively hope by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>for an inheritance incorruptible, incapable of defilement or decay, reserved in heaven for us</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>who are, during belief, kept safely by the power of God, for a deliverance prepared to be revealed in the last time;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>in whom you exult with joy though you are now for a little while, if it be necessary, distressed with divers trials;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>in order that your faith, which hath stood the test and is much more precious than gold which is of a perishable nature though tried by fire, may be found praise worthy, and honourable, and glorious, at the manifestation of Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>whom without knowing him personally you love; in whom though you do not now see him, yet you believe, and rejoice with an inexpressible and glorified joy,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>receiving as the completion of your faith the salvation of your souls:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>about which salvation the prophets, who prophesied concerning this favour for you, made diligent inquiry</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and search, trying to find to what time, and what manner of time, the spirit of Christ within them pointed, when it testified before hand the sufferings which were for Christ, and the glories which should succeed them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>to whom it was revealed that it was not for themselves, but for us, that they dispensed those things which have now been announced to you by them who proclaimed to you the glad tidings with a holy spirit sent from heaven; into which things angels have an earnest desire to look narrowly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Wherefore having girded up the loins of your understanding, being perfectly sober, keep your hope fixed on the favour to be conferred on you at the manifestation of Jesus Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>as obedient children, not fashioning yourselves in conformity to your former desires during your ignorance;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but as he who hath called you is holy, be ye also holy in the whole course of your life;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>for it is written, Be ye holy, because I am holy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And since you invoke, as father, him who without respect of persons judgeth every one according to his work, pass the time of your sojourning in fear;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>knowing that from that vain course of life, handed down to you from your fathers, you have been redeemed not with perishable things such as silver and gold,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>but with the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish and without spot,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>fore-ordained indeed before the foundation of the world, and manifested in these last times, for the sake of you</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>who by him believe in God, who hath raised him from the dead, and hath given him glory, so that you may have faith and hope in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Having, in obedience to the truth, purified your souls by the spirit for an unfeigned brotherly affection, love one another fervently with a pure heart,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>as you have been born again not of corruptible but of incorruptible seed, by the word of God, which liveth and endureth forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Because all flesh is as grass, and all the glory of man as a flower of grass. the grass withereth, and the flower thereof falleth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>but the decree of the Lord endureth forever, and this is the decree which hath been proclaimed as glad tidings for you;</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Therefore laying aside all malice, and all deceit, and every kind of hypocrisy, envy and slander,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>like newborn babes desire the pure milk of the word that by it you may thrive.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Since you have tasted that the Lord is gracious,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>to whom you are come as to a living stone, by men indeed rejected, but with God chosen and precious,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and you yourselves as living stones are built up a spiritual house, a holy priesthood to offer up spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>on which account also there is in the scripture this passage, Behold I lay in Sion a chosen, precious, chief corner stone, and he who confideth in it, shall not be ashamed,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>this honour then being for you who believe: but to the disbelieving, the stone, which the builders rejected that which was for the head of the corner,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>is indeed a stone of stumbling and a rock of offence. They disbelieving the word stumble at the thing for which they were laid:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>but you being a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people peculiarly set apart that you may publish the praises of him who called you out of darkness into his marvellous light</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>you who formerly were not a people but are now the people of God who were uncompassionated, but are now compassionated</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>beloved; I beseech you as strangers and sojourners to abstain from carnal lusts, which war against the soul:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>let your behaviour among the nations be virtuous, that when they speak against you as evil doers, they who have been eye witnesses may from your good works glorify God in the day of visitation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Be subject therefore to every human establishment for the Lord's sake, whether to a king as supreme,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>or to governor as persons sent by him for the punishment of evil doers, and for the praise of them who do well.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For it is the will of God that you should by such good behaviour curb the ignorance of foolish men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>As freemen, but not like those who use their freedom as a cover for wickedness, but as servants of God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>honour all men, love the brotherhood; fear God; honour the king.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>You who are servants, be subject to your masters with reverence, not only to the good and gentle, but also to the morose.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For this is pleasing, if from a conscientious regard to God one endureth grief suffering wrongfully.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For what glory is it, if when you commit a fault and are beaten, you suffer patiently? But if when acting well you meet with ill usage, and bear it, this is well pleasing in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For to this you have been called, because Christ himself suffered for you, leaving you an example that you should follow in his footsteps,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Who committed no sin, nor was guile found in his mouth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>who when he was reviled, did not revile again, when he suffered, did not threaten; but committed himself to him who judgeth righteously;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>who himself offered up our sins in his own body on the cross, that we, being freed from those sins, might live for righteousness; by whose stripes you have been healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>For you were like sheep going astray, but are now brought back to the shepherd and overseer of your souls.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In like manner ye wives, be subject to your own husbands, that if any of them disbelieve the word they may by the deportment of their wives, without a word, be won over,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>when they see your reverential, chaste behaviour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And let your adorning be, not that which is external by plaiting the hair with appendages of gold, nor finery of dress;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>but the hidden man of the heart, with the incorruptible ornament of a meek and quiet spirit, which is highly precious in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For thus, in former times, the holy women who trusted in God adorned themselves, submitting to their husbands,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>(as Sarah, whose daughters you are, obeyed Abraham, calling him lord) doing what was right, and alarmed by no terror.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Likewise ye husbands cohabit with your wives, paying respect to them as the weaker sex, and moreover as co-heirs with you of the grant of life, that there may be no impediment to your prayers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Finally, be all of one mind, sympathising with one another, full of brotherly love, compassionate, courteous</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>not rendering evil for evil, revile for revile; but on the contrary, blessing; knowing that you have been called for this, that you may inherit a blessing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For whoever desireth life; and loveth to see good days; Let him keep his tongue from evil, And his lips from speaking guile;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Let him depart from evil and do good; Let him seek peace and pursue it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Because the eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous, And his ears are open to their prayers: But the face of the Lord is against them who do evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Who then will hurt you if you be imitators of him who is good?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>But if you should even suffer on the account of righteousness, you are happy. Be not terrified with the fear of them, nor dismayed;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but sanctify the Lord in your hearts and be always prepared, in answer to every one who demandeth of you a reason for the hope which is in you, to make a defence with meekness and fear,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>having a good conscience, that when they speak against you as evil doers, they who calumniate your good conversation in Christ may be put to shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For if it be the will of God that you should suffer, it is better that you should suffer as well doers than as evil doers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Because Christ himself suffered once for sins, the just for the unjust, that he might bring us to God: being indeed put to death in flesh, but brought to life by that spirit</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>with which he went, and to the spirits which are now in prison</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>made proclamation at the time they were disobedient when the long suffering of God was waiting once for all in the day of Noe, while the ark was a building, in which a few, that be eight souls, made their escape during the flood;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>an antitype to which, namely baptism, (not a removal of the filth of the flesh, but an earnest conscientious application to God) doth now save us also, by means of the resurrection of Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>who, having gone to heaven, is at the right hand of God, angels and authorities and powers being made subject to him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Christ therefore having suffered in flesh for us, arm ye yourselves with this reflection, that he who hath suffered in flesh hath been stopped from sin,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>to the end that he may no longer live the rest of his time in flesh for the lusts of men; but for the will of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the past time of this life sufficeth to have wrought the will of the Gentiles, walking in lasciviousness, inordinate desires, excess of wine, revels, carouses, and abominable idolatries;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>at this they are surprized; and when you do not run with them into the same sink of debauchery, they rail.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They shall give an account to him who is prepared to judge living and dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For to this end also the gospel was proclaimed to the dead, that judged as they might be according to men in flesh, they might live according to God in spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now the end of all things is at hand, therefore be sober, and watch unto prayer,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and above all things have fervent love for one another: for this love will cover a multitude of sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Be hospitable to one another without grudging.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>According as every one hath received a free gift continue dispensing it to each other as good stewards of the manifold grace of God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>if any one speaketh, as speaking the oracles of God; if any one dispenseth, as dispensing out of a stock which God supplieth; that in all things God may be gloried through Jesus Christ, to whom belongeth the glory and the power, for the ages of the ages. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Beloved, be not surprized at the fiery trial among you, which is come upon you to try you, as if some strange thing had befallen you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>but inasmuch as you partake of the sufferings of the Christ, rejoice; that at the manifestation of his glory you may indeed rejoice with exceeding great joy. 14 If you are reproached for the name of Christ you are happy; because the spirit of the glory, even the spirit of God resteth on you. On their part indeed it is reviled, but on your part it is glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For let none of you suffer as a murderer, or as a thief, or a malefactor, or as a usurper of authority;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and if as a Christian, let him not be ashamed, but glorify God in this respect.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For the time is come when judgment is to begin at the house of God. And if it begin first with us, what must be the end of them who disregard the glad tidings of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>If the righteous scarcely escapeth, where shall the ungodly and sinner appear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Let them therefore who suffer according to the will of God, commit their souls to him in well doing, as to a faithful creator.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>With regard to the elders among you, being myself a fellow elder, and a witness of the sufferings of the Christ, and a partaker of the glory about to be revealed, I give them this exhortation</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Tend the flock of God which is among you, watching over it, not by constraint, but willingly; not with a view to sordid gain, but with a ready mind;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>not as exercising dominion over the lots, but as being examples to the flock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the chief shepherd shall appear, ye shall receive an unfading crown of glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Likewise ye who are young, submit to those more advanced in years. And being all submissive to one another; adorn yourselves with humility; because God resisteth the proud and granteth favour to the humble;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>therefore humble yourselves under the mighty hand of God, that he may in due time exalt you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Having cast all your care upon him, for he careth for you,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>be sober, be watchful: because your adversary the devil is walking about, like a roaring lion, seeking whom he may devour,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>him you should resist, standing firm in the faith, knowing that the same kind of sufferings are undergone by your brotherhood in the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Now may the God of all favour, who hath invited us to his eternal glory by Christ Jesus, when we have suffered a little may he himself fit, support, strengthen and establish you!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>To him be the glory and the power, for the ages of the ages. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>By Sylvanus the faithful brother I have, as I reckon, written briefly to you, exhorting, and testifying that this is the true favour of God for which you stand up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The congregation at Babylon salute you. So doth Marcus my son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Salute one another with a holy kiss. Peace be with you all who are in Christ Jesus. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>