<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>What was from the beginning; what we have heard; what we have seen with our eyes; what we have viewed attentively, and our hands have handled (with respect also to the word of the life</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>even the life was manifested, and we have seen, and testify, and announce to you, that eternal life which was with the Father, and hath been clearly manifested to us)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>that which we have seen and heard, we announce to you, that you also may have communion with us. Now this communion of ours is with the Father, and with his son Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And we write these things to you that your joy may be complete.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>This indeed is the message which we have heard from him, and announce to you, That God is light and in him there is no darkness at all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If we say that we have communion with him, and walk in darkness, we lie, and do not practise truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>But if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have communion with one another, and the blood of Jesus Christ his son cleanseth us from all sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>If we say that we have not sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If we confess our sins, He is faithful, and just to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If we say that we have not sinned, we make him a false speaker, and his word is not in us.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My children I write these things to you that you may not sin. But if any one sin, we have an advocate with the Father Jesus Christ the righteous,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he is an atonement for our sins, and not for ours only, but for those of the whole world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now by this we know that we have known him, if we keep his commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He who saith I know him, and doth not keep his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>But whosoever keepeth his word, in him indeed the love of? God is perfected. By this we know that we are in him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>he who saith he abideth in him, ought to walk as he walked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Brethren, I am not writing to you a new commandment but an old commandment, which you had from the beginning. This old commandment is the word which you heard from the beginning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Again I write to you a new commandment, a thing which is true in him, and in you. Because the darkness is past, and the light, the true light, now shineth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>he who saith that he is in the light, and hateth his brother, is still in darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He who loveth his brother, abideth in the light, and in it there is no stumbling block.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>But he who hateth his brother is in the darkness, and walketh in the darkness, and knoweth not whither he is going, because the darkness hath blinded his eyes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I write to you, children, because your sins are forgiven you on account of his name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I write to you, fathers, because you have known him, who is from the beginning. I write to you, young men, because you have overcome the evil one. I write to you, children, because you have known the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have written to you, fathers, because you have known him who is from the beginning. I have written to you, young men, because you are strong, and the word of God abideth in you, and you have overcome the evil one.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Love not the world nor the things in the world. If any one loveth the world, the love of the Father is not in him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh, and the desire of the eyes, and the pomp of this life are not of the Father, but are of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now the world is passing away, and the desire thereof; but he who doth the will of God shall abide forever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Children, the last period is come: and as you have heard that the Antichrist cometh, there are even now many Antichrists, by which we know that it is the last period.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>They went out from us; but they were not of us. For if they had been of us, they would have continued with us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>But to the end that they might be made manifest (because all are not of us) even you yourselves have an unction from the holy one, and know everyone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>I have not written to you because you do not know the truth; but because you know it, and because no kind of falsehood is of the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Who is the liar; but he who denieth that Jesus is the Christ? He is the Antichrist who denieth the Father and the Son:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>whosoever denieth the Son, hath not the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>As for you, therefore, let that which you have heard from the beginning abide in you. If that which you have heard from the beginning abide in you, then you will abide in the Son, and in the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>And this is the promise which he hath promised us, even the life which is everlasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>These things I have written to you with a view to them who are seducing you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>As for you, the unction which you have received from him abideth in you, and you have no need that any one should teach you. As then this unction itself teacheth you concerning all, and is true, and is not a falsity; abide ye in him as it hath taught you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>And now, children, abide in him, that when he shall appear we may have confidence, and not be made ashamed by him at his coming.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>If you know that he is righteous, you know that every one who practiseth righteousness is born of him.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Behold what a love the Father hath shewn us, that we should be called children of God: on this account the world doth not know us, because it did not know him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Beloved, we are now children of God. Though it hath not yet been manifested what we shall be, yet we know that when he shall appear we shall be like him: that we shall see him as he is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Now, everyone who hath this hope in him purifieth himself as he is pure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whosoever committeth sin, committeth a violation of law; for sin is a violation of law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Now, you know that he was manifested to take away our sins, and there is no sin in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whosoever abideth in him doth not sin: whosoever continueth to sin hath not seen him, nor known him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Children, let no one deceive you. He who practiseth righteousness is righteous, as he is righteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He who practiseth sin is of the devil, because the devil sinneth from the beginning; for this purpose the son of God was manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Whosoever is born of God doth not practise sin, because his seed abideth in him, and he cannot sin because he is born of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>By this the children of God are manifest, and the children of the devil. Whosoever doth not practise righteousness is not of God, nor he who doth not love his brother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For this is the message which you have heard from the beginning, that we should love one another,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and not be like Cain, who was of the evil one and slew his brother. And why did he slay him? Because his own works were evil, and his brother's righteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Wonder not, my brethren, if the world hate you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>We know that we have passed from death to life, because we love the brethren. He who loveth not his brother abideth in death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Whosoever hateth his brother is a murderer; and you know that no murderer hath everlasting life abiding in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>By this we know the love of God. Because he laid down his life for us, therefore we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whosoever hath worldly substance, and seeth his brother in want, and shutteth up his compassion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>My children, let us not love in word, and with the tongue, but in deed, and in truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>When we know by this that we are of the truth, let us in his presence persuade our hearts,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>in respect to what things soever our heart condemneth us, that God is greater than our hearts, and that he knoweth all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Beloved, if our heart doth not condemn us, we have confidence towards God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>and whatever we ask we obtain from him, because we keep his commandments, and do the things which are pleasing in his sight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Now this is his commandment, that we believe in the name of his son Jesus Christ and love one another, as he hath commanded us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And he who keepeth his commandments will abide in him, and he will abide in that man. And by this we know that he abideth in us, even by the spirit which he hath given us.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Beloved, trust not every spirit, but try the spirits whether they be of God; for many false teachers, are gone forth into the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>By this you know the spirit of God; every spirit which acknowledged! Jesus Christ come in flesh, is of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And every spirit which doth not acknowledge Jesus. Christ come in flesh, is not of God. This indeed is that of Antichrist which you have heard is coming, and is now already in the world:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>You, children, are of God, and have overcome them, because he who is in you is greater than he who is in the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>They are of the world, therefore they speak suitably to the world, and the world hearkeneth to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>We are of God. He who knoweth God, hearkeneth to us. He who is not of God doth not hearken to us. By this we know the spirit of truth and the spirit of error.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Beloved, let us love one another; for love is of God, and every one who loveth is born of God, and knoweth God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He who doth not love hath not known God, for God is love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>By this the love of God was manifested among us, because God sent his only begotten son into the world, that we may live by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>In this is the love; not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his son to be an atonement for our sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Beloved, if God so loved us; we surely ought to love one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>No one hath ever seen God. If we love one another, God abideth in us, and his love is perfected in us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>By this we know that we abide in him, and he in us, because he hath given us of his spirit;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and we have seen, and do testify, that the Father hath sent the Son to be the Saviour of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Whosoever will confess that Jesus is the son of God, God abideth in him, and he in God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now we have known and believed this love which God hath for us. God is love; and he who abideth in this love abideth in God, and God in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Love is by this perfected among us that we may have confidence in the day of judgment, because in this world we are as he is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>There is no fear in this love. This perfect love excludeth fear. Because fear is accompanied with torment, therefore he who feareth is not perfect in love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>As for us we love him because he first loved us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>If anyone saith, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar. For how can he who doth not love his brother whom he hath seen, love God, whom he hath not seen?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Besides, we have this commandment from him, That he who loveth God, love his brother also:</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Whosoever believeth that Jesus is the Christ is born of God; and every one who loveth him who begat, loveth him also who is begotten of him;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>by this we know that we love the children of God. While we love God, we keep his commandments;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>for this is the love of God that we keep his commandments. Now his commandments are not grievous,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>because whatever is born of God overcometh the world, and the victory which overcometh the world is our faith.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who is he that overcometh the world, but he who believeth that Jesus is the son of God?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>This Jesus is the Christ, whose coming was pointed out by water and by blood, not by the water only, but by the water and the blood; and the spirit is testifying this. Because the spirit is the truth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>because there are three that bear witness, the Spirit, and the Water, and the Blood, and these three are to one and the same thing,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>if we admit the testimony of men the testimony of God is greater, for this is the testimony of God, which he hath testified concerning his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He who believeth in the son of God hath this testimony in himself: he who doth not believe God, impeacheth his veracity, because he believeth not the testimony which God hath given concerning his son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Now this is the testimony, that God hath given us everlasting life, and this life is by his son:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>he who hath the son hath this life: he who hath not the son of God hath not this life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>These things I have written to you who believe in the name of the son of God, that you may know that you have everlasting life; and that you may believe in the name of the son of God:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>this also is the confidence which we have in him, that if we ask any thing according to his will he hearkeneth to us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Now, if we know that he hearkeneth to us in whatever we may ask; we know that we obtain from him the petitions which we have asked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>If any one see his brother committing a sin not unto death, let him ask, and he will give him life for them who do not sin unto death: there is a sin unto death, with respect to this I do not say that he should make petition.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Every act of unrighteousness is a sin; and there is a sin not unto death,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and we know that every one who is born of God doth not sin; he indeed who is born of God guardeth himself and the wicked one doth not cling to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>We know that we are of God and that the whole world is laid prostrate by the wicked one;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and we know that the son of God is come, and hath given us understanding that we may know him who is true; and we are in him who is true, and in his son Jesus Christ. He is the true God and the life eternal.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Dear children, keep yourselves from the idols. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>