<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The elder to Electa Cyria and her children whom in truth I love (and not only I, but all who have known the truth)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>on account of the truth which abideth in us, and will be with us for ever:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>with you be favour, mercy, peace from God the Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ the Son of the Father, in truth and love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I was greatly rejoiced because I found some of thy children walking in truth, as we received a commandment from the Father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I now intreat thee, Cyria, not as writing to thee a new commandment; but that which we had from the beginning, that we love one another;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and this love is that we may walk according to his commandments. This is the commandment, as you have heard from the beginning, that you may walk therein.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Because there are many deceivers come into the world, who do not acknowledge that Jesus Christ is come in flesh. (This is the deceiver, and the Antichrist)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Look to yourselves, that we may not lose our labour, but that we may receive ample wages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Whosoever transgresseth, and abideth not in the doctrine of the Christ, hath not God. He who abideth in the doctrine of the Christ hath both the Father and the Son.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If any one cometh to you, and doth not bring this doctrine, receive him not into your family; nor wish him success;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>for he who wisheth him success is a partaker with him in his evil works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Having many things to write to you, I determined not to commit them to paper and ink; but I hope to come to you, and deliver them by word of mouth, that our joy may be complete.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The children of thy sister Electa salute thee. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>