<book>
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A REVELATION of Jesus Christ, which God gave him, to shew to his servants things which must shortly come to pass, and which he sent by his angel, and signified to his servant John,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>who hath testified the word of God, and the testimony of Jesus Christ, and what he saw.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Happy he who readeth, and they who hear the words of this prophecy; and keep the things that are written therein! For the time is at hand!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>John to the seven congregations which are in Asia; favour be to you, and peace from him who is, and who was, and who is to come; and from the seven spirits which are before his throne;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and from Jesus Christ who is the faithful witness, the first born from the dead, and the sovereign of the kings of the earth. To him who hath loved us, and washed us from our sins with his blood,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and made us kings and priests to God, even his father to him be the glory and dominion for the ages of the ages. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold he is coming with clouds, and every eye shall see him, even they who pierced him; and for him all the tribes of the earth shall mourn. Yes, be it so.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I am the Alpha and the Omega, the beginning and the end, saith the Lord, who is, and who was, and who is to come, the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I John, who am your brother, and a partaker in this affliction, and in the kingdom and patience of Jesus Christ, was in the island which is called Patmos, on the account of the word of God and of the testimony of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I was in the spirit on the Lord's day, and I heard behind me a loud voice, like the sound of a trumpet,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>saying, I am the Alpha and the Omega; the first and the last, and what thou seest, write in a book, and send it to the seven congregations which are in Asia, to Ephesus and to Smyrna, and to Pergamus, and to Thyatira, and to Sardis, and to Philadelphia, and to Laodicea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Whereupon I turned to look towards the voice which spake to me; and upon turning about, I saw seven golden candlesticks,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and in the midst of the seven golden candlesticks one like a son of man, clothed with a robe down to the feet, and girded about the breast with a golden girdle;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and as for his head, the hairs like wool were glittering white as snow, and his eyes were like a flame of fire;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and his feet were like fine brass, as if they were glowing in a furnace; and his voice was like the sound of many waters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And he had in his right hand seven stars; and out of his mouth went a sharp two edged sword. And his countenance was like the sun shining in its strength.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And when I saw him I fell at his feet as one dead. Whereupon he laid his right hand on me, and said to me, Fear not. I am the first and the last,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>even he who liveth. Though I was dead yet behold I am alive, and live for the ages of the ages, Amen. And I have the keys of the mansion of the dead, and of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Write what thou hast seen, and the things which are, and the things which are about to be hereafter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>With respect to the hidden meaning of the seven stars which thou sawest in my right hand, and the seven golden candlesticks; the seven stars are the angels of the seven congregations and the seven candlesticks which thou sawest are the seven congregations.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>To the angel of the congregation at Ephesus write, Thus saith he who holdeth the seven stars in his right hand, who walketh in the midst of the seven golden candlesticks,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience, and that thou canst not bear with them who are evil, and hast tried them who pretend to be apostles, and are not, and hast found them liars,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and hast borne and dost exercise patience, and hast laboured for my name's sake, and hast not fainted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But I have this against thee that thou hast lost thy first love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Remember therefore from what thou hast fallen, and reform, and do thy first works; else I will come to thee quickly, and remove thy candlestick out of its place, unless thou reform.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>But thou hast this, that thou hatest the deeds of the Nicolaitans, which I also hate,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Whosoever hath an ear to hear let him hear what the spirit saith to the congregations. To him who overcometh I will give to eat of the tree of life which is in the midst of the paradise of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And to the angel of the congregation at Smyrna write, Thus saith the first and the last, who was dead and is alive,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>I know thy works, and thine affliction, and thy poverty, (though thou art rich) and the slander of them who say they are Jews, and are not, but are a synagogue of satan.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Be not terrified at what thou art about to suffer. Behold the devil will soon cast some of you into prison, that you may be tried; and ye will have tribulation ten days. Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee the crown of life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Let him who hath an ear hear what the spirit saith to the congregations. He who overcometh shall not be hurt by the second death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And to the angel of the congregation at Pergamus write, Thus saith he who hath the sharp two edged sword,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I know thy works, and where thou dwellest, even where the throne of satan is; yet thou holdest fast my name, and hast not denied the belief of me, even in the days in which Antipas was my faithful witness, who was slain among you where satan dwelleth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Nevertheless I have a few things against thee, because thou hast there them who hold the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balak to cast a stumbling block before the children of Israel, to eat things sacrificed to idols, and to commit fornication.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In like manner thou hast them who hold the doctrine of the Nicolaitans, which I hate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Reform. If thou dost not, I am coming to thee quickly, and I will fight against; them with the sword of my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Let him who hath an ear hear what the spirit saith to the congregations. To him who overcometh I will grant to eat of the manna which was laid up; and I will give him a white stone, and on that stone a new name written, which no one knoweth but he who receiveth it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And to the angel of the congregation at Thyatira write, Thus saith the son of God, whose eyes are like a flame of fire, and whose feet fire like fine brass;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>I know thy works, and thy love, and thy service, and thy faith, and thy patience, and that thy last works exceed the first:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>but I have a few things against thee, because thou sufferest that woman Jezabel, who calleth herself a prophetess, to teach and seduce my servants to commit fornication, and to eat things sacrificed to idols.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Though I gave her time to reform from her fornication, yet she hath not reformed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Behold I am about to cast her into a bed, and them who commit adultery with her into great tribulation, unless they reform from their works;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>and I will slay her children with death; and all the congregations shall know, that I am the searcher of reins and hearts, and will give to every one of you according to your works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>But to you I say, even to the rest at Thyatira, to as many as do not hold this doctrine, and who have not known the depths (as they call them) of satan; on you I will lay no other burthen, besides what you have;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>hold it fast until I come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>As for him who overcometh, and keepeth my works to the end, to him I will give power over the nations,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>(and he shall rule them with a rod of iron. Like vessels of potter's clay they shall be broken in pieces,)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>as I have received from my Father; and I will give him the morning star.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Let him who hath an ear, hear what the spirit saith to the congregations.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And to the angel of the congregation at Sardis write, Thus saith he, who hath the seven spirits of God and the seven stars. I know thy works, that thou hast the name of being alive, though thou art dead.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Be watchful, and strengthen the remains which are likely to die. For I have not found thy works perfect in the sight of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Remember therefore how thou hast received, and heard, and keep fast hold, and reform. For if thou wilt not watch, I will come against thee, as a thief, so that thou shall not know at what hour I shall come against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thou hast a few names even in Sardis who have not defiled their garments. These shall walk with me in white robes because they are worthy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>He who overcometh shall be clothed with white raiment, and I will not blot his name out of the book of life, but will acknowledge his name before my Father, and before his angels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Let him who hath an ear hem what the spirit saith to the congregations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And to the angel of the congregation at Philadelphia write thus saith the Holy one and the True, who hath the key the Son of David, who openeth and none shutteth, and who shutteth and none openeth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I know thy works. Behold I have set before thee an open door, and none can shut it. Because thou hast a little strength and hast kept my word, and hast not denied my name,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>behold I give thee some of the synagogue of satan, who say they are Jews and are not; but do lie. Behold I will make them come, and worship at thy feet, and know that I have loved thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Because thou hast kept the word of my patience, I will keep thee from the hour of trial which is coming soon on the whole world, to try the inhabitants of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Behold I am coming quickly. Hold fast what thou hast, that none may take thy crown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Him who overcometh I will make a pillar in the temple of my God, and he shall go out no more. And I will write on him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, (the new Jerusalem which cometh down out of heaven from my God) and mine own new name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Let him who hath an ear hear what the spirit saith to the congregations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And to the angel of the congregation of the Laodicians write, Thus saith the Amen, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation of God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot. I wish thou wert cold or hot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>So then; because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I am about to spit thee out of my mouth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>because thou sayest, I am rich and become wealthy, and have need of nothing, and knowest not that thou art wretched, and miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>I advise thee to purchase of me gold tried in the fire that thou mayst be rich, and white raiment that thou mayst be clothed, and that the shame of thy nakedness may not appear; and anoint thine eyes with eye salve, that thou mayst see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Whomsoever I love, I rebuke and chastise. Be zealous therefore, and reform.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Behold I stand at the door and knock. If any one will hearken to my voice and open the door, I will come in to him, and sup with him, and he with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>To him who overcometh I will grant to sit with me on my throne, as I have overcome, and sit with my Father on his throne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Let him who hath an ear hear what the spirit saith to the congregations.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>After this I looked and behold a door was opened in the heaven, and the voice which I heard at first like that of a trumpet speaking to me said, Come up hither and I will shew thee the things which must hereafter come to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thereupon I was immediately enrapt, and behold a throne was set in the heaven, and one was sitting on the throne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And he who was sitting was in appearance like a jasper and sardine stone, and there was a rainbow, in appearance like a smaragdine, around the throne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And around the throne there were four and twenty thrones; and on the thrones I saw the four and twenty elders sitting, clothed in white raiment and they had on their heads crowns of gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And from the throne proceed lightnings and thunders and voices. And there were seven lamps of fire blazing before the throne: these are the seven spirits of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And before the throne was a glassy sea resembling chrystal. And in the middle of the throne and around the throne were four animate beings full of eyes before and behind.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the first animate being was like a lion; and the second animate being was like a calf; and the third animate being had a face like a man; and the fourth animate being was like a flying eagle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the four animate beings had, each of them six wings around and underneath they were full of eyes. And they rest not day and night, saying, Holy, holy, holy, Lord God, the Almighty, who was and who is and who is to come!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when the animate beings give glory and honour and thanks to him who is seated on the throne, to him who liveth for the ages of the ages,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>the four and twenty elders are to prostrate themselves before him who is seated on the throne, and to worship him who liveth for the ages of the ages, and to cast their crowns before the throne saying,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thou, O Lord, art worthy to receive the glory and the honour and the power, because thou hast created all things, and at thy will they exist and were created.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And I saw in the right hand of him who was sitting on the throne a volume written within and on the back sealed with seven seals.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I saw a mighty angel proclaiming with a loud voice, Who is worthy to open the volume, even to loosen the seals of it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And no one in the heaven, nor on the earth, nor beneath the earth was able to open the volume and look into it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when I was weeping much because no one was found worthy to open and read the volume; even to look into it,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>one of the elders saith to me, weep not; behold! the lion who is of the tribe of Judah, the root of David, hath prevailed to open the volume and to loose the seven seals thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then I looked and behold in the midst of the throne and of the four animate beings and in the midst of the elders stood a lamb as if it had been slaughtered, having seven horns and seven eyes which are the seven spirits of God sent forth into all the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And he went and took the book out of the right hand of him who was sitting on the throne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And when he took the book, the four animate beings and the four and twenty elders fell down before the lamb, having, every of them, kitharas and golden cups full of incense which is the prayers of the saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And they sang a new song, saying, Worthy art thou to take the book and to open the seals of it, because thou hast been slain and hast purchased us for God with thy blood, out of every tribe and tongue and people and nation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and hast made us kings and priests for our God, and we shall reign on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And I looked and heard the voice of many angels around the throne and the animate beings and the elders and the number of them was myriads of myriads and thousands of thousands, 12 saying with a loud voice, Worthy is the lamb that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honour and glory and blessing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And I heard every created being which is in the heaven and on the earth and underneath the earth and those which are in the sea, even all in them, saying, to him who is sitting on the throne and to the lamb, be the blessing and the honour and the glory and the dominion for the ages of the ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the four animate beings said, Amen. And the four and twenty elders fell down and worshipped him who liveth for the ages of the ages.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And I looked when the lamb opened the first of the seals and I heard the first of the four animate beings say as with a voice of thunder, Come and see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I looked and behold! a white horse, and he who was mounted on him had a bow and a crown was given him and he went forth conquering and to conquer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And when he opened the second seal, I heard the second animate being say, Come and see?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And there went forth another horse of a fiery colour, and to him mounted thereon it was given to take peace from the earth and that men might slay one another; and a great sword was given him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And when he opened the third seal, I heard the third animate being say, Come and see? And I looked and behold! a black horse, and he who was mounted upon him had a balance in his hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I heard a voice in the midst of the four animate beings, saying, A choenix of wheat for a deniar and three choenices of barley for a deniar, but hurt not the oil and the wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when he opened the fourth seal, I heard the voice of the fourth animate being say, Come and see.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And I looked and behold! A pale horse, and one mounted on him, whose name was Pestilence; and the mansion of the dead followed him, and to them power was given to slay on the fourth part of the earth with sword and with famine and with pestilence, and by the wild beasts of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And when he opened the fifth seal I saw under the altar the souls of them who had been slain for the word of God and for the testimony which they had borne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And they cried with a loud voice, saying, How long, O sovereign, the holy one and the true, dost thou defer judging and avenging our blood on the inhabitants of the earth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And to every of them were given white robes and they were told that they should rest yet a little while till their fellow servants and their brethren who were about to be slain as well as they were completed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And I looked when he opened the sixth seal. And behold there was a great earthquake. And the sun became black as sackcloth made of hair; and the moon was like blood;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and the stars of heaven fell on the earth as a fig tree sheddeth its unripe figs when it is shaken by a mighty wind;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and the heaven recoiled like a scroll rolled up; and every mountain and island were moved from their places,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and the kings of the earth and the nobles and the rich and the chief commanders and the under officers and every bondman and every freeman hid themselves in the caves and among the rocks of the mountains,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>saying to the mountains and the rocks, Fall upon us, and hide us from the face of him who is sitting on the throne and from the wrath of the Lamb,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>for the great day of His wrath is come and who is able to stand?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after this I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth holding fast the four winds of the earth that no wind might blow on the earth or on the sea or on any tree.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I saw another angel coming up from the rising of the sun, having a seal of the living God; and he cried with a loud voice to the four angels who were empowered to hurt the earth and the sea,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>saying, Hurt not the earth nor the sea nor the trees until we seal the servants of our God on their foreheads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And I heard the number of them who were sealed: a hundred and forty four thousand were sealed of all the tribes of the children of Israel</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Of the tribe of Judah were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Reuben were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Gad were sealed twelve thousand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>of the tribe of Aser were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Nephthaleim were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Manasses were sealed twelve thousand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>of the tribe of Simeon were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Levi were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Issachar were sealed twelve thousand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>of the tribe of Zabulon were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Joseph were sealed twelve thousand; of the tribe of Benjamin were sealed twelve thousand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>After this I looked and behold! a great multitude, which no one could number, of every nation and of tribes and peoples and tongues standing before the throne and before the Lamb, clad in white robes; and palm branches in their hands;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and they cried with a loud voice, saying, To our God who is sitting on the throne and to the Lamb be ascribed this salvation?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Whereupon all the angels who stood around the throne and the elders and the four animate beings prostrated themselves before the throne and worshipped God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>saying, Amen! the blessing and the glory and the wisdom and the thanks and the honour and the power and the majesty be to our God for ages of the ages! Amen.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then one of the elders addressed me, saying, Who are these who are clad in white robes? and whence came they?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And I said to him, Sir, thou knowest? Then he said to me, These are they who have come out of great affliction and have washed their robes and made them white by the blood of the Lamb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>For this cause they are before the throne of God and serve him day and night in his temple. And he who sitteth on the throne will spread his tent over them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They shall no more hunger, nor shall they thirst any more; nor shall the sun dart upon them; nor any scorching heat:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>for the Lamb who is in the midst of the throne will tend them and guide them to living fountains of water; and God will wipe away every tear from their eyes.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when he opened the seventh seal, there was a silence in the heaven for about half an hour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I saw the seven angels who were standing in the presence of God, and to them seven trumpets were given.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And another angel came and stood by the altar, having a golden censer: and to him much incense was given, that he might offer it, for the prayers of all the saints, upon the golden altar which is before the throne.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the smoke of the incense for the prayers of the saints ascended from the hand of the angel before God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>the angel took the censer and filled it with some of the fire of the altar and threw it on the earth. And there were noises and thunders and lightnings and an earthquake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the seven angels who had the seven trumpets prepared themselves to sound.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the first angel sounded; and there was hail and fire mingled with blood which were thrown on the earth and the third part of the trees was burned up, and all the green grass was burned up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the second angel sounded, and something like a great mountain blazing with fire was cast into the sea; and the third part of the sea became blood;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and the third part of the creatures, which were in the sea and which had life, died; and the third part of the ships was destroyed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the third angel sounded; and there fell from heaven a great star blazing like a torch; and it fell upon the third part of the rivers and on the fountains of the waters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>(Now the name of the star is called wormwood.) And the third part of the waters became wormwood; and many of the men died of the waters because they were made bitter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the fourth angel sounded; and the third part of the sun, and the third part of the moon, and the third part of the stars were smitten, so that the third part of them was darkened and the day did not shine the third part of it and in like manner the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then I looked and heard an angel (as he was flying in mid-heaven) saying with a loud voice, Alas! Alas! Alas! for the inhabitants of the earth, because of the remaining sounds of the three trumpets which are about to sound.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And when the fifth angel sounded, I saw a star fallen from heaven on the earth. And to it was given the key of the pit of the bottomless gulf, and it opened the pit of the bottomless gulf; and a smoke ascended out of the pit like the smoke of a great furnace; and the sun and the air were darkened by the smoke of the pit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And out of the smoke there came forth locusts on the earth; and to them a power was given, as the scorpions of the earth have power;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and a charge was given to them not to hurt the grass of the earth nor any thing green nor any tree, nothing but the men only who have not the seal of God on their foreheads;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and they were enjoined not to kill these, but to torture them five months. And their torture was like the torture of a scorpion when it stingeth a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And in those days the men will seek death and shall not find it; and they will earnestly desire to die and death will flee from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now the shapes of these locusts were like horses prepared for battle; and they had on their heads as it were crowns of gold; and their faces were like the faces of men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and they had hair like the hair of women, and their teeth were like the teeth of lions;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and they had breast plates like breast plates of iron; and the sound of their wings was like the sound of chariots with horses rushing to battle,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and they have tails like scorpions and there were stings in their tails; and their power was to hurt men five months;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and they have a king over them the angel of the bottomless gulf, whose name in Hebrew is Abaddon, and in Greek he is called Apollyon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The first Woe is past and behold after these things there are two yet to come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the sixth angel sounded; and I heard a united voice from the four horns of the golden altar which is before God</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>saying to the sixth angel who had the trumpet, Loose the four angels who are bound at the great river Euphrates:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>and the four angels who were ready prepared were loosed for an hour, and a day, and a month, and a year, that they might slay the third part of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the number of the armies of the cavalry was two myriads of myriads: and I heard the number of them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and thus I saw the horses in the vision and them who were mounted on them having breast plates of fire, hyacinth and brimstone; and the heads of the horses were like the heads of lions; and out of their mouths issue fire and smoke and brimstone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>By these three the third part of the men was slain by the fire and by the smoke and by the brimstone which issue out of their mouths;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>for their powers are in their mouth and in their tails, for their tails having heads are like serpents and with these they do mischief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And when the rest of the men who were not slain by these chastisements neither reformed from the works of their hands so as not to worship the demons and the idols of gold and silver and brass and stone and wood which can neither see nor hear nor walk;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>nor reformed from their murders nor from their magical incantations, nor from their fornication nor from their thefts,</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I saw another mighty angel coming down out of heaven robed with a cloud, and there was a rainbow on his head; and his countenance was like the sun; and his feet were columns of fire,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he had in his hand a little book open. And he set his right foot on the sea and his left on the earth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and cried with a loud voice as a lion roareth. And when he had cried, seven thunders uttered their voices</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And when the seven thunders had uttered their voices I was going to write. And I heard a voice from heaven saying to me. Seal up those things which the seven thunders uttered and write them not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then the angel whom I saw standing on the sea and on the land lifted up his hand to heaven</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and sware by him who liveth for the ages of the ages, who created the heaven and the things therein, and, the earth and the things therein and the sea and the things therein, that there should no longer be a delay,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>but that in the days of the voice of the seventh angel, when he shall have sounded, as he soon will, the mystery of God shall be completed as he revealed the glad tidings to his servants the prophets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Then the voice which I heard from heaven spake to me again and said, Go, take the little book which is open in the hand of the angel who is standing on the sea and on the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>So I went to the angel and said to him, Give me that little book. And he said, Take it and eat it up; and it will make thy belly bitter, but in thy mouth it will be sweet as honey:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>so I took the little book out of the hand of the angel and ate it up; and it was in my mouth sweet as honey; and when I had eaten it up my belly was bitter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then he saith to me, Thou must prophesy again for many peoples and nations and tongues and kings.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And a measuring reed like a staff was given me, and the angel stood saying, Rise and measure the temple of God, and the altar, and them who are worshipping therein;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>but leave out the court which is on the outside of the temple and measure it not; for it is given to the nations and they shall trample the holy city forty two months.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I will give to my two witnesses and they shall prophesy a thousand two hundred and sixty days clothed in sackcloth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>These are the two olive trees and the two lamps which stand before the God of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And if any one attempt to injure them a fire issueth out of their mouth, and utterly devoureth their enemies. If any one indeed attempt to wrong them in this manner he ought to be slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>These have power to shut the heaven that it may not rain in the days of their prophesying; and they have power over the waters to turn them into blood, and to smite the earth with every calamity as often as they please.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when they shall be performing their testimony the beast which ascendeth out of the bottomless gulf will come to battle with them, and overcome them, and kill them,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and their corpses will be in the broad street of the great city which is spiritually called Sodom and Egypt where our Lord was crucified;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and some of the peoples and tribes and tongues and nations will see their dead bodies three days and a half and will not permit their dead bodies to be put in graves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And they who dwell on the earth will rejoice over them and be glad, and will send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented them who dwelt on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And after the three days and a half, a breath of life from God came upon them and they stood on their feet, and great fear fell upon them who beheld them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and they heard a loud voice from heaven saying to them, Come up hither; and they ascended up to heaven in the cloud and their enemies beheld them;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and at that period there was a great earthquake and the tenth part of the city fell and seven thousand names of men were destroyed by the earthquake. And the rest were terrified and gave glory to the God of heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The second woe passed away; and behold the third woe cometh quickly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then the seventh angel sounded and there were loud voices in heaven, saying, The kingdoms of the world are become the kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he shall reign for the ages of the ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And the four and twenty elders who were seated on their thrones before God fell on their faces and worshipped God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>saying, We thank thee O Lord, the God, the Almighty who is and who was and who is to come, because thou hast assumed thy great power and commenced thy reign.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The nations indeed were enraged and thy wrath came and the time for the dead to be avenged and for giving the reward to thy servants the teachers and to the saints and to them who fear thy name, small and great, and for destroying them who destroy the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the temple of God in heaven was opened; and the ark of his covenant in his temple was seen. And there were lightnings and noises and thunders and an earthquake and great hail.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And a great sign was seen in heaven, a woman clad with the sun, and the moon was under her feet and on her head a crown of twelve stars;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and being with child she crieth out being in labour and in the pangs of child birth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And another sign was seen in heaven and behold! a great red dragon having seven heads and ten horns and on his heads seven crowns;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and his tail dragged the third part of the stars of heaven and threw them on the earth. And the dragon stood before the woman who was in labour, that when she brought forth he might devour her child.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And she brought forth a masculine son who is to rule all the nations with a rod of iron. And this child of hers was suddenly conveyed away to God and his throne;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and the woman fled to the wilderness where she hath a place prepared of God that she may be nourished there a thousand two hundred and sixty days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And there was a war in heaven. Michael and his angels fought against the dragon; and the dragon and his angels fought;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but did not prevail, nor was their place any more found in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the great dragon was cast out that old serpent who is called The Devil and Satan who leadeth the whole world astray. He was thrown on the earth and his angels were thrown with him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And I heard a loud voice saying in heaven. Now is come salvation and the power and reign of our God and the authority of Christ himself; for the accuser of our brethren is cast down, he who accused them before our God day and night;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and they have conquered him by the blood of the lamb and by the word of their testimony and have not spared to expose their life even to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Therefore rejoice ye heavens and ye who dwell in them. Alas! for the inhabitants of the earth and the sea! for the devil is gone down to you in great wrath knowing that he hath but a little time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And when the dragon saw that he was cast on the earth he persecuted the woman who had brought forth the masculine child;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and to the woman were given two wings of the great eagle that she might fly to the wilderness to her place where she is nourished for a time and times and the half of a time from the face of the serpent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And the serpent spouted out of his mouth after the woman water like a river that she might be swept away by the stream;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and the earth helped the woman; and the earth opened its mouth and swallowed up the torrent which the dragon spouted out of his mouth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and the dragon was enraged at the woman and went to make war against the rest of her seed them who were keeping the commandments of God and maintaining the testimony of Jesus Christ.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And I was placed on the sand of the sea, and I saw a beast coming up out of the sea having seven heads and ten horns, and on its horns ten crowns, and on its heads a name of blasphemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the beast which I saw was like a leopard, and its feet as of a bear, and its mouth as the mouth of a lion. And the dragon gave it his power and his throne and great authority.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I saw one of its heads as if wounded to death; and this deadly wound of it was healed; and the whole earth followed this beast with admiration.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And they worshipped the dragon who had given the beast authority; and they worshipped the beast, saying, Who is like this beast? Who is able to fight with it?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And to it was given a mouth speaking great things and blasphemies. And power was given it to make war forty-two months.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And it opened its mouth for blasphemy against God, to slander his name and his tabernacle and them, who dwell in heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And power was given it to make war against the saints and to conquer them; and authority was given it over every tribe and tongue and nation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and it is to be worshipped by all the inhabitants of the earth whose names are not written from the foundation of the world in the book of life of the Lamb that was slain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If any one hath an ear to hear let him hear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If any one gathereth prisoners for captivity; into captivity he goeth; if any one shall kill with the sword; with the sword he ought to be slain. Here is the perseverance and the faith of the saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And I saw another wild beast coming up out of the earth; and it had two horns like a lamb; and it spake like a dragon;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and it executeth all the authority of the first beast in its presence and causeth the earth and its inhabitants to worship the first beast whose deadly wound was healed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And it performeth great signs so as to cause fire to come down out of heaven on the earth, in the sight of men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>and it leadeth astray the dwellers on the earth by the signs which it had power to do in the presence of the beast; commanding the inhabitants of die earth to make an image of the beast which had the wound of a sword and lived.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And power was granted to it to give breath to the image of the beast, so that the image of the beast might speak and cause all to be slain who would not worship the image of the beast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And it causeth all both little and great, both rich and poor, both freemen and slaves to receive a mark on their right hand or on their foreheads,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>and that none should buy or sell, but he who hath the mark, or the name of the beast or the number of its name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Here is wisdom. Let him who hath understanding calculate the number of the beast; for its number is that of a man and its number is 666.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And I looked and behold! a lamb was standing on the mountain Sion and with him a hundred and forty four thousand having the name of his father written on their foreheads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I heard a sound from heaven like the sound of many waters and like the sound of loud thunder. And I heard the sound of musicians playing on their kitharas</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and singing as it were a new song before the throne, and before the four animate beings, and the elders; and no one could learn the song, but the hundred and forty four thousand who had been redeemed from the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>These are they who were not defiled with women, for they are pure as virgins. These are they who follow the Lamb whithersoever he goeth. These were redeemed from among men; first fruits for God and the Lamb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And in their mouth there was no guile, for they were without blemish before the throne of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I saw another angel flying in mid-heaven having everlasting glad tidings to proclaim to the inhabitants of the earth even to every nation and tribe and tongue and people,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>saying with a loud voice, Fear God and give glory to him; for the hour of his judgment is come; and worship him who made the heaven and the earth and the sea, and the fountains of waters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And another angel followed saying, It is fallen Babylon is fallen! that great city; because she made all the nations drink of the poisonous wine of her fornication.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And a third angel followed them saying with a loud voice, If any one worship the beast or its image and receive its mark on his forehead or on his hand,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>he shall drink the venomous wine of God which is mixed up unadulterated in the cup of his indignation, and shall be tormented with fire and brimstone in the presence of the holy angels and in the presence of the Lamb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And the smoke of their torment riseth up for ages of ages. There is no rest day or night for them who worship the beast and its image, nor for any who receiveth the mark of its name.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Here is the patience of the saints! here they who keep the commandments of God and the belief of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Then I heard a voice from the heaven saying to me, Write, Happy the dead who die in the Lord henceforth! Yes, verily saith the spirit, that they may rest from their labours and their works accompany them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And I looked and behold! a white cloud and on the cloud one sitting like a son of man having on his head a crown of gold and in his hand a sharp sickle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And another angel came out of the temple crying with a loud voice to him who sat on the cloud, Put forth thy sickle and reap, for the time for thee to reap is come; for the harvest of the earth is ripe:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and he who was sitting on the cloud put forth his sickle on the earth and the earth was reaped.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And another angel came out of the temple in the heaven and he also had a sharp sickle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And another angel came out from the altar, having power over the fire and he cried with a loud voice to him who had the sharp sickle saying, Put forth that sharp sickle of thine and gather the clusters of the vine of the earth; for its grapes are ripe:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and the angel put forth his sickle on the earth and gathered the grapes of the vine of the earth and cast them into the great wine press of the wrath of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and the wine press was trodden without the city; and blood flowed out of the wine press up to the bridles of the horses for a thousand and six hundred furlongs.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then I saw another sign in heaven great and wonderful: seven angels having the seven last plagues because by them the wrath of God was finished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I saw as it were a sea of glass mingled with fire, and them who were victorious over the beast and over its image and over the number of its name, standing at the glassy sea having the musical instruments of God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and they sing the song of Moses the servant of God and the song of the lamb, saying, Great and marvellous are thy works, Lord, God, Almighty; Just and true are thy ways O thou king of the saints;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Who would not fear thee, O Lord, and glorify thy name? For thou alone art perfect. For all the nations will come and worship before thee, For thy rules of rectitude are made manifest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And after that I looked and behold! the temple of the tabernacle of the testimony in heaven was opened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And the seven angels having the seven plagues came out of the temple, clad in clean white linen and having their breasts girded with golden girdles.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And one of the four animate beings gave the seven angels seven golden vials full of the wrath of God who liveth for the ages of the ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the temple was filled with smoke because of the glory of God and of his majesty, so that no one could enter the temple until the seven plagues of the seven angels were finished.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And I heard a loud voice out of the temple saying to the seven angels, Go and pour out the vials of the wrath of God on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And the first angel went and poured out his vial on the earth; and there came a malignant and grievous ulcer upon the men, who had the mark of the beast, and on them who worshipped its image.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And the second angel poured out his vial on the sea, and it became as the blood of one dead; and every living creature in the sea died.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the third angel poured out his vial on the rivers, and on the fountains of waters; and they became blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And I heard the angel of the waters saying, Righteous art thou, O Lord, who art and who wast and who art to come, because thou hast passed these judgments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because they poured out the blood of thy saints and prophets, therefore thou hast given them blood to drink, for they deserve it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And I heard another from the altar, saying, Yes, Lord, God, Almighty, thy judgments are true and righteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>And the fourth angel poured out his vial on the sun; and power was given to it to scorch men with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the men were scorched with great heat; and they blasphemed the name of God who hath power over these plagues and did not reform to give glory to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the fifth angel poured out his vial on the throne of the beast, and its kingdom was darkened; and they gnawed their tongues for pain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and blasphemed the God of heaven because of their pain, and because of their ulcers, and did not reform from their works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And the sixth angel poured out his vial on the river the great river Euphrates, and the water thereof was dried up that a way might be prepared for the kings from the rising of the sun.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And I saw three unclean spirits like frogs, coming out of the mouth of the dragon and out of the mouth of the beast, and out of the mouth of the false prophet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>For these are spirits of demons making signs which go forth to the kings of the earth and the whole world, to gather them together to the battle of the great day of God the Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>(Behold my coming is as a thief cometh: Happy he who watcheth and keepeth his garments that he may not walk naked and expose his shame.)</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And when he had gathered them together to the place which is called in Hebrew Armageddon</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>then the seventh angel poured out his vial in the air: and there came a loud voice out of the temple in heaven from the throne saying, It is done.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And there were noises and thunders and lightnings and there was a great earthquake, such, that there had not been since men were on the earth such an extensive, so great a shock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the great city was divided into three parts; and the cities of the nations fell; and Babylon the great came into remembrance before God to give her the cup of the venemous wine of his indignation;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>and every island fled; and mountains were not found;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and great hail like talent weights pour down from heaven on the men; and the men blasphemed God, because of the plague of the hail; for the plague of the hail was very great.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then one of the seven angels who had the seven vials came to me and talked with me, saying to me, Come let me shew thee the judgment of the great harlot that sitteth on the many waters,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>with whom the kings of the earth have committed fornication, and the inhabitants of the earth have been made drunk with the wine of her fornication.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And he carried me away in spirit to a wilderness; and I saw a woman sitting on a scarlet beast full of blasphemous names, which had seven heads and ten horns.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the woman was clad in purple and scarlet and adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls; and she had in her hand a golden cup full of the abominations and impurity of her fornication;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>and on her forehead there was a name written, Mystery, Babylon The Great, the mother of the harlots and the abominations of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I saw the woman drunk with the blood of the saints and with the blood of the witnesses of Jesus; and when I saw her I expressed my astonishment with great amaze.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And the angel said to me, Why art thou amazed? I will tell thee the mystery of this woman and of the beast which carrieth her, which hath seven heads and ten horns.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The beast which thou sawest was and is not and is soon to ascend out of the bottomless gulf and go to destruction; and the inhabitants of the earth, whose names are not written in the book of life from the foundation of the world will wonder when they see the beast, because it was and is not although indeed it is.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Let the mind which hath wisdom attend. The seven heads are seven mountains on which the woman sitteth</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>and they are seven kings. Five have fallen, and one is and the other is not yet come; and when he hath come he must continue but a little while;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>and the beast, which was and is not, is itself the eighth and is of the seven and goeth to destruction;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and the ten horns which thou sawest are ten kings who have not yet received a kingdom, but are about to take authority as kings one short period of time with the beast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>These have one mind and will transfer their power and authority to the beast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>These will make war against the lamb, and the lamb will overcome them; for he is Lord of lords and King of kings; and they who are with him are called and chosen and faithful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Then he saith to me, The waters which thou sawest where the harlot sitteth are peoples, and multitudes and nations and tongues:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and with regard to the ten horns which thou sawest on the beast, these will hate the harlot and will make her desolate and naked and devour her flesh, and burn her with fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>For God hath put it into their hearts to execute his sentence and to execute one design and to give their kingdom to the beast until the words of God are accomplished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Now the woman which thou sawest is that great city which hath sovereignty over the kings of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after this I saw another angel coming down out of heaven having great authority; and the earth was illumined with his glory;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he cried mightily, saying with a loud voice, It is fallen! Babylon the great is fallen, and is become the habitation of demons, and a hold of every unclean spirit, and a cage of every unclean and hateful bird,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>because all the nations have drunk of the poison of her fornication and the kings of the earth have committed fornication with her, and the merchants of the earth have been enriched by the abundance of her luxury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And I heard another voice out of heaven saying, Come out of her, my people, that you may not partake of her sins and that you may not receive of her punishments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Because her sins have reached to heaven and God hath remembered her acts of injustice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>render to her as she hath rendered to you and requite her double according to her works. In the cup in which she mingled, mingle for her a double portion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>In proportion to her ostentation and luxury inflict on her torment and grief. Because she saith in her heart, I am enthroned a queen and am not a widow, and shall not see sorrow;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>therefore in one day these calamities shall come upon her, pestilence and sorrow and famine; and she shall be consumed with fire; for the Lord God who judgeth her is mighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And the kings of the earth who have committed fornication and lived luxuriously with her will wail and beat their breasts for her, when they see the smoke of her burning</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>standing afar off for fear of her torment, saying, Alas! Alas! that great city Babylon! that 'mighty city! for in one hour thy judgment is come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The merchants of the earth also will weep and mourn for her; because no one any more buyeth their merchandize</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>the merchandize of gold and silver and precious stones and pearls; and of cotton and purple and silk and scarlet; and every sort of odoriferous wood and the various wares of ivory and of most precious wood and of brass and iron and marble,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and cinnamon and frankincense and myrrh and incense and wine and oil and fine flour and wheat and cattle and sheep and horses and chariots and the bodies and souls of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Even the autumnal fruits, thy soul's desire are gone from thee; and all these delicious and all those splendid things are gone from thee and thou shalt find them no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The venders of these things who have been enriched by her will stand far off for fear of her torment, weeping and wailing</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>and saying, Alas! Alas! the great city! she that was clothed with cotton and purple and scarlet and adorned with gold and precious stones and pearls!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>for in one hour what a mass of wealth is laid waste! And every one sailing to the place, both mariners and traffickers by sea stood afar off</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>and screamed when they saw the smoke of her burning, saying, What city was like this great city?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and they put dust on their heads and cried weeping and wailing and saying, Alas! Alas! the great city by which all who have ships at sea were enriched by means of her wealth; for in one hour she is desolated.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Rejoice over her, O heaven! and ye holy apostles and prophets; for God hath avenged you on her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Then a mighty angel took up a stone like a great millstone and cast it into the sea saying, Thus with violence shall Babylon that great city be dashed down and shall be found no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And the sound of harpers and of musicians and of pipers and of trumpeters shall no more be heard in thee. And no artist of any kind shall ever be found in thee again. And the sound of a millstone shall never be heard in thee again;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>nor shall the light of a lamp ever shine in thee any more, nor the voice of a bridegroom and bride ever be heard in thee; for thy merchants were the nobles of the earth; for by thy bewitching arts all the nations were led astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>And in her was found the blood of prophets and saints and of all who were slain on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>And after this I heard a loud voice of a great multitude in heaven, saying, Alleluia! the salvation and the glory and the honour and the power be to the Lord our God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>for true and righteous are his judgments; for he hath passed sentence on the great harlot who corrupted the earth with her fornication; and hath avenged the blood of his servants, at her hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>(And again they said, alleluia!) and the smoke of her goeth up for the ages of the ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And the four and twenty elders and the four animate beings fell down and worshipped God who sat on the throne, saying, Amen. Alleluia.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And there came out from the throne a voice, saying, Praise our God, all ye his servants and ye who fear him, both small and great.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>And I heard as it were a voice of a great multitude and as a sound of many waters, and as it were a peal of mighty thunder saying, Alleluia. Because the Lord God the Omnipotent reigneth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>let us rejoice and exult with joy and ascribe to him the glory; for the marriage of the lamb is come and his spouse hath made herself ready</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and it hath been granted her, that she should be arrayed in a cotton robe clean and white for this cotton is the righteous acts of the saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then the angel saith to me, Write, Happy they who are invited to the marriage supper of the lamb! then he saith to me, These are the true words of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Whereupon I fell down at his feet to worship him. And he saith to me, See thou do not. I am the fellow servant of thee and of thy brethren who have the testimony of Jesus. Worship God. For the spirit of this prophecy is the testimony of Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then I saw the heaven opened and behold a white horse I and he who was mounted on him was called; Faithful And True, and with righteousness he judgeth and maketh war.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>His eyes are like a flame of fire; and on his head are many crowns and he hath a name written which no one but himself knoweth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>and he was clothed with a mantle dipped in blood; and his name is The Word or God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the armies in heaven clad in cotton robes white and clean followed him on white horses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And out of his mouth issueth a sharp sword that with it he may smite the nations. And he himself tendeth them with an iron crook; and he himself treadeth the press of the venemous and raging wine of God Almighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And he hath on his mantle and on his thigh this name written King Of Kings And Lord Of Lords.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And I saw an angel standing in the sun and he cried with a loud voice to all the birds which fly in mid-heaven saying, Come and gather yourselves together to the supper of the great God;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>that you may eat the flesh of kings and the flesh of generals, and the flesh of mighty men, and the flesh of horses and of them mounted on them and the flesh of all both freemen and slaves, both small and great.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And I saw the beast and the kings of the earth and their armies assembled to come to a battle with him who was mounted on the horse and with his army.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And the beast was taken and with him the false prophet who did these signs before him by which he led astray them who had received the mark of the beast, and them who worshipped his image. Both these were cast alive into the lake of fire burning with brimstone;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>and the rest were slain with the sword of him who was mounted on the horse; with that which issueth out of his mouth; and all the birds were glutted with their flesh.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then I saw an angel coming down out of heaven, having the key of the bottomless gulf and a great chain in his hand;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and he laid hold on the dragon, the old serpent which is the Devil and Satan and bound him a thousand years</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>and cast him into the bottomless gulf and shut him up, and sealed it on him that he might not lead the nations astray any more until the thousand years were ended. And after that he must be loosed for a short time.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And I saw thrones and to them who sat on them judgment was given, and I saw the souls of them who had been slain for the testimony of Jesus and for the word of God and who had not worshipped the beast nor its image, nor received the mark on their forehead or on their hand. And they lived and reigned with the Christ the thousand years;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>but the rest of the dead did not revive until the thousand years were completed. This is the first resurrection.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Happy and holy is he who hath a portion in this first resurrection. Over them the second death hath no power, but they shall be priests of God and the Christ and shall reign with him a thousand years.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And when the thousand years are ended Satan will be let loose from his prison</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>and will go forth to seduce the nations which are in the four corners of the earth Gog and Magog to assemble them for battle; the number of whom will be as the sand of the sea.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>And they came up on the breadth of the earth and surrounded the camp of the saints and the beloved city, and fire came down from God out of heaven and devoured them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And the Devil who was seducing them was cast into the lake of fire and brimstone where the beast and the false prophet are; and they shall be tormented day and night for the ages of the ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Then I saw a great white throne and him who sat thereon from whose presence the earth and the heaven fled away and there was no place found for them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>And I saw the dead, small and great, standing before God. And books were opened; and another book was opened namely that of Life. And the dead were judged by the writings in those books according to their works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And the sea delivered up the dead in it; and death and the mansion of the dead delivered up the dead in them; and they were judged, every one according to his works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And death and the mansion of the dead were cast into the lake of fire. This is the second death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And whoever was not found written in the book of life was thrown into the lake of fire.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth; for the former heaven and the former earth were passed away and the sea is no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And I John saw the holy city, the new Jerusalem coming down from God out of heaven, prepared like a bride adorned for her husband.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And I heard a loud voice from heaven saying, Behold the tabernacle of God with men! and he will dwell with them; and they will be his people; and God himself will be with them their God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And God will wipe away every tear from their eyes. And there shall no more be death; nor shall grief, nor screaming, nor pain be any more; for the former things are gone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And he who sat on the throne said, Behold I make all things new. Then he saith to me, Write that these words are true and faithful;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>and he said to me, It is done; I am the Alpha and the Omega the beginning and the end; to him who thirsteth I will give without cost from the fountain of the water of life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He who overcometh shall inherit all things; and I will be his God and he shall be my son:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>but the cowards and the unbelieving and abominable and murderers and prostitutes, and sorcerers and idolaters and all liars shall have their portion in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone. This is the second death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then one of the angels who had the seven vials full of the seven last plagues came to me and spoke to me saying, Come let me shew thee the bride the Lamb's wife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And he carried me away in spirit to a great and high mountain and shewed me the great city: the holy Jerusalem coming down out of heaven from God,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>having the glory of God. And its lustre was like a most precious stone, like a jasper shining as chrystal;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>and it had a great and high wall with twelve gates and at the gates twelve angels and on the gates were graven the names of the twelve tribes of the children of Israel</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>On the east three gates; on the north three gates; on the south three gates; on the west three gates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And the wall of the city had twelve foundations on which were the names of the twelve apostles of the Lamb.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And he who was talking with me had a golden reed to measure the city and its gates and its wall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Now the city is a square and its length is as much as its breadth. And he measured the city with the rod twelve thousand furlongs; the length and the breadth and the height are equal. 17 And he measured its wall, a hundred and forty four cubits, the measure of a man which is that of an angel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>---</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And its wall was built of jasper and the city was pure gold, like clear glass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>And the foundations of the wall of the city were adorned with every precious stone. The first foundation was jasper; and the second, sapphire; the third, chalcedony; the fourth, emerald;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>the fifth, sardonyx; the sixth, sardus; the seventh, chrysolite; the eighth, beryl; the ninth, topaz; the tenth, chrysoprasus; the eleventh, hyacinth; the twelfth, amethyst.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>And the twelve gates were twelve pearls. Every several gate was of one pearl. And the street of the city was pure gold, like transparent glass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And in it I saw no temple; for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb is its temple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>And the city had no need of the sun nor of the moon to enlighten it; for the glory of God enlightened it; and the lamb is its lamp:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>and the nations of the saved will walk in its light; and the kings of the earth will bring their glory and honour into it;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>and its gates shall not be shut by day; for there shall be no night there.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>And the glory and the honour of the nations shall be brought to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>And there shall in no wise enter into it any thing which defileth or maketh an abomination or uttereth a lie; none but they who are enrolled in the Lamb's book of life.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Then he shewed me a pure river of the water of life, clear as chrystal, issuing from the throne of God and the lamb;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>and in the middle of the broad street of the city on both sides of the river at proper distances there was a tree of life bearing twelve crops of fruit, yielding its fruit every month and the leaves of the tree are to heal the nations.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>And nothing subject to a curse shall ever be there; but the throne of God and of the Lamb shall be in it, and his servants shall serve him</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>and see his face; and his name shall be on their foreheads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And there shall be no night there; nor have they any need of a lamp or of the light of the sun; for the Lord God giveth them light; and they shall reign for the ages of the ages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Then he said to me, These words are faithful and true. And the Lord the God of the holy prophets hath sent his angel to shew his servants what must shortly come to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold I am coming quickly. Happy he who keepeth the words of the prophecy of this book.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Now, I John saw and heard these things. And when I had heard and seen I prostrated myself to worship at the feet of the angel who pointed them out to me;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>and he saith to me, See thou do not: I am a fellow servant of thee and of thy brethren the prophets and of them who keep the words of this book: Worship God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Then he saith to me, seal not up the words of the prophecy of this book for the time is near.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Let him who is unjust be unjust still and him who is polluted be polluted still; and let the just be still just and the holy still holy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now behold I am coming quickly and my reward is with me to render to every one as his work shall be.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>I am the Alpha and the Omega: the beginning and the end; the first and the last.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Happy they who perform his commandments that they may have access to the tree of life and enter by the gates into the city:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>but without are the dogs and the sorcerers and the prostitutes and the murderers and the idolaters and every one who loveth and practiseth falsehood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I Jesus have sent my angel to testify these things to you for the congregations. I am the root and the offspring of David; the bright and the morning star.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Now the spirit and the bride say, Come; and let him who heareth say Come. And let every one who thirsteth come; and let every one who is willing take of the water of life at free cost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>For I testify to every one who heareth the words of the prophecy of this book, if any one addeth to these things God will lay on him the plagues written of in this book;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>and if any one taketh away from the words of the book of this prophecy God will take away his portion of the tree of life and of the holy city which are written of in this book.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He who testifieth these things saith, I am indeed coming quickly. Amen, even so come, Lord Jesus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The favour of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all! Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>