<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Chapter 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The parables of Solomon, the son of David, king of Israel,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>To know wisdom, and instruction:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>To understand the words of prudence: and to receive the instruction of doctrine, justice, and judgment, and equity:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>To give subtilty to little ones, to the young man knowledge and understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>A wise man shall hear, and shall be wiser: and he that understandeth, shall possess governments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He shall understand a parable, and the interpretation, the words of the wise, and their mysterious sayings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom. Fools despise wisdom and instruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>My son, hear the instruction of thy father, and forsake not the law of thy mother:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>That grace may be added to thy head, and a chain of gold to thy neck.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>My son, if sinners shall entice thee, consent not to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>If they shall say: Come with us, let us lie in wait for blood, let us hide snares for the innocent without cause:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let us swallow him up alive like hell, and whole as one that goeth down into the pit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>We shall find all precious substance, we shall fill our houses with spoils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Cast in thy lot with us, let us all have one purse.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>My son, walk not thou with them, restrain thy foot from their paths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For their feet run to evil, and make haste to shed blood.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>But a net is spread in vain before the eyes of them that have wings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And they themselves lie in wait for their own blood, and practise deceits against their own souls.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So the ways of every covetous man destroy the souls of the possessors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Wisdom preacheth abroad, she uttereth her voice in the streets:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>At the head of multitudes she crieth out, in the entrance of the gates of the city she uttereth her words, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>O children, how long will you love childishness, and fools covet those things which are hurtful to themselves, and the unwise hate knowledge?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Turn ye at my reproof: behold I will utter my spirit to you, and will shew you my words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Because I called, and you refused: I stretched out my hand, and there was none that regarded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>You have despised all my counsel, and have neglected my reprehensions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>I also will laugh in your destruction, and will mock when that shall come to you which you feared.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>When sudden calamity shall fall on you, and destruction, as a tempest, shall be at hand: when tribulation and distress shall come upon you:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Then shall they call upon me, and I will not hear: they shall rise in the morning and shall not find me:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Because they have hated instruction, and received not the fear of the Lord,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Nor consented to my counsel, but despised all my reproof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Therefore they shall eat the fruit of their own way, and shall be filled with their own devices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The turning away of little ones shall kill them, and the prosperity of fools shall destroy them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>But he that shall hear me, shall rest without terror, and shall enjoy abundance, without fear of evils.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="Chapter 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My son, if thou wilt receive my words, and wilt hide my commandments with thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>That thy ear may hearken to wisdom: incline thy heart to know prudence:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For if thou shalt call for wisdom, and incline thy heart to prudence:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>If thou shalt seek her as money, and shalt dig for her as for a treasure:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Then shalt thou understand the fear of the Lord, and shalt find the knowledge of God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because the Lord giveth wisdom: and out of his mouth cometh prudence and knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He will keep the salvation of the righteous, and protect them that walk in simplicity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Keeping the paths of justice, and guarding the ways of saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Then shalt thou understand justice, and judgment, and equity, and every good path.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If wisdom shall enter into thy heart, and knowledge please thy soul:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Counsel shall keep thee, and prudence shall preserve thee,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>That thou mayst be delivered from the evil way, and from the man that speaketh perverse things:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Who leave the right way, and walk by dark ways:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Who are glad when they have done evil, and rejoice in most wicked things:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Whose ways are perverse, and their steps infamous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>That thou mayst be delivered from the strange women, and from the stranger, who softeneth her words:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>And forsaketh the guide of her youth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And hath forgotten the covenant of her God: for her house inclineth unto death, and her paths to hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>None that go in unto her shall return again, neither shall they take hold of the paths of life,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>That thou mayst walk in a good way: and mayst keep the paths of the just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>For they that are upright shall dwell in the earth, and the simple shall continue in it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>But the wicked shall be destroyed from the earth: and they that do unjustly shall be taken away from it.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="Chapter 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My son, forget not my law, and let thy heart keep my commandments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For they shall add to thee length of days, and years of life and peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Let not mercy and truth leave thee, put them about thy neck, and write them in the tables of thy heart:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And thou shalt find grace and good understanding before God and men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Have confidence in the Lord with all thy heart, and lean not upon thy own prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>In all thy ways think on him, and he will direct thy steps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Be not wise in thy own conceit: fear God, and depart from evil:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>For it shall be health to thy navel, and moistening to thy bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Honour the Lord with thy substance, and give him of the first of all thy fruits:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And thy barns shall be filled with abundance, and thy presses shall run over with wine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>My son, reject not the correction of the Lord: and do not faint when thou art chastised by him:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>For whom the Lord loveth, he chastiseth: and as a father in the son he pleaseth himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Blessed is the man that findeth wisdom and is rich in prudence:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The purchasing thereof is better than the merchandise of silver, and her fruit than the chiefest and purest gold:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>She is more precious than all riches: and all the things that are desired, are not to be compared with her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Length of days is in her right hand, and in her left hand riches and glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Her ways are beautiful ways, and all her paths are peaceable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>She is a tree of life to them that lay hold on her: and he that shall retain her is blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The Lord by wisdom hath founded the earth, hath established the heavens by prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>By his wisdom the depths have broken out, and the clouds grow thick with dew.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>My son, let not these things depart from thy eyes: keep the law and counsel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>And there shall be life to thy soul, and grace to thy mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Then shalt thou walk confidently in thy way, and thy foot shall not stumble:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>If thou sleep, thou shalt not fear: thou shalt rest, and thy sleep shall be sweet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Be not afraid of sudden fear, nor of the power of the wicked falling upon thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For the Lord will be at thy side, and will keep thy foot that thou be not taken.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Do not withhold him from doing good, who is able: if thou art able, do good thyself also.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Say not to thy friend: Go, and come again: and to morrow I will give to thee: when thou canst give at present.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Practise not evil against thy friend, when he hath confidence in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Strive not against a man without cause, when he hath done thee no evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Envy not the unjust man, and do not follow his ways:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>For every mocker is an abomination to the Lord, and his communication is with the simple.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Want is from the Lord in the house of the wicked: but the habitations of the just shall be blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>He shall scorn the scorners, and to the meek he will give grace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>The wise shall possess glory: the promotion of fools is disgrace.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="Chapter 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Hear, ye children, the instruction of a father, and attend that you may know prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I will give you a good gift, forsake not my law.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For I also was my father&#8217;s son, tender and as an only son in the sight of my mother:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>And he taught me, and said: Let thy heart receive my words, keep my commandments, and thou shalt live.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Get wisdom, get prudence: forget not, neither decline from the words of my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Forsake her not, and she shall keep thee: love her, and she shall preserve thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The beginning of wisdom, get wisdom, and with all thy possession purchase prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Take hold on her, and she shall exalt thee: thou shalt be glorified by her, when thou shalt embrace her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>She shall give to thy head increase of graces, and protect thee with a noble crown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Hear, O my son, and receive my words, that years of life may be multiplied to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I will shew thee the way of wisdom, I will lead thee by the paths of equity:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Which when thou shalt have entered, thy steps shall not be straitened, and when thou runnest thou shalt not meet a stumblingblock.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Take hold on instruction, leave it not: keep it, because it is thy life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Be not delighted in the paths of the wicked, neither let the way of evil men please thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Flee from it, pass not by it: go aside, and forsake it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For they sleep not except they have done evil: and their sleep is taken away unless they have made some to fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>They eat the bread of wickedness, and drink the wine of iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>But the path of the just, as a shining light, goeth forwards and increaseth even to perfect day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The way of the wicked is darksome: they know not where they fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>My son, hearken to my words, and incline thy ear to my sayings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Let them not depart from thy eyes, keep them in the midst of thy heart:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For they are life to those that find them, and health to all flesh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>With all watchfulness keep thy heart, because life issueth out from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Remove from thee a froward mouth, and let detracting lips be far from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Let thy eyes look straight on, and let thy eyelids go before thy steps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Make straight the path for thy feet, and all thy ways shall be established.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Decline not to the right hand, nor to the left: turn away thy foot from evil. For the Lord knoweth the ways that are on the right hand: but those are perverse which are on the left hand. But he will make thy courses straight, he will bring forward thy ways in peace.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5" preferred_title="Chapter 5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My son, attend to my wisdom, and incline thy ear to my prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>That thou mayst keep thoughts, and thy lips may preserve instruction. Mind not the deceit of a woman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For the lips of a harlot are like a honeycomb dropping, and her throat is smoother than oil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But her end is bitter as wormwood, and sharp as a two-edged sword.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Her feet go down into death, and her steps go in as far as hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>They walk not by the path of life, her steps are wandering, and unaccountable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Now therefore, my son, hear me, and depart not from the words of my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Remove thy way far from her, and come not nigh the doors of her house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Give not thy honour to strangers, and thy years to the cruel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Lest strangers be filled with thy strength, and thy labours be in another man&#8217;s house,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And thou mourn at the last, when thou shalt have spent thy flesh and thy body, and say:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Why have I hated instruction, and my heart consented not to reproof,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And have not heard the voice of them that taught me, and have not inclined my ear to masters?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I have almost been in all evil, in the midst of the church and of the congregation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Drink water out of thy own cistern, and the streams of thy own well:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Let thy fountains be conveyed abroad, and in the streets divide thy waters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Keep them to thyself alone, neither let strangers be partakers with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Let thy vein be blessed, and rejoice with the wife of thy youth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Let her be thy dearest hind, and most agreeable fawn: let her breasts inebriate thee at all times; be thou delighted continually with her love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Why art thou seduced, my son, by a strange woman, and art cherished in the bosom of another?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The Lord beholdeth the ways of man, and considereth all his steps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>His own iniquities catch the wicked, and he is fast bound with the ropes of his own sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He shall die, because he hath not received instruction, and in the multitude of his folly he shall be deceived.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6" preferred_title="Chapter 6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My son, if thou be surety for thy friend, thou hast engaged fast thy hand to a stranger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thou art ensnared with the words of thy mouth, and caught with thy own words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Do therefore, my son, what I say, and deliver thyself: because thou art fallen into the hand of thy neighbour. Run about, make haste, stir up thy friend:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Give not sleep to thy eyes, neither let thy eyelids slumber.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Deliver thyself as a doe from the hand, and as a bird from the hand of the fowler.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Go to the ant, O sluggard, and consider her ways, and learn wisdom:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Which, although she hath no guide, nor master, nor captain,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Provideth her meat for herself in the summer, and gathereth her food in the harvest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>How long wilt thou sleep, O sluggard? when wilt thou rise out of thy sleep?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thou wilt sleep a little, thou wilt slumber a little, thou wilt fold thy hands a little to sleep:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>And want shall come upon thee, as a traveller, and poverty as a man armed. But if thou be diligent, thy harvest shall come as a fountain, and want shall flee far from thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A man that is an apostate, an unprofitable man, walketh with a perverse mouth,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He winketh with the eyes, presseth with the foot, speaketh with the finger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>With a wicked heart he deviseth evil, and at all times he soweth discord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>To such a one his destruction shall presently come, and he shall suddenly be destroyed, and shall no longer have any remedy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Six things there are, which the Lord hateth, and the seventh his soul detesteth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, hands that shed innocent blood,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A heart that deviseth wicked plots, feet that are swift to run into mischief,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>A deceitful witness that uttereth lies, and him that soweth discord among brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>My son, keep the commandments of thy father, and forsake not the law of thy mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Bind them in thy heart continually, and put them about thy neck.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>When thou walkest, let them go with thee: when thou sleepest, let them keep thee; and when thou awakest, talk with them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Because the commandment is a lamp, and the law a light, and reproofs of instruction are the way of life:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>That they may keep thee from the evil woman, and from the flattering tongue of the stranger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Let not thy heart covet her beauty, be not caught with her winks:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For the price of a harlot is scarce one loaf: but the woman catcheth the precious soul of a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Can a man hide fire in his bosom, and his garments not burn?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Or can he walk upon hot coals, and his feet not be burnt?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>So he that goeth in to his neighbour&#8217;s wife, shall not be clean when he shall touch her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The fault is not so great when a man hath stolen: for he stealeth to fill his hungry soul:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And if he be taken he shall restore sevenfold, and shall give up all the substance of his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But he that is an adulterer, for the folly of his heart shall destroy his own soul:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>He gathereth to himself shame and dishonour, and his reproach shall not be blotted out:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Because the jealousy and rage of the husband will not spare in the day of revenge,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>Nor will he yield to any man&#8217;s prayers, nor will he accept for satisfaction ever so many gifts.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7" preferred_title="Chapter 7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My son, keep my words, and lay up my precepts with thee. Son,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Keep my commandments, and thou shalt live: and my law as the apple of thy eye:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Bind it upon thy fingers, write it upon the tables of thy heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Say to wisdom: Thou art my sister: and call prudence thy friend,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>That she may keep thee from the woman that is not thine, and from the stranger who sweeteneth her words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>For I look out of the window of my house through the lattice,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>And I see little ones, I behold a foolish young man,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Who passeth through the street by the corner, and goeth nigh the way of her house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>In the dark, when it grows late, in the darkness and obscurity of the night,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>And behold a woman meeteth him in harlot&#8217;s attire prepared to deceive souls; talkative and wandering,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Not bearing to be quiet, not able to abide still at home,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Now abroad, now in the streets, now lying in wait near the corners.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>And catching the young man, she kisseth him, and with an impudent face, flattereth, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>I vowed victims for prosperity, this day I have paid my vows.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Therefore I am come out to meet thee, desirous to see thee, and I have found thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>I have woven my bed with cords, I have covered it with painted tapestry, brought from Egypt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Come, let us be inebriated with the breasts, and let us enjoy the desired embraces, till the day appear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For my husband is not at home, he is gone a very long journey.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He took with him a bag of money: he will return home the day of the full moon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>She entangled him with many words, and drew him away with the flattery of her lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Immediately he followeth her as an ox led to be a victim, and as a lamb playing the wanton, and not knowing that he is drawn like a fool to bonds,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Till the arrow pierce his liver: as if a bird should make haste to the snare, and knoweth not that his life is in danger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Now therefore, my son, hear me, and attend to the words of my mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Let not thy mind be drawn away in her ways: neither be thou deceived with her paths.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>For she hath cast down many wounded, and the strongest have been slain by her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Her house is the way to hell, reaching even to the inner chambers of death.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8" preferred_title="Chapter 8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Doth not wisdom cry aloud, and prudence put forth her voice?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Standing in the top of the highest places by the way, in the midst of the paths,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Beside the gates of the city, in the very doors she speaketh, saying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>O ye men, to you I call, and my voice is to the sons of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>O little ones, understand subtilty, and ye unwise, take notice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Hear, for I will speak of great things: and my lips shall be opened to preach right things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>My mouth shall meditate truth, and my lips shall hate wickedness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>All my words are just, there is nothing wicked nor perverse in them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>They are right to them that understand, and just to them that find knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Receive my instruction, and not money: choose knowledge rather than gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For wisdom is better than all the most precious things: and whatsoever may be desired cannot be compared to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>I wisdom dwell in counsel, and am present in learned thoughts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The fear of the Lord hateth evil: I hate arrogance, and pride, and every wicked way, and a mouth with a double tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Counsel and equity is mine, prudence is mine, strength is mine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>By me kings reign, and lawgivers decree just things,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>By me princes rule, and the mighty decree justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>I love them that love me: and they that in the morning early watch for me, shall find me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>With me are riches and glory, glorious riches and justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>For my fruit is better than gold and the precious stone, and my blossoms than choice silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>I walk in the way of justice, in the midst of the paths of judgment,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>That I may enrich them that love me, and may fill their treasures.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The Lord possessed me in the beginning of his ways, before he made any thing from the beginning.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>I was set up from eternity, and of old before the earth was made.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The depths were not as yet, and I was already conceived, neither had the fountains of waters as yet sprung out:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The mountains with their huge bulk had not as yet been established: before the hills I was brought forth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He had not yet made the earth, nor the rivers, nor the poles of the world.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>When he prepared the heavens, I was present: when with a certain law and compass he enclosed the depths:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When he established the sky above, and poised the fountains of waters:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>When he compassed the sea with its bounds, and set a law to the waters that they should not pass their limits: when he balanced the foundations of the earth;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I was with him forming all things: and was delighted every day, playing before him at all times;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Playing in the world: and my delights were to be with the children of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Now therefore, ye children, hear me: Blessed are they that keep my ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Hear instruction and be wise, and refuse it not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Blessed is the man that heareth me, and that watcheth daily at my gates, and waiteth at the posts of my doors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>He that shall find me, shall find life, and shall have salvation from the Lord:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="36">
      <content>But he that shall sin against me, shall hurt his own soul. All that hate me love death.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="9" preferred_title="Chapter 9">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Wisdom hath built herself a house, she hath hewn her out seven pillars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>She hath slain her victims, mingled her wine, and set forth her table.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>She hath sent her maids to invite to the tower, and to the walls of the city:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Whosoever is a little one, let him come to me. And to the unwise she said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Come, eat my bread, and drink the wine which I have mingled for you.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Forsake childishness, and live, and walk by the ways of prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He that teacheth a scorner, doth an injury to himself: and he that rebuketh a wicked man, getteth himself a blot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Rebuke not a scorner lest he hate thee. Rebuke a wise man, and he will love thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Give an occasion to a wise man, and wisdom shall be added to him. Teach a just man, and he shall make haste to receive it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom: and the knowledge of the holy is prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For by me shall thy days be multiplied, and years of life shall be added to thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If thou be wise, thou shalt be so to thyself: and if a scorner, thou alone shalt bear the evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>A foolish woman and clamorous, and full of allurements, and knowing nothing at all,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Sat at the door of her house, upon a seat, in a high place of the city,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>To call them that pass by the way, and go on their journey:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He that is a little one, let him turn to me. And to the fool she said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Stolen waters are sweeter, and hidden bread is more pleasant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>And he did not know that giants are there, and that her guests are in the depths of hell.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="10" preferred_title="Chapter 10">
    <fragment>
      <content>THE PARABLES OF SOLOMON.</content>
    </fragment>
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A wise son maketh the father glad: but a foolish son is the sorrow of his mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Treasures of wickedness shall profit nothing: but justice shall deliver from death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The Lord will not afflict the soul of the just with famine, and he will disappoint the deceitful practices of the wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The slothful hand hath wrought poverty: but the hand of the industrious getteth riches. He that trusteth to lies feedeth the winds: and the same runneth after birds that fly away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>He that gathered in the harvest, is a wise son: but he that snorteth in the summer, is the son of confusion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The blessing of the Lord is upon the head of the just: but iniquity covereth the mouth of the wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The memory of the just is with praises: and the name of the wicked shall rot.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The wise of heart receiveth precepts: a fool is beaten with lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He that walketh sincerely, walketh confidently: but he that perverteth his ways, shall be manifest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He that winketh with the eye shall cause sorrow: and the foolish in lips shall be beaten.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The mouth of the just is a vein of life: and the mouth of the wicked covereth iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Hatred stirreth up strifes: and charity covereth all sins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>In the lips of the wise is wisdom found: and a rod on the back of him that wanteth sense.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Wise men lay up knowledge: but the mouth of the fool is next to confusion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The substance of a rich man is the city of his strength: the fear of the poor is their poverty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The work of the just is unto life: but the fruit of the wicked, unto sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The way of life, to him that observeth correction: but he that forsaketh reproofs goeth astray.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Lying lips hide hatred: he that uttereth reproach is foolish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>In the multitude of words there shall not want sin: but he that refraineth his lips is most wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The tongue of the just is as choice silver: but the heart of the wicked is nothing worth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The lips of the just teach many: but they that are ignorant, shall die in the want of understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The blessing of the Lord maketh men rich: neither shall affliction be joined to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>A fool worketh mischief as it were for sport: but wisdom is prudence to a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>That which the wicked feareth, shall come upon him: to the just their desire shall be given.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>As a tempest that passeth, so the wicked shall be no more: but the just is as an everlasting foundation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>As vinegar to the teeth, and smoke to the eyes, so is the sluggard to them that sent him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The fear of the Lord shall prolong days: and the years of the wicked shall be shortened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The expectation of the just is joy; but the hope of the wicked shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The strength of the upright is the way of the Lord: and fear to them that work evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The just shall never be moved: but the wicked shall not dwell on the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The mouth of the just shall bring forth wisdom: the tongue of the perverse shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The lips of the just consider what is acceptable: and the mouth of the wicked uttereth perverse things.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="11" preferred_title="Chapter 11">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A DECEITFUL balance is an abomination before the Lord: and a just weight is his will.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Where pride is, there also shall be reproach: but where humility is, there also is wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The simplicity of the just shall guide them: and the deceitfulness of the wicked shall destroy them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Riches shall not profit in the day of revenge: but justice shall deliver from death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The justice of the upright shall make his way prosperous: and the wicked man shall fall by his own wickedness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The justice of the righteous shall deliver them: and the unjust shall be caught in their own snares.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When the wicked man is dead, there shall be no hope any more: and the expectation of the solicitous shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The just is delivered out of distress: and the wicked shall be given up for him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The dissembler with his mouth deceiveth his friend: but the just shall be delivered by knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>When it goeth well with the just the city shall rejoice: and when the wicked perish there shall be praise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>By the blessing of the just the city shall be exalted: and by the mouth of the wicked it shall be overthrown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>He that despiseth his friend, is mean of heart: but the wise man will hold his peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He that walketh deceitfully, revealeth secrets: but he that is faithful, concealeth the thing committed to him by his friend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Where there is no governor, the people shall fall: but there is safety where there is much counsel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He shall be afflicted with evil, that is surety for a stranger: but he that is aware of the snares, shall be secure.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>A gracious woman shall find glory: and the strong shall have riches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>A merciful man doth good to his own soul: but he that is cruel casteth off even his own kindred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The wicked maketh an unsteady work: but to him that soweth justice, there is a faithful reward.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Clemency prepareth life: and the pursuing of evil things, death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>A perverse heart is abominable to the Lord: and his will is in them that walk sincerely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Hand in hand the evil man shall not be innocent: but the seed of the just shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A golden ring in a swine&#8217;s snout, a woman fair and foolish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The desire of the just is all good: the expectation of the wicked is indignation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Some distribute their own goods, and grow richer: others take away what is not their own, and are always in want.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The soul which blesseth, shall be made fat: and he that inebriateth, shall be inebriated also himself.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He that hideth up corn, shall be cursed among the people: but a blessing upon the head of them that sell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Well doth he rise early who seeketh good things; but he that seeketh after evil things shall be oppressed by them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>He that trusteth in his riches shall fall: but the just shall spring up as a green leaf.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He that troubleth his own house, shall inherit the winds: and the fool shall serve the wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The fruit of the just man is a tree of life: and he that gaineth souls, is wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>If the just man receive in the earth, how much more the wicked and the sinner.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="12" preferred_title="Chapter 12">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>He that loveth correction, loveth knowledge: but he that hateth reproof is foolish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He that is good, shall draw grace from the Lord: but he that trusteth in his own devices doth wickedly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Men shall not be strengthened by wickedness: and the root of the just shall not be moved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>A diligent woman is a crown to her husband: and she that doth things worthy of confusion, is a rottenness in his bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The thoughts of the just are judgments: and the counsels of the wicked are deceitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The words of the wicked lie in wait for blood: the mouth of the just shall deliver them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Turn the wicked, and they shall not be: but the house of the just shall stand firm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>A man shall be known by his learning: but he that is vain and foolish, shall be exposed to contempt.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Better is the poor man that provideth for himself, than he that is glorious and wanteth bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The just regardeth the lives of his beasts: but the bowels of the wicked are cruel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He that tilleth his land shall be satisfied with bread: but he that pursueth idleness is very foolish. He that is delighted in passing his time over wine, leaveth a reproach in his strong holds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The desire of the wicked is the fortification of evil men: but the root of the just shall prosper.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>For the sins of the lips, ruin draweth nigh to the evil man: but the just shall escape out of distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>By the fruit of his own mouth shall a man be filled with good things, and according to the works of his hands it shall be repaid him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The way of a fool is right in his own eyes: but he that is wise hearkeneth unto counsels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>A fool immediately sheweth his anger: but he that dissembleth injuries is wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He that speaketh that which he knoweth, sheweth forth justice: but he that lieth, is a deceitful witness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>There is that promiseth, and is pricked as it were with a sword of conscience: but the tongue of the wise is health.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The lip of truth shall be steadfast for ever: but he that is a hasty witness, frameth a lying tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Deceit is in the heart of them that think evil things: but joy followeth them that take counsels of peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Whatsoever shall befall the just man, it shall not make him sad: but the wicked shall be filled with mischief.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Lying lips are an abomination to the Lord: but they that deal faithfully please him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>A cautious man concealeth knowledge: and the heart of fools publisheth folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The hand of the valiant shall bear rule: but that which is slothful, shall be under tribute.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Grief in the heart of a man shall bring him low, but with a good word he shall be made glad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He that neglecteth a loss for the sake of a friend, is just: but the way of the wicked shall deceive them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The deceitful man shall not find gain: but the substance of a just man shall be precious gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In the path of justice is life: but the by-way leadeth to death.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="13" preferred_title="Chapter 13">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A WISE son heareth the doctrine of his father: but he that is a scorner, heareth not when he is reproved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Of the fruit of his own mouth shall a man be filled with good things: but the soul of transgressors is wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>He that keepeth his mouth, keepeth his soul: but he that hath no guard on his speech shall meet with evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The sluggard willeth and willeth not: but the soul of them that work, shall be made fat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The just shall hate a lying word: but the wicked confoundeth, and shall be confounded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Justice keepeth the way of the innocent: but wickedness overthroweth the sinner.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>One is as it were rich, when he hath nothing: and another is as it were poor, when he hath great riches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The ransom of a man&#8217;s life are his riches: but he that is poor beareth not reprehension.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The light of the just giveth joy: but the lamp of the wicked shall be put out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Among the proud there are always contentions: but they that do all things with counsel, are ruled by wisdom.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Substance got in haste shall be diminished: but that which by little and little is gathered with the hand shall increase.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Hope that is deferred afflicteth the soul: desire when it cometh is a tree of life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Whosoever speaketh ill of any thing, bindeth himself for the time to come: but he that feareth the commandment, shall dwell in peace. Deceitful souls go astray in sins: the just are merciful, and shew mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The law of the wise is a fountain of life, that he may decline from the ruin of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Good instruction shall give grace: in the way of scorners is a deep pit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The prudent man doth all things with counsel: but he that is a fool, layeth open his folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The messenger of the wicked shall fall into mischief: but a faithful ambassador is health.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Poverty and shame to him that refuseth instruction: but he that yieldeth to reproof, shall be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The desire that is accomplished, delighteth the soul: fools hate them that flee from evil things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He that walketh with the wise, shall be wise: a friend of fools shall become like to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Evil pursueth sinners: and to the just good shall be repaid.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The good man leaveth heirs, sons, and grandsons: and the substance of the sinner is kept for the just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Much food is in the tillage of fathers: but for others it is gathered without judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He that spareth the rod hateth his son: but he that loveth him correcteth him betimes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The just eateth and filleth his soul: but the belly of the wicked is never to be filled.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="14" preferred_title="Chapter 14">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A WISE woman buildeth her house: but the foolish will pull down with her hands that also which is built.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>He that walketh in the right way, and feareth God, is despised by him that goeth by an infamous way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>In the mouth of a fool is the rod of pride: but the lips of the wise preserve them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Where there are no oxen, the crib is empty: but where there is much corn, there the strength of the ox is manifest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>A faithful witness will not lie: but a deceitful witness uttereth a lie.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>A scorner seeketh wisdom, and findeth it not: the learning of the wise is easy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Go against a foolish man, and he knoweth not the lips of prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The wisdom of a discreet man is to understand his way: and the imprudence of fools erreth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>A fool will laugh at sin, but among the just grace shall abide.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The heart that knoweth the bitterness of his own soul, in his joy the stranger shall not intermeddle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The house of the wicked shall be destroyed: but the tabernacles of the just shall flourish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>There is a way which seemeth just to a man: but the ends thereof lead to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Laughter shall be mingled with sorrow, and mourning taketh hold of the end of joy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>A fool shall be filled with his own ways, and the good man shall be above him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The innocent believeth every word: the discreet man considereth his steps. No good shall come to the deceitful son: but the wise servant shall prosper in his dealings, and his way shall be made straight.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>A wise man feareth and declineth from evil: the fool leapeth over and is confident.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The impatient man shall work folly: and the crafty man is hateful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The childish shall possess folly, and the prudent shall look for knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The evil shall fall down before the good: and the wicked before the gates of the just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The poor man shall be hateful even to his own neighbour: but the friends of the rich are many.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He that despiseth his neighbour, sinneth: but he that sheweth mercy to the poor, shall be blessed. He that believeth in the Lord, loveth mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>They err that work evil: but mercy and truth prepare good things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>In much work there shall be abundance: but where there are many words, there is oftentimes want.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The crown of the wise is their riches: the folly of fools, imprudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>A faithful witness delivereth souls: and the double dealer uttereth lies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>In the fear of the Lord is confidence of strength, and there shall be hope for his children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, to decline from the ruin of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>In the multitude of people is the dignity of the king: and in the small number of people the dishonour of the prince.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>He that is patient, is governed with much wisdom: but he that is impatient, exalteth his folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Soundness of heart is the life of the flesh: but envy is the rottenness of the bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>He that oppresseth the poor, upbraideth his Maker: but he that hath pity on the poor, honoureth him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The wicked man shall be driven out in his wickedness: but the just hath hope in his death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>In the heart of the prudent resteth wisdom, and it shall instruct all the ignorant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>Justice exalteth a nation: but sin maketh nations miserable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>A wise servant is acceptable to the king: he that is good for nothing shall feel his anger.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="15" preferred_title="Chapter 15">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A MILD answer breaketh wrath: but a harsh word stirreth up fury.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The tongue of the wise adorneth knowledge: but the mouth of fools bubbleth out folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The eyes of the Lord in every place behold the good and the evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>A peaceable tongue is a tree of life: but that which is immoderate, shall crush the spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>A fool laugheth at the instruction of his father: but he that regardeth reproofs shall become prudent. In abundant justice there is the greatest strength: but the devices of the wicked shall be rooted out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The house of the just is very much strength: and in the fruits of the wicked is trouble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The lips of the wise shall disperse knowledge: the heart of fools shall be unlike.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The victims of the wicked are abominable to the Lord: the vows of the just are acceptable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The way of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord: he that followeth justice is beloved by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Instruction is grievous to him that forsaketh the way of life: he that hateth reproof shall die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Hell and destruction are before the Lord: how much more the hearts of the children of men?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A corrupt man loveth not one that reproveth him: nor will he go to the wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>A glad heart maketh a cheerful countenance: but by grief of mind the spirit is cast down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The heart of the wise seeketh instruction: and the mouth of fools feedeth on foolishness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>All the days of the poor are evil: a secure mind is like a continual feast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Better is a little with the fear of the Lord, than great treasures without content.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>It is better to be invited to herbs with love, than to a fatted calf with hatred.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A passionate man stirreth up strifes: he that is patient appeaseth those that are stirred up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The way of the slothful is as a hedge of thorns; the way of the just is without offence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>A wise son maketh a father joyful: but the foolish man despiseth his mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Folly is joy to the fool: and the wise man maketh straight his steps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Designs are brought to nothing where there is no counsel: but where there are many counsellors, they are established.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>A man rejoiceth in the sentence of his mouth: and a word in due time is best.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The path of life is above for the wise, that he may decline from the lowest hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The Lord will destroy the house of the proud: and will strengthen the borders of the widow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Evil thoughts are an abomination to the Lord: and pure words most beautiful shall be confirmed by him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He that is greedy of gain troubleth his own house: but he that hateth bribes shall live. By mercy and faith sins are purged away: and by the fear of the Lord every one declineth from evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The mind of the just studieth obedience: the mouth of the wicked overfloweth with evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The Lord is far from the wicked: and he will hear the prayers of the just.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The light of the eyes rejoiceth the soul: a good name maketh the bones fat.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The ear that heareth the reproofs of life, shall abide in the midst of the wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>He that rejecteth instruction, despiseth his own soul: but he that yieldeth to reproof possesseth understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>The fear of the Lord is the lesson of wisdom: and humility goeth before glory.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="16" preferred_title="Chapter 16">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>It is the part of man to prepare the soul: and of the Lord to govern the tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>All the ways of a man are open to his eyes: the Lord is the weigher of spirits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Lay open thy works to the Lord: and thy thoughts shall be directed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The Lord hath made all things for himself: the wicked also for the evil day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Every proud man is an abomination to the Lord: though hand should be joined to hand, he is not innocent. The beginning of a good way is to do justice; and this is more acceptable with God, than to offer sacrifices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>By mercy and truth iniquity is redeemed: and by the fear of the Lord men depart from evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>When the ways of man shall please the Lord, he will convert even his enemies to peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Better is a little with justice, than great revenues with iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The heart of man disposeth his way: but the Lord must direct his steps.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Divination is in the lips of the king, his mouth shall not err in judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Weight and balance are judgments of the Lord: and his work all the weights of the bag.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>They that act wickedly are abominable to the king: for the throne is established by justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Just lips are the delight of kings: he that speaketh right things shall be loved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The wrath of a king is as messengers of death: and the wise man will pacify it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>In the cheerfulness of the king&#8217;s countenance is life: and his clemency is like the latter rain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Get wisdom, because it is better than gold: and purchase prudence, for it is more precious than silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The path of the just departeth from evils: he that keepeth his soul keepeth his way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Pride goeth before destruction: and the spirit is lifted up before a fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>It is better to be humbled with the meek, than to divide spoils with the proud.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>The learned in word shall find good things: and he that trusteth in the Lord is blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The wise in heart shall be called prudent: and he that is sweet in words shall attain to greater things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Knowledge is a fountain of life to him that possesseth it: the instruction of fools is foolishness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The heart of the wise shall instruct his mouth: and shall add grace to his lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Well ordered words are as a honeycomb: sweet to the soul, and health to the bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>There is a way that seemeth to a man right: and the ends thereof lead to death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The soul of him that laboureth, laboureth for himself, because his mouth hath obliged him to it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The wicked man diggeth evil, and in his lips is a burning fire.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>A perverse man stirreth up quarrels: and one full of words separateth princes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>An unjust man allureth his friend: and leadeth him into a way that is not good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>He that with fixed eyes deviseth wicked things, biting his lips, bringeth evil to pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Old age is a crown of dignity, when it is found in the ways of justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>The patient man is better than the valiant: and he that ruleth his spirit, than he that taketh cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Lots are cast into the lap, but they are disposed of by the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="17" preferred_title="Chapter 17">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Better is a dry morsel with joy, than a house full of victims with strife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>A wise servant shall rule over foolish sons, and shall divide the inheritance among the brethren.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>As silver is tried by fire, and gold in the furnace: so the Lord trieth the hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The evil man obeyeth an unjust tongue: and the deceitful hearkeneth to lying lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>He that despiseth the poor, reproacheth his Maker; and he that rejoiceth at another man&#8217;s ruin, shall not be unpunished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Children&#8217;s children are the crown of old men: and the glory of children are their fathers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Eloquent words do not become a fool, nor lying lips a prince.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The expectation of him that expecteth, is a most acceptable jewel: whithersoever he turneth himself, he understandeth wisely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He that concealeth a transgression, seeketh friendships: he that repeateth it again, separateth friends.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>A reproof availeth more with a wise man, than a hundred stripes with a fool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>An evil man always seeketh quarrels: but a cruel angel shall be sent against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>It is better to meet a bear robbed of her whelps, than a fool trusting in his own folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He that rendereth evil for good, evil shall not depart from his house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The beginning of quarrels is as when one letteth out water: before he suffereth reproach he forsaketh judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>He that justifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the just, both are abominable before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>What doth it avail a fool to have riches, seeing he cannot buy wisdom? He that maketh his house high, seeketh a downfall: and he that refuseth to learn, shall fall into evils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He that is a friend loveth at all times: and a brother is proved in distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A foolish man will clap hands, when he is surety for his friend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He that studieth discords, loveth quarrels: and he that exalteth his door, seeketh ruin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He that is of a perverse heart, shall not find good: and he that perverteth his tongue, shall fall into evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>A fool is born to his own disgrace: and even his father shall not rejoice in a fool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A joyful mind maketh age flourishing: a sorrowful spirit drieth up the bones.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The wicked man taketh gifts out of the bosom, that he may pervert the paths of judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Wisdom shineth in the face of the wise: the eyes of fools are in the ends of the earth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>A foolish son is the anger of the father: and the sorrow of the mother that bore him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>It is no good thing to do hurt to the just: nor to strike the prince, who judgeth right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He that setteth bounds to his words, is knowing and wise: and the man of understanding is of a precious spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Even a fool, if he will hold his peace shall be counted wise: and if he close his lips, a man of understanding.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="18" preferred_title="Chapter 18">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>He that hath a mind to depart from a friend seeketh occasions: he shall ever be subject to reproach.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>A fool receiveth not the words of prudence: unless thou say those things which are in his heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The wicked man when he is come into the depth of sins, contemneth: but ignominy and reproach follow him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Words from the mouth of a man are as deep water: and the fountain of wisdom as an overflowing stream.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>It is not good to accept the person of the wicked, to decline from the truth of judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>The lips of a fool intermeddle with strife: and his mouth provoketh quarrels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The mouth of a fool is his destruction: and his lips are the ruin of his soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The words of the double tongued are as if they were harmless: and they reach even to the inner parts of the bowels. Fear casteth down the slothful: and the souls of the effeminate shall be hungry.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He that is loose and slack in his work, is the brother of him that wasteth his own works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The name of the Lord is a strong tower: the just runneth to it, and shall be exalted.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The substance of the rich man is the city of his strength, and as a strong wall compassing him about.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Before destruction, the heart of a man is exalted: and before he be glorified, it is humbled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He that answereth before he heareth sheweth himself to be a fool, and worthy of confusion.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The spirit of a man upholdeth his infirmity: but a spirit that is easily angered, who can bear?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>A wise heart shall acquire knowledge: and the ear of the wise seeketh instruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>A man&#8217;s gift enlargeth his way, and maketh him room before princes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The just is first accuser of himself: his friend cometh, and shall search him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The lot suppresseth contentions, and determineth even between the mighty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>A brother that is helped by his brother, is like a strong city: and judgments are like the bars of cities.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Of the fruit of a man&#8217;s mouth shall his belly be satisfied: and the offspring of his lips shall fill him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Death and life are in the power of the tongue: they that love it, shall eat the fruits thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>He that hath found a good wife, hath found a good thing, and shall receive a pleasure from the Lord. He that driveth away a good wife, driveth away a good thing: but he that keepeth an adulteress, is foolish and wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The poor will speak with supplications, and the rich will speak roughly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>A man amiable in society, shall be more friendly than a brother.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="19" preferred_title="Chapter 19">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Better is the poor man, that walketh in his simplicity, than a rich man that is perverse in his lips, and unwise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Where there is no knowledge of the soul, there is no good: and he that is hasty with his feet shall stumble.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The folly of a man supplanteth his steps: and he fretteth in his mind against God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Riches make many friends: but from the poor man, even they whom he had, depart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>A false witness shall not be unpunished: and he that speaketh lies shall not escape.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Many honour the person of him that is mighty, and are friends of him that giveth gifts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The brethren of the poor man hate him: moreover also his friends have departed far from him. He that followeth after words only, shall have nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But he that possesseth a mind, loveth his own soul, and he that keepeth prudence shall find good things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>A false witness shall not be unpunished: and he that speaketh lies, shall perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Delicacies are not seemly for a fool: nor for a servant to have rule over princes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The learning of a man is known by patience: and his glory is to pass over wrongs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>As the roaring of a lion, so also is the anger of a king: and his cheerfulness as the dew upon the grass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>A foolish son is the grief of his father: and a wrangling wife is like a roof continually dropping through.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>House and riches are given by parents: but a prudent wife is properly from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep, and an idle soul shall suffer hunger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He that keepeth the commandment, keepeth his own soul: but he that neglecteth his own way, shall die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He that hath mercy on the poor, lendeth to the Lord: and he will repay him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Chastise thy son, despair not: but to the killing of him set not thy soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He that is impatient, shall suffer damage: and when he shall take away he shall add another thing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Hear counsel, and receive instruction, that thou mayst be wise in thy latter end.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>There are many thoughts in the heart of a man: but the will of the Lord shall stand firm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A needy man is merciful: and better is the poor than the lying man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The fear of the Lord is unto life: and he shall abide in fulness without being visited with evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The slothful hideth his hand under his armpit, and will not so much as bring it to his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The wicked man being scourged, the fool shall be wiser: but if thou rebuke a wise man he will understand discipline.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He that afflicteth his father, and chaseth away his mother, is infamous and unhappy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Cease not, O my son, to hear instruction, and be not ignorant of the words of knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>An unjust witness scorneth judgment: and the mouth of the wicked devoureth iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Judgments are prepared for scorners: and striking hammers for the bodies of fools.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="20" preferred_title="Chapter 20">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Wine is a luxurious thing, and drunkenness riotous: whosoever is delighted therewith shall not be wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As the roaring of a lion, so also is the dread of a king: he that provoketh him, sinneth against his own soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>It is an honour for a man to separate himself from quarrels: but all fools are meddling with reproaches.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Because of the cold the sluggard would not plough: he shall beg therefore in the summer, and it shall not be given him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Counsel in the heart of a man is like deep water: but a wise man will draw it out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Many men are called merciful: but who shall find a faithful man?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The just that walketh in his simplicity, shall leave behind him blessed children.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The king, that sitteth on the throne of judgment, scattereth away all evil with his look.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Who can say: My heart is clean, I am pure from sin?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Diverse weights and diverse measures, both are abominable before God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>By his inclinations a child is known, if his works be clean and right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The hearing ear, and the seeing eye, the Lord hath made them both.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Love not sleep, lest poverty oppress thee: open thy eyes, and be filled with bread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>It is nought, it is nought, saith every buyer: and when he is gone away, then he will boast.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>There is gold, and a multitude of jewels: but the lips of knowledge are a precious vessel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Take away the garment of him that is surety for a stranger, and take a pledge from him for strangers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The bread of lying is sweet to a man: but afterwards his mouth shall be filled with gravel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Designs are strengthened by counsels: and wars are to be managed by governments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Meddle not with him that revealeth secrets, and walketh deceitfully, and openeth wide his lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>He that curseth his father, and mother, his lamp shall be put out in the midst of darkness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>The inheritance gotten hastily in the beginning, in the end shall be without a blessing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Say not: I will return evil: wait for the Lord and he will deliver thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Diverse weights are an abomination before the Lord: a deceitful balance is not good.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The steps of man are guided by the Lord: but who is the man that can understand his own way?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>It is ruin to a man to devour holy ones, and after vows to retract.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>A wise king scattereth the wicked, and bringeth over them the wheel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The spirit of a man is the lamp of the Lord, which searcheth all the hidden things of the bowels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Mercy and truth preserve the king, and his throne is strengthened by clemency.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The joy of young men is their strength: and the dignity of old men, their grey hairs.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>The blueness of a wound shall wipe away evils: and stripes in the more inward parts of the belly.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="21" preferred_title="Chapter 21">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>As the divisions of waters, so the heart of the king is in the hand of the Lord: whithersoever he will he shall turn it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Every way of a man seemeth right to himself: but the Lord weigheth the hearts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>To do mercy and judgment, pleaseth the Lord more than victims.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Haughtiness of the eyes is the enlarging of the heart: the lamp of the wicked is sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>The thoughts of the industrious always bring forth abundance: but every sluggard is always in want.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He that gathereth treasures by a lying tongue, is vain and foolish, and shall stumble upon the snares of death.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The robberies of the wicked shall be their downfall, because they would not do judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The perverse way of a man is strange: but as for him that is pure, his work is right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>It is better to sit in a corner of the housetop, than with a brawling woman, and in a common house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The soul of the wicked desireth evil, he will not have pity on his neighbour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>When a pestilent man is punished, the little one will be wiser: and if he follow the wise, he will receive knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The just considereth seriously the house of the wicked, that he may withdraw the wicked from evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He that stoppeth his ear against the cry of the poor, shall also cry himself and shall not be heard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>A secret present quencheth anger: and a gift in the bosom the greatest wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>It is joy to the just to do judgment: and dread to them that work iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>A man that shall wander out of the way of doctrine, shall abide in the company of the giants.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>He that loveth good cheer, shall be in want: he that loveth wine, and fat things, shall not be rich.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>The wicked is delivered up for the just: and the unjust for the righteous.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>It is better to dwell in a wilderness, than with a quarrelsome and passionate woman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>There is a treasure to be desired, and oil in the dwelling of the just: and the foolish man shall spend it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He that followeth justice and mercy, shall find life, justice, and glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The wise man hath scaled the city of the strong, and hath cast down the strength of the confidence thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He that keepeth his mouth and his tongue, keepeth his soul from distress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The proud and the arrogant is called ignorant, who in anger worketh pride.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Desires kill the slothful: for his hands have refused to work at all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He longeth and desireth all the day: but he that is just, will give, and will not cease.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The sacrifices of the wicked are abominable, because they are offered of wickedness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>A lying witness shall perish: an obedient man shall speak of victory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>The wicked man impudently hardeneth his face: but he that is righteous, correcteth his way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>There is no wisdom, there is no prudence, there is no counsel against the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>The horse is prepared for the day of battle: but the Lord giveth safety.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="22" preferred_title="Chapter 22">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>A GOOD name is better than great riches: and good favour is above silver and gold.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>The rich and poor have met one another: the Lord is the maker of them both.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The prudent man saw the evil, and hid himself: the simple passed on, and suffered loss.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>The fruit of humility is the fear of the Lord, riches and glory and life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Arms and swords are in the way of the perverse: but he that keepeth his own soul departeth far from them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>It is a proverb: A young man according to his way, even when he is old he will not depart from it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The rich ruleth over the poor: and the borrower is servant to him that lendeth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He that soweth iniquity shall reap evils, and with the rod of his anger he shall be consumed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He that is inclined to mercy shall be blessed: for of his bread he hath given to the poor. He that maketh presents shall purchase victory and honour: but he carrieth away the souls of the receivers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Cast out the scoffer, and contention shall go out with him, and quarrels and reproaches shall cease.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>He that loveth cleanness of heart, for the grace of his lips shall have the king for his friend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The eyes of the Lord preserve knowledge: and the words of the unjust are overthrown.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The slothful man saith: There is a lion without, I shall be slain in the midst of the streets.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The mouth of a strange woman is a deep pit: he whom the Lord is angry with, shall fall into it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Folly is bound up in the heart of a child, and the rod of correction shall drive it away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He that oppresseth the poor, to increase his own riches, shall himself give to one that is richer, and shall be in need.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Incline thy ear, and hear the words of the wise: and apply thy heart to my doctrine:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Which shall be beautiful for thee, if thou keep it in thy bowels, and it shall flow in thy lips:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>That thy trust may be in the Lord, wherefore I have also shewn it to thee this day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Behold I have described it to thee three manner of ways, in thoughts and knowledge:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>That I might shew thee the certainty, and the words of truth, to answer out of these to them that sent thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Do no violence to the poor, because he is poor: and do not oppress the needy in the gate:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Because the Lord will judge his cause, and will afflict them that have afflicted his soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>Be not a friend to an angry man, and do not walk with a furious man:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Lest perhaps thou learn his ways, and take scandal to thy soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Be not with them that fasten down their hands, and that offer themselves sureties for debts:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For if thou have not wherewith to restore, what cause is there, that he should take the covering from thy bed?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Pass not beyond the ancient bounds which thy fathers have set.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Hast thou seen a man swift in his work? he shall stand before kings, and shall not be before those that are obscure.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="23" preferred_title="Chapter 23">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>When thou shalt sit to eat with a prince, consider diligently what is set before thy face:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>And put a knife to thy throat, if it be so that thou have thy soul in thy own power.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Be not desirous of his meats, in which is the bread of deceit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Labour not to be rich: but set bounds to thy prudence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Lift not up thy eyes to riches which thou canst not have: because they shall make themselves wings like those of an eagle, and shall fly towards heaven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Eat not with an envious man, and desire not his meats:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Because like a soothsayer, and diviner, he thinketh that which he knoweth not. Eat and drink, will he say to thee: and his mind is not with thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The meats which thou hadst eaten, thou shalt vomit up: and shalt loose thy beautiful words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Speak not in the ears of fools: because they will despise the instruction of thy speech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Touch not the bounds of little ones: and enter not into the field of the fatherless:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For their near kinsman is strong: and he will judge their cause against thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let thy heart apply itself to instruction: and thy ears to words of knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Withhold not correction from a child: for if thou strike him with the rod, he shall not die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Thou shalt beat him with the rod, and deliver his soul from hell.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>My son, if thy mind be wise, my heart shall rejoice with thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>And my reins shall rejoice, when thy lips shall speak what is right.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Let not thy heart envy sinners: but be thou in the fear of the Lord all the day long:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Because thou shalt have hope in the latter end, and thy expectation shall not be taken away.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Hear thou, my son, and be wise: and guide thy mind in the way.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Be not in the feasts of great drinkers, nor in their revellings, who contribute flesh to eat:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>Because they that give themselves to drinking, and that club together shall be consumed; and drowsiness shall be clothed with rags.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Hearken to thy father, that begot thee: and despise not thy mother when she is old.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Buy truth, and do not sell wisdom, and instruction, and understanding.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>The father of the just rejoiceth greatly: he that hath begotten a wise son, shall have joy in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Let thy father, and thy mother be joyful, and let her rejoice that bore thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>My son, give me thy heart: and let thy eyes keep my ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>For a harlot is a deep ditch: and a strange woman is a narrow pit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>She lieth in wait in the way as a robber, and him whom she shall see unwary, she will kill.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Who hath woe? whose father hath woe? who hath contentions? who falls into pits? who hath wounds without cause? who hath redness of eyes?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Surely they that pass their time in wine, and study to drink off their cups.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Look not upon the wine when it is yellow, when the colour thereof shineth in the glass: it goeth in pleasantly,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>But in the end, it will bite like a snake, and will spread abroad poison like a basilisk.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Thy eyes shall behold strange women, and thy heart shall utter perverse things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And thou shalt be as one sleeping in the midst of the sea, and as a pilot fast asleep, when the stern is lost.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="35">
      <content>And thou shalt say: They have beaten me, but I was not sensible of pain: they drew me, and I felt not: when shall I awake, and find wine again?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="24" preferred_title="Chapter 24">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Seek not to be like evil men, neither desire to be with them:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Because their mind studieth robberies, and their lips speak deceits.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>By wisdom the house shall be built, and by prudence it shall be strengthened.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>By instruction the storerooms shall be filled with all precious and most beautiful wealth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>A wise man is strong: and a knowing man, stout and valiant.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Because war is managed by due ordering: and there shall be safety where there are many counsels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Wisdom is too high for a fool, in the gate he shall not open his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He that deviseth to do evils, shall be called a fool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>The thought of a fool is sin: and the detracter is the abomination of men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>If thou lose hope being weary in the day of distress, thy strength shall be diminished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Deliver them that are led to death: and those that are drawn to death forbear not to deliver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>If thou say: I have not strength enough: he that seeth into the heart, he understandeth, and nothing deceiveth the keeper of thy soul, and he shall render to a man according to his works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Eat honey, my son, because it is good, and the honeycomb most sweet to thy throat:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>So also is the doctrine of wisdom to thy soul: which when thou hast found, thou shalt have hope in the end, and thy hope shall not perish.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Lie not in wait, nor seek after wickedness in the house of the just, nor spoil his rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>For a just man shall fall seven times and shall rise again: but the wicked shall fall down into evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>When thy enemy shall fall, be not glad, and in his ruin let not thy heart rejoice:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Lest the Lord see, and it displease him, and he turn away his wrath from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>Contend not with the wicked, nor seek to be like the ungodly:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>For evil men have no hope of things to come, and the lamp of the wicked shall be put out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>My son, fear the Lord and the king: and have nothing to do with detractors.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For their destruction shall rise suddenly: and who knoweth the ruin of both?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>These things also to the wise: It is not good to have respect to persons in judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>They that say to the wicked man: Thou art just: shall be cursed by the people, and the tribes shall abhor them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>They that rebuke him, shall be praised: and a blessing shall come upon them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He shall kiss the lips, who answereth right words.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Prepare thy work without, and diligently till thy ground: that afterward thou mayst build thy house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Be not witness without cause against thy neighbour: and deceive not any man with thy lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Say not: I will do to him as he hath done to me: I will render to every one according to his work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>I passed by the field of the slothful man, and by the vineyard of the foolish man:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>And behold it was all filled with nettles, and thorns had covered the face thereof, and the stone wall was broken down.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>Which when I had seen, I laid it up in my heart, and by the example I received instruction.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>Thou wilt sleep a little, said I, thou wilt slumber a little, thou wilt fold thy hands a little to rest:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="34">
      <content>And poverty shall come to thee as a runner, and beggary as an armed man.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="25" preferred_title="Chapter 25">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>These are also parables of Solomon, which the men of Ezechias king of Juda copied out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>It is the glory of God to conceal the word, and the glory of kings to search out the speech.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The heaven above, and the earth beneath, and the heart of kings is unsearchable.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Take away the rust from silver, and there shall come forth a most pure vessel:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Take away wickedness from the face of the king, and his throne shall be established with justice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Appear not glorious before the king, and stand not in the place of great men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For it is better that it should be said to thee: Come up hither; than that thou shouldst be humbled before the prince.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The things which thy eyes have seen, utter not hastily in a quarrel: lest afterward thou mayst not be able to make amends, when thou hast dishonoured thy friend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Treat thy cause with thy friend, and discover not the secret to a stranger:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Lest he insult over thee, when he hath heard it, and cease not to upbraid thee. Grace and friendship deliver a man: keep these for thyself, lest thou fall under reproach.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>To speak a word in due time, is like apples of gold on beds of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>As an earring of gold and a bright pearl, so is he that reproveth the wise, and the obedient ear.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>As the cold of snow in the time of harvest, so is a faithful messenger to him that sent him, for he refresheth his soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>As clouds, and wind, when no rain followeth, so is the man that boasteth, and doth not fulfil his promises.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>By patience a prince shall be appeased, and a soft tongue shall break hardness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Thou hast found honey, eat what is sufficient for thee, lest being glutted therewith thou vomit it up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Withdraw thy foot from the house of thy neighbour, lest having his fill he hate thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>A man that beareth false witness against his neighbour, is like a dart and a sword and a sharp arrow.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>To trust to an unfaithful man in the time of trouble, is like a rotten tooth, and weary foot,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>And one that looseth his garment in cold weather. As vinegar upon nitre, so is he that singeth songs to a very evil heart. As a moth doth by a garment, and a worm by the wood: so the sadness of a man consumeth the heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>If thy enemy be hungry, give him to eat: if he thirst, give him water to drink:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>For thou shalt heap hot coals upon his head, and the Lord will reward thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>The north wind driveth away rain, as doth a sad countenance a backbiting tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>It is better to sit in a corner of the housetop, than with a brawling woman, and in a common house.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>As cold water to a thirsty soul, so is good tidings from a far country.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>A just man falling down before the wicked, is as a fountain troubled with the foot, and a corrupted spring.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>As it is not good for a man to eat much honey, so he that is a searcher of majesty, shall be overwhelmed by glory.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>As a city that lieth open and is not compassed with walls, so is a man that cannot refrain his own spirit in speaking.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="26" preferred_title="Chapter 26">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>As snow in summer, and rain in harvest, so glory is not seemly for a fool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As a bird flying to other places, and a sparrow going here or there: so a curse uttered without cause shall come upon a man.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>A whip for a horse, and a snaffle for an ass, and a rod for the back of fools.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Answer not a fool according to his folly, lest thou be made like him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Answer a fool according to his folly, lest he imagine himself to be wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>He that sendeth words by a foolish messenger, is lame of feet and drinketh iniquity.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>As a lame man hath fair legs in vain: so a parable is unseemly in the mouth of fools.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>As he that casteth a stone into the heap of Mercury: so is he that giveth honour to a fool.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>As if a thorn should grow in the hand of a drunkard: so is a parable in the mouth of fools.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Judgment determineth causes: and he that putteth a fool to silence, appeaseth anger.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>As a dog that returneth to his vomit, so is the fool that repeateth his folly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Hast thou seen a man wise in his own conceit? there shall be more hope of a fool than of him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The slothful man saith: There is a lion in the way, and a lioness in the roads.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>As the door turneth upon its hinges, so doth the slothful upon his bed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The slothful hideth his hand under his armpit, and it grieveth him to turn it to his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The sluggard is wiser in his own conceit, than seven men that speak sentences.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>As he that taketh a dog by the ears, so is he that passeth by in anger, and meddleth with another man&#8217;s quarrel.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>As he is guilty that shooteth arrows, and lances unto death:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>So is the man that hurteth his friend deceitfully: and when he is taken, saith: I did it in jest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>When the wood faileth, the fire shall go out: and when the talebearer is taken away, contentions shall cease.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>As coals are to burning coals, and wood to fire, so an angry man stirreth up strife.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>The words of a talebearer are as it were simple, but they reach to the innermost parts of the belly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Swelling lips joined with a corrupt heart, are like an earthen vessel adorned with silver dross.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>An enemy is known by his lips, when in his heart he entertaineth deceit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>When he shall speak low, trust him not: because there are seven mischiefs in his heart.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He that covereth hatred deceitfully, his malice shall be laid open in the public assembly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He that diggeth a pit, shall fall into it: and he that rolleth a stone, it shall return to him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>A deceitful tongue loveth not truth: and a slippery mouth worketh ruin.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="27" preferred_title="Chapter 27">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Boast not for to morrow, for thou knowest not what the day to come may bring forth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Let another praise thee, and not thy own mouth: a stranger, and not thy own lips.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>A stone is heavy, and sand weighty: but the anger of a fool is heavier than them both.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Anger hath no mercy, nor fury when it breaketh forth: and who can bear the violence of one provoked?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Open rebuke is better than hidden love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Better are the wounds of a friend, than the deceitful kisses of an enemy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>A soul that is full shall tread upon the honeycomb: and a soul that is hungry shall take even bitter for sweet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>As a bird that wandereth from her nest, so is a man that leaveth his place.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Ointment and perfumes rejoice the heart: and the good counsels of a friend are sweet to the soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Thy own friend, and thy father&#8217;s friend forsake not: and go not into thy brother&#8217;s house in the day of thy affliction. Better is a neighbour that is near, than a brother afar off.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Study wisdom, my son, and make my heart joyful, that thou mayst give an answer to him that reproacheth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The prudent man seeing evil hideth himself: little ones passing on have suffered losses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Take away his garment that hath been surety for a stranger: and take from him a pledge for strangers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>He that blesseth his neighbour with a loud voice, rising in the night, shall be like to him that curseth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Roofs dropping through in a cold day, and a contentious woman are alike.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>He that retaineth her, is as he that would hold the wind, and shall call in the oil of his right hand.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Iron sharpeneth iron, so a man sharpeneth the countenance of his friend.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He that keepeth the fig tree, shall eat the fruit thereof: and he that is the keeper of his master, shall be glorified.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>As the faces of them that look therein, shine in the water, so the hearts of men are laid open to the wise.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Hell and destruction are never filled: so the eyes of men are never satisfied.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>As silver is tried in the fining-pot and gold in the furnace: so a man is tried by the mouth of him that praiseth. The heart of the wicked seeketh after evils, but the righteous heart seeketh after knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>Though thou shouldst bray a fool in the mortar, as when a pestle striketh upon sodden barley, his folly would not be taken from him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Be diligent to know the countenance of thy cattle, and consider thy own flocks:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>For thou shalt not always have power: but a crown shall be given to generation and generation.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The meadows are open, and the green herbs have appeared, and the hay is gathered out of the mountains.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Lambs are for thy clothing: and kids for the price of the field.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>Let the milk of the goats be enough for thy food, and for the necessities of thy house, and for maintenance for thy handmaids.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="28" preferred_title="Chapter 28">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The wicked man fleeth, when no man pursueth: but the just, bold as a lion, shall be without dread.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>For the sins of the land many are the princes thereof: and for the wisdom of a man, and the knowledge of those things that are said, the life of the prince shall be prolonged.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>A poor man that oppresseth the poor, is like a violent shower, which bringeth a famine.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>They that forsake the law, praise the wicked man: they that keep it, are incensed against him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Evil men think not on judgment: but they that seek after the Lord, take notice of all things.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Better is the poor man walking in his simplicity, than the rich in crooked ways.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>He that keepeth the law is a wise son: but he that feedeth gluttons, shameth his father.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>He that heapeth together riches by usury and loan, gathereth them for him that will be bountiful to the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>He that turneth away his ears from hearing the law, his prayer shall be an abomination.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>He that deceiveth the just in a wicked way, shall fall in his own destruction: and the upright shall possess his goods.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The rich man seemeth to himself wise: but the poor man that is prudent shall search him out.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>In the joy of the just there is great glory: when the wicked reign, men are ruined.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>He that hideth his sins, shall not prosper: but he that shall confess, and forsake them, shall obtain mercy.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Blessed is the man that is always fearful: but he that is hardened in mind, shall fall into evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>As a roaring lion, and a hungry bear, so is a wicked prince over the poor people.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>A prince void of prudence shall oppress many by calumny: but he that hateth covetousness, shall prolong his days.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>A man that doth violence to the blood of a person, if he flee even to the pit, no man will stay him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>He that walketh uprightly, shall be saved: he that is perverse in his ways shall fall at once.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>He that tilleth his ground, shall be filled with bread: but he that followeth idleness shall be filled with poverty.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>A faithful man shall be much praised: but he that maketh haste to be rich, shall not be innocent.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He that hath respect to a person in judgment, doth not well: such a man even for a morsel of bread forsaketh the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A man, that maketh haste to be rich, and envieth others, is ignorant that poverty shall come upon him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>He that rebuketh a man, shall afterward find favour with him, more than he that by a flattering tongue deceiveth him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He that stealeth any thing from his father, or from his mother: and saith, This is no sin, is the partner of a murderer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>He that boasteth, and puffeth up himself, stirreth up quarrels: but he that trusteth in the Lord, shall be healed. He that trusteth in his own heart, is a fool: but he that walketh wisely, he shall be saved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>He that giveth to the poor, shall not want: he that despiseth his entreaty, shall suffer indigence.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>When the wicked rise up, men shall hide themselves: when they perish, the just shall be multiplied.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="29" preferred_title="Chapter 29">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The man that with a stiff neck despiseth him that reproveth him, shall suddenly be destroyed: and health shall not follow him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>When just men increase, the people shall rejoice: when the wicked shall bear rule, the people shall mourn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>A man that loveth wisdom, rejoiceth his father: but he that maintaineth harlots, shall squander away his substance.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>A just king setteth up the land: a covetous man shall destroy it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>A man that speaketh to his friend with flattering and dissembling words, spreadeth a net for his feet.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>A snare shall entangle the wicked man when he sinneth: and the just shall praise and rejoice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The just taketh notice of the cause of the poor: the wicked is void of knowledge.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Corrupt men bring a city to ruin: but wise men turn away wrath.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If a wise man contend with a fool, whether he be angry, or laugh, he shall find no rest.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Bloodthirsty men hate the upright: but just men seek his soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>A fool uttereth all his mind: a wise man deferreth, and keepeth it till afterwards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A prince that gladly heareth lying words, hath all his servants wicked.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The poor man and the creditor have met one another: the Lord is the enlightener of them both.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>The king that judgeth the poor in truth, his throne shall be established for ever.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The rod and reproof give wisdom: but the child that is left to his own will bringeth his mother to shame.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>When the wicked are multiplied, crimes shall be multiplied: but the just shall see their downfall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Instruct thy son, and he shall refresh thee, and shall give delight to thy soul.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>When prophecy shall fail, the people shall be scattered abroad: but he that keepeth the law is blessed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>A slave will not be corrected by words: because he understandeth what thou sayest, and will not answer.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Hast thou seen a man hasty to speak? folly is rather to be looked for, than his amendment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>He that nourisheth his servant delicately from his childhood, afterwards shall find him stubborn.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>A passionate man provoketh quarrels: and he that is easily stirred up to wrath, shall be more prone to sin.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Humiliation followeth the proud: and glory shall uphold the humble of spirit.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>He that is partaker with a thief, hateth his own soul: he heareth one putting him to his oath, and discovereth not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>He that feareth man, shall quickly fall: he that trusteth in the Lord, shall be set on high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>Many seek the face of the prince: but the judgment of every one cometh forth from the Lord.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The just abhor the wicked man: and the wicked loathe them that are in the right way. The son that keepeth the word, shall be free from destruction.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="30" preferred_title="Chapter 30">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The words of Gatherer the son of Vomiter. The vision which the man spoke with whom God is, and who being strengthened by God, abiding with him, said:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I am the most foolish of men, and the wisdom of men is not with me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I have not learned wisdom, and have not known the science of saints.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Who hath ascended up into heaven, and descended? who hath held the wind in his hands? who hath bound up the waters together as in a garment? who hath raised up all the borders of the earth? what is his name, and what is the name of his son, if thou knowest?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Every word of God is fire tried: he is a buckler to them that hope in him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Add not any thing to his words, lest thou be reproved, and found a liar:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Two things I have asked of thee, deny them not to me before I die.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Remove far from me vanity, and lying words. Give me neither beggary, nor riches: give me only the necessaries of life:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Lest perhaps being filled, I should be tempted to deny, and say: Who is the Lord? or being compelled by poverty, I should steal, and forswear the name of my God.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Accuse not a servant to his master, lest he curse thee, and thou fall.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>There is a generation that curseth their father, and doth not bless their mother.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A generation that are pure in their own eyes, and yet are not washed from their filthiness.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>A generation, whose eyes are lofty, and their eyelids lifted up on high.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>A generation, that for teeth hath swords, and grindeth with their jaw teeth, to devour the needy from off the earth, and the poor from among men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The horseleech hath two daughters that say: Bring, bring. There are three things that never are satisfied, and the fourth never saith: It is enough.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Hell, and the mouth of the womb, and the earth which is not satisfied with water: and the fire never saith: It is enough.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>The eye that mocketh at his father, and that despiseth the labour of his mother in bearing him, let the ravens of the brooks pick it out, and the young eagles eat it.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>Three things are hard to me, and the fourth I am utterly ignorant of.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>The way of an eagle in the air, the way of a serpent upon a rock, the way of a ship in the midst of the sea, and the way of a man in youth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>Such is also the way of an adulterous woman, who eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and saith: I have done no evil.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>By three things the earth is disturbed, and the fourth it cannot bear:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>By a slave when he reigneth: by a fool when he is filled with meat:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>By an odious woman when she is married: and by a bondwoman when she is heir to her mistress.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>There are four very little things of the earth, and they are wiser than the wise:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>The ants, a feeble people, which provide themselves food in the harvest:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>The rabbit, a weak people, which maketh its bed in the rock:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>The locust hath no king, yet they all go out by their bands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>The stellio supporteth itself on hands, and dwelleth in kings&#8217; houses.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>There are three things, which go well, and the fourth that walketh happily:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>A lion, the strongest of beasts, who hath no fear of any thing he meeteth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>A cock girded about the loins: and a ram: and a king, whom none can resist.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="32">
      <content>There is that hath appeared a fool after he was lifted up on high: for if he had understood, he would have laid his hand upon his mouth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="33">
      <content>And he that strongly squeezeth the paps to bring out milk, straineth out butter: and he that violently bloweth his nose, bringeth out blood: and he that provoketh wrath bringeth forth strife.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="31" preferred_title="Chapter 31">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>The words of king Lamuel. The vision wherewith his mother instructed him.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>What, O my beloved, what, O the beloved of my womb, what, O the beloved of my vows?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Give not thy substance to women, and thy riches to destroy kings.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Give not to kings, O Lamuel, give not wine to kings: because there is no secret where drunkenness reigneth:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>And lest they drink and forget judgments, and pervert the cause of the children of the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Give strong drink to them that are sad: and wine to them that are grieved in mind:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Let them drink, and forget their want, and remember their sorrow no more.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Open thy mouth for the dumb, and for the causes of all the children that pass.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Open thy mouth, decree that which is just, and do justice to the needy and poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Who shall find a valiant woman? far and from the uttermost coasts is the price of her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The heart of her husband trusteth in her, and he shall have no need of spoils.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>She will render him good, and not evil, all the days of her life.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>She hath sought wool and flax, and hath wrought by the counsel of her hands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>She is like the merchant&#8217;s ship, she bringeth her bread from afar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>And she hath risen in the night, and given a prey to her household, and victuals to her maidens.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>She hath considered a field, and bought it: with the fruit of her hands she hath planted a vineyard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>She hath girded her loins with strength, and hath strengthened her arm.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="18">
      <content>She hath tasted and seen that her traffic is good: her lamp shall not be put out in the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="19">
      <content>She hath put out her hand to strong things, and her fingers have taken hold of the spindle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="20">
      <content>She hath opened her hand to the needy, and stretched out her hands to the poor.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="21">
      <content>She shall not fear for her house in the cold of snow: for all her domestics are clothed with double garments.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="22">
      <content>She hath made for herself clothing of tapestry: fine linen, and purple is her covering.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="23">
      <content>Her husband is honourable in the gates, when he sitteth among the senators of the land.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="24">
      <content>She made fine linen, and sold it, and delivered a girdle to the Chanaanite.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="25">
      <content>Strength and beauty are her clothing, and she shall laugh in the latter day.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="26">
      <content>She hath opened her mouth to wisdom, and the law of clemency is on her tongue.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="27">
      <content>She hath looked well to the paths of her house, and hath not eaten her bread idle.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="28">
      <content>Her children rose up, and called her blessed: her husband, and he praised her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="29">
      <content>Many daughters have gathered together riches: thou hast surpassed them all.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="30">
      <content>Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vain: the woman that feareth the Lord, she shall be praised.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="31">
      <content>Give her of the fruit of her hands: and let her works praise her in the gates.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>