<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Chapter 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Let him kiss me with the kiss of his mouth: for thy breasts are better than wine,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Smelling sweet of the best ointments. Thy name is as oil poured out: therefore young maidens have loved thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Draw me: we will run after thee to the odour of thy ointments. The king hath brought me into his storerooms: we will be glad and rejoice in thee, remembering thy breasts more than wine: the rightous love thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I am black but beautiful, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, as the tents of Cedar, as the curtains of Solomon.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Do not consider me that I am brown, because the sun hath altered my colour: the sons of my mother have fought against me, they have made me the keeper in the vineyards: my vineyard I have not kept.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Shew me, O thou whom my soul loveth, where thou feedest, where thou liest in the midday, lest I begin to wander after the flocks of thy companions.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>If thou know not thyself, O fairest among women, go forth, and follow after the steps of the flocks, and feed thy kids beside the tents of the shepherds.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>To my company of horsemen, in Pharao&#8217;s chariots, have I likened thee, O my love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thy cheeks are beautiful as the turtledove&#8217;s, thy neck as jewels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>We will make thee chains of gold, inlaid with silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>While the king was at his repose, my spikenard sent forth the odour thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>A bundle of myrrh is my beloved to me, he shall abide between my breasts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>A cluster of cypress my love is to me, in the vineyards of Engaddi.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Behold thou art fair, O my love, behold thou art fair, thy eyes are as those of doves.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Behold thou art fair, my beloved, and comely. Our bed is flourishing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>The beams of our houses are of cedar, our rafters of cypress trees.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="Chapter 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>I am the flower of the field, and the lily of the valleys.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>As the lily among thorns, so is my love among the daughters.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>As the apple tree among the trees of the woods, so is my beloved among the sons. I sat down under his shadow, whom I desired: and his fruit was sweet to my palate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>He brought me into the cellar of wine, he set in order charity in me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Stay me up with flowers, compass me about with apples: because I languish with love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>His left hand is under my head, and his right hand shall embrace me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>I adjure you, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes, and the harts of the field, that you stir not up, nor make the beloved to awake, till she please.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The voice of my beloved, behold he cometh leaping upon the mountains, skipping over the hills.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>My beloved is like a roe, or a young hart. Behold he standeth behind our wall, looking through the windows, looking through the lattices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Behold my beloved speaketh to me: Arise, make haste, my love, my dove, my beautiful one, and come.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For winter is now past, the rain is over and gone.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>The flowers have appeared in our land, the time of pruning is come: the voice of the turtle is heard in our land:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The fig tree hath put forth her green figs: the vines in flower yield their sweet smell. Arise, my love, my beautiful one, and come:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>My dove in the clefts of the rock, in the hollow places of the wall, shew me thy face, let thy voice sound in my ears: for thy voice is sweet, and thy face comely.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>Catch us the little foxes that destroy the vines: for our vineyard hath flourished.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>My beloved to me, and I to him who feedeth among the lilies,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Till the day break, and the shadows retire. Return: be like, my beloved, to a roe, or to a young hart upon the mountains of Bether.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="Chapter 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>In my bed by night I sought him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, and found him not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I will rise, and will go about the city: in the streets and the broad ways I will seek him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, and I found him not.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The watchmen who keep the city, found me: Have you seen him, whom my soul loveth?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>When I had a little passed by them, I found him whom my soul loveth: I held him: and I will not let him go, till I bring him into my mother&#8217;s house, and into the chamber of her that bore me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes and the harts of the fields, that you stir not up, nor awake my beloved, till she please.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Who is she that goeth up by the desert, as a pillar of smoke of aromatical spices, of myrrh, and frankincense, and of all the powders of the perfumer?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Behold threescore valiant ones of the most valiant of Israel, surrounded the bed of Solomon?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>All holding swords, and most expert in war: every man&#8217;s sword upon his thigh, because of fears in the night.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>King Solomon hath made him a litter of the wood of Libanus:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>The pillars thereof he made of silver, the seat of gold, the going up of purple: the midst he covered with charity for the daughters of Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Go forth, ye daughters of Sion, and see king Solomon in the diadem, wherewith his mother crowned him in the day of his espousals, and in the day of the joy of his heart.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="4" preferred_title="Chapter 4">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>How beautiful art thou, my love, how beautiful art thou! thy eyes are doves&#8217; eyes, besides what is hid within. Thy hair is as flocks of goats, which come up from mount Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thy teeth as flocks of sheep, that are shorn, which come up from the washing, all with twins, and there is none barren among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thy lips are as a scarlet lace: and thy speech sweet. Thy cheeks are as a piece of a pomegranate, besides that which lieth hid within.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thy neck is as the tower of David, which is built with bulwarks: a thousand bucklers hang upon it, all the armour of valiant men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thy two breasts like two young roes that are twins, which feed among the lilies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Till the day break, and the shadows retire, I will go to the mountain of myrrh, and to the hill of frankincense.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thou art all fair, O my love, and there is not a spot in thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Come from Libanus, my spouse, come from Libanus, come: thou shalt be crowned from the top of Amana, from the top of Sanir and Hermon, from the dens of the lions, from the mountains of the leopards.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thou hast wounded my heart, my sister, my spouse, thou hast wounded my heart with one of thy eyes, and with one hair of thy neck.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>How beautiful are thy breasts, my sister, my spouse! thy breasts are more beautiful than wine, and the sweet smell of thy ointments above all aromatical spices.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Thy lips, my spouse, are as a dropping honeycomb, honey and milk are under thy tongue; and the smell of thy garments, as the smell of frankincense.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>My sister, my spouse, is a garden enclosed, a garden enclosed, a fountain sealed up.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thy plants are a paradise of pomegranates with the fruits of the orchard. Cypress with spikenard.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Spikenard and saffron, sweet cane and cinnamon, with all the trees of Libanus, myrrh and aloes with all the chief perfumes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>The fountain of gardens: the well of living waters, which run with a strong stream from Libanus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>Arise, O north wind, and come, O south wind, blow through my garden, and let the aromatical spices thereof flow.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="5" preferred_title="Chapter 5">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Let my beloved come into his garden, and eat the fruit of his apple trees. I am come into my garden, O my sister, my spouse, I have gathered my myrrh, with my aromatical spices: I have eaten the honeycomb with my honey, I have drunk my wine with my milk: eat, O friends, and drink, and be inebriated, my dearly beloved.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I sleep, and my heart watcheth: the voice of my beloved knocking: Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled: for my head is full of dew, and my locks of the drops of the nights.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>I have put off my garment, how shall I put it on? I have washed my feet, how shall I defile them?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>My beloved put his hand through the key hole, and my bowels were moved at his touch.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>I arose up to open to my beloved: my hands dropped with myrrh, and my fingers were full of the choicest myrrh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>I opened the bolt of my door to my beloved: but he had turned aside, and was gone. My soul melted when he spoke: I sought him, and found him not: I called, and he did not answer me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>The keepers that go about the city found me: they struck me: and wounded me: the keepers of the walls took away my veil from me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem, if you find my beloved, that you tell him that I languish with love.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>What manner of one is thy beloved of the beloved, O thou most beautiful among women? what manner of one is thy beloved of the beloved, that thou hast so adjured us?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>My beloved is white and ruddy, chosen out of thousands.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>His head is as the finest gold: his locks as branches of palm trees, black as a raven.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>His eyes as doves upon brooks of waters, which are washed with milk, and sit beside the plentiful streams.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>His cheeks are as beds of aromatical spices set by the perfumers. His lips are as lilies dropping choice myrrh.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>His hands are turned and as of gold, full of hyacinths. His belly as of ivory, set with sapphires.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>His legs as pillars of marble, that are set upon bases of gold. His form as of Libanus, excellent as the cedars.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>His throat most sweet, and he is all lovely: such is my beloved, and he is my friend, O ye daughters of Jerusalem.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="17">
      <content>Whither is thy beloved gone, O thou most beautiful among women? whither is thy beloved turned aside, and we will seek him with thee?</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="6" preferred_title="Chapter 6">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>My beloved is gone down into his garden, to the bed of aromatical spices, to feed in the gardens, and to gather lilies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I to my beloved, and my beloved to me, who feedeth among the lilies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thou art beautiful, O my love, sweet and comely as Jerusalem: terrible as an army set in array.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Turn away thy eyes from me, for they have made me flee away. Thy hair is as a flock of goats, that appear from Galaad.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thy teeth as a flock of sheep, which come up from the washing, all with twins, and there is none barren among them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Thy cheeks are as the bark of a pomegranate, beside what is hidden within thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>There are threescore queens, and fourscore concubines, and young maidens without number.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>One is my dove, my perfect one is but one, she is the only one of her mother, the chosen of her that bore her. The daughters saw her, and declared her most blessed: the queens and concubines, and they praised her.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Who is she that cometh forth as the morning rising, fair as the moon, bright as the sun, terrible as an army set in array?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I went down into the garden of nuts, to see the fruits of the valleys, and to look if the vineyard had flourished, and the pomegranates budded.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>I knew not: my soul troubled me for the chariots of Aminadab.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Return, return, O Sulamitess: return, return that we may behold thee.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="7" preferred_title="Chapter 7">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>What shalt thou see in the Sulamitess but the companies of camps? How beautiful are thy steps in shoes, O prince&#8217;s daughter! The joints of thy thighs are like jewels, that are made by the hand of a skilful workman.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Thy navel is like a round bowl never wanting cups. Thy belly is like a heap of wheat, set about with lilies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>Thy two breasts are like two young roes that are twins.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>Thy neck as a tower of ivory. Thy eyes like the fishpools in Hesebon, which are in the gate of the daughter of the multitude. Thy nose is as the tower of Libanus, that looketh toward Damascus.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Thy head is like Carmel: and the hairs of thy head as the purple of the king bound in the channels.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>How beautiful art thou, and how comely, my dearest, in delights!</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Thy stature is like to a palm tree, and thy breasts to clusters of grapes.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>I said: I will go up into the palm tree, and will take hold of the fruit thereof: and thy breasts shall be as the clusters of the vine: and the odour of thy mouth like apples.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Thy throat like the best wine, worthy for my beloved to drink, and for his lips and his teeth to ruminate.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I to my beloved, and his turning is towards me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Come, my beloved, let us go forth into the field, let us abide in the villages.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Let us get up early to the vineyards, let us see if the vineyard flourish, if the flowers be ready to bring forth fruits, if the pomegranates flourish: there will I give thee my breasts.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>The mandrakes give a smell. In our gates are all fruits: the new and the old, my beloved, I have kept for thee.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="8" preferred_title="Chapter 8">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Who shall give thee to me for my brother, sucking the breasts of my mother, that I may find thee without, and kiss thee, and now no man may despise me?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>I will take hold of thee, and bring thee into my mother&#8217;s house: there thou shalt teach me, and I will give thee a cup of spiced wine and new wine of my pomegranates.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>His left hand under my head, and his right hand shall embrace me.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem, that you stir not up, nor awake my love till she please.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Who is this that cometh up from the desert, flowing with delights, leaning upon her beloved? Under the apple tree I raised thee up: there thy mother was corrupted, there she was defloured that bore thee.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Put me as a seal upon thy heart, as a seal upon thy arm, for love is strong as death, jealousy as hard as hell, the lamps thereof are fire and flames.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>Many waters cannot quench charity, neither can the floods drown it: if a man should give all the substance of his house for love, he shall despise it as nothing.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>Our sister is little, and hath no breasts. What shall we do to our sister in the day when she is to be spoken to?</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>If she be a wall: let us build upon it bulwarks of silver: if she be a door, let us join it together with boards of cedar.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>I am a wall: and my breasts are as a tower since I am become in his presence as one finding peace.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>The peaceable had a vineyard, in that which hath people: he let out the same to keepers, every man bringeth for the fruit thereof a thousand pieces of silver.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>My vineyard is before me. A thousand are for thee, the peaceable, and two hundred for them that keep the fruit thereof.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Thou that dwellest in the gardens, the friends hearken: make me hear thy voice.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Flee away, O my beloved, and be like to the roe, and to the young hart upon the mountains of aromatical spices.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>