<book>
  <chapter num="1" preferred_title="Chapter 1">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Paul, a servant of God, and an apostle of Jesus Christ, according to the faith of the elect of God and the acknowledging of the truth, which is according to godliness:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>Unto the hope of life everlasting, which God, who lieth not, hath promised before the times of the world:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>But hath in due times manifested his word in preaching, which is committed to me according to the commandment of God our Saviour:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>To Titus my beloved son, according to the common faith, grace and peace from God the Father, and from Christ Jesus our Saviour.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>For this cause I left thee in Crete, that thou shouldest set in order the things that are wanting, and shouldest ordain priests in every city, as I also appointed thee:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>If any be without crime, the husband of one wife, having faithful children, not accused of riot, or unruly.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>For a bishop must be without crime, as the steward of God: not proud, not subject to anger, not given to wine, no striker, not greedy of filthy lucre:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>But given to hospitality, gentle, sober, just, holy, continent:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Embracing that faithful word which is according to doctrine, that he may be able to exhort in sound doctrine, and to convince the gainsayers.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>For there are also many disobedient, vain talkers, and seducers: especially they who are of the circumcision:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Who must be reproved, who subvert whole houses, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre&#8217;s sake.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>One of them a prophet of their own, said, The Cretians are always liars, evil beasts, slothful bellies.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>This testimony is true. Wherefore rebuke them sharply, that they may be sound in the faith;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Not giving heed to Jewish fables and commandments of men, who turn themselves away from the truth.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>All things are clean to the clean: but to them that are defiled, and to unbelievers, nothing is clean: but both their mind and their conscience are defiled.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="16">
      <content>They profess that they know God: but in their works they deny him; being abominable, and incredulous, and to every good work reprobate.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="2" preferred_title="Chapter 2">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>But speak thou the things that become sound doctrine:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>That the aged men be sober, chaste, prudent, sound in faith, in love in patience.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>The aged women, in like manner, in holy attire, not false accusers, not given to much wine, teaching well:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>That they may teach the young women to be wise, to love their husbands, to love their children,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>To be discreet, chaste, sober, having a care of the house, gentle, obedient to their husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Young men, in like manner, exhort that they be sober.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>In all things shew thyself an example of good works, in doctrine, in integrity, in gravity,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>The sound word that can not be blamed: that he, who is on the contrary part, may be afraid, having no evil to say of us.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>Exhort servants to be obedient to their masters, in all things pleasing, not gainsaying:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>Not defrauding, but in all things shewing good fidelity, that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>For the grace of God our Saviour hath appeared to all men;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>Instructing us, that, denying ungodliness and worldly desires, we should live soberly, and justly, and godly in this world,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Looking for the blessed hope and coming of the glory of the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ,</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>Who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and might cleanse to himself a people acceptable, a pursuer of good works.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>These things speak, and exhort and rebuke with all authority. Let no man despise thee.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter num="3" preferred_title="Chapter 3">
    <verse num="1">
      <content>Admonish them to be subject to princes and powers, to obey at a word, to be ready to every good work.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="2">
      <content>To speak evil of no man, not to be litigious, but gentle: shewing all mildness towards all men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="3">
      <content>For we ourselves also were some time unwise, incredulous, erring, slaves to divers desires and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, and hating one another.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="4">
      <content>But when the goodness and kindness of God our Saviour appeared:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="5">
      <content>Not by the works of justice, which we have done, but according to his mercy, he saved us, by the laver of regeneration, and renovation of the Holy Ghost;</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="6">
      <content>Whom he hath poured forth upon us abundantly, through Jesus Christ our Saviour:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="7">
      <content>That, being justified by his grace, we may be heirs, according to hope of life everlasting.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="8">
      <content>It is a faithful saying: and these things I will have thee affirm constantly: that they, who believe in God, may be careful to excel in good works. These things are good and profitable unto men.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="9">
      <content>But avoid foolish questions, and genealogies, and contentions, and strivings about the law. For they are unprofitable and vain.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="10">
      <content>A man that is a heretic, after the first and second admonition, avoid:</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="11">
      <content>Knowing that he, that is such an one, is subverted, and sinneth, being condemned by his own judgment.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="12">
      <content>When I shall send to thee Artemas or Tychicus, make haste to come unto me to Nicopolis. For there I have determined to winter.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="13">
      <content>Send forward Zenas, the lawyer, and Apollo, with care, that nothing be wanting to them.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="14">
      <content>And let our men also learn to excel in good works for necessary uses: that they be not unfruitful.</content>
    </verse>
    <verse num="15">
      <content>All that are with me salute thee: salute them that love us in the faith. The grace of God be with you all. Amen.</content>
    </verse>
  </chapter>
</book>