<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>In the land of Uz there lived a man whose name was Job. This man was blameless and upright; he feared God and shunned evil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He had seven sons and three daughters,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>and he owned seven thousand sheep, three thousand camels, five hundred yoke of oxen and five hundred donkeys, and had a large number of servants. He was the greatest man among all the people of the East.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>His sons used to take turns holding feasts in their homes, and they would invite their three sisters to eat and drink with them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>When a period of feasting had run its course, Job would send and have them purified. Early in the morning he would sacrifice a burnt offering for each of them, thinking, "Perhaps my children have sinned and cursed God in their hearts." This was Job's regular custom.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>One day the angels </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> came to present themselves before the LORD, and Satan </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> also came with them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The LORD said to Satan, "Where have you come from?" Satan answered the LORD, "From roaming through the earth and going back and forth in it."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Then the LORD said to Satan, "Have you considered my servant Job? There is no one on earth like him; he is blameless and upright, a man who fears God and shuns evil."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"Does Job fear God for nothing?" Satan replied.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"Have you not put a hedge around him and his household and everything he has? You have blessed the work of his hands, so that his flocks and herds are spread throughout the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>But stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your face."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The LORD said to Satan, "Very well, then, everything he has is in your hands, but on the man himself do not lay a finger." Then Satan went out from the presence of the LORD.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>One day when Job's sons and daughters were feasting and drinking wine at the oldest brother's house,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>a messenger came to Job and said, "The oxen were plowing and the donkeys were grazing nearby,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>and the Sabeans attacked and carried them off. They put the servants to the sword, and I am the only one who has escaped to tell you!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>While he was still speaking, another messenger came and said, "The fire of God fell from the sky and burned up the sheep and the servants, and I am the only one who has escaped to tell you!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>While he was still speaking, another messenger came and said, "The Chaldeans formed three raiding parties and swept down on your camels and carried them off. They put the servants to the sword, and I am the only one who has escaped to tell you!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>While he was still speaking, yet another messenger came and said, "Your sons and daughters were feasting and drinking wine at the oldest brother's house,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>when suddenly a mighty wind swept in from the desert and struck the four corners of the house. It collapsed on them and they are dead, and I am the only one who has escaped to tell you!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>At this, Job got up and tore his robe and shaved his head. Then he fell to the ground in worship</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>and said: "Naked I came from my mother's womb, and naked I will depart. </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> The LORD gave and the LORD has taken away; may the name of the LORD be praised."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>In all this, Job did not sin by charging God with wrongdoing. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">the sons of God</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> </content>
            <content kind="EM">Satan</content>
            <content> means </content>
            <content kind="EM">accuser.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">will return there</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>On another day the angels </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> came to present themselves before the LORD, and Satan also came with them to present himself before him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>And the LORD said to Satan, "Where have you come from?" Satan answered the LORD, "From roaming through the earth and going back and forth in it."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Then the LORD said to Satan, "Have you considered my servant Job? There is no one on earth like him; he is blameless and upright, a man who fears God and shuns evil. And he still maintains his integrity, though you incited me against him to ruin him without any reason."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Skin for skin!" Satan replied. "A man will give all he has for his own life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But stretch out your hand and strike his flesh and bones, and he will surely curse you to your face."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The LORD said to Satan, "Very well, then, he is in your hands; but you must spare his life."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>So Satan went out from the presence of the LORD and afflicted Job with painful sores from the soles of his feet to the top of his head.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Then Job took a piece of broken pottery and scraped himself with it as he sat among the ashes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>His wife said to him, "Are you still holding on to your integrity? Curse God and die!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He replied, "You are talking like a foolish </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> woman. Shall we accept good from God, and not trouble?" In all this, Job did not sin in what he said. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>When Job's three friends, Eliphaz the Temanite, Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite, heard about all the troubles that had come upon him, they set out from their homes and met together by agreement to go and sympathize with him and comfort him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>When they saw him from a distance, they could hardly recognize him; they began to weep aloud, and they tore their robes and sprinkled dust on their heads.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Then they sat on the ground with him for seven days and seven nights. No one said a word to him, because they saw how great his suffering was.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">the sons of God</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> The Hebrew word rendered </content>
            <content kind="EM">foolish</content>
            <content> denotes moral deficiency.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>After this, Job opened his mouth and cursed the day of his birth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He said:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>"May the day of my birth perish, and the night it was said, `A boy is born!'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>That day--may it turn to darkness; may God above not care about it; may no light shine upon it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>May darkness and deep shadow </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> claim it once more; may a cloud settle over it; may blackness overwhelm its light.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>That night--may thick darkness seize it; may it not be included among the days of the year nor be entered in any of the months.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>May that night be barren; may no shout of joy be heard in it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>May those who curse days </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> curse that day, those who are ready to rouse Leviathan.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>May its morning stars become dark; may it wait for daylight in vain and not see the first rays of dawn,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>for it did not shut the doors of the womb on me to hide trouble from my eyes. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"Why did I not perish at birth, and die as I came from the womb?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Why were there knees to receive me and breasts that I might be nursed?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>For now I would be lying down in peace; I would be asleep and at rest</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>with kings and counselors of the earth, who built for themselves places now lying in ruins,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>with rulers who had gold, who filled their houses with silver.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Or why was I not hidden in the ground like a stillborn child, like an infant who never saw the light of day?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>There the wicked cease from turmoil, and there the weary are at rest.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Captives also enjoy their ease; they no longer hear the slave driver's shout.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>The small and the great are there, and the slave is freed from his master. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"Why is light given to those in misery, and life to the bitter of soul,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>to those who long for death that does not come, who search for it more than for hidden treasure,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>who are filled with gladness and rejoice when they reach the grave?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Why is life given to a man whose way is hidden, whom God has hedged in?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>For sighing comes to me instead of food; my groans pour out like water.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>What I feared has come upon me; what I dreaded has happened to me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>I have no peace, no quietness; I have no rest, but only turmoil."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">5</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">and the shadow of death</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">8</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">the sea</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Eliphaz the Temanite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"If someone ventures a word with you, will you be impatient? But who can keep from speaking?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Think how you have instructed many, how you have strengthened feeble hands.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Your words have supported those who stumbled; you have strengthened faltering knees.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But now trouble comes to you, and you are discouraged; it strikes you, and you are dismayed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Should not your piety be your confidence and your blameless ways your hope? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Consider now: Who, being innocent, has ever perished? Where were the upright ever destroyed?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>As I have observed, those who plow evil and those who sow trouble reap it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>At the breath of God they are destroyed; at the blast of his anger they perish.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The lions may roar and growl, yet the teeth of the great lions are broken.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The lion perishes for lack of prey, and the cubs of the lioness are scattered. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"A word was secretly brought to me, my ears caught a whisper of it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Amid disquieting dreams in the night, when deep sleep falls on men,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>fear and trembling seized me and made all my bones shake.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>A spirit glided past my face, and the hair on my body stood on end.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>It stopped, but I could not tell what it was. A form stood before my eyes, and I heard a hushed voice:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>`Can a mortal be more righteous than God? Can a man be more pure than his Maker?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>If God places no trust in his servants, if he charges his angels with error,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>how much more those who live in houses of clay, whose foundations are in the dust, who are crushed more readily than a moth!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Between dawn and dusk they are broken to pieces; unnoticed, they perish forever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Are not the cords of their tent pulled up, so that they die without wisdom?'</content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Some interpreters end the quotation after verse 17.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Call if you will, but who will answer you? To which of the holy ones will you turn?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Resentment kills a fool, and envy slays the simple.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I myself have seen a fool taking root, but suddenly his house was cursed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>His children are far from safety, crushed in court without a defender.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The hungry consume his harvest, taking it even from among thorns, and the thirsty pant after his wealth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>For hardship does not spring from the soil, nor does trouble sprout from the ground.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Yet man is born to trouble as surely as sparks fly upward. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"But if it were I, I would appeal to God; I would lay my cause before him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>He performs wonders that cannot be fathomed, miracles that cannot be counted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He bestows rain on the earth; he sends water upon the countryside.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The lowly he sets on high, and those who mourn are lifted to safety.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>He thwarts the plans of the crafty, so that their hands achieve no success.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>He catches the wise in their craftiness, and the schemes of the wily are swept away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Darkness comes upon them in the daytime; at noon they grope as in the night.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>He saves the needy from the sword in their mouth; he saves them from the clutches of the powerful.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>So the poor have hope, and injustice shuts its mouth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Blessed is the man whom God corrects; so do not despise the discipline of the Almighty. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For he wounds, but he also binds up; he injures, but his hands also heal.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>From six calamities he will rescue you; in seven no harm will befall you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>In famine he will ransom you from death, and in battle from the stroke of the sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>You will be protected from the lash of the tongue, and need not fear when destruction comes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>You will laugh at destruction and famine, and need not fear the beasts of the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>For you will have a covenant with the stones of the field, and the wild animals will be at peace with you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>You will know that your tent is secure; you will take stock of your property and find nothing missing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>You will know that your children will be many, and your descendants like the grass of the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>You will come to the grave in full vigor, like sheaves gathered in season. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"We have examined this, and it is true. So hear it and apply it to yourself."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Shaddai</content>
            <content>; here and throughout Job</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"If only my anguish could be weighed and all my misery be placed on the scales!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>It would surely outweigh the sand of the seas-- no wonder my words have been impetuous.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The arrows of the Almighty are in me, my spirit drinks in their poison; God's terrors are marshaled against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Does a wild donkey bray when it has grass, or an ox bellow when it has fodder?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Is tasteless food eaten without salt, or is there flavor in the white of an egg </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>I refuse to touch it; such food makes me ill. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Oh, that I might have my request, that God would grant what I hope for,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>that God would be willing to crush me, to let loose his hand and cut me off!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Then I would still have this consolation-- my joy in unrelenting pain-- that I had not denied the words of the Holy One. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"What strength do I have, that I should still hope? What prospects, that I should be patient?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Do I have the strength of stone? Is my flesh bronze?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Do I have any power to help myself, now that success has been driven from me? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"A despairing man should have the devotion of his friends, even though he forsakes the fear of the Almighty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>But my brothers are as undependable as intermittent streams, as the streams that overflow</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>when darkened by thawing ice and swollen with melting snow,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>but that cease to flow in the dry season, and in the heat vanish from their channels.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Caravans turn aside from their routes; they go up into the wasteland and perish.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>The caravans of Tema look for water, the traveling merchants of Sheba look in hope.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>They are distressed, because they had been confident; they arrive there, only to be disappointed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Now you too have proved to be of no help; you see something dreadful and are afraid.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Have I ever said, `Give something on my behalf, pay a ransom for me from your wealth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>deliver me from the hand of the enemy, ransom me from the clutches of the ruthless'? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"Teach me, and I will be quiet; show me where I have been wrong.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>How painful are honest words! But what do your arguments prove?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Do you mean to correct what I say, and treat the words of a despairing man as wind?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>You would even cast lots for the fatherless and barter away your friend. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"But now be so kind as to look at me. Would I lie to your face?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Relent, do not be unjust; reconsider, for my integrity is at stake. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Is there any wickedness on my lips? Can my mouth not discern malice? </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this phrase is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">29</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">my righteousness still stands</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Does not man have hard service on earth? Are not his days like those of a hired man?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Like a slave longing for the evening shadows, or a hired man waiting eagerly for his wages,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>so I have been allotted months of futility, and nights of misery have been assigned to me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>When I lie down I think, `How long before I get up?' The night drags on, and I toss till dawn.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>My body is clothed with worms and scabs, my skin is broken and festering. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"My days are swifter than a weaver's shuttle, and they come to an end without hope.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Remember, O God, that my life is but a breath; my eyes will never see happiness again.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The eye that now sees me will see me no longer; you will look for me, but I will be no more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>As a cloud vanishes and is gone, so he who goes down to the grave </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> does not return.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He will never come to his house again; his place will know him no more. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"Therefore I will not keep silent; I will speak out in the anguish of my spirit, I will complain in the bitterness of my soul.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Am I the sea, or the monster of the deep, that you put me under guard?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>When I think my bed will comfort me and my couch will ease my complaint,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>even then you frighten me with dreams and terrify me with visions,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>so that I prefer strangling and death, rather than this body of mine.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I despise my life; I would not live forever. Let me alone; my days have no meaning. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"What is man that you make so much of him, that you give him so much attention,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>that you examine him every morning and test him every moment?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Will you never look away from me, or let me alone even for an instant?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>If I have sinned, what have I done to you, O watcher of men? Why have you made me your target? Have I become a burden to you? </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Why do you not pardon my offenses and forgive my sins? For I will soon lie down in the dust; you will search for me, but I will be no more."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">9</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">20</content>
            <content> A few manuscripts of the Masoretic Text, an ancient Hebrew scribal tradition and Septuagint; most manuscripts of the Masoretic Text </content>
            <content kind="EM">I have become a burden to myself.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Bildad the Shuhite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"How long will you say such things? Your words are a blustering wind.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Does God pervert justice? Does the Almighty pervert what is right?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>When your children sinned against him, he gave them over to the penalty of their sin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But if you will look to God and plead with the Almighty,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>if you are pure and upright, even now he will rouse himself on your behalf and restore you to your rightful place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Your beginnings will seem humble, so prosperous will your future be. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Ask the former generations and find out what their fathers learned,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>for we were born only yesterday and know nothing, and our days on earth are but a shadow.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Will they not instruct you and tell you? Will they not bring forth words from their understanding?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Can papyrus grow tall where there is no marsh? Can reeds thrive without water?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>While still growing and uncut, they wither more quickly than grass.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Such is the destiny of all who forget God; so perishes the hope of the godless.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>What he trusts in is fragile </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ; what he relies on is a spider's web.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>He leans on his web, but it gives way; he clings to it, but it does not hold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>He is like a well-watered plant in the sunshine, spreading its shoots over the garden;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>it entwines its roots around a pile of rocks and looks for a place among the stones.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>But when it is torn from its spot, that place disowns it and says, `I never saw you.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Surely its life withers away, and </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> from the soil other plants grow. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"Surely God does not reject a blameless man or strengthen the hands of evildoers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>He will yet fill your mouth with laughter and your lips with shouts of joy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Your enemies will be clothed in shame, and the tents of the wicked will be no more."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">14</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Surely all the joy it has is that</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Indeed, I know that this is true. But how can a mortal be righteous before God?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Though one wished to dispute with him, he could not answer him one time out of a thousand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>His wisdom is profound, his power is vast. Who has resisted him and come out unscathed?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>He moves mountains without their knowing it and overturns them in his anger.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>He shakes the earth from its place and makes its pillars tremble.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>He speaks to the sun and it does not shine; he seals off the light of the stars.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He alone stretches out the heavens and treads on the waves of the sea.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>He is the Maker of the Bear and Orion, the Pleiades and the constellations of the south.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He performs wonders that cannot be fathomed, miracles that cannot be counted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>When he passes me, I cannot see him; when he goes by, I cannot perceive him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>If he snatches away, who can stop him? Who can say to him, `What are you doing?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>God does not restrain his anger; even the cohorts of Rahab cowered at his feet. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"How then can I dispute with him? How can I find words to argue with him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Though I were innocent, I could not answer him; I could only plead with my Judge for mercy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Even if I summoned him and he responded, I do not believe he would give me a hearing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>He would crush me with a storm and multiply my wounds for no reason.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He would not let me regain my breath but would overwhelm me with misery.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>If it is a matter of strength, he is mighty! And if it is a matter of justice, who will summon him </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Even if I were innocent, my mouth would condemn me; if I were blameless, it would pronounce me guilty. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Although I am blameless, I have no concern for myself; I despise my own life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>It is all the same; that is why I say, `He destroys both the blameless and the wicked.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>When a scourge brings sudden death, he mocks the despair of the innocent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>When a land falls into the hands of the wicked, he blindfolds its judges. If it is not he, then who is it? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>"My days are swifter than a runner; they fly away without a glimpse of joy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>They skim past like boats of papyrus, like eagles swooping down on their prey.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>If I say, `I will forget my complaint, I will change my expression, and smile,'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>I still dread all my sufferings, for I know you will not hold me innocent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Since I am already found guilty, why should I struggle in vain?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>Even if I washed myself with soap </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> and my hands with washing soda,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>you would plunge me into a slime pit so that even my clothes would detest me. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>"He is not a man like me that I might answer him, that we might confront each other in court.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>If only there were someone to arbitrate between us, to lay his hand upon us both,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>someone to remove God's rod from me, so that his terror would frighten me no more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>Then I would speak up without fear of him, but as it now stands with me, I cannot. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> See Septuagint; Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">me.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">30</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">snow</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"I loathe my very life; therefore I will give free rein to my complaint and speak out in the bitterness of my soul.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I will say to God: Do not condemn me, but tell me what charges you have against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Does it please you to oppress me, to spurn the work of your hands, while you smile on the schemes of the wicked?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Do you have eyes of flesh? Do you see as a mortal sees?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Are your days like those of a mortal or your years like those of a man,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>that you must search out my faults and probe after my sin--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>though you know that I am not guilty and that no one can rescue me from your hand? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Your hands shaped me and made me. Will you now turn and destroy me?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Remember that you molded me like clay. Will you now turn me to dust again?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Did you not pour me out like milk and curdle me like cheese,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>clothe me with skin and flesh and knit me together with bones and sinews?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>You gave me life and showed me kindness, and in your providence watched over my spirit. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"But this is what you concealed in your heart, and I know that this was in your mind:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>If I sinned, you would be watching me and would not let my offense go unpunished.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>If I am guilty--woe to me! Even if I am innocent, I cannot lift my head, for I am full of shame and drowned in </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> my affliction.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>If I hold my head high, you stalk me like a lion and again display your awesome power against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>You bring new witnesses against me and increase your anger toward me; your forces come against me wave upon wave. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"Why then did you bring me out of the womb? I wish I had died before any eye saw me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>If only I had never come into being, or had been carried straight from the womb to the grave!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Are not my few days almost over? Turn away from me so I can have a moment's joy</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>before I go to the place of no return, to the land of gloom and deep shadow, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>to the land of deepest night, of deep shadow and disorder, where even the light is like darkness."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">and aware of</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">21</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">and the shadow of death</content>
            <content>; also in verse 22</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Zophar the Naamathite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Are all these words to go unanswered? Is this talker to be vindicated?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Will your idle talk reduce men to silence? Will no one rebuke you when you mock?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>You say to God, `My beliefs are flawless and I am pure in your sight.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Oh, how I wish that God would speak, that he would open his lips against you</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>and disclose to you the secrets of wisdom, for true wisdom has two sides. Know this: God has even forgotten some of your sin. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Can you fathom the mysteries of God? Can you probe the limits of the Almighty?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>They are higher than the heavens--what can you do? They are deeper than the depths of the grave </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> --what can you know?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Their measure is longer than the earth and wider than the sea. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"If he comes along and confines you in prison and convenes a court, who can oppose him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Surely he recognizes deceitful men; and when he sees evil, does he not take note?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But a witless man can no more become wise than a wild donkey's colt can be born a man. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"Yet if you devote your heart to him and stretch out your hands to him,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>if you put away the sin that is in your hand and allow no evil to dwell in your tent,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>then you will lift up your face without shame; you will stand firm and without fear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>You will surely forget your trouble, recalling it only as waters gone by.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Life will be brighter than noonday, and darkness will become like morning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>You will be secure, because there is hope; you will look about you and take your rest in safety.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>You will lie down, with no one to make you afraid, and many will court your favor.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>But the eyes of the wicked will fail, and escape will elude them; their hope will become a dying gasp."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">8</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">than Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">wild donkey can be born tame</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Doubtless you are the people, and wisdom will die with you!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>But I have a mind as well as you; I am not inferior to you. Who does not know all these things? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"I have become a laughingstock to my friends, though I called upon God and he answered-- a mere laughingstock, though righteous and blameless!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Men at ease have contempt for misfortune as the fate of those whose feet are slipping.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The tents of marauders are undisturbed, and those who provoke God are secure-- those who carry their god in their hands. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"But ask the animals, and they will teach you, or the birds of the air, and they will tell you;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>or speak to the earth, and it will teach you, or let the fish of the sea inform you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Which of all these does not know that the hand of the LORD has done this?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>In his hand is the life of every creature and the breath of all mankind.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Does not the ear test words as the tongue tastes food?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Is not wisdom found among the aged? Does not long life bring understanding? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"To God belong wisdom and power; counsel and understanding are his.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>What he tears down cannot be rebuilt; the man he imprisons cannot be released.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>If he holds back the waters, there is drought; if he lets them loose, they devastate the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>To him belong strength and victory; both deceived and deceiver are his.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>He leads counselors away stripped and makes fools of judges.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He takes off the shackles put on by kings and ties a loincloth </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> around their waist.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He leads priests away stripped and overthrows men long established.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>He silences the lips of trusted advisers and takes away the discernment of elders.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>He pours contempt on nobles and disarms the mighty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>He reveals the deep things of darkness and brings deep shadows into the light.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>He makes nations great, and destroys them; he enlarges nations, and disperses them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>He deprives the leaders of the earth of their reason; he sends them wandering through a trackless waste.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>They grope in darkness with no light; he makes them stagger like drunkards. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">secure in what God's hand brings them</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">shackles of kings and ties a belt</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"My eyes have seen all this, my ears have heard and understood it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>What you know, I also know; I am not inferior to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>But I desire to speak to the Almighty and to argue my case with God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>You, however, smear me with lies; you are worthless physicians, all of you!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>If only you would be altogether silent! For you, that would be wisdom.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Hear now my argument; listen to the plea of my lips.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Will you speak wickedly on God's behalf? Will you speak deceitfully for him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Will you show him partiality? Will you argue the case for God?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Would it turn out well if he examined you? Could you deceive him as you might deceive men?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He would surely rebuke you if you secretly showed partiality.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Would not his splendor terrify you? Would not the dread of him fall on you?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Your maxims are proverbs of ashes; your defenses are defenses of clay. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"Keep silent and let me speak; then let come to me what may.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Why do I put myself in jeopardy and take my life in my hands?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Though he slay me, yet will I hope in him; I will surely </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> defend my ways to his face.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Indeed, this will turn out for my deliverance, for no godless man would dare come before him!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Listen carefully to my words; let your ears take in what I say.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Now that I have prepared my case, I know I will be vindicated.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Can anyone bring charges against me? If so, I will be silent and die. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"Only grant me these two things, O God, and then I will not hide from you:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Withdraw your hand far from me, and stop frightening me with your terrors.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Then summon me and I will answer, or let me speak, and you reply.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>How many wrongs and sins have I committed? Show me my offense and my sin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Why do you hide your face and consider me your enemy?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Will you torment a windblown leaf? Will you chase after dry chaff?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>For you write down bitter things against me and make me inherit the sins of my youth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>You fasten my feet in shackles; you keep close watch on all my paths by putting marks on the soles of my feet. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"So man wastes away like something rotten, like a garment eaten by moths. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">He will surely slay me; I have no hope -- / yet I will</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Man born of woman is of few days and full of trouble.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>He springs up like a flower and withers away; like a fleeting shadow, he does not endure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Do you fix your eye on such a one? Will you bring him </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> before you for judgment?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Who can bring what is pure from the impure? No one!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Man's days are determined; you have decreed the number of his months and have set limits he cannot exceed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>So look away from him and let him alone, till he has put in his time like a hired man. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"At least there is hope for a tree: If it is cut down, it will sprout again, and its new shoots will not fail.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Its roots may grow old in the ground and its stump die in the soil,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>yet at the scent of water it will bud and put forth shoots like a plant.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But man dies and is laid low; he breathes his last and is no more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>As water disappears from the sea or a riverbed becomes parched and dry,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>so man lies down and does not rise; till the heavens are no more, men will not awake or be roused from their sleep. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"If only you would hide me in the grave </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> and conceal me till your anger has passed! If only you would set me a time and then remember me!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>If a man dies, will he live again? All the days of my hard service I will wait for my renewal </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> to come.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>You will call and I will answer you; you will long for the creature your hands have made.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Surely then you will count my steps but not keep track of my sin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>My offenses will be sealed up in a bag; you will cover over my sin. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"But as a mountain erodes and crumbles and as a rock is moved from its place,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>as water wears away stones and torrents wash away the soil, so you destroy man's hope.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>You overpower him once for all, and he is gone; you change his countenance and send him away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>If his sons are honored, he does not know it; if they are brought low, he does not see it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>He feels but the pain of his own body and mourns only for himself."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">3</content>
            <content> Septuagint, Vulgate and Syriac; Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">me</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">14</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">release</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="15">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Eliphaz the Temanite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Would a wise man answer with empty notions or fill his belly with the hot east wind?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Would he argue with useless words, with speeches that have no value?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>But you even undermine piety and hinder devotion to God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Your sin prompts your mouth; you adopt the tongue of the crafty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Your own mouth condemns you, not mine; your own lips testify against you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Are you the first man ever born? Were you brought forth before the hills?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Do you listen in on God's council? Do you limit wisdom to yourself?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>What do you know that we do not know? What insights do you have that we do not have?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The gray-haired and the aged are on our side, men even older than your father.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Are God's consolations not enough for you, words spoken gently to you?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Why has your heart carried you away, and why do your eyes flash,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>so that you vent your rage against God and pour out such words from your mouth? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"What is man, that he could be pure, or one born of woman, that he could be righteous?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>If God places no trust in his holy ones, if even the heavens are not pure in his eyes,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>how much less man, who is vile and corrupt, who drinks up evil like water! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Listen to me and I will explain to you; let me tell you what I have seen,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>what wise men have declared, hiding nothing received from their fathers</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>(to whom alone the land was given when no alien passed among them):</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>All his days the wicked man suffers torment, the ruthless through all the years stored up for him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Terrifying sounds fill his ears; when all seems well, marauders attack him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>He despairs of escaping the darkness; he is marked for the sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>He wanders about--food for vultures </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ; he knows the day of darkness is at hand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Distress and anguish fill him with terror; they overwhelm him, like a king poised to attack,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>because he shakes his fist at God and vaunts himself against the Almighty,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>defiantly charging against him with a thick, strong shield. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"Though his face is covered with fat and his waist bulges with flesh,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>he will inhabit ruined towns and houses where no one lives, houses crumbling to rubble.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>He will no longer be rich and his wealth will not endure, nor will his possessions spread over the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>He will not escape the darkness; a flame will wither his shoots, and the breath of God's mouth will carry him away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Let him not deceive himself by trusting what is worthless, for he will get nothing in return.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Before his time he will be paid in full, and his branches will not flourish.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>He will be like a vine stripped of its unripe grapes, like an olive tree shedding its blossoms.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>For the company of the godless will be barren, and fire will consume the tents of those who love bribes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>They conceive trouble and give birth to evil; their womb fashions deceit."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">23</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">about, looking for food</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="16">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"I have heard many things like these; miserable comforters are you all!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Will your long-winded speeches never end? What ails you that you keep on arguing?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>I also could speak like you, if you were in my place; I could make fine speeches against you and shake my head at you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But my mouth would encourage you; comfort from my lips would bring you relief. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"Yet if I speak, my pain is not relieved; and if I refrain, it does not go away.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Surely, O God, you have worn me out; you have devastated my entire household.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>You have bound me--and it has become a witness; my gauntness rises up and testifies against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>God assails me and tears me in his anger and gnashes his teeth at me; my opponent fastens on me his piercing eyes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Men open their mouths to jeer at me; they strike my cheek in scorn and unite together against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>God has turned me over to evil men and thrown me into the clutches of the wicked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>All was well with me, but he shattered me; he seized me by the neck and crushed me. He has made me his target;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>his archers surround me. Without pity, he pierces my kidneys and spills my gall on the ground.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Again and again he bursts upon me; he rushes at me like a warrior. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"I have sewed sackcloth over my skin and buried my brow in the dust.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>My face is red with weeping, deep shadows ring my eyes;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>yet my hands have been free of violence and my prayer is pure. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"O earth, do not cover my blood; may my cry never be laid to rest!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Even now my witness is in heaven; my advocate is on high.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>My intercessor is my friend</content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> as my eyes pour out tears to God;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>on behalf of a man he pleads with God as a man pleads for his friend. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"Only a few years will pass before I go on the journey of no return.</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">20</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">My friends treat me with scorn</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="17">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>My spirit is broken, my days are cut short, the grave awaits me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Surely mockers surround me; my eyes must dwell on their hostility. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>"Give me, O God, the pledge you demand. Who else will put up security for me?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>You have closed their minds to understanding; therefore you will not let them triumph.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>If a man denounces his friends for reward, the eyes of his children will fail. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>"God has made me a byword to everyone, a man in whose face people spit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>My eyes have grown dim with grief; my whole frame is but a shadow.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Upright men are appalled at this; the innocent are aroused against the ungodly.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Nevertheless, the righteous will hold to their ways, and those with clean hands will grow stronger. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"But come on, all of you, try again! I will not find a wise man among you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>My days have passed, my plans are shattered, and so are the desires of my heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>These men turn night into day; in the face of darkness they say, `Light is near.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>If the only home I hope for is the grave, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> if I spread out my bed in darkness,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>if I say to corruption, `You are my father,' and to the worm, `My mother' or `My sister,'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>where then is my hope? Who can see any hope for me?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Will it go down to the gates of death </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> ? Will we descend together into the dust?"</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">16</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="18">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Bildad the Shuhite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"When will you end these speeches? Be sensible, and then we can talk.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Why are we regarded as cattle and considered stupid in your sight?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>You who tear yourself to pieces in your anger, is the earth to be abandoned for your sake? Or must the rocks be moved from their place? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"The lamp of the wicked is snuffed out; the flame of his fire stops burning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>The light in his tent becomes dark; the lamp beside him goes out.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>The vigor of his step is weakened; his own schemes throw him down.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>His feet thrust him into a net and he wanders into its mesh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>A trap seizes him by the heel; a snare holds him fast.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>A noose is hidden for him on the ground; a trap lies in his path.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Terrors startle him on every side and dog his every step.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Calamity is hungry for him; disaster is ready for him when he falls.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>It eats away parts of his skin; death's firstborn devours his limbs.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>He is torn from the security of his tent and marched off to the king of terrors.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Fire resides </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> in his tent; burning sulfur is scattered over his dwelling.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>His roots dry up below and his branches wither above.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>The memory of him perishes from the earth; he has no name in the land.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>He is driven from light into darkness and is banished from the world.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He has no offspring or descendants among his people, no survivor where once he lived.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Men of the west are appalled at his fate; men of the east are seized with horror.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Surely such is the dwelling of an evil man; such is the place of one who knows not God."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Nothing he had remains</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="19">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"How long will you torment me and crush me with words?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Ten times now you have reproached me; shamelessly you attack me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>If it is true that I have gone astray, my error remains my concern alone.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>If indeed you would exalt yourselves above me and use my humiliation against me,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>then know that God has wronged me and drawn his net around me. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Though I cry, `I've been wronged!' I get no response; though I call for help, there is no justice.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He has blocked my way so I cannot pass; he has shrouded my paths in darkness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>He has stripped me of my honor and removed the crown from my head.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He tears me down on every side till I am gone; he uproots my hope like a tree.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>His anger burns against me; he counts me among his enemies.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>His troops advance in force; they build a siege ramp against me and encamp around my tent. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"He has alienated my brothers from me; my acquaintances are completely estranged from me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>My kinsmen have gone away; my friends have forgotten me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>My guests and my maidservants count me a stranger; they look upon me as an alien.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I summon my servant, but he does not answer, though I beg him with my own mouth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>My breath is offensive to my wife; I am loathsome to my own brothers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Even the little boys scorn me; when I appear, they ridicule me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>All my intimate friends detest me; those I love have turned against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>I am nothing but skin and bones; I have escaped with only the skin of my teeth. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Have pity on me, my friends, have pity, for the hand of God has struck me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Why do you pursue me as God does? Will you never get enough of my flesh? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"Oh, that my words were recorded, that they were written on a scroll,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>that they were inscribed with an iron tool on </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> lead, or engraved in rock forever!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>I know that my Redeemer </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> lives, and that in the end he will stand upon the earth. </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>And after my skin has been destroyed, yet </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> in </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> my flesh I will see God;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>I myself will see him with my own eyes--I, and not another. How my heart yearns within me! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>"If you say, `How we will hound him, since the root of the trouble lies in him, </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> '</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>you should fear the sword yourselves; for wrath will bring punishment by the sword, and then you will know that there is judgment. </content>
            <note_ref>8</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">20</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">only my gums</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">and</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">25</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">defender</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">25</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">upon my grave</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">26</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">And after I awake, though this [body] has been destroyed, then</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">26</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM"> apart from</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">28</content>
            <content> Many Hebrew manuscripts, Septuagint and Vulgate; most Hebrew manuscripts </content>
            <content kind="EM">me</content>
        </note>
        <note num="8">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">29</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">that you may come to know the Almighty</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="20">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Zophar the Naamathite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"My troubled thoughts prompt me to answer because I am greatly disturbed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I hear a rebuke that dishonors me, and my understanding inspires me to reply. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Surely you know how it has been from of old, ever since man </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> was placed on the earth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>that the mirth of the wicked is brief, the joy of the godless lasts but a moment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Though his pride reaches to the heavens and his head touches the clouds,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>he will perish forever, like his own dung; those who have seen him will say, `Where is he?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Like a dream he flies away, no more to be found, banished like a vision of the night.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The eye that saw him will not see him again; his place will look on him no more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>His children must make amends to the poor; his own hands must give back his wealth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The youthful vigor that fills his bones will lie with him in the dust. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"Though evil is sweet in his mouth and he hides it under his tongue,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>though he cannot bear to let it go and keeps it in his mouth,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>yet his food will turn sour in his stomach; it will become the venom of serpents within him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>He will spit out the riches he swallowed; God will make his stomach vomit them up.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>He will suck the poison of serpents; the fangs of an adder will kill him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>He will not enjoy the streams, the rivers flowing with honey and cream.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>What he toiled for he must give back uneaten; he will not enjoy the profit from his trading.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>For he has oppressed the poor and left them destitute; he has seized houses he did not build. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"Surely he will have no respite from his craving; he cannot save himself by his treasure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Nothing is left for him to devour; his prosperity will not endure.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>In the midst of his plenty, distress will overtake him; the full force of misery will come upon him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>When he has filled his belly, God will vent his burning anger against him and rain down his blows upon him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Though he flees from an iron weapon, a bronze-tipped arrow pierces him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>He pulls it out of his back, the gleaming point out of his liver. Terrors will come over him;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>total darkness lies in wait for his treasures. A fire unfanned will consume him and devour what is left in his tent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The heavens will expose his guilt; the earth will rise up against him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>A flood will carry off his house, rushing waters </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> on the day of God's wrath.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Such is the fate God allots the wicked, the heritage appointed for them by God."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Adam</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">28</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">The possessions in his house will be carried off, washed away</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="21">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Listen carefully to my words; let this be the consolation you give me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Bear with me while I speak, and after I have spoken, mock on. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Is my complaint directed to man? Why should I not be impatient?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Look at me and be astonished; clap your hand over your mouth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>When I think about this, I am terrified; trembling seizes my body.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Why do the wicked live on, growing old and increasing in power?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>They see their children established around them, their offspring before their eyes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Their homes are safe and free from fear; the rod of God is not upon them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Their bulls never fail to breed; their cows calve and do not miscarry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>They send forth their children as a flock; their little ones dance about.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>They sing to the music of tambourine and harp; they make merry to the sound of the flute.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>They spend their years in prosperity and go down to the grave </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> in peace. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Yet they say to God, `Leave us alone! We have no desire to know your ways.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Who is the Almighty, that we should serve him? What would we gain by praying to him?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>But their prosperity is not in their own hands, so I stand aloof from the counsel of the wicked. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>"Yet how often is the lamp of the wicked snuffed out? How often does calamity come upon them, the fate God allots in his anger?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>How often are they like straw before the wind, like chaff swept away by a gale?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>[It is said,] `God stores up a man's punishment for his sons.' Let him repay the man himself, so that he will know it!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Let his own eyes see his destruction; let him drink of the wrath of the Almighty. </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>For what does he care about the family he leaves behind when his allotted months come to an end? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"Can anyone teach knowledge to God, since he judges even the highest?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>One man dies in full vigor, completely secure and at ease,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>his body </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> well nourished, his bones rich with marrow.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Another man dies in bitterness of soul, never having enjoyed anything good.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Side by side they lie in the dust, and worms cover them both. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"I know full well what you are thinking, the schemes by which you would wrong me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>You say, `Where now is the great man's house, the tents where wicked men lived?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Have you never questioned those who travel? Have you paid no regard to their accounts--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>that the evil man is spared from the day of calamity, that he is delivered from </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> the day of wrath?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>Who denounces his conduct to his face? Who repays him for what he has done?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>He is carried to the grave, and watch is kept over his tomb.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>The soil in the valley is sweet to him; all men follow after him, and a countless throng goes </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> before him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>"So how can you console me with your nonsense? Nothing is left of your answers but falsehood!"</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">in an instant</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17-20</content>
            <content> Verses 17 and 18 may be taken as exclamations and 19 and 20 as declarations.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">30</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">man is reserved for the day of calamity, / that he is brought forth to</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">as a countless throng went</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="22">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Eliphaz the Temanite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Can a man be of benefit to God? Can even a wise man benefit him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>What pleasure would it give the Almighty if you were righteous? What would he gain if your ways were blameless? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Is it for your piety that he rebukes you and brings charges against you?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Is not your wickedness great? Are not your sins endless?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>You demanded security from your brothers for no reason; you stripped men of their clothing, leaving them naked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>You gave no water to the weary and you withheld food from the hungry,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>though you were a powerful man, owning land-- an honored man, living on it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>And you sent widows away empty-handed and broke the strength of the fatherless.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>That is why snares are all around you, why sudden peril terrifies you,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>why it is so dark you cannot see, and why a flood of water covers you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"Is not God in the heights of heaven? And see how lofty are the highest stars!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Yet you say, `What does God know? Does he judge through such darkness?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Thick clouds veil him, so he does not see us as he goes about in the vaulted heavens.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Will you keep to the old path that evil men have trod?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>They were carried off before their time, their foundations washed away by a flood.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>They said to God, `Leave us alone! What can the Almighty do to us?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Yet it was he who filled their houses with good things, so I stand aloof from the counsel of the wicked. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"The righteous see their ruin and rejoice; the innocent mock them, saying,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>`Surely our foes are destroyed, and fire devours their wealth.' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Submit to God and be at peace with him; in this way prosperity will come to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Accept instruction from his mouth and lay up his words in your heart.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>If you return to the Almighty, you will be restored: If you remove wickedness far from your tent</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>and assign your nuggets to the dust, your gold of Ophir to the rocks in the ravines,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>then the Almighty will be your gold, the choicest silver for you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Surely then you will find delight in the Almighty and will lift up your face to God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>You will pray to him, and he will hear you, and you will fulfill your vows.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>What you decide on will be done, and light will shine on your ways.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>When men are brought low and you say, `Lift them up!' then he will save the downcast.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>He will deliver even one who is not innocent, who will be delivered through the cleanness of your hands."</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="23">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Even today my complaint is bitter; his hand </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> is heavy in spite of </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> my groaning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>If only I knew where to find him; if only I could go to his dwelling!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>I would state my case before him and fill my mouth with arguments.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>I would find out what he would answer me, and consider what he would say.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Would he oppose me with great power? No, he would not press charges against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>There an upright man could present his case before him, and I would be delivered forever from my judge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"But if I go to the east, he is not there; if I go to the west, I do not find him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>When he is at work in the north, I do not see him; when he turns to the south, I catch no glimpse of him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But he knows the way that I take; when he has tested me, I will come forth as gold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>My feet have closely followed his steps; I have kept to his way without turning aside.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>I have not departed from the commands of his lips; I have treasured the words of his mouth more than my daily bread. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"But he stands alone, and who can oppose him? He does whatever he pleases.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>He carries out his decree against me, and many such plans he still has in store.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>That is why I am terrified before him; when I think of all this, I fear him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>God has made my heart faint; the Almighty has terrified me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Yet I am not silenced by the darkness, by the thick darkness that covers my face. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> Septuagint and Syriac; Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">the hand on me</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">heavy on me in</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="24">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Why does the Almighty not set times for judgment? Why must those who know him look in vain for such days?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Men move boundary stones; they pasture flocks they have stolen.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>They drive away the orphan's donkey and take the widow's ox in pledge.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>They thrust the needy from the path and force all the poor of the land into hiding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Like wild donkeys in the desert, the poor go about their labor of foraging food; the wasteland provides food for their children.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>They gather fodder in the fields and glean in the vineyards of the wicked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Lacking clothes, they spend the night naked; they have nothing to cover themselves in the cold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>They are drenched by mountain rains and hug the rocks for lack of shelter.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The fatherless child is snatched from the breast; the infant of the poor is seized for a debt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Lacking clothes, they go about naked; they carry the sheaves, but still go hungry.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>They crush olives among the terraces </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ; they tread the winepresses, yet suffer thirst.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The groans of the dying rise from the city, and the souls of the wounded cry out for help. But God charges no one with wrongdoing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"There are those who rebel against the light, who do not know its ways or stay in its paths.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>When daylight is gone, the murderer rises up and kills the poor and needy; in the night he steals forth like a thief.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The eye of the adulterer watches for dusk; he thinks, `No eye will see me,' and he keeps his face concealed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>In the dark, men break into houses, but by day they shut themselves in; they want nothing to do with the light.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>For all of them, deep darkness is their morning </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> ; they make friends with the terrors of darkness. </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"Yet they are foam on the surface of the water; their portion of the land is cursed, so that no one goes to the vineyards.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>As heat and drought snatch away the melted snow, so the grave </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> snatches away those who have sinned.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>The womb forgets them, the worm feasts on them; evil men are no longer remembered but are broken like a tree.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>They prey on the barren and childless woman, and to the widow show no kindness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>But God drags away the mighty by his power; though they become established, they have no assurance of life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>He may let them rest in a feeling of security, but his eyes are on their ways.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>For a little while they are exalted, and then they are gone; they are brought low and gathered up like all others; they are cut off like heads of grain. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>"If this is not so, who can prove me false and reduce my words to nothing?"</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">olives between the millstones</content>
            <content>; the meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">them, their morning is like the shadow of death</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">of the shadow of death</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">19</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="25">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Bildad the Shuhite replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Dominion and awe belong to God; he establishes order in the heights of heaven.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Can his forces be numbered? Upon whom does his light not rise?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>How then can a man be righteous before God? How can one born of woman be pure?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>If even the moon is not bright and the stars are not pure in his eyes,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>how much less man, who is but a maggot-- a son of man, who is only a worm!"</content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="26">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"How you have helped the powerless! How you have saved the arm that is feeble!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>What advice you have offered to one without wisdom! And what great insight you have displayed!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Who has helped you utter these words? And whose spirit spoke from your mouth? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"The dead are in deep anguish, those beneath the waters and all that live in them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Death </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> is naked before God; Destruction </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> lies uncovered.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>He spreads out the northern [skies] over empty space; he suspends the earth over nothing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He wraps up the waters in his clouds, yet the clouds do not burst under their weight.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>He covers the face of the full moon, spreading his clouds over it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He marks out the horizon on the face of the waters for a boundary between light and darkness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>The pillars of the heavens quake, aghast at his rebuke.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>By his power he churned up the sea; by his wisdom he cut Rahab to pieces.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>By his breath the skies became fair; his hand pierced the gliding serpent.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>And these are but the outer fringe of his works; how faint the whisper we hear of him! Who then can understand the thunder of his power?" </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Sheol</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Abaddon</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="27">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>And Job continued his discourse:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"As surely as God lives, who has denied me justice, the Almighty, who has made me taste bitterness of soul,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>as long as I have life within me, the breath of God in my nostrils,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>my lips will not speak wickedness, and my tongue will utter no deceit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>I will never admit you are in the right; till I die, I will not deny my integrity.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>I will maintain my righteousness and never let go of it; my conscience will not reproach me as long as I live. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"May my enemies be like the wicked, my adversaries like the unjust!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>For what hope has the godless when he is cut off, when God takes away his life?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Does God listen to his cry when distress comes upon him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Will he find delight in the Almighty? Will he call upon God at all times? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>"I will teach you about the power of God; the ways of the Almighty I will not conceal.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>You have all seen this yourselves. Why then this meaningless talk? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"Here is the fate God allots to the wicked, the heritage a ruthless man receives from the Almighty:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>However many his children, their fate is the sword; his offspring will never have enough to eat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The plague will bury those who survive him, and their widows will not weep for them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Though he heaps up silver like dust and clothes like piles of clay,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>what he lays up the righteous will wear, and the innocent will divide his silver.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>The house he builds is like a moth's cocoon, like a hut made by a watchman.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He lies down wealthy, but will do so no more; when he opens his eyes, all is gone.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Terrors overtake him like a flood; a tempest snatches him away in the night.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>The east wind carries him off, and he is gone; it sweeps him out of his place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>It hurls itself against him without mercy as he flees headlong from its power.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>It claps its hands in derision and hisses him out of his place. </content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="28">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"There is a mine for silver and a place where gold is refined.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Iron is taken from the earth, and copper is smelted from ore.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Man puts an end to the darkness; he searches the farthest recesses for ore in the blackest darkness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Far from where people dwell he cuts a shaft, in places forgotten by the foot of man; far from men he dangles and sways.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>The earth, from which food comes, is transformed below as by fire;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>sapphires </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> come from its rocks, and its dust contains nuggets of gold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>No bird of prey knows that hidden path, no falcon's eye has seen it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Proud beasts do not set foot on it, and no lion prowls there.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Man's hand assaults the flinty rock and lays bare the roots of the mountains.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He tunnels through the rock; his eyes see all its treasures.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He searches </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> the sources of the rivers and brings hidden things to light. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"But where can wisdom be found? Where does understanding dwell?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Man does not comprehend its worth; it cannot be found in the land of the living.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The deep says, `It is not in me'; the sea says, `It is not with me.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>It cannot be bought with the finest gold, nor can its price be weighed in silver.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>It cannot be bought with the gold of Ophir, with precious onyx or sapphires.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Neither gold nor crystal can compare with it, nor can it be had for jewels of gold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Coral and jasper are not worthy of mention; the price of wisdom is beyond rubies.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>The topaz of Cush cannot compare with it; it cannot be bought with pure gold. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"Where then does wisdom come from? Where does understanding dwell?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>It is hidden from the eyes of every living thing, concealed even from the birds of the air.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Destruction </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> and Death say, `Only a rumor of it has reached our ears.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>God understands the way to it and he alone knows where it dwells,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>for he views the ends of the earth and sees everything under the heavens.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>When he established the force of the wind and measured out the waters,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>when he made a decree for the rain and a path for the thunderstorm,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>then he looked at wisdom and appraised it; he confirmed it and tested it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>And he said to man, `The fear of the Lord--that is wisdom, and to shun evil is understanding.'" </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">6</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">lapis lazuli</content>
            <content>; also in verse 16</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Septuagint, Aquila and Vulgate; Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">He dams up</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Abaddon</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="29">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Job continued his discourse:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"How I long for the months gone by, for the days when God watched over me,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>when his lamp shone upon my head and by his light I walked through darkness!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Oh, for the days when I was in my prime, when God's intimate friendship blessed my house,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>when the Almighty was still with me and my children were around me,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>when my path was drenched with cream and the rock poured out for me streams of olive oil. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"When I went to the gate of the city and took my seat in the public square,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>the young men saw me and stepped aside and the old men rose to their feet;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>the chief men refrained from speaking and covered their mouths with their hands;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>the voices of the nobles were hushed, and their tongues stuck to the roof of their mouths.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Whoever heard me spoke well of me, and those who saw me commended me,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>because I rescued the poor who cried for help, and the fatherless who had none to assist him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>The man who was dying blessed me; I made the widow's heart sing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>I put on righteousness as my clothing; justice was my robe and my turban.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>I was eyes to the blind and feet to the lame.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>I was a father to the needy; I took up the case of the stranger.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>I broke the fangs of the wicked and snatched the victims from their teeth. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>"I thought, `I will die in my own house, my days as numerous as the grains of sand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>My roots will reach to the water, and the dew will lie all night on my branches.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>My glory will remain fresh in me, the bow ever new in my hand.' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"Men listened to me expectantly, waiting in silence for my counsel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>After I had spoken, they spoke no more; my words fell gently on their ears.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>They waited for me as for showers and drank in my words as the spring rain.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>When I smiled at them, they scarcely believed it; the light of my face was precious to them. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>I chose the way for them and sat as their chief; I dwelt as a king among his troops; I was like one who comforts mourners. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this clause is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="30">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"But now they mock me, men younger than I, whose fathers I would have disdained to put with my sheep dogs.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Of what use was the strength of their hands to me, since their vigor had gone from them?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Haggard from want and hunger, they roamed </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> the parched land in desolate wastelands at night.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>In the brush they gathered salt herbs, and their food </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> was the root of the broom tree.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>They were banished from their fellow men, shouted at as if they were thieves.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>They were forced to live in the dry stream beds, among the rocks and in holes in the ground.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>They brayed among the bushes and huddled in the undergrowth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>A base and nameless brood, they were driven out of the land. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"And now their sons mock me in song; I have become a byword among them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>They detest me and keep their distance; they do not hesitate to spit in my face.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Now that God has unstrung my bow and afflicted me, they throw off restraint in my presence.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>On my right the tribe </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> attacks; they lay snares for my feet, they build their siege ramps against me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>They break up my road; they succeed in destroying me-- without anyone's helping them. </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>They advance as through a gaping breach; amid the ruins they come rolling in.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Terrors overwhelm me; my dignity is driven away as by the wind, my safety vanishes like a cloud. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"And now my life ebbs away; days of suffering grip me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Night pierces my bones; my gnawing pains never rest.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>In his great power [God] becomes like clothing to me </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> ; he binds me like the neck of my garment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He throws me into the mud, and I am reduced to dust and ashes. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>"I cry out to you, O God, but you do not answer; I stand up, but you merely look at me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>You turn on me ruthlessly; with the might of your hand you attack me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>You snatch me up and drive me before the wind; you toss me about in the storm.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>I know you will bring me down to death, to the place appointed for all the living. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"Surely no one lays a hand on a broken man when he cries for help in his distress.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Have I not wept for those in trouble? Has not my soul grieved for the poor?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>Yet when I hoped for good, evil came; when I looked for light, then came darkness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>The churning inside me never stops; days of suffering confront me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>I go about blackened, but not by the sun; I stand up in the assembly and cry for help.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>I have become a brother of jackals, a companion of owls.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>My skin grows black and peels; my body burns with fever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>My harp is tuned to mourning, and my flute to the sound of wailing. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">3</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">gnawed</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">4</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">fuel</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">me. `No one can help him,' [they say].</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Hebrew; Septuagint </content>
            <content kind="EM">[God] grasps my clothing</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="31">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"I made a covenant with my eyes not to look lustfully at a girl.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>For what is man's lot from God above, his heritage from the Almighty on high?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Is it not ruin for the wicked, disaster for those who do wrong?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Does he not see my ways and count my every step? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"If I have walked in falsehood or my foot has hurried after deceit--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>let God weigh me in honest scales and he will know that I am blameless--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>if my steps have turned from the path, if my heart has been led by my eyes, or if my hands have been defiled,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>then may others eat what I have sown, and may my crops be uprooted. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"If my heart has been enticed by a woman, or if I have lurked at my neighbor's door,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>then may my wife grind another man's grain, and may other men sleep with her.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>For that would have been shameful, a sin to be judged.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>It is a fire that burns to Destruction </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ; it would have uprooted my harvest. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"If I have denied justice to my menservants and maidservants when they had a grievance against me,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>what will I do when God confronts me? What will I answer when called to account?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Did not he who made me in the womb make them? Did not the same one form us both within our mothers? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"If I have denied the desires of the poor or let the eyes of the widow grow weary,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>if I have kept my bread to myself, not sharing it with the fatherless--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>but from my youth I reared him as would a father, and from my birth I guided the widow--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>if I have seen anyone perishing for lack of clothing, or a needy man without a garment,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>and his heart did not bless me for warming him with the fleece from my sheep,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>if I have raised my hand against the fatherless, knowing that I had influence in court,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>then let my arm fall from the shoulder, let it be broken off at the joint.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>For I dreaded destruction from God, and for fear of his splendor I could not do such things. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>"If I have put my trust in gold or said to pure gold, `You are my security,'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>if I have rejoiced over my great wealth, the fortune my hands had gained,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>if I have regarded the sun in its radiance or the moon moving in splendor,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>so that my heart was secretly enticed and my hand offered them a kiss of homage,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>then these also would be sins to be judged, for I would have been unfaithful to God on high. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"If I have rejoiced at my enemy's misfortune or gloated over the trouble that came to him--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>I have not allowed my mouth to sin by invoking a curse against his life--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>if the men of my household have never said, `Who has not had his fill of Job's meat?'--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>but no stranger had to spend the night in the street, for my door was always open to the traveler--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>if I have concealed my sin as men do, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> by hiding my guilt in my heart</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>because I so feared the crowd and so dreaded the contempt of the clans that I kept silent and would not go outside </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>("Oh, that I had someone to hear me! I sign now my defense--let the Almighty answer me; let my accuser put his indictment in writing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Surely I would wear it on my shoulder, I would put it on like a crown.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>I would give him an account of my every step; like a prince I would approach him.)-- </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>"if my land cries out against me and all its furrows are wet with tears,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>if I have devoured its yield without payment or broken the spirit of its tenants,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>then let briers come up instead of wheat and weeds instead of barley." The words of Job are ended. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">Abaddon</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">as Adam did</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="32">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>So these three men stopped answering Job, because he was righteous in his own eyes.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>But Elihu son of Barakel the Buzite, of the family of Ram, became very angry with Job for justifying himself rather than God.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>He was also angry with the three friends, because they had found no way to refute Job, and yet had condemned him. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Now Elihu had waited before speaking to Job because they were older than he.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>But when he saw that the three men had nothing more to say, his anger was aroused.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>So Elihu son of Barakel the Buzite said: "I am young in years, and you are old; that is why I was fearful, not daring to tell you what I know.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>I thought, `Age should speak; advanced years should teach wisdom.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>But it is the spirit </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> in a man, the breath of the Almighty, that gives him understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>It is not only the old </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> who are wise, not only the aged who understand what is right. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"Therefore I say: Listen to me; I too will tell you what I know.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>I waited while you spoke, I listened to your reasoning; while you were searching for words,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>I gave you my full attention. But not one of you has proved Job wrong; none of you has answered his arguments.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Do not say, `We have found wisdom; let God refute him, not man.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But Job has not marshaled his words against me, and I will not answer him with your arguments. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"They are dismayed and have no more to say; words have failed them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Must I wait, now that they are silent, now that they stand there with no reply?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>I too will have my say; I too will tell what I know.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>For I am full of words, and the spirit within me compels me;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>inside I am like bottled-up wine, like new wineskins ready to burst.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>I must speak and find relief; I must open my lips and reply.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>I will show partiality to no one, nor will I flatter any man;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>for if I were skilled in flattery, my Maker would soon take me away. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">3</content>
            <content> Masoretic Text; an ancient Hebrew scribal tradition </content>
            <content kind="EM">Job, and so had condemned God</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">8</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Spirit</content>
            <content>; also in verse 18</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">9</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">many</content>
            <content>; or </content>
            <content kind="EM">great</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="33">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"But now, Job, listen to my words; pay attention to everything I say.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>I am about to open my mouth; my words are on the tip of my tongue.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>My words come from an upright heart; my lips sincerely speak what I know.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>The Spirit of God has made me; the breath of the Almighty gives me life.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Answer me then, if you can; prepare yourself and confront me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>I am just like you before God; I too have been taken from clay.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>No fear of me should alarm you, nor should my hand be heavy upon you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"But you have said in my hearing-- I heard the very words--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>`I am pure and without sin; I am clean and free from guilt.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Yet God has found fault with me; he considers me his enemy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He fastens my feet in shackles; he keeps close watch on all my paths.' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"But I tell you, in this you are not right, for God is greater than man.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Why do you complain to him that he answers none of man's words </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>For God does speak--now one way, now another-- though man may not perceive it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>In a dream, in a vision of the night, when deep sleep falls on men as they slumber in their beds,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>he may speak in their ears and terrify them with warnings,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>to turn man from wrongdoing and keep him from pride,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>to preserve his soul from the pit, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> his life from perishing by the sword. </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Or a man may be chastened on a bed of pain with constant distress in his bones,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>so that his very being finds food repulsive and his soul loathes the choicest meal.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>His flesh wastes away to nothing, and his bones, once hidden, now stick out.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>His soul draws near to the pit, </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> and his life to the messengers of death. </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>"Yet if there is an angel on his side as a mediator, one out of a thousand, to tell a man what is right for him,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>to be gracious to him and say, `Spare him from going down to the pit </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> ; I have found a ransom for him'--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>then his flesh is renewed like a child's; it is restored as in the days of his youth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>He prays to God and finds favor with him, he sees God's face and shouts for joy; he is restored by God to his righteous state.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Then he comes to men and says, `I sinned, and perverted what was right, but I did not get what I deserved.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>He redeemed my soul from going down to the pit, </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> and I will live to enjoy the light.' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>"God does all these things to a man-- twice, even three times--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>to turn back his soul from the pit, </content>
            <note_ref>8</note_ref>
            <content> that the light of life may shine on him. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>"Pay attention, Job, and listen to me; be silent, and I will speak.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>If you have anything to say, answer me; speak up, for I want you to be cleared.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>But if not, then listen to me; be silent, and I will teach you wisdom." </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">that he does not answer for any of his actions</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">preserve him from the grave</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">18</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">from crossing the River</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">He draws near to the grave</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">22</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">to the dead</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">grave</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">28</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">redeemed me from going down to the grave</content>
        </note>
        <note num="8">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">30</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">turn him back from the grave</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="34">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Elihu said:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Hear my words, you wise men; listen to me, you men of learning.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>For the ear tests words as the tongue tastes food.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Let us discern for ourselves what is right; let us learn together what is good. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"Job says, `I am innocent, but God denies me justice.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Although I am right, I am considered a liar; although I am guiltless, his arrow inflicts an incurable wound.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>What man is like Job, who drinks scorn like water?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He keeps company with evildoers; he associates with wicked men.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>For he says, `It profits a man nothing when he tries to please God.' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>"So listen to me, you men of understanding. Far be it from God to do evil, from the Almighty to do wrong.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He repays a man for what he has done; he brings upon him what his conduct deserves.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>It is unthinkable that God would do wrong, that the Almighty would pervert justice.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Who appointed him over the earth? Who put him in charge of the whole world?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>If it were his intention and he withdrew his spirit </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and breath,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>all mankind would perish together and man would return to the dust. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"If you have understanding, hear this; listen to what I say.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Can he who hates justice govern? Will you condemn the just and mighty One?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Is he not the One who says to kings, `You are worthless,' and to nobles, `You are wicked,'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>who shows no partiality to princes and does not favor the rich over the poor, for they are all the work of his hands?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>They die in an instant, in the middle of the night; the people are shaken and they pass away; the mighty are removed without human hand. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>"His eyes are on the ways of men; he sees their every step.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>There is no dark place, no deep shadow, where evildoers can hide.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>God has no need to examine men further, that they should come before him for judgment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Without inquiry he shatters the mighty and sets up others in their place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Because he takes note of their deeds, he overthrows them in the night and they are crushed.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>He punishes them for their wickedness where everyone can see them,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>because they turned from following him and had no regard for any of his ways.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>They caused the cry of the poor to come before him, so that he heard the cry of the needy.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>But if he remains silent, who can condemn him? If he hides his face, who can see him? Yet he is over man and nation alike,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>to keep a godless man from ruling, from laying snares for the people. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>"Suppose a man says to God, `I am guilty but will offend no more.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Teach me what I cannot see; if I have done wrong, I will not do so again.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Should God then reward you on your terms, when you refuse to repent? You must decide, not I; so tell me what you know. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>"Men of understanding declare, wise men who hear me say to me,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>`Job speaks without knowledge; his words lack insight.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Oh, that Job might be tested to the utmost for answering like a wicked man!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>To his sin he adds rebellion; scornfully he claps his hands among us and multiplies his words against God." </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">14</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">Spirit</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="35">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Elihu said:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Do you think this is just? You say, `I will be cleared by God. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> '</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Yet you ask him, `What profit is it to me, </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> and what do I gain by not sinning?' </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"I would like to reply to you and to your friends with you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Look up at the heavens and see; gaze at the clouds so high above you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>If you sin, how does that affect him? If your sins are many, what does that do to him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>If you are righteous, what do you give to him, or what does he receive from your hand?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Your wickedness affects only a man like yourself, and your righteousness only the sons of men. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"Men cry out under a load of oppression; they plead for relief from the arm of the powerful.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>But no one says, `Where is God my Maker, who gives songs in the night,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>who teaches more to us than to </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> the beasts of the earth and makes us wiser than </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> the birds of the air?'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>He does not answer when men cry out because of the arrogance of the wicked.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Indeed, God does not listen to their empty plea; the Almighty pays no attention to it.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>How much less, then, will he listen when you say that you do not see him, that your case is before him and you must wait for him,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>and further, that his anger never punishes and he does not take the least notice of wickedness. </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>So Job opens his mouth with empty talk; without knowledge he multiplies words." </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">2</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">My righteousness is more than God's</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">3</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">you</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">teaches us by</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">us wise by</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Symmachus, Theodotion and Vulgate; the meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="36">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Elihu continued:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Bear with me a little longer and I will show you that there is more to be said in God's behalf.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>I get my knowledge from afar; I will ascribe justice to my Maker.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Be assured that my words are not false; one perfect in knowledge is with you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"God is mighty, but does not despise men; he is mighty, and firm in his purpose.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>He does not keep the wicked alive but gives the afflicted their rights.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>He does not take his eyes off the righteous; he enthrones them with kings and exalts them forever.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>But if men are bound in chains, held fast by cords of affliction,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>he tells them what they have done-- that they have sinned arrogantly.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>He makes them listen to correction and commands them to repent of their evil.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>If they obey and serve him, they will spend the rest of their days in prosperity and their years in contentment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>But if they do not listen, they will perish by the sword </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and die without knowledge. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"The godless in heart harbor resentment; even when he fetters them, they do not cry for help.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>They die in their youth, among male prostitutes of the shrines.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>But those who suffer he delivers in their suffering; he speaks to them in their affliction. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"He is wooing you from the jaws of distress to a spacious place free from restriction, to the comfort of your table laden with choice food.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>But now you are laden with the judgment due the wicked; judgment and justice have taken hold of you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Be careful that no one entices you by riches; do not let a large bribe turn you aside.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Would your wealth or even all your mighty efforts sustain you so you would not be in distress?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Do not long for the night, to drag people away from their homes. </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Beware of turning to evil, which you seem to prefer to affliction. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"God is exalted in his power. Who is a teacher like him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Who has prescribed his ways for him, or said to him, `You have done wrong'?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Remember to extol his work, which men have praised in song.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>All mankind has seen it; men gaze on it from afar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>How great is God--beyond our understanding! The number of his years is past finding out. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>"He draws up the drops of water, which distill as rain to the streams </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> ;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>the clouds pour down their moisture and abundant showers fall on mankind.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>Who can understand how he spreads out the clouds, how he thunders from his pavilion?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>See how he scatters his lightning about him, bathing the depths of the sea.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>This is the way he governs </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> the nations and provides food in abundance.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>He fills his hands with lightning and commands it to strike its mark.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>His thunder announces the coming storm; even the cattle make known its approach. </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">12</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">will cross the River</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">20</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for verses 18-20 is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">27</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">distill from the mist as rain</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">31</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">nourishes</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">announces his coming-- the One zealous against evil</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="37">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"At this my heart pounds and leaps from its place.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Listen! Listen to the roar of his voice, to the rumbling that comes from his mouth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>He unleashes his lightning beneath the whole heaven and sends it to the ends of the earth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>After that comes the sound of his roar; he thunders with his majestic voice. When his voice resounds, he holds nothing back.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>God's voice thunders in marvelous ways; he does great things beyond our understanding.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>He says to the snow, `Fall on the earth,' and to the rain shower, `Be a mighty downpour.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>So that all men he has made may know his work, he stops every man from his labor. </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>The animals take cover; they remain in their dens.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>The tempest comes out from its chamber, the cold from the driving winds.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>The breath of God produces ice, and the broad waters become frozen.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>He loads the clouds with moisture; he scatters his lightning through them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>At his direction they swirl around over the face of the whole earth to do whatever he commands them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>He brings the clouds to punish men, or to water his earth </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> and show his love. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>"Listen to this, Job; stop and consider God's wonders.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Do you know how God controls the clouds and makes his lightning flash?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>Do you know how the clouds hang poised, those wonders of him who is perfect in knowledge?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>You who swelter in your clothes when the land lies hushed under the south wind,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>can you join him in spreading out the skies, hard as a mirror of cast bronze? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"Tell us what we should say to him; we cannot draw up our case because of our darkness.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Should he be told that I want to speak? Would any man ask to be swallowed up?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Now no one can look at the sun, bright as it is in the skies after the wind has swept them clean.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Out of the north he comes in golden splendor; God comes in awesome majesty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The Almighty is beyond our reach and exalted in power; in his justice and great righteousness, he does not oppress.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Therefore, men revere him, for does he not have regard for all the wise in heart? </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> "</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">he fills all men with fear by his power</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">13</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">to favor them</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">for he does not have regard for any who think they are wise.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="38">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then the LORD answered Job out of the storm. He said:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Who is this that darkens my counsel with words without knowledge?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Brace yourself like a man; I will question you, and you shall answer me. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"Where were you when I laid the earth's foundation? Tell me, if you understand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Who marked off its dimensions? Surely you know! Who stretched a measuring line across it?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>On what were its footings set, or who laid its cornerstone--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>while the morning stars sang together and all the angels </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> shouted for joy? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Who shut up the sea behind doors when it burst forth from the womb,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>when I made the clouds its garment and wrapped it in thick darkness,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>when I fixed limits for it and set its doors and bars in place,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>when I said, `This far you may come and no farther; here is where your proud waves halt'? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"Have you ever given orders to the morning, or shown the dawn its place,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>that it might take the earth by the edges and shake the wicked out of it?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The earth takes shape like clay under a seal; its features stand out like those of a garment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>The wicked are denied their light, and their upraised arm is broken. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>"Have you journeyed to the springs of the sea or walked in the recesses of the deep?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>Have the gates of death been shown to you? Have you seen the gates of the shadow of death </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Have you comprehended the vast expanses of the earth? Tell me, if you know all this. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"What is the way to the abode of light? And where does darkness reside?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Can you take them to their places? Do you know the paths to their dwellings?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Surely you know, for you were already born! You have lived so many years! </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>"Have you entered the storehouses of the snow or seen the storehouses of the hail,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>which I reserve for times of trouble, for days of war and battle?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>What is the way to the place where the lightning is dispersed, or the place where the east winds are scattered over the earth?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>Who cuts a channel for the torrents of rain, and a path for the thunderstorm,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>to water a land where no man lives, a desert with no one in it,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>to satisfy a desolate wasteland and make it sprout with grass?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Does the rain have a father? Who fathers the drops of dew?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>From whose womb comes the ice? Who gives birth to the frost from the heavens</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>when the waters become hard as stone, when the surface of the deep is frozen? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>"Can you bind the beautiful </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> Pleiades? Can you loose the cords of Orion?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Can you bring forth the constellations in their seasons </content>
            <note_ref>4</note_ref>
            <content> or lead out the Bear </content>
            <note_ref>5</note_ref>
            <content> with its cubs?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Do you know the laws of the heavens? Can you set up [God's </content>
            <note_ref>6</note_ref>
            <content> ] dominion over the earth? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>"Can you raise your voice to the clouds and cover yourself with a flood of water?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="35">
            <content>Do you send the lightning bolts on their way? Do they report to you, `Here we are'?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="36">
            <content>Who endowed the heart </content>
            <note_ref>7</note_ref>
            <content> with wisdom or gave understanding to the mind </content>
            <note_ref>8</note_ref>
            <content> ?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="37">
            <content>Who has the wisdom to count the clouds? Who can tip over the water jars of the heavens</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="38">
            <content>when the dust becomes hard and the clods of earth stick together? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="39">
            <content>"Do you hunt the prey for the lioness and satisfy the hunger of the lions</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="40">
            <content>when they crouch in their dens or lie in wait in a thicket?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="41">
            <content>Who provides food for the raven when its young cry out to God and wander about for lack of food? </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">7</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">the sons of God</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">gates of deep shadows</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">31</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">the twinkling</content>
            <content>; or </content>
            <content kind="EM">the chains of the</content>
        </note>
        <note num="4">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">32</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">the morning star in its season</content>
        </note>
        <note num="5">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">32</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">out Leo</content>
        </note>
        <note num="6">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">33</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">his</content>
            <content>; or </content>
            <content kind="EM">their</content>
        </note>
        <note num="7">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">36</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
        <note num="8">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">36</content>
            <content> The meaning of the Hebrew for this word is uncertain.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="39">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Do you know when the mountain goats give birth? Do you watch when the doe bears her fawn?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Do you count the months till they bear? Do you know the time they give birth?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>They crouch down and bring forth their young; their labor pains are ended.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Their young thrive and grow strong in the wilds; they leave and do not return. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>"Who let the wild donkey go free? Who untied his ropes?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>I gave him the wasteland as his home, the salt flats as his habitat.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>He laughs at the commotion in the town; he does not hear a driver's shout.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>He ranges the hills for his pasture and searches for any green thing. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>"Will the wild ox consent to serve you? Will he stay by your manger at night?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Can you hold him to the furrow with a harness? Will he till the valleys behind you?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Will you rely on him for his great strength? Will you leave your heavy work to him?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>Can you trust him to bring in your grain and gather it to your threshing floor? </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>"The wings of the ostrich flap joyfully, but they cannot compare with the pinions and feathers of the stork.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>She lays her eggs on the ground and lets them warm in the sand,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>unmindful that a foot may crush them, that some wild animal may trample them.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>She treats her young harshly, as if they were not hers; she cares not that her labor was in vain,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>for God did not endow her with wisdom or give her a share of good sense.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>Yet when she spreads her feathers to run, she laughs at horse and rider. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>"Do you give the horse his strength or clothe his neck with a flowing mane?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Do you make him leap like a locust, striking terror with his proud snorting?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>He paws fiercely, rejoicing in his strength, and charges into the fray.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>He laughs at fear, afraid of nothing; he does not shy away from the sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The quiver rattles against his side, along with the flashing spear and lance.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>In frenzied excitement he eats up the ground; he cannot stand still when the trumpet sounds.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>At the blast of the trumpet he snorts, `Aha!' He catches the scent of battle from afar, the shout of commanders and the battle cry. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>"Does the hawk take flight by your wisdom and spread his wings toward the south?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Does the eagle soar at your command and build his nest on high?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>He dwells on a cliff and stays there at night; a rocky crag is his stronghold.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>From there he seeks out his food; his eyes detect it from afar.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>His young ones feast on blood, and where the slain are, there is he." </content>
        </verse>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="40">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>The LORD said to Job:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"Will the one who contends with the Almighty correct him? Let him who accuses God answer him!"</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Then Job answered the LORD:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>"I am unworthy--how can I reply to you? I put my hand over my mouth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>I spoke once, but I have no answer-- twice, but I will say no more."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Then the LORD spoke to Job out of the storm:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>"Brace yourself like a man; I will question you, and you shall answer me. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>"Would you discredit my justice? Would you condemn me to justify yourself?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Do you have an arm like God's, and can your voice thunder like his?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>Then adorn yourself with glory and splendor, and clothe yourself in honor and majesty.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Unleash the fury of your wrath, look at every proud man and bring him low,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>look at every proud man and humble him, crush the wicked where they stand.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Bury them all in the dust together; shroud their faces in the grave.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Then I myself will admit to you that your own right hand can save you. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>"Look at the behemoth, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> which I made along with you and which feeds on grass like an ox.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>What strength he has in his loins, what power in the muscles of his belly!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>His tail </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> sways like a cedar; the sinews of his thighs are close-knit.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>His bones are tubes of bronze, his limbs like rods of iron.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>He ranks first among the works of God, yet his Maker can approach him with his sword.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>The hills bring him their produce, and all the wild animals play nearby.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Under the lotus plants he lies, hidden among the reeds in the marsh.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>The lotuses conceal him in their shadow; the poplars by the stream surround him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>When the river rages, he is not alarmed; he is secure, though the Jordan should surge against his mouth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>Can anyone capture him by the eyes, </content>
            <note_ref>3</note_ref>
            <content> or trap him and pierce his nose? </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Possibly the hippopotamus or the elephant</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">17</content>
            <content> Possibly trunk</content>
        </note>
        <note num="3">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">24</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">by a water hole</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="41">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>"Can you pull in the leviathan </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> with a fishhook or tie down his tongue with a rope?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>Can you put a cord through his nose or pierce his jaw with a hook?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Will he keep begging you for mercy? Will he speak to you with gentle words?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>Will he make an agreement with you for you to take him as your slave for life?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>Can you make a pet of him like a bird or put him on a leash for your girls?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Will traders barter for him? Will they divide him up among the merchants?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Can you fill his hide with harpoons or his head with fishing spears?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>If you lay a hand on him, you will remember the struggle and never do it again!</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>Any hope of subduing him is false; the mere sight of him is overpowering.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>No one is fierce enough to rouse him. Who then is able to stand against me?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Who has a claim against me that I must pay? Everything under heaven belongs to me. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>"I will not fail to speak of his limbs, his strength and his graceful form.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>Who can strip off his outer coat? Who would approach him with a bridle?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>Who dares open the doors of his mouth, ringed about with his fearsome teeth?</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>His back has </content>
            <note_ref>2</note_ref>
            <content> rows of shields tightly sealed together;</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>each is so close to the next that no air can pass between.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>They are joined fast to one another; they cling together and cannot be parted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>His snorting throws out flashes of light; his eyes are like the rays of dawn.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>Firebrands stream from his mouth; sparks of fire shoot out.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>Smoke pours from his nostrils as from a boiling pot over a fire of reeds.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>His breath sets coals ablaze, and flames dart from his mouth.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>Strength resides in his neck; dismay goes before him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>The folds of his flesh are tightly joined; they are firm and immovable.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>His chest is hard as rock, hard as a lower millstone.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>When he rises up, the mighty are terrified; they retreat before his thrashing.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="26">
            <content>The sword that reaches him has no effect, nor does the spear or the dart or the javelin.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="27">
            <content>Iron he treats like straw and bronze like rotten wood.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="28">
            <content>Arrows do not make him flee; slingstones are like chaff to him.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="29">
            <content>A club seems to him but a piece of straw; he laughs at the rattling of the lance.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="30">
            <content>His undersides are jagged potsherds, leaving a trail in the mud like a threshing sledge.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="31">
            <content>He makes the depths churn like a boiling caldron and stirs up the sea like a pot of ointment.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="32">
            <content>Behind him he leaves a glistening wake; one would think the deep had white hair.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="33">
            <content>Nothing on earth is his equal-- a creature without fear.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="34">
            <content>He looks down on all that are haughty; he is king over all that are proud."</content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">1</content>
            <content> Possibly the crocodile</content>
        </note>
        <note num="2">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">15</content>
            <content> Or </content>
            <content kind="EM">His pride is his</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
    <chapter num="42">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Then Job replied to the LORD:</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>"I know that you can do all things; no plan of yours can be thwarted.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>[You asked,] `Who is this that obscures my counsel without knowledge?' Surely I spoke of things I did not understand, things too wonderful for me to know. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>["You said,] `Listen now, and I will speak; I will question you, and you shall answer me.'</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>My ears had heard of you but now my eyes have seen you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>Therefore I despise myself and repent in dust and ashes." </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>After the LORD had said these things to Job, he said to Eliphaz the Temanite, "I am angry with you and your two friends, because you have not spoken of me what is right, as my servant Job has.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>So now take seven bulls and seven rams and go to my servant Job and sacrifice a burnt offering for yourselves. My servant Job will pray for you, and I will accept his prayer and not deal with you according to your folly. You have not spoken of me what is right, as my servant Job has."</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>So Eliphaz the Temanite, Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite did what the LORD told them; and the LORD accepted Job's prayer.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>After Job had prayed for his friends, the LORD made him prosperous again and gave him twice as much as he had before.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>All his brothers and sisters and everyone who had known him before came and ate with him in his house. They comforted and consoled him over all the trouble the LORD had brought upon him, and each one gave him a piece of silver </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> and a gold ring.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>The LORD blessed the latter part of Job's life more than the first. He had fourteen thousand sheep, six thousand camels, a thousand yoke of oxen and a thousand donkeys.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>And he also had seven sons and three daughters.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>The first daughter he named Jemimah, the second Keziah and the third Keren-Happuch.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Nowhere in all the land were there found women as beautiful as Job's daughters, and their father granted them an inheritance along with their brothers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>After this, Job lived a hundred and forty years; he saw his children and their children to the fourth generation.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>And so he died, old and full of years. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">11</content>
            <content> Hebrew </content>
            <content kind="EM">him a kesitah</content>
            <content>; a kesitah was a unit of money of unknown weight and value.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
</book>
