<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1">
            <content>Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy our brother, To Philemon our dear friend and fellow worker,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="2">
            <content>to Apphia our sister, to Archippus our fellow soldier and to the church that meets in your home: </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="3">
            <content>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="4">
            <content>I always thank my God as I remember you in my prayers,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="5">
            <content>because I hear about your faith in the Lord Jesus and your love for all the saints.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="6">
            <content>I pray that you may be active in sharing your faith, so that you will have a full understanding of every good thing we have in Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="7">
            <content>Your love has given me great joy and encouragement, because you, brother, have refreshed the hearts of the saints.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="8">
            <content>Therefore, although in Christ I could be bold and order you to do what you ought to do,</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="9">
            <content>yet I appeal to you on the basis of love. I then, as Paul--an old man and now also a prisoner of Christ Jesus--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="10">
            <content>I appeal to you for my son Onesimus, </content>
            <note_ref>1</note_ref>
            <content> who became my son while I was in chains.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="11">
            <content>Formerly he was useless to you, but now he has become useful both to you and to me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="12">
            <content>I am sending him--who is my very heart--back to you.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="13">
            <content>I would have liked to keep him with me so that he could take your place in helping me while I am in chains for the gospel.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="14">
            <content>But I did not want to do anything without your consent, so that any favor you do will be spontaneous and not forced.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="15">
            <content>Perhaps the reason he was separated from you for a little while was that you might have him back for good--</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="16">
            <content>no longer as a slave, but better than a slave, as a dear brother. He is very dear to me but even dearer to you, both as a man and as a brother in the Lord.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="17">
            <content>So if you consider me a partner, welcome him as you would welcome me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="18">
            <content>If he has done you any wrong or owes you anything, charge it to me.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="19">
            <content>I, Paul, am writing this with my own hand. I will pay it back--not to mention that you owe me your very self.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="20">
            <content>I do wish, brother, that I may have some benefit from you in the Lord; refresh my heart in Christ.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="21">
            <content>Confident of your obedience, I write to you, knowing that you will do even more than I ask.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="22">
            <content>And one thing more: Prepare a guest room for me, because I hope to be restored to you in answer to your prayers. </content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="23">
            <content>Epaphras, my fellow prisoner in Christ Jesus, sends you greetings.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="24">
            <content>And so do Mark, Aristarchus, Demas and Luke, my fellow workers.</content>
        </verse>
        <verse num="25">
            <content>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. </content>
        </verse>
        <note num="1">
            <content kind="REF_VERSE_START">10</content>
            <content> </content>
            <content kind="EM">Onesimus</content>
            <content> means </content>
            <content kind="EM">useful.</content>
        </note>
    </chapter>
</book>
